<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive Design of a Global Opacity Transfer Function for Direct Volume Rendering of Ultrasound Data *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dieter</forename><surname>Hönigmann</surname></persName>
							<email>dieter.hoenigmann@acv.ac.at</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Johannes</forename><surname>Ruisz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christoph</forename><surname>Haider</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Advanced Computer Vision GmbH -ACV</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Advanced Computer Vision GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Donau-City-Strasse 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>1220</postCode>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle, Washington</settlement>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive Design of a Global Opacity Transfer Function for Direct Volume Rendering of Ultrasound Data *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:51+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.3 [Computing Methodologies]: Computer Graphics-Picture/Image Generation</term>
					<term>I.3.7 [Computing Methodologies]: Computer Graphics-Three-Dimensional Graphics and Realism</term>
					<term>J.3 [Computer Applications]: Life and Medical Sciences</term>
					<term>3D ultrasound, direct volume rendering, transfer function</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>(a) Linear OTF (b) Manually designed piecewise lin. OTF (c) Adaptively designed OTF Figure 1: Direct volume rendering of an ultrasound data set of a fetus using three different global opacity transfer functions (OTF).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Direct volume rendering is a method which is readily available for visualization of volumetric data without the need to compute an explicit surface model prior to visualization. In biomedical imaging, many imaging modalities allow the acquisition of 3D data of anatomy. For this reason, direct volume rendering is particularly popular. This is especially true for modalities where the segmentation task is difficult to handle. 3D ultrasound imaging is one of these modalities. The following characteristics make many conventional segmentation and visualization techniques fail:</p><p>• The coherent nature of the ultrasound imaging pulse is responsible for interference effects and the appearance of speckle artifacts which often exceed the specular echo intensity.</p><p>• The dynamic range is much lower as in x-ray computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).</p><p>• Variations in the intensity of neighboring voxels are high, even within areas of homogeneous tissue. Rather, signal intensity locally increases at the interface between adjacent tissues.</p><p>• Boundaries show varying gray level caused by the variation of surface curvature and orientation to the sound source. The regions representing boundaries are not sharp but show a width of several pixels.</p><p>• Surfaces are partially or completely shadowed from objects closer to and within the direction of the sound source.</p><p>• Sonography is a highly interactive modality: the physician moves the sound source and expects to immediately see the image from the new point-of-view. Thus, all visualization techniques need to work in or near real-time.</p><p>For an overview on 3D ultrasound imaging and its applications see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Fenster and Downey 2000]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[Nelson and Pretorius 1998</ref>].</p><p>It is important to understand that in the direct volume rendering approach the delineation of the surface by some kind of 3D segmentation of the original data set is replaced by applying an opacity transfer function <ref type="bibr">(OTF)</ref>. Proper design of this function, which maps voxel properties to opacities, is of great importance and determines the final result of the visualization process, as one can see in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>.</p><p>Georgios <ref type="bibr">Sakas et al.</ref> were among the first to point out that MRI and CT surface reconstruction techniques do not yield reasonable results if applied to ultrasound data  <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[Sakas and Walter 1995]</ref>. Instead, they suggest a multi-scale binarize, lowpass, threshold &amp; propagate (BLTP) method to preprocess the volumetric data. Subsequently, they employ direct volume rendering for surface visualization, using a slightly modified version of Marc Levoy's standard volume rendering pipeline <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[Levoy 1988</ref>]. Their approach yields pleasing results in case of data sets with high contrast between the structures of interest and the background. In the conclusions of , they state that a surface extraction method which adapts to the local characteristics could improve the appearance of the rendered volume. We propose the adaptation of the OTF using surface information.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows: We briefly summarize previous work on OTF design in section 2 and discuss the most commonly used OTF in 3D sonography, a piecewise linear OTF, in section 3.We derive some properties of linear OTFs using a simple data model in section 4. We focus our examinations on image contrast and present an alternative family of parabolic OTFs which outperform linear OTFs concerning this feature. In section 5 we introduce our methodology to adjust OTFs to a specific data set in an automated way. The paper ends with results achieved by our approach in section 6 and conclusions in section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Previous Work</head><p>In the past different OTF design approaches have been suggested. Basically, there are two classes, namely these which require user interaction, and those which work fully automatic. Among the latter is a stochastic optimization technique based on objective measures of the rendered image suggested by Taosong He et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[He et al. 1996]</ref>. Unfortunately, their evolutionary approach is computationally demanding, and the definition of objective measures for rendered ultrasound data is not easy.</p><p>A different approach based on histogram volumes has been proposed by <ref type="bibr">Gordon Kindlmann et al. in</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[Kindlmann and Durkin 1998</ref>]. This approach unfortunately requires that the regions of interest are boundaries between different materials modeled by a step edge. This is a reasonable assumption for anatomical structures in CT data sets, but not for ultrasound data 1 . An OTF design technique using 3D filter responses proposed by Yoshinobu Sato et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[Sato et al. 2000]</ref> uses even more detailed models of local structures such as sheets, lines, and blobs, and is thus not applicable to ultrasound data, either.</p><p>A 3D field topology approach by Issei Fujishiro et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[Fujishiro et al. 2000]</ref> as well as the evaluation of the contour spectrum by Chandrajit Bajaj et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[Bajaj et al. 1997]</ref> are based on the evaluation of isosurfaces. As discussed above, in sonography tissue boundaries often show varying gray levels caused by the variation of surface curvature and orientation to the sound source, or shadowing. The structure of interest will thus most probably not match with an isosurface.</p><p>Christof Rezk-Salama et al. suggested to use manually designed "optimal" transfer functions as reference templates <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Rezk-Salama et al. 2000]</ref>. By non-linear time warping they compute a non-linear distortion of the data value axis to obtain alignment of the normalized histograms of both the reference data set and the data set currently under examination. Unfortunately, for sonographic data alignment of the histograms is not a sufficient criterion to obtain a pleasing visualization.</p><p>Hence, although all these automated transfer function design techniques have proven to be useful in many visualization tasks (with the histogram volume approach probably being the most promising one according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[Pfister et al. 2001]</ref>) the unique characteristics of sonographic data prevents their application.</p><p>Opposed to the previous techniques, there are interactive transfer function design approaches. Here, the VolumePro real-time volume rendering system is certainly the milestone <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[Pfister et al. 1999</ref>]. On the other hand, some authors suggest software-based ways of interactively modifying color and/or opacity transfer functions: Kazufumi <ref type="bibr">Kaneda et al.</ref> propose to use a weighted sum of basis images to obtain images rendered using different color maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[Kaneda et al. 1996]</ref>; Marks et al. suggest so called design galleries <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[Marks et al. 1997]</ref>; and Vivek Srivastava et al. propose to store a compressed list of samples along each ray thus avoiding expensive sample interpolation and shading computation <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[Srivastava et al. 2003</ref>].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Piecewise Linear Opacity Transfer Functions</head><p>The most commonly used transfer function for rendering of volumetric ultrasound data is based on Marc Levoy's seminal paper on direct volume rendering <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[Levoy 1988</ref>]. He suggested an opacity transfer function considering the intensity I(x i ) of a voxel x i as well as its gradient ∇I(x i ). Because of the low signal-to-noise ratio of sonographic data and the high sensitivity of the gradient to noise this transfer function is hardly ever used for ultrasound data visualization directly. Rather, it is common practice to either preprocess the data as proposed by Sakas in  and <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[Sakas and Walter 1995]</ref>, or to base the transfer function solely on image intensity. In the latter case, a commonly used OTF is a simple piecewise linear monotonically increasing function</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">α(I) =      0 if I &lt; L L , a(I − L L ) if L L ≤ I ≤ L H , a(L H − L L ) if I &gt; L H .</formula><p>(1) This OTF resembles a "fuzzy" segmentation of the entire data volume by an intensity threshold: Voxels with intensities I below L L are classified as "invisible", i.e., their opacity α is set to zero. Intensities between L L and L H have increasing opacities while intensities above L H yield maximum opacity. An OTF of this form is useful for visualization of anatomical structures embedded in hypoechoic areas, i.e. areas with low signal intensity. A typical example is the data set of a fetus floating in amniotic fluid. For the result one obtains for L L = 20, a = 0.5, and L H = 255 see <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>(b). The shape of the OTF is motivated by an increase in signal intensities near tissue boundaries, such as the interface between amniotic fluid and fetal tissue (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 4 and 5)</ref>.</p><p>Despite the simplicity of (1) three parameters need to be determined. Usually, this adjustment has to be done manually on a trialand-error basis not only for every single data set but also depending on the view. It is also not clear whether a piecewise linear OTF allows to obtain an optimal visualization for a given data set. Thus, let us have a look at the properties of linear OTFs in the following section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Contrast in Rendered Images</head><p>In order to produce a 2D projection of voxel values in the viewing plane we use the volumetric compositing stage proposed by Marc Levoy in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[Levoy 1988</ref>]: Rays are cast from the eye into the voxel arrays and color and opacity information are combined into single values to provide a final pixel intensity. For a single voxel at position k along the ray,</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">C out = C in 1 − α(k) + c(k)α(k),<label>(2)</label></formula><p>with C out the outgoing intensity and color for the voxel, C in the incoming intensity, α(k) the opacity assigned to the voxel at position k along the ray and c(k) its color or intensity. The final intensity C(r) due to the set of K voxels that intercept the ray r is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">C(r) = K ∑ k=0 c(r, k)α(r, k) K ∏ i=k+1 1 − α(r, i) ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where (r, k) is the k-th voxel along the r-th ray, and c(r, 0) is the color of an opaque background, i.e. α(r, 0) = 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Assumptions</head><p>Subsequently, we want to derive how different OTFs and different data sets influence the outcome of Levoy's volumetric compositing scheme (3). We are not aiming at a discussion of interpolation strategies. Thus, to keep things simple, we assume that the rendering direction is orthogonal to the data volume and that the rendered image is of the same size as the projection of the data volume in rendering direction. Further, we consider a single ray r only and assume a sampling rate along r equal to the voxel distance. For the sake of a clear notation we use α(c) to denote the intensity based opacity transfer function, whereas α k denotes the opacity as a function of the position of voxels along the ray r, which is α(r, k) in Levoy's notation. Consequently, we refer to signal intensities at a certain voxel as c k rather than c(r, k).</p><p>Having simplified the volumetric compositing process, we now apply this scheme to a simple data model. One of the most important applications of volume rendering of 3D ultrasound data is the visualization of a fetus embedded in amniotic fluid. Therefore, we are particularly interested in visualizing tissue H with high signal intensity located behind some lower intensity area L. The simplest data model capable of covering this scenario consists of voxels of two different intensities, c 1 and c 2 . We assume that, in viewing direction, the ray first passes through voxels with intensity c 2 , and that intensity changes to c 1 at location k * , i.e.  <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>: Data model used for assessing the effect of an OTF on contrast.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">c k = c 1 if 0 ≤ k &lt; k * c 2 if k * ≤ k ≤ K.<label>(4)</label></formula><p>We now substitute (4) in (3) and obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">C = k * −1 ∑ k=0 c 1 α(c 1 ) k * −1 ∏ i=k+1 1 − α(c 1 ) K ∏ i=k * 1 − α(c 2 ) + K ∑ k=k * c 2 α(c 2 ) K ∏ i=k+1 1 − α(c 2 ) = k * −1 ∑ k=0 c 1 α(c 1 ) 1 − α(c 1 ) k * −k−1 1 − α(c 2 ) K−k * +1 + K ∑ k=k * c 2 α(c 2 ) 1 − α(c 2 ) K−k .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Replacing the geometric sums in (5) by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">n ∑ k=0 q k = 1 − q n+1 1 − q ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>and substituting the position indices by the length</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">L 1 = k * , L 2 = K − k * + 1,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>we obtain the coefficients of the linear combination of c 1 and c 2 yielding the final pixel intensity</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">C = c 1 1 − α(c 2 ) L 2 1 − 1 − α(c 1 ) L 1 + c 2 1 − 1 − α(c 2 ) L 2 .<label>(8)</label></formula><p>We may now assess the effect of changing intensities c 1 and c 2 of the data model as well as the effect of choosing different OTFs. We are particularly interested in achieving sufficiently high contrast in volume rendering of ultrasound data. In this context, we have to distinguish two different types of contrast: First, there is contrast in the rendered image due to a spatial discontinuity of the structures under examination with identical scattering characteristics, i.e., intensities c 1 and c 2 are identical, but the position k * of the intensity transition is different for two rays, see <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(a). We will refer to this type of contrast as depth contrast. Second, there is contrast due to different scattering characteristics of adjacent tissues, i.e., the position k * of the intensity transition is the same, but the intensity c 1 changes, cf. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(b). We refer to the latter type of contrast as tissue contrast.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Depth Contrast</head><p>We can draw some conclusions about the contrast caused by a spatial discontinuity of constant signal intensity by means of (8).    For c 2 &gt; c 1 there is no depth contrast at all because the bright and thus opaque foreground voxels occlude the rear voxels. These intensities are indicated in red in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3(a)</ref>. Further, although we chose a low slope a = 0.1 to reduce occlusion effects, depth contrast ∆C is below 0.1 for a large range of intensities, indicated in yellow in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3(a)</ref>. The depth contrast is reasonably high only for bright c 1 and low c 2 , i.e. for a distinct transition between tissues, indicated in green in the upper right part of the graph.</p><p>In order to increase depth contrast also for tissues of moderate contrast we have to employ a transfer function of different shape. We experimented with parabolic OTFs, which we obtain by simply squaring the voxel intensity c prior to applying the linear OTF, i.e. α(c) = ac 2 . Parabolic OTFs tend to make low intensity voxels more transparent. Thus we expect enhanced depth contrast. Using the same scaling of a = 0.1 we obtain depth contrast depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3(b)</ref>. Indeed, the green area indicating sufficiently high contrast (∆C &gt; 0.1) increases. The respective graph for an OTF α(c) = ac 4 is finally depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3(c)</ref>. Here, in a wide range of c 1 and c 2 depth contrast is increased in comparison to the linear OTF.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Tissue Contrast</head><p>Discussing tissue contrast, i.e. contrast due to different scattering characteristics of adjacent tissues, we once again confine ourselves to the scenario of tissue H with high signal intensity located behind some lower intensity area L. Further, we assume that the surface of H is located at position k * for every ray cast through the volume and that area L has fixed signal intensity c 2 . Having made these assumptions we want to evaluate how a change of echogenicity of H from c 1 to c * 1 influences pixel brightness. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3(d)</ref> depicts the tissue contrast ∆C = C(c 1 , c 2 = 0.2, k * = 50) −C(c * 1 , c 2 = 0.2, k * = 50) one can achieve by means of a linear OTF. In this case, two rays are cast through a volume of depth 100 with H starting at k * = 50 and intensity of c 2 = 0.2. Tissue contrast is very low even in case of c 1 c * 1 . Again, we also used a parabolic OTF, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>(e), and a 4th order parabolic one, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>(f), all scaled by a = 0.1. Similar to depth contrast we can enhance tissue contrast by using parabolic OTFs.</p><p>But we have to care for not exaggerating it: <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures 3(g)</ref>-3(i) depict the relative contrast, i.e., the ratio of pixel contrast to voxel contrast. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3(i)</ref> shows that in the case of a 4th-order parabolic OTF the relative contrast is greater than 1.5 for voxel intensities colored yellow in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3(i)</ref>. This means that the actual difference in voxel intensities will be amplified by a factor of up to two in the rendered image. Therefore, we base our further considerations on parabolic OTFs, where we have sufficient tissue contrast in a wide area indicated in green in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>(h).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Adaptive OTF Design</head><p>Hence, from a theoretical point of view, parabolic OTFs outperform linear OTFs concerning image contrast. We now provide means to adjust an OTF to a specific data set. We aim at an automated adjustment to allow the online computation of an optimal OTF for acquired volume data sets at high frame rates. Unfortunately, we lack an objective function which would allow to tune the OTF by an optimization approach. Nevertheless, we aim at an automated adaptation of OTFs. To achieve this goal we take an heuristic approach as follows: We detect the interface between tissue H with high echogenicity and low echogenic area L. Subsequently we use information about H and L to modify an initial OTF. The task of choosing an appropriate surface is not easy. There are the following difficulties: Because of the noisy characteristics of ultrasound data, it might be difficult to identify the interface between H and L (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref>). There might be multiple interfaces of equal magnitude, but at different intensities. If we have identified the interface between H and L, most probably it will be some kind of noisy ramp rather than one distinct step edge.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Surface Detection</head><p>The proposed methodology for estimating the tissue surface is based on the evaluation of so called tube cores. Having defined the z-axis parallel to the ray casting direction, a tube core is a collection of voxels gathered by traversing the volume in z-direction with a specific diameter. Considering the discrete framework, we specify the diameter by its width in x-and y-direction in voxels. A tube core resembles an intensity profile as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref>, but has an extension greater than one in x-and y-direction. Using a tube core width greater than one is motivated by the noise inherent in ultrasound data. We place these tube cores in an equally spaced raster. In order to further reduce the effects of low signal-to-noise ratio we evaluate the signal intensities along a tube core t within Multiscale detection starts with the detection of the first local maximum at a coarse scale of the interface indicating function, indicated by the red dot. We then compute the range (dotted lines) for subsequent maximum detection at finer scales. cells C t i of specific depth. The size of these cells is thus defined by the diameter of the tube core and the cell depth. We may then assess statistical parameters of the signal intensities within the cells, such as the mean signal intensity I(C t i ). Our goal is the detection of the position of a surface within the tube core. The measure we use for this task is the variance of the intensities within the cells. Thus, we use this parameter as interface indicating function. We will expunge the only disadvantage of this parameter, the missing information about edge direction, by subsequent processing.</p><p>Choosing the interface indicating function does not provide the final solution of our problem, the detection of the interface we want to visualize. A closer look at the graph of the interface indicating function in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref> unveils that it is not sufficient to look for the global maximum. Rather, we are looking for the first significant local maximum, in viewing direction.</p><p>We adopted the scale space filtering approach, originally proposed by Witkin <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[Witkin 1983]</ref>, to this problem. This method describes signals in terms of their extrema, managing ambiguity of scale in an organized and natural way. The signal is expanded by convolution with Gaussian kernels of decreasing size over a continuum scales. We track interfaces, i.e. maxima of the interface indicating function, in the vicinity of the result of the interface detection in the previous scale. Within this range we choose the first local maximum in viewing direction. We iterate this procedure until we finally locate an interface in the original scale. The multiscale detection of the interface in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> is depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>. The suggested method does not necessarily detect the most prominent nor the very first interface in the tube core.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Transfer Function Modification</head><p>The aim of modification of the OTF is to reduce opacity for intensities which typically appear prior to the detected surface while enhancing opacity of the intensities located at the surface. Our approach is a multiplicative one. We start with an OTF of parabolic shape and modify the initial OTF by one basis function per tube core. We extract two parameters for every tube core t: The mean signal intensity I t L of all cells prior to the position of detected sur- PSfrag replacements intensity <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>: Graph of all basis functions f t used to adapt the initial OTF to the data set of <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> in a multiplicative way. Each basis function has a minimum at the mean intensity I t L prior to the detected surface and a maximum at the mean intensity I t H of the cell which is located at the surface detected for each tube core t. The range of f t depends on tube core quality parameters w t S and w tÎ . face s t ; and the mean signal intensity I t H of the cell located exactly at the detected surface. Then, we design each individual basis function g t (x) to have a minimum at I t L and a maximum at I t H . One famliy of functions suitable for this task are functions of the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">g t (x) = a x e −b(x−c) 2 ,<label>(9)</label></formula><p>which we scale to the range of values [-1;1] with a maximum at I t H and a minimum at I t L by choosing</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">a = √ 2be, b = 2 (I t H − I t L ) 2 , c = 1 √ 2b + I t L .<label>(10)</label></formula><p>We now have to transform the basis function to an appropriate range for multiplication, i.e. f t (x) = (1 + d t ) g t <ref type="bibr">(x)</ref> .</p><p>The proposed method for detecting tissue interfaces works very well even for data with low signal-to-noise ratio, but it does not detect the correct interface in every single case. On the other hand, it might even happen that there is no interface at all to detect, since the position of the tube core is outside the anatomical structures we want to visualize. Therefore, we have to provide means to detect these cases and eliminate their influence on the final OTF. There are two constraints at hand for determining the reliability of surface detection. First, the maximum intensity before the surface must not exceed a certain value. Otherwise, we either detected too deep an interface, or the entire tube core is located within hyperechoic tissue. Hence, we compute a quality measure w tÎ for each tube core t based on the evaluation of the mean intensities I(C t i ) of all cells C t i prior to the detected surface s t . LetÎ t L be the maximum of these intensity values, i.e.Î t L = max</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">i&lt;s t I(C t i ).<label>(12)</label></formula><p>We then compute the histogram hÎ of the maximum intensitiesÎ t L of all tube cores t. By accumulation and normalization of the histogram we finally obtain the quality factor w tÎ for a specific tube core t with maximum intensityÎ t L :</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">w tÎ = 1 − 1 NÎ t L ∑ I=0 hÎ(I),<label>(13)</label></formula><p>with N the total number of tube cores. We obtain a second quality measure w t S in a similar way based on the histogram h S of intensity slopes S t at the detected surface position s t of every tube core t. Again, accumulation and normalization of the histogram allows us to assess a quality factor w t S for a specific tube core t with slope S t :</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">w t S = 1 N ∑ S t S=0 h S (S) if S &gt; 0 0 otherwise.<label>(14)</label></formula><p>w tÎ and w t S allow the elimination of any influence of tube cores located within tissue of constant echogenicity, but also a reduction of the influence of surfaces with weak manifestation. In addition, we also exclude all tube cores with negative slope of intensity at the surface position, thereby eliminating the drawback of the chosen interface indicating function. We use the quality measures w tÎ and w t S to modulate the parameter d t in (11): We choose</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">d t = d max • w tÎ • w t S .<label>(15)</label></formula><p>The graph of all basis functions for the volume rendered in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> is depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Results</head><p>For the visualization of the 199 × 197 × 199 voxel data set in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> we use a grid of 15 × 15 tube cores with an inter-tube core distance of 13 voxels in each direction and a cell size of 5 × 5 × 5 voxels. The size of the Gaussian kernels employed for setting up the scale space is 2 n , 3 ≤ n ≤ 7. Both the original and the modified OTF are depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>. By a highly efficient implementation of the proposed algorithm using the Intel R C++ Compiler 7.0 and Intel R VTune TM Performance Analyzer 7.0 we yield an OTF for this volume within 29.38 milliseconds on a 2.5 GHz Intel R Pentium R 4based PC with 512 MB RAM. Thus, we could compute an optimal OTF at a rate of 34 volumes per second. It is worth mentioning that we did not optimize volume data access assuming that data access is one task of the ray-casting / interpolation subsystem. Expectedly, surface detection is by a factor of more than 5 more demanding than the iterative OTF design, even though scalespace has been implemented by an FFT.</p><p>Further examples of the quality one can obtain by following our approach are depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 9</ref>. These are data sets of moderate quality as they often arise in 3D ultrasound imaging in clinical settings. Of course the proposed method also yields excellent results for data sets of superior quality, such as in <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref>.  <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref>: The adaptive OTF design also yields superior results for high quality data sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Conclusions</head><p>We presented a novel technique for adaptively designing an opacity transfer function for a sonographic data set in real time. By analyzing tube cores we yield an estimate for the position of the most prominent tissue transition, in rendering direction, in a highly efficient way. We analyze the tube core cells prior to and at the detected interface and use this information to adaptively design an initial, parabolic OTF in a multiplicative way. Of course, the tube core modification can also be applied to OTFs of different shape. E.g., for visualization of hypoechoic lesions or cysts, a monotonically decreasing OTF, modified by a variant of our approach, could be used.</p><p>In the case of fetal scans, there often is different echogenicity of amniotic fluid even within a single data set. There are two approaches to handle these situations: First, interactive placement of the tube cores by the user allows optimal visualization of a region of interest. Unfortunately, movement of the ultrasound transducer requires repeated user interaction. A more suitable solution of this problem is a modification of the proposed technique towards individually designing OTFs for rendering of subsets of the volume. This adaptable volume processing approach would allow simultaneous visualization of the volume subsets by individually designed OTFs. Care has to be taken to obtain a smooth transition between "neighboring" OTFs, otherwise artifacts may arise.</p><p>Finally, consider that we do not aim at a fully automatic determination of the OTF, as the "optimal" OTF does not only depend on the data set but also on the diagnostic task. Our technique provides a default OTF for a specific volume and view, which can be modified by the user by an easy to understand parameter, namely the maximum opacity. This parameter influences the overall transparency of the volume. Once set, this parameter may remain constant as long as the view does not change significantly.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Depth contrast ∆C of a spatial discontinuity of constant signal intensity from k * = 10 to k * = 50, using an OTF α(c) = ac. Depth contrast ∆C of a spatial discontinuity as inFigure 3(a), using an OTF α(c) = ac 2 . Depth contrast ∆C of a spatial discontinuity as inFigure 3(a), using an OTF α(c) = ac 4 . Tissue contrast ∆C of a discontinuity in tissue echogenicity at k * = 50 from c 1 to c * 1 , c 2 = 0.2, using an OTF α(c) = ac. Tissue contrast ∆C of a discontinuity in tissue echogenicity as inFigure 3(d), using an OTF α(c) = ac 2 . Tissue contrast ∆C of a discontinuity in tissue echogenicity as inFigure 3(d), using an OTF α(c) = ac 4 . Relative tissue contrast ∆C/(c 1 − c * 1 ) of a discontinuity in tissue echogenicity as inFigure 3(d), using an OTF α(c) = ac. Relative tissue contrast ∆C/(c 1 − c * 1 ) of a discontinuity in tissue echogenicity as inFigure 3(d), using an OTF α(c) = ac 2 . Relative tissue contrast ∆C/(c 1 − c * 1 ) of a discontinuity in tissue echogenicity as inFigure 3(d), using an OTF α(c) = ac 4 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Effect of choosing different OTFs on the contrast caused by a spatial discontinuity and a discontinuity in tissue echogenicity. Maximum opacity for all OTFs is a = 0.1. For details see sections 4.2 and 4.3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Signal intensity profile of the ultrasound data set of Figure 1. The position of an interface between tissue of different echogenicity is indicated by a dot. For the position of the profile see Figure 5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>(a) shows the depth contrast ∆C = C(c 1 , c 2 , k * = 10) − C(c 1 , c 2 , k * = 50) arising from a linear OTF for every combination of voxel intensities c 1 and c 2 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Two orthogonal cross sections of the ultrasound data set ofFigure 1. The position of the intensity profile ofFigure 4is between the yellow lines. The position of the interface between amniotic fluid and fetal head detected by analysis of a tube core is indicated by short red lines.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>The interface indicating function and the position of the interface between amniotic fluid and fetal head in Figure 4 and Figure 5 is depicted in blue.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Dotted: initial parabolic OTF. Solid: result of the modification by basis functions of Figure 7, used in Figure 1(c). Dashed: manually adjusted piecewise linear OTF used in Figure 1(b).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Further results of adaptive OTF design applied to moderate quality data sets arising frequently in clinical settings. The original OTF is indicated as dotted line, the adapted OTF as solid line.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">An extension of this method towards multidimensional transfer functions byKniss et al.  aims at the visualization of multivariate volume data<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[Kniss et al. 2002]</ref>.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Acknowledgment</head><p>The authors would like to acknowledge the contributions of Armin Schoisswohl of GE Medical Systems Kretztechnik, Zipf, Austria, in providing the 3D ultrasound data sets and valuable discussions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The contour spectrum</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bajaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pascucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Schikore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization &apos;97, Proceedings, IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">539</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="173" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Three-dimensional ultrasound imaging. In Handbook of Medical Imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fenster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Downey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>J. Beutel, H. L. Kundel, and R. L. V. Metter</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="463" to="509" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>1 ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume data mining using 3d field topology analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fujishiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Takeshima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Azuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation of transfer functions with stochastic search techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization &apos;96. Proceedings., IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page">489</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast volume rendering with adjustable color maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kaneda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dobashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Symposium on Volume Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="14" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semi-automatic generation of transfer functions for direct volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Durkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Symposium on Volume Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">170</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="86" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidimensional transfer functions for interactive volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Display of surfaces from volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design galleries: a general approach to setting parameters for computer graphics and animation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Andalman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bearsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gib-Son</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hodgins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mirtich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ruml</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ryall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Seims</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shieber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH 97</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="400" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional ultrasound imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pretorius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ultrasound in Medicine and Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1243" to="1270" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The volumepro real-time ray-casting system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hardenbergh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knittel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Seiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH 99</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="260" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The transfer function bake-off. multidimensional transfer functions for interactive volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bajaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Avila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Raghu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Machiraju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jinho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic adjustment of transfer functions for direct volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rezk-Salama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hastreiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Scherer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Greiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Vision, Modeling, and Visualization</title>
		<meeting>Vision, Modeling, and Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="357" to="364" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting surfaces from fuzzy 3d ultrasound data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM SIGGRAPH 1995, ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="474" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preprocessing and volume rendering of 3d ultrasonic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-A</forename><surname>Schreyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grimm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IEEE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tissue classification based on 3d local intensity structures for volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Westin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bhalerao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nakajima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shiraga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">160</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive transfer function modification for volume rendering using compressed sample runs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Chebrolu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics International</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scale-space filtering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Witkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<meeting>International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1019" to="1022" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
