<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Curved Anatomic Structures with Surface Sections</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Saroul</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne*</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><surname>Gerlach</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne*</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roger</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hersch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne*</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Curved Anatomic Structures with Surface Sections</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:51+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.3 [Computer Graphics]: Picture/Image Generation -Viewing Algorithms</term>
					<term>I.3.6 [Computer Graphics]: Methodology and Techniques -Interaction Techniques</term>
					<term>J.3 [Computer Applications]: Life and Medical sciences visualization, anatomic structures, curved sections, surface extraction, interactive flattening</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The extraction of planar sections from volume images is the most commonly used technique for inspecting and visualizing anatomic structures. We propose to generalize the concept of planar section to the extraction of curved cross-sections (free form surfaces). Compared with planar slices, curved cross-sections may easily follow the trajectory of tubular structures and organs such as the aorta or the colon. They may be extracted from a 3D volume, displayed as a 3D view and possibly flattened. Flattening of curved cross-sections allows to inspect spatially complex relationship between anatomic structures and their neighbourhood. They also allow to carry out measurements along a specific orientation. For the purpose of facilitating the interactive specification of free form surfaces, users may navigate in real time within the body and select the slices on which the surface control points will be positioned. Immediate feedback is provided by displaying boundary curves as cylindrical markers within a 3D view composed of anatomic organs, planar slices and possibly free form surface sections. Extraction of curved surface sections is an additional service that is available online as a Java applet (http://visiblehuman.epfl.ch). It may be used as an advanced tool for exploring and teaching anatomy.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>State of the art tomographic imaging systems allow to visualize planar slices having an arbitrary orientation. Planar slices enable radiologists to inspect organs for diagnostic purposes. Planar slices are also useful for teaching anatomy. However, oblique planar slices do not always allow to adequately follow curved anatomic structures. For instance, planar cross sections do not allow to see the continuity of tubular structures, such as the vena cava ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 1a)</ref>.</p><p>For visualizing such structures, one may specify and extract a ruled surface <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1b</ref>) from the original volume (an operation called curved planar reformation). However, ruled surfaces are not well suited for visualizing structures with many branches such as an arterial tree. Ruled surfaces are also too restricted for tracking anatomic structures with irregular geometry such as the pelvis. In this paper, we propose to extend the notion of cross section, which generally designates the extraction of a planar slice, to the extraction of free form surfaces. In contrast to planar slices, surfaces may follow curved anatomic structures. By flattening such surfaces, one may inspect these structures and their neighbourhood. a) Planar slice b) Flattened ruled surface <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. A ruled surface extracted from the Visible Human shows the continuity of the vena cava.</p><p>One challenge resides in offering interaction means facilitating the specification of surfaces following winded tubular structures within a 3D volume. To meet this challenge, we introduce surface specification tools which rely on interactive slicing and on the placement of marker points inside the volume. A second challenge resides in proposing a free form surface flattening paradigm meeting the expectation of the user, i.e. minimizing the distortions close to a curve of interest and preserving distances along a user specified orientation.</p><p>In Section 2, we outline possible approaches for surface extraction. In Section 3, we describe how to specify ruled surfaces along trajectories following tubular anatomic structures. In Section 4, we introduce our free form surface extraction and flattening methods. In Sections 5 and 6, we describe an application integrating interactive surface specification, extraction *Peripheral System Laboratory, {laurent.saroul, sebastian.gerlach, rd.hersch}@epfl.ch <ref type="bibr">IEEE Visualization 2003</ref><ref type="bibr">, October 19-24, 2003</ref>, Seattle, Washington, USA 0-7803-8120-3/03/$17.00 ©2003 IEEE and display, together with the display of the surrounding anatomic structures. Conclusions and possible future improvements are presented in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Possible approaches</head><p>The simplest approach for specifying a ruled surface is to let the user specify a trajectory on an oblique slice and define the ruling vector perpendicular to this slice <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[Figueiredo and Hersch 2002]</ref>. For angiography applications, paths inside vascular tree structures may be computed and corresponding ruled surfaces may be extracted <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[He et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kanitsar et al. 2002]</ref>. These multiple surfaces are flattened onto the same image but discontinuities are unavoidable.</p><p>In order to be able to visualize branching structures without introducing discontinuities, we propose to lay out a Coons surface across the different branches of a tubular structure. Since the 3D display of a surface does not allow to inspect all surface parts within a single view, we introduce a user-driven flattening method particularly well suited for interactive applications. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Haker et al. [1999]</ref> propose a technique to flatten the brain surface both for anatomical study and for analyzing functional magnetic resonance images. A discretized Laplace Beltrami operator maps a topological sphere onto a disc by globally minimizing distortions. Similar methods are applied to the 3D visualization of colon CT images <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[Haker et al. 2000]</ref>. For cylindrical anatomic structures, attempts were made, for instance for virtual colonoscopy, to project the colon's surface onto a cylinder for virtual colonoscopy <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Bartroli et al. 2001]</ref>. These surface flattening methods are not adapted to our problem since they are designed for the flattening of precomputed organ surfaces models and not for inspecting surfaces crossing sets of organs or tubular structures. Furthermore, they do not provide support for interactivity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Specification and extraction of ruled surfaces</head><p>We first consider ruled surfaces for tracking curved anatomic structures. We focus our attention on ruled surfaces with a directrix ( ) t α and a ruling vector of constant orientation p :</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">( , ) ( ) t t p σ ν α ν = +<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Such ruled surfaces are developable and easy to define, since they only require the definition of the directrix ( ) t α and of the ruling vector p . A ruled surface may therefore be easily specified by a 2D natural spline located in a planar cross-section, with its ruling vector orthogonal to that cross section <ref type="figure">(Fig. 1</ref>).</p><p>However, a ruled surface whose directrix is located within a plane does not allow to easily visualize non-planar tubular structures such as the aorta. To provide support for specifying true 3D trajectories, we propose, by interactive slicing, to interactively move forward and backward within the 3D volume and place directrix control points (marker points) within the considered tubular structure, e.g. the aorta or the vena cava.</p><p>As ruling vector, we choose a vector orthogonal to the main orientations of the curve. Indeed, if the ruling vector is not adequately chosen, two ruling lines Structures intersected by these lines may then be present at two different locations within the resulting flattened surface, making the image interpretation difficult. Compared with <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Kanitsar et al. [2002]</ref> where the ruling vector has a fixed orientation within the (Oxy) plane, our method allows to compute the most adequate ruling vector automatically by avoiding as much as possible cases where ruling lines become identical. To offer additional freedom and improve the visualization, users are allowed to rotate the ruling vector in the plane orthogonal to the main orientation of the 3D trajectory.</p><p>The main orientations of the 3D trajectory are computed using principal component analysis. The trajectory is first represented by a polyline, i.e. a set of discretization points { , ,...., } S = 1 2 n x x</p><p>x .</p><p>We compute the center of gravity G of this set, and the covariance matrix B, taking into account G and all points of S:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">1 1 ( ) . ( ) 1 n T i B n = = − − − i G i G x x x x<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Since covariance matrix B is symmetric, the normalized eigenvectors of B form a local coordinate system <ref type="bibr">( , , , )</ref> a b c G x x x with center G and axes , ,  We may change the orientation of the ruled surface by rotating ruling vector p in the plane ( , , )</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">b c G x x cos sin b c p x x θ θ θ = ⋅ + ⋅ (3) a) b) c)</formula><p>Figure 3. Extraction of ruled surfaces following the aorta, with different ruling vectors.</p><p>After discretization of the surface into rectangular facets, the labeled texture of the surface is extracted from the 3D volume image and visualized ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 3)</ref>. Such a ruled surface allows to visualize an entire section of the aorta together with its neighbourhood. By rotating p θ up to 180°, one may scan the full 3D neighbourhood of the considered trajectory.</p><p>In order to obtain a global view of the surface within a single image, one may flatten the ruled surface without introducing is first approximated by a polyline, whose segments, together with the ruling vector, define a succession of rectangular facets. These rectangular facets are resampled according to the display grid. Corresponding voxels are extracted from the 3D volume data using nearest-neighbour or trilinear interpolation. Facets parts are then merged into the final display buffer <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Fig. 4</ref>). By being able to display the entire surface within a single image, one may quickly and precisely inspect it without having to rotate the view and possibly miss certain parts of the surface <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 5</ref>). Since flattened ruled surfaces preserve distances, accurate distance measurements are possible. Furthermore, since each pixel on the flattened surface can be selected precisely, marker points can easily be placed and their 3D coordinates displayed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Free Form Surfaces</head><p>Despite their usefulness, ruled surfaces do not offer enough flexibility for visualizing irregular anatomic structures such as the pelvis or the jaw. Furthermore, with a ruled surface, it is difficult to define a surface section that passes through a part of the aorta tree, i.e. the aorta together with its outgoing tubular structures. To offer a higher degree of freedom, we propose to use free form surfaces as visualization means.</p><p>The first difficulty is to find a method which enables an easy and accurate placement of a surface within a 3D volume. A second challenge resides in proposing an intuitive user-driven flattening method for free form surfaces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Specification and extraction of free form surfaces</head><p>With Coons free form surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[Hoschek and Lasser 1993]</ref>, users may interactively place boundary curves along structures of interest. The surface interpolates these boundary curves. <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. Surface interpolation between curves.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">P(0,1) P(1,1) P(1,0) P(0,0) P(u,v) u v</formula><p>To facilitate the placement of the marker points defining the desired Coons surface boundary curves, users may navigate in real time across the volume (Section 5). On the desired slices, they may position marker points. Each set of successive marker points defines a surface boundary curve. The surface interpolating the boundary curves may then be extracted from the 3D volume and displayed in 3D, together with other related anatomic structures.</p><p>Let us describe the construction of Coons surfaces. Given n boundary cubic splines specified by the user, varying along the u parameter, the two other boundary cubic splines are constructed which pass through the extremities of these n curves <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6</ref>, red curves). The resulting system of boundary curves is interpolated by Coons patches <ref type="bibr">[Hoschek and Lasser 1993, pp. 371-382]</ref>. Starting with the n curves specified by user, we can construct n-1 Coons patches by carrying out for each patch the following interpolation 0 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">1 1 0 0 1 1 ( ) ( ) ( , ) ( ( ,0), ( ,1)) ( (0, ), (1, )) ( ) ( ) ( ) (0,0) (0,1) ( ( ), ( )) (1,0) (1,1) ( ) f v fu P u v P u P u P v P v f v fu f v P P f u f u P P f v = + − (4) ( ) t α p ( ) t α′ (1,1) v P (0,1) v P ( ,1) v c P u ( ,0) c P u ( ,1) c P u (1, ) P v (0, ) P v</formula><p>Boundary curve specified by markers Computed boundary curve</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(0, ) u P v</formula><p>where ( , ) P i v and ( , ) P u i are the parametric representations of the boundary curves for 0,1 i = and where i f are blending functions.</p><p>Since each boundary curve is a cubic spline with 2 C continuity, the corresponding patch has also 2 C continuity. We choose cubic Hermite polynomials as blending functions, which satisfy the continuity conditions</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">1, ( ) 0, i i k i k f k i k δ = = = ≠ and ( ) 0, i f k ′ = for , 0,1. i k =<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Thus, derivatives of the patch along boundaries are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">0 1 0 1 ( , ) ( ,0). ( ) ( ,1). ( ) ( , ) (0, ). ( ) (1, ). ( ) u u u v v v P i v P i f v P i f v P u i P i f u P i f u = + = + for 0,1. i =<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Using these functions, the tangent vectors to the curve <ref type="bibr">( , )</ref> c P u v at the point <ref type="bibr">( ,1)</ref>   <ref type="figure">(Fig. 6)</ref>. In contrast to bi-cubic patches <ref type="bibr">[Hoschek and Lasser 1993, pp. 382-385]</ref>, the presented bilinear interpolation with Hermite polynomials does not require to specify the derivatives along boundary curves <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>. Curved section revealing the variation of the aorta lumen diameter.</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">( ,0), v P u ( ,1), v P u (0, ) u P v and (1, ) u P v . a) b)</formula><p>As an example, a surface across the aorta is constructed by specifying boundary curves within several distant axial slices crossing the aorta <ref type="figure">(Fig. 7a)</ref>. The boundary curves are oriented according to the lumen's main diameter. The resulting surface follows the largest aorta diameter and reveals diameter variations <ref type="figure">(Fig. 7b</ref>).</p><p>As a further example, we construct a surface passing through the aorta, the subclavian, the carotid and the brachiocephalic arteries. This surface is then extracted and displayed together with a 3D view of the aorta and the corresponding arteries <ref type="figure">(Fig. 8b)</ref> or alone <ref type="figure">(Fig. 8c)</ref>. This allows to illustrate the connections between the aorta and the outgoing arteries. a) b) c) <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>. Curved section passing through a part of the aorta tree.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flattening of Coons surfaces</head><p>Coons surfaces are not developable, i.e. it is not possible to unfold them without distortions. The unfolding of non developable surfaces is the inverse problem of texture mapping. In texture mapping, a planar image is mapped to a surface by globally minimizing distortions on the resulting 3D surface <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Salomon 1999</ref>]. In our case, we would like to map a texture laid out on a surface onto the plane. Instead of globally minimizing distortions, we prefer to minimize distortions in a region of interest in order to inspect it with a higher precision. In addition, we may preserve distances along a user specified orientation. The user may then interactively modify the region of interest and the orientation of distance preservation in order to observe successive regions of interest.</p><p>In a previous approach to surface flattening, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bennis et al. [1991]</ref> unfold a parametric surface by flattening neighbouring transversal isoparametric curves v C (v=const) so as to preserve both arc length and geodesic curvature <ref type="figure">(Fig. 9</ref>). This surface flattening method is not well suited for our application, since it does not provide an intuitive feeling about how metric distortions are distributed on the resulting flattened image. Indeed, within the flattened image, distances are not preserved along a specific direction but along curved lines <ref type="figure">(Fig. 9b, red curves)</ref>. . Flattening of a parametric surface according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bennis et al. [1991]</ref>.</p><p>Due to the preservation of the geodesic curvature along the curves, this method may also introduce self intersections between unfolded transversal curves. To provide a more intuitive</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">v C v C′ S S′</formula><p>distribution of metrics distortions and allow to choose the desired orientation of distance preservation, we propose to reparameterize the surface before carrying out the flattening step. Such a reparameterization may ensure that transversal isoparametric curves correspond to the intersection between the surface and parallel planes of constant orientation. These transversal curves are then flattened into straight lines with distance preservation. In contrast to <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[Bennis et al. 1991]</ref>, where arc length is preserved along curves defined by the initial parameterization, our method allows to choose the desired orientation of arc length preservation. In addition, by construction, it prevents the apparition of self intersections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Algorithm Description</head><p>In a first step, the user selects a curve</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">0 u C 0 m a x { ,0 } u u v v =</formula><p>≤ ≤ on the surface S as the reference curve for flattening purpose. The angular distortions will be minimized along this curve <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">(Fig. 10)</ref>. Then, a plane orientation { , } P a b = is chosen according to the desired orientation along which distances should be preserved. One may define the plane orientation interactively or it may be computed automatically, e.g. as a plane orthogonal to the main orientation of the reference curve C into a plane by preserving the geodesic curvature 2 at each sample point and by preserving the distance between points, according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[Bennis et al. 1991</ref> Each facet (quadrilateral) of the resulting flattened surface is sampled according to the display grid. The corresponding colors are then extracted from the 3D volume image by nearest neighbour or trilinear interpolation. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 11</ref> shows a curved surface following the aorta and the corresponding flattened surface obtained with the algorithm described above. A grid showing the curves along which distances are preserved may be superposed on the flattened image <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">(Fig.  11c</ref>). Since distances, within the resulting flattened image, are preserved along a constant orientation <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">(Fig. 11c)</ref>, the distribution of metric distortions becomes rather intuitive. Measurements may be carried out along that orientation.   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 12</ref> shows the flattening of a surface passing through the aorta tree. In order to minimize the distortions within a different area, one may choose another band of interest by selecting a different curve of reference. A different orientation of the planes j P may also be specified ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 12b and 12c)</ref>. The new flattened surface is then recomputed.</p><p>The proposed surface flattening method provides a global view of a curved section within a single image, without introducing discontinuities. Distortions are present but the user may interactively choose their distribution and therefore inspect accurately all the surface parts. Flattened views may be used for illustrating properties of curved anatomic structures or for carrying out measurements along a user specified orientation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Interactive specification of surfaces</head><p>In order to interactively specify in 3D space the boundary curves or trajectories defining a surface of interest, we use both interactive slicing across the volume image and the 3D display of organ surfaces and slices. Interactive slicing <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[Gerlach and Hersch 2002]</ref> enables navigating within the Visible Human volume image <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[Ackerman 1998</ref>] by continuously extracting slices at a speed of several slices per second, according to the displacement of the mouse (backward and forward translation, rotation, zoom). The 3D visualization interface <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[Evesque et al. 2002</ref>] allows users to construct 3D anatomical scenes by combining planar slices and 3D anatomical structures which may be selected and automatically loaded from the Visible Human server. User may zoom in and out, rotate and translate the scene as well as displace and rotate the planar slices located within the scene.</p><p>To accurately place points within the 3D volume, one should preferably use the interactive real time navigator for slicing through the volume data and halt on the slices on which marker points are to be specified. For understanding the 3D context, the current slice is displayed both in the real time navigator and in the 3D visualization interface, together with surrounding organ surface models ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Fig. 13)</ref>. At any time, both views may be synchronized. This facilitates interactive and dynamic positioning of slices by mouse displacements. Users may also modify the position of the slice in the 3D view by dragging it to the desired location and simultaneously see the corresponding movement in the slice navigator.</p><p>The presented approach relying on the synchronization between the slice navigator interface and the 3D viewer is similar to the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[Gering et al. 1999]</ref>, used in surgical planning applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interactive specification of trajectories and boundary curves</head><p>By combining the real time slice navigation and the 3D visualization interface, users may specify trajectories or boundary curves within the 3D volume by using markers. Markers are fat 3D cubic spline curves defined by several user-specified control points (marker points). Marker points may be freely placed by clicking with the mouse at the desired position on the selected slice. The markers are extruded as cylinders. Their intersection with the current slice is displayed <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Fig. 14, right view)</ref>.</p><p>However, the real time navigator does not provide a global view of the curve. The 3D visualization interface displays the marker as a 3D cylinder along the curve <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Fig. 14, left view)</ref>. By making organ models appear as partly transparent surfaces, the 3D curvilinear marker and its surrounding anatomic structures can be displayed simultaneously. In the example of <ref type="figure">Fig.</ref> 14, the aorta model is displayed in transparency and reveals the 3D marker curve located inside it. Since both views are synchronized, the current marker shape is displayed in 3D while it is being specified by placing control points with the real time slice navigator. This ensures an optimal interactivity and an accurate placement of the marker splines. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 14</ref>. Simultaneous display of a marker in the slice navigator and in the 3D visualization interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Exploration of anatomic structures with surfaces and 3D models</head><p>Let us summarize how users may make use of our interactive application to inspect anatomic structure of interest. In a first step, organ models surrounding the structures of interest are loaded and displayed in the 3D visualization interface <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 15a)</ref>. Then, using interactive slicing and thanks to the synchronized 3D display of the scene, marker points are positioned within the volume image. After specifying several boundary curves (markers), the application computes the resulting free form surface and requests from the server to extract the corresponding surface texture elements from the volume image. The surface elements are extracted from the 3D volume and sent back to the client for display. The boundary curves may be modified in order to adjust the shape or the location of the surface. Compared with conventional curved sections, free form surfaces allow to follow non tubular structures, such as the sternum and the costal cartilage. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 15</ref> shows a surface passing through the sternum and costal cartilages and the resulting flattened image. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 16</ref> shows a surface following the jaw. The flattened image reveals all teeth within a single image. The simultaneous display of surfaces and organs greatly facilitates the understanding and the interpretation of the flattened images.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>In the present contribution, we generalize the concept of planar slices, which are widely used in medical imaging, to curved crosssections. Curved cross-sections such as ruled surfaces or free form surfaces extracted from 3D volume images enable an accurate visualization of curved anatomic structures.</p><p>We integrate the curved cross-section extraction into an interactive slicing application allowing to visualize both the current slice and its representation within the surrounding anatomic scene. Combining the 2D slice view and the 3D scene view enables users to accurately position in 3D the control points determining the location and properties of the desired curved section. Free form surface boundaries as well as ruled surface trajectories are displayed as fat 3D cylindrical curves, visible both at their intersection with the current slice and within the 3D view.</p><p>Flattening of ruled and free form surfaces enables to follow curved anatomic structures. Free form surfaces are especially well suited for tracking tubular tree structures such as the vascular or arterial trees. While the flattening of a ruled surface is straightforward, flattening of a free form surface needs to be intuitive, i.e. the user should be able to specify the regions of the surface which should be reproduced at a high fidelity. We present a first solution to the "interactive flattening" problem by minimizing distortions along a band of interest, i.e. a band whose central curve is a user-selected constant parameter curve. We also allow users to specify an orientation, along which distances are preserved.</p><p>For a thorough inspection of a surface, the user may successively select different bands of interest. He may also carry out measurements along the orientation along which distances are preserved. In the near future, we intend to further extend the interactive flattening paradigm in order to allow users to freely specify their region of interest and to provide information about the locations and the amplitudes of the distortions.</p><p>The present application is available on the Web, as an additional service offered by the Visible Human server (http://visiblehuman.epfl.ch). It provides both to the general public and to the professionals interested in anatomy an additional tool for visualizing complex anatomic structures and their intricate relationships.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and is used as the ruling vector p(Fig. 2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 2. Computation of the ruling vector</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Flattening a ruled surface.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Flattened ruled surfaces following the aorta (with three different ruling vectors).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 9. Flattening of a parametric surface according to Bennis et al. [1991].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>surface along u, we obtain a set of curves u C ( u const = ). For each sample point j M of the initial curve 0 u C , the plane j P of orientation P passing trough j M is computed. The intersection points between j P and the family of curves u C provide a discrete representation of the intersection of the surface and plane j P (Fig. 10) 1 . By iterating along all sample points of 0 u C , we obtain a family of discrete curves h C . Each discrete curve h C corresponds to the intersection of a plane j P and the family of curves u C . With the new parameterization defined by the family of curves u C and the family of curves h C , the flattening algorithm runs as follow: 1. Map the initial curve 0 u</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>of double intersections between the plane j P and the surface S, we choose the intersection curve closest to the previously computed intersection curve 1 h C − .2  The geodesic curvature g k of a curve ( ) C s belonging to a surface S, at a point X, is the norm of the derivative of the tangential vector g t of ( ) C s at X according to the arc length parameter s, i.e. ( ) Flattening of a Coons surface preserving distances along a user-specified orientation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Flattening of a free form surface following the aorta.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Flattening of a free form surface passing through the aorta tree with different orientations of distance preservation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Synchronization between views.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 16 .</head><label>16</label><figDesc>a) 3D view b) Flattened view Figure 15. Surface following the costal cartilage and the sternum. Surface section passing through the jaw.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors would like to thank Peter Ratiu from Harvard Medical School for creating the images of <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. We also thank Jean Pierre Hornung, Beat Riederer and their students from the Medical School of the University of Lausanne for helpful discussions about the visualization interface and for suggesting anatomic structures of interest.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Appendix: Curve flattening with arc length and geodesic curvature preservation (according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[Bennis et al. 1991</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>])</head><p>Let us recall that surface curves are approximated by polylines. A curve C that is to be mapped onto the plane contains</p><p>Let us denote by i n and i p T , respectively, the normal vector and the tangent plane to the surface at point M − given by the formulas: This curve flattening algorithm preserves the geodesic curvature at each sample point and the arc length between sample points.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Visible Human Project</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ackerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the IEEE</title>
		<meeting>of the IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="504" to="511" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual Colon Flattening</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Bartroli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Wegenkittl R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>König</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Gröller E</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE TCVG Symposium on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE TCVG Symposium on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="136" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Piecewise Surface Flattening For Non-distorted Texture Mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vézien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Iglésias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics, SIGGRAPH´</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building 3D Anatomical Scenes on the Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Evesque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gerlach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Visualization and Computer Animation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallel Unfolding and Visualization of Curved Surfaces Extracted From Large Three Dimensional Volumes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Figueiredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Electronic Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="433" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Integrated Visualization System for Surgical Planning and Guidance using Image Fusion and Interventional Imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nabavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Grimson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Everett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jolesz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Second International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention (MICCAI)</title>
		<meeting>the Second International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention (MICCAI)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="809" to="819" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Real-Time Navigator For The Visible Human</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gerlach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Internet Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the Laplace-Beltrami Operator and Brain Surface Flattening</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Angenent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tannenbaun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="700" to="711" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nondistorting Flattening For Virtual Colonoscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Angenent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tannenbaun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Third International Conference On Medical Robotics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Medial Axis Reformation: A New Visualization Method For CT Angiography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Academic Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="726" to="733" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fundamentals of Computer Aided Geometric Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hoschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="387" />
			<pubPlace>AK Peters</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CPR -Curved Planar Reformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kanitsar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fleischmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Felkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Visualization 2002 (Vis02)</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Visualization 2002 (Vis02)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="44" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computer Graphics &amp; Geometric Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Salomon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="552" to="556" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
