<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Reflection Nebula Visualization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marcus</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Magnor</surname></persName>
							<email>magnor@mpi-sb.mpg.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kristian</forename><surname>Hildebrand</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrei</forename><surname>Lintu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
							<email>hanson@cs.indiana.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">MPI Informatik</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">MPI Informatik</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">MPI Informatik</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Indiana University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Reflection Nebula Visualization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-20T19:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.3 [Computer Graphics]: Picture/Image Generation-Viewing algorithms</term>
					<term>I.3.7 [Computer Graphics]: Three-Dimensional Graphics and Realism-Color, shading, shadowing, and texture</term>
					<term>J.2 [Computer Applications]: Physical Sciences and Engineering-Astronomy volume rendering, global illumination, dust, nebula, astronomy</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Stars form in dense clouds of interstellar gas and dust. The residual dust surrounding a young star scatters and diffuses its light, making the star&apos;s &quot;cocoon&quot; of dust observable from Earth. The resulting structures, called reflection nebulae, are commonly very colorful in appearance due to wavelength-dependent effects in the scattering and extinction of light. The intricate interplay of scattering and extinction cause the color hues, brightness distributions, and the apparent shapes of such nebulae to vary greatly with viewpoint. We describe here an interactive visualization tool for realistically rendering the appearance of arbitrary 3D dust distributions surrounding one or more illuminating stars. Our rendering algorithm is based on the physical models used in astrophysics research. The tool can be used to create virtual fly-throughs of reflection nebulae for interactive desktop visualizations, or to produce scientifically accurate animations for educational purposes, e.g., in planetarium shows. The algorithm is also applicable to investigate on-the-fly the visual effects of physical parameter variations, exploiting visualization technology to help gain a deeper and more intuitive understanding of the complex interaction of light and dust in real astrophysical settings.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Reflection nebulae are among the most colorful objects in the night sky, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>, which is why science fiction movies and popular science journals frequently feature pictures of these captivating interstellar entities. Besides their aesthetic appeal, reflection nebulae also have considerable scientific relevance. They are the birth places of new stars, and their astrophysical study reveals new insights into star formation and stellar composition. Interesting physics is also responsible for the colorful visual appearance of reflection nebulae. The intricate interplay of wavelength-dependent light scattering and extinction gives rise to large variations in color hue and brightness. Depending on the viewpoint, reflection nebulae exhibit wide variations in appearance; unfortunately, we cannot witness these variations directly for any single nebula because, since our observational vantage point is fixed on or near the Earth, we cannot appreciably change our viewing angle. This makes virtual tours of reflection nebulae a popular target of virtual astronomy animations. 3D tours of astronomical nebulae in current planetarium shows typically begin from real observational data, and include varying de- grees of artistic work to generate the views from non-Earth viewpoints <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. To authentically reproduce the dependence of a nebula's appearance on viewpoint and dust distribution, however, substantial scientific modeling work must be done to faithfully represent the physical environment. Accurate, physics-based 3D visualizations of reflection nebulae are also needed for educational purposes if the goal is to gain a deeper understanding of the complex interactions of light and dust in interstellar space.</p><p>Here we propose a significant extension to the current approach to 3D modeling and visualization of reflection nebulae. Based on the same physical models that are used in astrophysics research, we present an interactive visualization tool for arbitrary threedimensional dust distributions surrounding one or more illuminating stars. Anisotropic scattering characteristics, wavelength dependence, multiple scattering, and trajectory-dependent extinction are taken into account. Besides supplying faithful renderings, our system also supports exploring the visual effects of changing a nebula's physical parameters, an essential visualization function for astrophysical hypothesis checking. The visualization tool can be used in conjunction with synthetic 3D nebula models as well as dust distributions derived from real nebulae, allowing for artistic freedom and scientific rigor at the same time.</p><p>In the following Section, we review related previous work. After an introductory overview of the fundamental physics of reflection nebulae in Section 3, we describe our visualization model in Section 4. Section 5 highlights the interactive rendering algorithm and its implementation in graphics hardware. We present visualization results and discuss our approach in Section 6, before we conclude with an outlook on future extensions in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>255</head><p>Please see supplementary material on conference DVD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IEEE Visualization 2005</head><p>October 23-28, Minneapolis, MN, USA 0-7803-9462-3/05/$20.00 ©2005 IEEE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RELATED WORK</head><p>While tools for visualizing astrophysical simulation results are in common use, only a few publications address visually realistic, physics-based rendering techniques of actual astronomical objects. Nadeau et al. at the San Diego Supercomputer Center (SDSC) created a fly-through animation of the Orion Nebula for the Hayden Planetarium in New York <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. The nebula model was based on astrophysical analysis of decades of observational data <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Rendering the final, 150-second animation at high resolution took 12 hours on SDSC's IBM RS/6000 SP supercomputer using 952 processors <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. More recently, Magnor et al. reconstructed and rendered 3D models of planetary nebulae <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. This work applied emissive volume rendering to interactively visualize the ionized gas on conventional PC graphics hardware. In contrast to planetary nebulae consisting of glowing gas, however, the reflection nebulae considered here do not directly emit visible light. Instead, light from one or more nearby stars is scattered and absorbed by interstellar dust in the stellar neighborhood. While the appearance of a planetary nebula varies with changing viewpoint only in shape and brightness distribution, reflection nebulae additionally change in color due to wavelength-dependent scattering and extinction. This physically different, and considerably more complex, illumination mechanism requires a rendering algorithm for reflection nebulae that accurately takes wavelength-dependent scattering and extinction properties of interstellar dust into account.</p><p>In 1938, Henyey and Greenstein derived analytical expressions for the color and brightness distributions of reflection nebulae for idealized geometrical configurations <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Their optical model of reflection nebulae is generally accepted in astrophysics <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref> and forms the basis of our rendering algorithm.</p><p>In volume rendering terms, a reflection nebula constitutes a participating medium. Volume rendering techniques have been proposed that take into account volumetric absorption and anisotropic scattering characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> as well as the effects of multiple scattering <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>. More recently, advanced algorithms have been presented to better approximate global illumination effects, either for general visualization purposes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, or to obtain more realistic rendering results of natural phenomena exhibiting volumetric scattering characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>. Similar to Riley et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, our visualization approach is based on pre-computing multiplescattering phase functions and tabulating angle-dependent scattering probabilities. Our method can be employed in conjunction with any arbitrary, even experimentally measured, single-particle phase function because we rely on full Monte-Carlo simulations to derive multi-scattering probability density distributions prior to rendering. To be able to pre-compute local illumination per volume element, star illumination geometry and dust distribution are kept fixed. During rendering, viewpoint and viewing direction are freely and interactively navigatable all around as well as through the nebula volume. Our interactive visualization algorithm builds on recent work in ray-based direct volume rendering exploiting modern PC graphics hardware <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>, to which we additionally introduce a hierarchical multi-resolution approach to reproduce large-scale global illumination effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">REFLECTION NEBULAE</head><p>Reflection nebulae are clouds of gas and dust that lie in the vicinity of one or more stars, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>. By scattering the star's light in all directions, the dust becomes visible to us. Besides scattering, interstellar dust also absorbs an appreciable amount of the incident light. In regions of high dust density, most light from beyond the dust cloud is absorbed, forming a so-called dark nebula, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>.</p><p>Reflection nebulae are often associated with very hot stars of spectral class O or B <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Because such hot stars have only a short life span (on the order of 10 6 years in comparison to 10 10 years for our Sun), they must have formed only recently, leading to the conclusion that a reflection nebula represents the remains of the star's protostellar cloud.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Interstellar Dust</head><p>The space between stars is not entirely empty, but is filled with very low density, yet rather filthy, smoke-like gas. If interstellar material were compressed to the density of air, objects would disappear in the haze at a distance of less than one meter <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. This interstellar dust stems predominantly from so-called asymptotic giant branch (AGB) stars, evolved and comparatively cool stars whose stellar wind carries with it large amounts of carbon and silicates from the stars' surface. This stellar "soot" is a mixture of a variety of chemical compounds and represents an ensemble of various different dust particles whose individual dust grain size varies roughly between 100nm and 1µm.</p><p>The scattering properties of a single particle are accurately described by Mie scattering theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. To describe the net optical effect of the very large number of different dust grains illuminated by polychromatic, unpolarized light, astrophysicists frequently resort to only two (weakly wavelength-dependent) scalar parameters: the ensemble values for the albedo and for the single-particle scattering anisotropy of the dust <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. It turns out that these two parameters suffice to correctly characterize the optical properties of interstellar dust to within today's observational accuracy.</p><p>The albedo a = [0, 1] is the ratio of radiosity to irradiance, i.e., the average percentage of radiation incident on a dust particle that is being scattered. If the dust is completely black and all incident light is absorbed, its albedo is zero. In the other extreme, all incident radiation is scattered and the albedo value is one. From the average absorption coefficient σ abs and scattering coefficient σ sct , dust albedo is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">a = σ sct σ abs + σ sct = σ sct σ ext .</formula><p>Absorption and scattering together give rise to light extinction in turbid media, so the sum of both yields the extinction coefficient</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">σ ext = σ abs + σ sct .</formula><p>The size of interstellar dust grains is roughly on the order of the wavelength of visible light. This leads to anisotropic scattering, Each voxel receives direct light from the star, attenuated along the distance r. Part of the illuminating light is scattered towards the observer, depending on the scattering depth τ sct at the voxel (x, y, z) as well as the angle θ between view direction and radial illumination vector. As it traverses the path l from the voxel to the observer, the scattered light undergoes further extinction.</p><p>i.e., the scattering probability is direction-dependent. For spherical particles and unpolarized light, scattering is symmetric around the incident radiation direction, so scattering probability varies only with deflection angle θ , <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>. In astrophysics research, the phase function of interstellar dust is frequently modeled using an analytic expression proposed by Henyey and Greenstein <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">p(θ ) = 1 − g 2 2(1 + g 2 − 2g cos θ ) 3/2 .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>The Henyey-Greenstein phase function has only one free parameter g. This anisotropy factor g denotes the cosine of the mean scattering angle. For a given value of g = [−1, 1], (1) yields the probability distribution p as a function of scattering angle θ . Observations have shown that, within measurement error margins, the optical properties of interstellar dust are the same throughout the galaxy <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. At visible wavelengths, the albedo is a ≈ 0.6, and the scattering anisotropy factor is g ≈ 0.6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. While albedo and scattering anisotropy are more or less constant at visible wavelengths, the scattering coefficient σ sct varies appreciably with wavelength. While blue light is scattered almost twice as often as red light, the exact ratio of scattering prabability at red and blue wavelengths varies somewhat for different regions in the Galaxy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Color</head><p>In astrophysical settings, object color is commonly referred to in terms of band-filtered observations. The Johnson color system features three bands in the visible range of the spectrum that approximately correspond to the RGB colors in computer graphics. The peak filter wavelengths and half-maximum pass bandwidths are 445 ± 47nm for the blue (B band), 551 ± 44nm for the green (visible, V band), and 658 ± 69nm for the red (R band) spectral region <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>Because the scattering coefficient σ sct varies with wavelength, extinction is also wavelength-dependent. The extinction A, extinction depth, or optical depth τ opt = A = σ ext • l is the product of total path length l and the average extinction coefficient σ ext along the way, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>. To express the relative amount of extinction A at different wavelengths λ , the ratio of total to selective visual extinction R V is frequently used in astrophysics. It is related to the slope of the extinction curve A(λ ) near the V band (green).</p><p>Cardelli et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> give an empirical formula to find the extinction A for the U and R band relative to the V band for arbitrary R V values. For the standard value R V = 3.1, relative extinction factors are A B /A V = 1.324 and A R /A V = 0.748 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. In dense clouds, however, R V ≈ 5 which yields A R /A V = 0.8 and A B /A V = 1.2, i.e. scattering increases more slowly with decreasing wavelength, hinting at a slightly larger average particle size. In summary, an individual, average interstellar dust grain scatters light predominantly in the forward direction (g &gt; 0) and is made up of grayish material (a &lt; 1, σ abs (λ ) ≈ const). Because scattering probability increases with decreasing wavelength, scattered light is bluer than the incident light, while transmitted, unscattered light becomes redder.</p><p>Because dust concentrations in reflection nebulae can reach high densities, the illuminating star light may be scattered not only once, but multiple times. The scattering depth τ sct = σ sct l denotes the average number of scattering events that a photon undergoes along a travel path length l. It is directly proportional to dust particle density. For albedo values a &lt; 1, multiple scattering causes the scattered light to diminish because at each scattering event, a fraction (1 − a) of the incident light is absorbed. After n scattering events, only a n of the initial illuminating radiance is still present. Overall scattering anisotropy also decreases with g n , so that after several scattering events, the scattered light is in essence distributed isotropically over all directions.</p><p>To account for multiple scattering exactly, full-fledged, computationally very expensive radiative transfer simulations are required. Alternatively, we propose a hierarchical multi-resolution strategy to take multiple scattering into account, Section 4.2. This enables us to faithfully render nebulae at interactive frame rates without serious impact on the overall accuracy of the appearance for most situations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">VISUALIZATION MODEL</head><p>We discretize the volume of the reflection nebula into volume elements (voxels). Each voxel is assigned its individual scattering depth τ sct = σ sct l, where l is the linear size of the voxel, and the scattering coefficient σ sct is directly proportional to local dust density. Let us assume that one illuminating star is located at the center of the volume, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>. The radiance received by a voxel located at a point (x, y, z) a distance r from the star depends on the star's radiant power Φ star and the optical depth τ opt = τ sct /a accumulated along the way:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">L ill = Φ star 4π r 2 e − r 0 τ opt (r )/r dr .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Voxel illumination L ill does not change with viewpoint, so it can be pre-computed for each voxel, subject to the constraint that dust distribution and illumination geometry stay fixed. Of the illuminating radiance reaching a voxel, a fraction P(τ sct , θ ) is scattered in the observer's direction,</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">L sct = L ill • P(τ sct , θ ) .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>The scattered light L sct must then still travel the path l from the voxel to the observer, along which the light is again attenuated:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">L obs = L sct e − l 0 τ opt (l )/l dl .<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Total observed radiance is derived by summing up L obs from all voxels along each line of sight. The scattering and extinction calculations must be performed for the red, green, and blue channel separately because σ ext and τ sct vary with wavelength, Section 3.2.</p><p>To render a reflection nebula that is lit by more than one star, pervoxel illumination (2) is pre-computed for each illuminating star Figure 4: Directional scattering probability of a voxel P(τ sct , θ ) with albedo a = 0.6 and anisotropy factor g = 0.6 employing the Henyey-Greenstein phase function <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The forward scattering direction is to the right (θ = 0). With increasing scattering depth τ sct , overall scattering first increases, then decreases again. Relative forward scattering also decreases until for the highest scattering depth τ sct = 10, more light is actually being scattered backward than forward due to extinction within the voxel volume.</p><p>separately. During rendering, the scattered radiance per voxel <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">3</ref>is evaluated for all stars. Thanks to the superposition principle, the contributions from all stars to the per-voxel scattered radiance can be simply summed before computing the observed radiance (4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Voxel Scattering Characteristics</head><p>The fraction P(τ sct , θ ) of illumination radiance that is scattered from the voxel into the viewing direction depends on the scattering depth τ sct (i.e., dust density) of the voxel as well as on the deflection angle θ between the incident ray from the star and the viewing direction, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>. Because dust density can be so high that an illuminating photon is likely to be scattered several times within the voxel before exiting, multiple scattering must be taken into account when deriving P(τ sct , θ ). We use Monte-Carlo simulation to pre-compute and tabulate scattering probabilities P(τ sct , θ ) for 1000 scattering depth values between τ sct = 0 and 10, each for 72 directions between cos θ = −1 and +1. The Appendix gives details of the Monte-Carlo simulation. The table is run for the albedo and anisotropy values a = 0.6, g = 0.6 of interstellar dust, as suggested by the astrophysics literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. To explore the effects of albedo and anisotropy variations on reflection nebula appearance, we also compute tables for different albedo and anisotropy values. While we employ here the Henyey-Greenstein phase function (1), note that our approach can be used in conjunction with any arbitrary single-particle phase function. <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> depicts the direction-dependent scattering probability distribution of a voxel for different scattering depths τ sct . Due to multiple scattering, directional dependence changes drastically with voxel scattering depth. With increasing dust concentration, the total amount of scattered light first increases, then starts to decrease for very dense dust. Regions of thin to moderate dust are dominated by forward scattering, while very dense dust regions exhibit mostly backward scattering.</p><p>The combined effects of anisotropy, multiple scattering, absorption, wavelength dependence, and geometric configuration on reflection nebula appearance is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>. The otherwise empty nebula volume is initialized by setting the voxels in the frontmost layer, as seen from the observer, and the layer on the far side of the illuminating star to non-zero scattering depth values. Scattering depth increases with angle. A thin veil of dust appears bluer than the illuminating star, whether the dust is in front of or behind the star. With increasing scattering depth, however, extinction affects blue light more strongly than red light, and the light passing through the dust from the star to the viewer becomes redder and dimmer. In contrast, the light reflected back from the dust behind the star takes on the color of the illuminating star while its brightness asymptotically reaches a fixed level. These findings are in accordance with analytical considerations <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The contrast in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref> has been optimized to bring out the color changes. In reality, thin dust in front of the star appears much brighter than dust behind it due to forward scattering, as is obvious from <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Multiple Scattering</head><p>Using Monte-Carlo simulation to determine the scattering probability distribution P(τ sct , θ ), we can correctly account for multiple scattering on a local, per-voxel level. Photons that leave a voxel but are scattered back into it from neighboring regions, however, are not taken into account this way. Note that these neglected multiplyscattered photons can only increase overall observed radiance L obs .</p><p>To faithfully reproduce the wide-range effect of multiple scattering, we pursue a hierarchical approach, <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>. During precomputation, the full-resolution voxel model V 0 is down-sampled n times along all three dimensions. For each downsampling step, the scattering depths τ sct from eight neighboring voxels are averaged, and twice this average value is assigned to the corresponding lower-resolution voxel. The factor of two comes from the doubled linear size of the lower-resolution voxel. For each volume resolution V i , we also pre-compute voxel illumination, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</p><p>During visualization, we render a resolution pyramid of images I i , i = 0, ..., n, each obtained from the corresponding volume representation V i , <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>. We then down-sample the rendered images I i to obtainĪ i+1 . Note that the images I j andĪ j have the same resolution but are generated from different-resolution volumes V j and V j−1 , respectively. I j includes the effect of photons that at resolution level V j−1 exit a voxel but are scattered back into it from one of the adjacent voxels. I j is therefore a little brighter thanĪ j . Because multiple scattering can only add to observed radiance, the difference image</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">∆I j = I j −Ī j</formula><p>is clipped to non-negative values and up-sampled to obtain ∆Î j−1 .</p><p>Starting from the second-lowest resolution level considered, the upsampled difference image ∆Î i is added to the difference image of the corresponding resolution level ∆I i to obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">∆I * i = ∆Î i + ∆I i .</formula><p>The difference image ∆I * i is repeatedly up-sampled and combined with ∆I i for all resolution levels i &gt; 0 until the full-resolution level i = 0 is reached. The final image I is obtained by adding the accumulated difference image to the image rendered from the fullresolution volume: I = I 0 + I * 0 . This final image includes the effect of multiple scattering up to the scale length of the lowest resolution level taken into account. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 7</ref> depicts the effect of wide-range multiple scattering at different scale lengths in forward and backward scattering direction. For a homogeneous, planar layer of dust in front of the illuminating star, global multiple scattering noticeably increases nebula surface brightness. Also, nebula color becomes more bluish because of the monotonically increasing scattering probability with shorter wavelength. For dust on the star's far side, on the other hand, wide-range multiple scattering has only little effect.</p><p>We remark that the described approach assumes that a homogeneous and a non-homogeneous dust distribution of the same average density both yield the same average scattered radiance. Strictly speaking, this assumption is valid only for smoothly varying dust concentrations. In regions dominated by strong density gradients the approach still yields qualitatively plausible results, but, of course, our method cannot substitute for full radiative transfer simulations in the general case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Nebula Generation</head><p>Our visualization tool can render realistic views of any given 3D dust distribution. For planetarium shows, the generation of a specific reflection nebula may be driven by artistic and esthetic design criteria, while in an astrophysical setting, the dust distribution may be intended to reproduce the measured experimental brightness distribution of some real nebula.</p><p>For the former case, we found that the following recipe generates natural-appearing synthetic reflection nebulae. In accordance <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>: Multi-resolution rendering to incorporate the global effect of multiple scattering on nebula appearance: A resolution pyramid of images I i is rendered from the mipmap representation V i of the nebula volume. Images from one resolution level are down-sampled (↓) and subtracted from the images rendered at the next-lower resolution. From the lowest-resolution level upwards, the difference images are subsequently up-sampled (↑) and summed. The accumulated difference image is added to the full-resolution image I 0 to yield the resulting image I. with the physical processes accompanying star formation, we assume that stellar winds from the illuminating star have swept clean the immediate surroundings, so that the star is situated within a bubble of relatively low dust concentration. The swept-up dust accumulates along the edge of the bubble where, accordingly, dust density increases sharply. Beyond the bubble, dust concentration falls off exponentially with increasing radial distance. Since stars typically form in very large interstellar clouds, and because reflection nebulae are visible only around stars that form near the edge of such a cloud, the far side of the nebula volume is filled with highdensity, optically dense interstellar dust. Because the dust along the edge of the bubble has been swept up by hydrodynamic stellar wind processes, dust concentration is not homogeneous. To mimic corresponding variations in local dust density, we use 3D Perlin noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> to modulate voxel scattering depth τ sct (x, y, z). A wide variety of different-looking, yet realistically appearing nebulae can be created by varying Perlin noise amplitude and frequency, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">INTERACTIVE RENDERING</head><p>Prior to visualization, the pre-computed scattering table is uploaded as a 2D floating-point texture to graphics memory. A floating-point 3D texture stores the scattering depth τ sct for each voxel. Depending on the number of illuminating stars, one or more 3D arrays store the pre-computed illumination L ill for each voxel. Additionally, emissive radiance L em is stored per voxel. The 3D emission texture allows us to simulate ionized, glowing gas clouds that may be intermixed with the interstellar dust, as well as to visualize the illuminating star. Ionized gas radiates isotropically in all directions, so L em can be added directly to the scattered radiance L sct in (3). Both contributions undergo the same extinction on the way from the voxel to the observer L obs , (4).</p><p>Our reflection nebula visualization algorithm is based on GPUbased ray-casting. After determining viewing ray parameters as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, we use a fragment program to step along each viewing vector from front to back in voxel-length intervals. At each step, we look up local scattering depth τ sct , voxel illumination L ill , and emissive RGB radiance values L em from the 3D volume textures, taking advantage of hardware-accelerated trilinear interpolation. The fragment program computes the angle between viewing ray direction and the incident star-light direction θ , and queries the scattering probability table to determine P(τ sct , θ ). Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">3</ref>is evaluated, and the emissive radiance L em is added. If more than one star illuminates the dust cloud, scattered radiance is evaluated for each star and summed up per voxel. Rendering times and memory requirements increase linearly with the number of stars.</p><p>To quickly compute (4), we accumulate extinction depth τ opt while stepping along the ray. For each ray, extinction depth τ sct is initialized either to zero or to a fixed offset in case we wish to include interstellar extinction outside the nebula. At each step i along the viewing ray, local extinction is added up, τ i+1 opt = τ i opt + τ i+1 sct /a. Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">4</ref>can then be quickly evaluated. Note that (3) and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_5">4</ref>are actually computed for the red, green, and blue channel separately by weighting τ sct according to Section 3.2. To take large-scale global illumination effects into account, the hierarchical multi-resolution algorithm described in Section 4.2 is implemented to run entirely on the GPU. For display, the rendered image is optionally normalized and gamma-corrected.</p><p>To interactively explore the effects of different physical parameters on nebula appearance, fragment shader constants like star color, ratio of total-to-selective visual extinction R V , and albedo can be changed on the fly. We can upload scattering tables computed for different albedo and anisotropy values as well as for arbitrary phase functions. The result is an artificial but physically plausible rendition of the reflection nebula.</p><p>The change in appearance due to different viewing directions can be evaluated by simply rotating the nebula. However, to appreciate the full range of color variations, e.g., for planetarium shows, we want to be able to move the viewpoint inside the nebula. By moving the viewpoint through the dust towards the star, previously dark clouds become transparent and overall reddening decreases until the bluish tint of backscattered starlight dominates. We appropriately modify the original GPU-based ray-casting algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref> to solve the problem that arises when the near clipping planes fall within the volume.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">RESULTS</head><p>Our visualization tool is designed to render realistic images of reflection nebulae. A side-by-side comparison of a photo composite of an actual nebula (IC 5146) and the visualization of a simulated dust distribution is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 8</ref>. Note how our rendering algorithm produces color hues very similar to reality, and how our synthetically generated dust distribution convincingly mimics overall appearance of the real nebula. The importance of multiple scattering on large scales can be seen in <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref>. The increase in nebula surface brightness with hierarchy levels included suggests that we are looking at rather thin dust that is situated in front of the illuminating star. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 10</ref> presents screenshots from a fly-around and a fly-through sequence for two synthetic nebulae to illustrate the change in shape and color with viewpoint. From the outside, the nebula appears reddish with dark regions of dense dust. Once inside the nebula, backscattered light is responsible for the blueenhanced appearance. The wide variety in shape and color of re-flection nebulae following from dust density distribution is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref>. Depending on dust concentration and geometric dust configuration, the scattered star light reaches the viewpoint almost unhindered (bluish appearance), attenuated to varying degrees (reddish appearance), or not at all (dark regions).</p><p>In addition to physical visualizations, we can also explore the influence of varying different physical parameters on nebula appearance. The images in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref> show the same nebula from the same viewpoint, but for different parameter settings. The astrophysically correct reference image is depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12(a)</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12(b)</ref> illustrates nebula appearance if the dust in the nebula behaves more like galactic dust, i.e., R V = 3.1. Because for R V = 3.1, relative extinction rises more steeply with decreasing wavelength than for R V = 5, nebula colors are somewhat more vivid. In reality, reflection nebulae are associated with hot O or B stars. In our visualization tool, however, we can exchange the illuminating star, e.g., for our own Sun, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12(c)</ref>. The cooler star temperature causes the entire nebula to appear redder. Finally, we can vary the scattering and absorption properties of the interstellar dust grains. For an increased albedo value, the entire nebula becomes brighter, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12(d)</ref>. By enhancing forward scattering characteristics, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref>(e), already bright regions become brighter, while overall contrast increases. In conjunction with known dust configurations of actual nebulae, studying the effects of dust albedo and scattering anisotropy on nebula appearance with our visualization tool helps to understand the optical properties of interstellar dust <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p><p>In the presence of one illuminating star and with multi-resolution rendering turned off, our rendering algorithm performs at 7.5 frames per second on an nVidia GeForce 6800 Ultra graphics board, rendering at 512 × 512-pixel resolution from a 128 3 -voxel model. With multi-resolution rendering turned on, rendering frame rate drops to 6.1 frames per second, taking 3 resolution levels into account. Alternatively, for 2,3,4 or 5 illuminating stars, rendering frame rates are 4.7, 3.6, 2.5, and 1.9 Hz, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have presented an interactive visualization tool to realistically render reflection nebula appearance from physical principles. The algorithm runs on conventional hardware and allows the user to interactively vary viewing position and direction as well as to change physical parameters of the nebula. Multiple scattering is taken into account locally as well as on large scales. Our visualization tool can be used to create virtual fly-throughs of reflection nebulae for interactive desktop visualizations, or to produce scientifically accurate animations for educational purposes. By varying physical parameter values, the algorithm can be used to visualize and validate hypothetical models for observed data Next, we want to use our algorithm to recover the 3D shape of actual nebulae. We intend to make use of additional observations in the infrared <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> to be able to better constrain the reconstruction problem. To recover both the gas and the dust component of gaseous nebulae, we will include emission-line images in addition to color-bandpass images. By concentrating first on planetary nebulae, additional geometric constraints can be exploited <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX: MONTE-CARLO SIMULATION OF ANISOTROPIC PHOTON SCATTERING</head><p>Let the simulation consider N photons. Each photon is initialized with a weight w 0 = 1/N. Instead of a cube of edge length l, a voxel is modeled as a sphere of the same volume. The scattering coefficient is σ sct = τ sct /l. The photon is placed on the sphere at x 0 with its travel direction d 0 pointing towards the sphere's center. In the following, the photon is traced through the volume until it either emerges from the sphere, in which case its remaining weight w i is <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>: Wide-range multiple scattering: To include global multiple scattering effects, a multi-resolution rendering approach is pursued. From left to right, the images show the effect when taking n = 0, 1, 2 and 3 resolution levels into account (all images linear gamma, identical range). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>: Screenshots from a fly-around sequence of a nebula illuminated by five stars (left), and images of a fly-through sequence with a single central star (right). Left: From the outside, nebulae appear reddish due to wavelength-dependent extinction. Right: Once inside the nebula, thin dust backscatters predominantly blue light, while light backscattered from dense dust assumes the color of the illuminating star. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Reflection nebulae: Recently formed, hot stars illuminate the surrounding interstellar dust that scatters and absorbs the star light to give rise to a large range of color hues and brightness variations. (Rho Ophiuchi region, from [28], c T. and D. Hallas)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>NGC 1999: A recently formed hot star illuminates the surrounding interstellar dust that scatters and absorbs the star light to create a colorful reflection nebula. (from<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> c NASA/STScI)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Nebula model: The nebula volume is discretized into voxels.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Color variations in reflection nebulae as a function of geometric configuration and scattering depth τ sct . The scattering depth is constant in the radial direction and increases with angle from the top (τ sct = 0) to the bottom (τ sct = 10). The illuminating star light is white.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Effect of wide-range multiple scattering: a homogeneous layer of dust in front of (upper row) and behind an illuminating central star (lower row) is rendered, taking into account n = 0, 1, 2 resolution levels (left to right).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Left: Photo (color composite) of the "Cocoon" reflection nebula IC 5146 (from<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, c Greg Crinklaw); right: rendering result for a simulated dust distribution with 4 illuminating stars, composited into a star field photo for enhanced visual realism.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 11 :Figure 12 :</head><label>1112</label><figDesc>Renditions of different 3D dust distributions. Varying physical parameters: (a) visualization for the standard values a = 0.6, g = 0.6, R V = 5, and an illuminating O-class star; (b) same as (a), but R V = 3.1; (c) same as (a), but for an illuminating star similar to our Sun (G2V-class); (d) same as (a), but a = 0.8; (e) same as (a), but g = 0.8.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>added to the appropriate direction bin B[cos θ ] of its emergence angle cos θ = d i • d 0 , or its weight w i falls below a minimum threshold and the photon is discarded. Given a uniformly distributed (pseudo-) random variable u = [0, 1], the next scattering event of the photon takes place after it has travelled a length</p><p>where σ sct = 1/r is the scattering coefficient. From the previous position x i and direction d i , the new scattering site's 3D coordinates are</p><p>To determine the new scattering direction d i+1 , scattering anisotropy must be taken into account. We are free to use any analytic or measured single-particle phase function. Here, we rely on the Henyey-Greenstein phase function (1), adopted from astrophysics research. For (1), the cumulative distribution function can be inverted analytically to yield</p><p>if g = 0, i.e., for non-isotropic scattering. In azimuthal angle φ , scattering probability is constant,</p><p>Both random variables v, w = [0, 1] are uniformly distributed.</p><p>To compute the new scattering direction</p><p>in Cartesian coordinates, two cases must be distinguished. If the previous photon direction</p><p>was almost parallel to the z-axis, e.g., d z &gt; 0.9999, then</p><p>The photon weight is multiplied by the albedo, w i+1 = w i • a. The photon is traced until it either leaves the sphere, or until its weight w i falls below a preset threshold. The simulation ends after simulating all N photons. The accumulated values in the bins, B[cos θ ], represent the row of entries for τ sct in the scattering probability table P(τ sct , θ ).</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Galactic Astronomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Binney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Merrifield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scattering properties of the dust in the reflection nebula IC 435</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Calzetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Witt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bianchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between infrared, optical, and ultraviolet extinction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cardelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Clayton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mathis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">345</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cocoon nebula (IC 5146</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Crinklaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Space artist and plantarium animation specialist</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Donald</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.donaldedavis.com/.privatee-mailconversation" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Wonders of the universe -planetarium show</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sutherland</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.es.com/products/digitaltheater/wonders2.jpg" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">NASA/ESA Hubble Heritage Image Gallery. NGC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume-rendered galactic animations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Genetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Pleiades reflection nebula. II. simple model constraints on dust properties and scattering geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nordsieck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">589</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="362" to="377" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interstellar dust scattering properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Astrophysics of dust, ASP conference series</title>
		<editor>A. Witt, G. Clayton, and B. Draine</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The theory of the colors of reflection nebulae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Henyey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Greenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="580" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="1938" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffuse radiation in the galaxy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Henyey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Greenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1941" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A practical model for subsurface light transport</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM Conference on Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH &apos;01)</title>
		<meeting>ACM Conference on Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH &apos;01)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="518" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ray tracing volume densitites</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kajiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Von Herzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM Conference on Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH&apos;84)</title>
		<meeting>ACM Conference on Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH&apos;84)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model for volume lighting and modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Premoze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shirley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="162" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acceleration techniques for gpu-based volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="292" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constrained inverse volume rendering for planetary nebulae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magnor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Duric</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="90" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optical models for direct volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Max</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Volume visualization of the evolution of an emission nebula</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nadeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Engquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://vis.sdsc.edu/research/hayden2.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing stars and emission nebulae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nadeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Genetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Napear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pailthorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Emmart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wesselak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An image synthesizer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Perlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM Conference on Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH&apos;85)</title>
		<meeting>ACM Conference on Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH&apos;85)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="296" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Path integration for light transport in volumes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Premoze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ashikhmin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shirley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Eurographics Symposium on Rendering (EGSR&apos;03)</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics Symposium on Rendering (EGSR&apos;03)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="63" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient rendering of atmospheric phenomena</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tessendorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Eurographics Symposium on Rendering (EGSR&apos;04)</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics Symposium on Rendering (EGSR&apos;04)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="386" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The zonal method for calculating light intensities in the presence of a participating medium</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rushmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Torrance</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. on Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advanced GPU raycasting</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scharsach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cg.tuwien.ac.at/studentwork/CESCG/proceedings.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Central European Seminar on Computer Graphics (CESG&apos;05)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scattering of infrared radiation by dust in NGC 7023 and NGC 2023</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sellgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Werner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dinerstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">400</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple scattering as a diffusion process</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Eurographics Rendering Workshop (EGRW&apos;95)</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics Rendering Workshop (EGRW&apos;95)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gallery of astrophotography -nebulae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hallas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Light Scattering by Small Particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Van De Hulst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
			<publisher>Dover Publications, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CCD surface photometry of bright reflection nebulae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Witt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="852" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<publisher>December</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The scattering phase function of interstellar grains: The case of the reflection nebula NGC 7023</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Witt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bohlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stecher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">261</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="509" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A three-dimensional model of the Orion nebula</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>O'dell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Astrophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">438</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="784" to="793" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
