<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">VolQD: Direct Volume Rendering of Multi-million Atom Quantum Dot Simulations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
							<email>qiaow@purdue.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ebert</surname></persName>
							<email>ebertd@purdue.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alireza</forename><surname>Entezari</surname></persName>
							<email>aentezar@cs.sfu.ca</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marek</forename><surname>Korkusinski</surname></persName>
							<email>marekk@purdue.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gerhard</forename><surname>Klimeck</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">VolQD: Direct Volume Rendering of Multi-million Atom Quantum Dot Simulations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-20T19:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.3 [Computer Graphics]: Picture/Image Generation-Display algorithms</term>
					<term>Bitmap and framebuffer operations; I.3.7 [Computer Graphics]: Three-Dimensional Graphics and Realism-Raytracing volume visualization</term>
					<term>volume rendering</term>
					<term>programmable graphics hardware</term>
					<term>face-centered cubic lattice</term>
					<term>reconstruction filter</term>
					<term>quantum dots</term>
					<term>atomistic simulation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>In this work we present a hardware-accelerated direct volume rendering system for visualizing multivariate wave functions in semiconducting quantum dot (QD) simulations. The simulation data contains the probability density values of multiple electron orbitals for up to tens of millions of atoms, computed by the NEMO3-D quantum device simulator software run on large-scale cluster architectures. These atoms form two interpenetrating crystalline Face Centered Cubic lattices (FCC), where each FCC cell comprises the eight corners of a cubic cell and six additional face centers. We have developed compact representation techniques for the FCC lattice within PC graphics hardware texture memory, hardware-accelerated linear and cubic reconstruction schemes, and new multi-field rendering techniques utilizing logarithmic scale transfer functions. Our system also enables the user to drill down through the simulation data and execute statistical queries using general-purpose computing on the GPU (GPGPU).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The rapid progress in nanofabrication technologies has led to the emergence of new classes of nanodevices. Numerical simulations have become increasingly popular for studying the electronic properties of these devices. As their sizes reach the level of hundreds down to even tens of nanometers, the atomistic granularity of constituent materials can no longer be neglected: effects of surface roughness or distortions of the crystal lattice can have a deleterious impact on the device performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Simulation software like NEMO3-D specializes in analyzing the electronic properties of nanodevices with atomistic details. The physicists and electrical engineers in our team are conducting large-scale simulations using NEMO3-D to model semiconducting quantum dots (QDs). QDs are nano-scale solid-state structures that can confine a small number of free electrons in a small space. These free electrons are countable in contrast to standard semiconductor devices, where hundreds of thousands of electrons stream through a device to establish a particular state of the system. It is possible to precisely control the number of contained electrons and their excitation energy, thus manipulating the material properties. This leads to many promising applications such as infrared detectors, lasers with tunable wavelengths, high-density low energy consumption memory chips and logical gates for quantum computing.</p><p>The scientists develop their understanding of QD's electronic properties through the study of the electron orbitals under varying electrical or magnetic fields. An electron orbital in an atom is described by a mathematical function called the wave function. It defines a probability density function, which is the likelihood of an electron appearing in the orbital. In the device simulations pertinent to this work, Arsenide (As), Gallium (Ga) and Indium (In) atoms form crystalline Face Centered Cubic lattices (FCC) (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>), and a wave function is computed for each electron orbital in each atom. To realistically model the device, QD simulations often involve millions of atoms, making the resultant data very large and cumbersome to interpret. In this paper we present the VolQD system, which specializes in the analysis of QD electron wave functions. The system allows the scientists to visualize, intuitively navigate, and interactively query simulation statistics accelerated through general-purpose GPU computing. Our system is also well suited for visualizing other multivariate data built on FCC lattices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Molecular Visualization</head><p>Most molecular visualization techniques display molecular assemblies with two types of representations: surface and structural rendering. Surface rendering mainly presents molecules as spacefilling surfaces often defined by the van der Waal radii of the atoms. These surfaces can also be isosurfaces of molecular dynamics properties (e.g., electronic potential). They are broadly employed in many areas of study, for instance drug design <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and proteinfolding <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Besides conventional triangulated surface models, implicit surfaces were also proposed by Blinn <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> to model molecules with flexible bonds. On the other hand, structural rendering emphasizes the underlying skeletal construction of the molecule, and often displays models using primitives like spheres for atoms and cylinders for bonds (Ball-and-Stick model). Visualization platforms like Visual Molecular Dynamics (VMD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, RasMol <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and its derivative Protein Explorer <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> are examples that handle either or both structural and surface rendering. However, none of these systems currently offers flexible full-scale volume rendering capabilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Volume Visualization</head><p>While a large amount of volume visualization research has focused on traditional volumes sampled on Cartesian lattices, little work has been published on other regular lattices, including the FCC lattice. Theußl et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> first explored the use of the Body Centered Cubic lattice (BCC) as an optimal sampling structure for three dimensional sampling. Neophytou and Mueller <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> also considered the use of optimal sampling structures in 4-D for time varying data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IEEE Visualization 2005</head><p>October 23-28, Minneapolis, MN, USA 0-7803-9462-3/05/$20.00 ©2005 IEEE. </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">p p x , p y , p z d d 1 , d 2 , d 3 , d 4 , d 5 s * s *</formula><p>The primary challenge for visualizing alternative regular lattices is that there is very little work on reconstruction on non-Cartesian lattices. Theußl et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> used radial extension of one dimensional filters on BCC, which resulted in blurry and rather inaccurate images. They also explored various ad-hoc reconstruction schemes with mixed results <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. Entezari et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> devised a family of box splines with the proper geometry for reconstruction on BCC and demonstrated the optimality of the sampling structure. In this work we adopt a similar reconstruction scheme for the FCC lattice.</p><p>The class of cell projection approaches for visualizing unstructured meshes are applicable to FCC lattices, since the FCC lattice can be decomposed into a tetrahedral mesh. The cell projection algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> was later extended to utilize the programmable graphics pipeline for hardware acceleration (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>). However, the decomposition of FCC lattices results in an enormous number of tetrahedra (in general, several tetrahedra per atom vertex). Therefore, the interactive rendering of multi-million atom simulations is difficult, even with graphics hardware acceleration.</p><p>In contrast, our VolQD system uses a texture-based volume rendering approach based on Westermann and Ertl's work <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. Texture-based volume rendering is well suited for the FCC lattices for several reasons. First, FCC lattices can be compactly represented in local graphics memory using 3-D textures. Second, the lattice geometry is not required for the rendering. Finally, a straightforward implementation with custom reconstruction filters can be achieved using modern programmable graphics hardware. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CHARACTERISTICS OF SIMULATION DATA</head><p>The device models pertinent to this work are composed of the InAs QD embedded in a GaAs barrier material as demonstrated schematically in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The QD crystalline structure is known as a zinc blende, which comprises two interpenetrating FCC lattices with a displacement of 1/4 of the lattice parameter (the size of a FCC cell) along each major axis (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2b</ref>). Every atom in a lattice is the center of a regular tetrahedron formed by the four neighboring atoms from the other lattice.</p><p>An atom has 20 electron orbitals grouped into up and down spin domains. A spin domain is shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref>. The sum of the  probability density values of the 20 orbitals across the simulation is normalized to exactly 1, meaning an electron is bounded by the device. The scientists in our team are most interested in the wave functions of s, p, d and s * electron orbitals with up and down spins, each of which is the combination of the member orbitals within the class. Thus, the simulation data sets are 8-field multivariate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">VISUALIZATION REQUIREMENTS</head><p>To make VolQD a useful and convenient tool for the scientists, we identified the following visualization requirements, which directed the design and implementation of our system: 1. Scalability: Quantitative simulations of QDs generate gigabytes of binary data. To scale to visualizing large simulations, a compact memory footprint of data is very important.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Interactivity:</head><p>The system should be responsive to user commands even when rendering large simulation data.</p><p>3. Multi-field: QD simulations are multivariate (see Section 3). The capability of rendering multiple electron orbitals is vital for studying the composition of the electron cloud and device electronic properties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Statistics:</head><p>The system should also cater to the ways physicists study simulation results. Intuitive mechanisms are needed to answer quantitative queries and generate important statistics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">HARDWARE-ACCELERATED FCC VISUALIZATION</head><p>To guarantee quick volume loading and switching, raw simulation data is preprocessed into binary texture files (see Section 5.1). Our texture representation for FCC lattices is an extension of the approach proposed by Röber et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> for BCC grids. A configuration file associates a set of texture files to a particular simulation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Texture Representation</head><p>Modern graphics hardware provides excellent support for volume textures defined on Cartesian grids. To take advantage of accelerated texture access and trilinear interpolation, a texture representation that closely matches the Cartesian coordinate system is highly desirable. As discussed earlier, the zinc blende structure comprises two FCC lattices with a constant displacement vector. If we define a texture coordinate system for one lattice, the texture coordinates for the other lattice can be derived analytically. We identify the unit cubic cell composed of 8 FCC corners as the base cell (see   This decomposition scheme is well suited for utilizing graphics texture memory, since each sub-grid is defined in the Cartesian coordinate system. Furthermore, the 4 Cartesian grids of a FCC lattice fit naturally in a RGBA volume texture, with each texel storing a quadruple of atoms (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4)</ref>. We align the texture coordinate system with the base grid of one FCC lattice (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3a)</ref>. Given a sampling point with texture coordinates (x, y, z) in the base grid, the corresponding coordinates for the remaining grids are derived analytically by vector translation (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>). Note that OpenGL textures are cell-centered; thus, the first atom is mapped to the texture coordinate of the 0-th texel r = (2n r ) −1 where n r is the r-dimension of the texture. The texture coordinates (x ′ , y ′ , z ′ ) for the other FCC grid can be obtained using the zinc blende dis- </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">) −1 , 1 − (2n r ) −1 ] for dimension n r . atom texture coordinates A (x, y, z) B (x − 1 2n x , y − 1 2n y , z) C (x − 1 2n x , y, z − 1 2n z ) D (x, y − 1 2n y , z − 1 2n z ) placement vector ∆ v: (x ′ , y ′ , z ′ ) = (x, y, z) − ∆ v, where ∆ v = ((4n x ) −1 , (4n y ) −1 , (4n z ) −1 ).</formula><p>It is worth noting that un-extended OpenGL 8-bit textures do not offer sufficient resolution for small wave function values. Our solution is to use 16-bit floating point textures, which are supported by the latest class of graphics hardware, in our case the Nvidia Geforce 6800. This feature is accessible via ATI texture float extension with GL RGBA FLOAT16 ATI as the texture internal format <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Reconstruction Filters</head><p>The linear reconstruction filter is implemented using the hardware trilinear interpolation. Any given sample point in the zinc blende is simultaneously located in the 8 Cartesian sub-lattices. Because all lattices are symmetric and structurally identical, there should be no bias among them. Thus, we can assume an equally weighted contribution from each lattice. The contribution from each lattice is obtained by reading the 3-D textures using the proper texture coordinates (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>). This filter kernel covers up to 64 neighboring atoms surrounding the sample point at the cost of 8 texture lookups plus an average operation. The disadvantage of the trilinear kernel is that due to the averaging, the interpolation result at a grid point may not agree with the actual grid voxel value. Thus, it could produce unsmooth interpolation in regions of extremely high gradient. However, such effects are generally unnoticeable for an overwhelming majority of the data sets we have tested. Therefore, due to its efficiency and sufficiently good quality, the trilinear reconstruction kernel is employed during user interaction. To achieve greater rendering quality of simulation data sets featuring high gradient fields, we explored the optimal sampling pattern and higher order reconstruction filter for the FCC lattices.</p><p>The simplest interpolation scheme on a lattice is derived from its Voronoi diagram. The nearest neighbor interpolation assigns the value of the sample at a lattice point to all of the points in the space that fall inside the Voronoi cell of that lattice point. Since the Voronoi cells of all the lattice points are identical, we can refer to the Voronoi cell of a lattice without ambiguity. Therefore, the characteristic function of the FCC lattice constitutes the kernel for the nearest neighbor interpolation on this lattice. The Voronoi cell of the FCC lattice is depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 5a</ref>.</p><p>Higher order reconstruction schemes involve kernels with a support larger than the Voronoi cell; in other words, the reconstruction takes information not only from the nearest sample point but the closest surrounding points in the lattice. We define the nearest neighbors cell of a lattice point to be the set of all lattice points that share a non-degenerate face with the Voronoi cell of that point. The nearest neighbor points of an FCC lattice point is a cuboctahedron as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 5b</ref>.</p><p>The linear element on the FCC lattice is then defined as a function with a linear drop off from the center of the cuboctahedron towards its 12 vertices. The derivation of such a function is motivated by the method first described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>The convexity of the cuboctahedron allows us to derive it as an intersection of a set of half spaces. The cuboctahedron can be constructed by cutting the corners of a cube. Consider a cube of size 2, centered at the origin, we can describe it as an intersection of six half spaces:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">±x ≤ 1, ±y ≤ 1, ±z ≤ 1 (1)</formula><p>To cut the corners of this cube, we need to intersect this object with the half spaces:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">1 2 ((±x) + (±y) + (±z)) ≤ 1<label>(2)</label></formula><p>Therefore, all points inside a cuboctahedron enclosed inside the cube centered at the origin are in the intersection of the aforementioned spaces. Now, for each face of the cuboctahedron consider a pyramid with its apex at the center of the cuboctahedron whose base face f has a unit normal,n f , facing outward. For any point p within this pyramid, the scalar product p•n f is larger than such a product between p and normals from the other faces. Therefore, if we define a function φ :</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">R 3 → R: φ : (p) −→ max n f p •n f</formula><p>its level sets are polyhedra that are all cuboctahedron. Thus, we can use the axial symmetries of the faces formed by the half planes of the cube in Equation 1 and the corner faces of the cuboctahedron in Equation 2 to write the above description of the cuboctahedron as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">φ (x, y, z) = max(|x|, |y|, |z|, 1 2 (|x| + |y| + |z|))</formula><p>Therefore, φ (x, y, z) = s describes concentric cuboctahedra that are centered on the origin and are growing in size with the parameter s. Since we need a function whose value is maximum at the origin and drops linearly to zero at the twelve vertices, we derive the linear element on the FCC lattice by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">L FCC (x, y, z) = max(0, 1 − max(|x|, |y|, |z|, 1 2 (|x| + |y| + |z|))) (3)</formula><p>The cubic order reconstruction is generated by the convolution of two linear kernel interpolators in Equation 3. However, analytical derivation of such a function is not known and is the subject of current research. Nonetheless, we can numerically evaluate such a function by sampling the linear element in Equation 3 on a certain resolution and then perform a discrete convolution on the resulting volume. The result of such a convolution is a sampling of the cubic order reconstruction kernel, which can be stored as a 3-D texture and accessed via texture reading. When tested on a simulation data set with high gradient magnitudes, the reconstruction quality of the cubic kernel is noticeably better than that of the trilinear kernel (see <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>).</p><p>In our current hardware implementation, for memory efficiency the cubic and trilinear kernels share the texture data with interpolation mode set to GL LINEAR. Because the cubic filter requires un-interpolated values from the neighboring grid points prior to reconstruction, the texture coordinates have to be transformed to hit exactly the voxel centers. Although higher quality, our initial implementation of the cubic kernel is non-interactive. Thus, the cubic reconstruction filter is currently only used for offline rendering of non-linearly varying simulation data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Logarithmic Transfer Function</head><p>Transfer functions are by far the most broadly adopted tool for volume visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>, since they enable the user to assign material properties and selectively highlight details. Recent research explored a special class of transfer function, where opacities are defined on a logarithmic scale <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. In a hardware-accelerated rendering system, the transfer function is often implemented using a texture lookup table, where optical properties are indexed by data samples, and the mapping of scalar s to the lookup texture coordinate r is usually linear. Such an implementation is greatly challenged by the unique nature of some QD simulation data. In these data sets, while a majority of the scalars are extremely small, the overall data extends to a high dynamic range. For instance, in a two million atom simulation, the overall data range is [0, 7.0 × 10 −7 ], while 80% of the total samples fall into the range of [0, 1.0×10 <ref type="bibr">−12</ref> ]. An ideal transfer function should guarantee sufficient resolution for small scalars, while at the same time cover a large dynamic range. Such a transfer function, if defined linearly, is infeasible to implement using textures, since it would require a prohibitively high resolution. The highest resolution 1-D texture in the current OpenGL 2.0 implementation is only 4096 <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, which is not sufficient. Folding a high resolution 1-D lookup table into a higher-dimensional one is possible. However, interactive texture updates at such resolution remain difficult. Therefore, inspired by Kraus et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, a logarithmic mapping of the probability scalar s to lookup texture coordinate r is defined. Note because log b 0 = −∞, a scalar 0 ≤ s ≤ ε is mapped to the 0-th texel r = (2n) −1 . The largest scalar s max is mapped to r = 1 − (2n) −1 . The definition ε = b −(n−1) s max guarantees this logarithmic mapping, where n is the resolution of the lookup table, ε and b are user supplied parameters. The lookup table resolution n is determined by the logarithmic base b and the ratio s max /ε:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">n = log b s max ε + 1</formula><p>The logarithmic scale is applied to the filtered data s to derive the texture coordinate r in the fragment program:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">r = 2 max log b s ε , 0 + 1 2n<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Our system recommends appropriate b values that guarantee optimal lookup table sizes after the user sets the ε. For the same two million atom example, if b = 1.2 and ε = 10 −10 s max , the required lookup table resolution n is only 127. Updating textures of such size is extremely fast. For maximum flexibility, based on the data histogram the users can also switch to a conventional linearly mapped transfer function to handle data sets with a more uniform data distribution. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Multi-field Visualization</head><p>Most relevant previous research explored 3-D transfer functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and Gaussian transfer functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for multi-field visualization. Higher-dimension transfer functions are well suited for visualizing features characterized by the interaction among data fields. On the other hand, electron orbitals in QD simulations are defined as separate physical and computation domains. Although contributing to the overall electron cloud, as orthogonal and mutually exclusive fields, the orbitals do not interact among themselves. This data property allows us to utilize a more straightforward multi-channel transfer function design. Each electron orbital is assigned a transfer function channel. The transfer function user interface organizes the channels into tabs, which can be added or removed according to the visualization requirements as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7</ref>. The wave functions of different orbitals are co-located at the center of the atom without any ordering. Therefore, the most appropriate rendering method is to apply the transfer function f i (x) to its corresponding filtered scalar s i , then additively blend the orbitals. We assume f i (s i ) = (C i , α i ), where C i is the color, α i is the opacity, m is the number of slices and k is a global scaling parameter to ensure the combined rendering does not saturate:</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">α = ∑ n i=1 α i mn and C = k ∑ n i=1 α i C i n<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Note that α is modulated by m to prevent overly opaque images as the number of volume slices increases. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref> shows the electron orbital renderings of the first excited state of a InAs QD device with 21 million atoms. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref> and 9 are the electron orbital renderings of the second and third excited state of a two million atom InAs QD system, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">DATA EXPLORATION AND STATISTICS GENERATION</head><p>Many traditional visualization techniques are more qualitative than quantitative. Although effective in showing mesoscale information, they may not be suited for gaining quantitative insights into the data. For example, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref> and 9 indicate that qualitative differences of s, s* versus p, d orbitals through different nodal shapes. However, for a quantitative analysis statistical distributions are needed. These quantitative statistics are of particular interest when the wave functions already look qualitatively similar as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>. Recent research has explored novel quantity-driven visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. In this work we address the two classes of quantitative queries that are most important to the scientists in our team:</p><p>(a) the number or percentage of the atoms with one or more orbitals satisfying certain criteria, (b) the percentage contributions of orbitals to the total electron cloud.</p><p>To facilitate these queries, our system implements drill down data navigation. The user can explore the whole volume, axisaligned cuboid sub-volumes, or arbitrarily oriented slices. Statistics can be generated interactively during navigation (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10)</ref>. Our system adopts popular GPGPU approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref> and performs queries utilizing GPU fragment programs. Volume slices are rasterized to invoke the query kernel. The kernel then operates on the orbital data streamed from the texture memory via texture access and reconstruction filtering. For query class (a), fragments that do not pass the query are discarded using the CG "discard" instruction. Similar fragment termination instructions are also available in other GPU programming APIs. The ARB occlusion query extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> informs the application of the count of the fragments passing the query, which is directly proportional to the number of atoms satisfying the query. We then render the slice again and "pass" all fragments using a trivial shader to obtain the total fragment count. Percentage statistics are then computed. Similar queries are straightforward to extend to the whole volume or any sub-volumes v by simply accumulating fragment counts from multiple slices. To query the number of atoms n satisfying a certain criteria in v, assuming the total number of atoms N and total volume V , we derive n = Nv/V . Query class (b) is executed similarly by rasterizing the slices. However, instead of color values, the fragment output comprises the orbital scalars, which are written to an off-screen floating point render buffer (pbuffer) used as the accumulation buffer. Up to 4  outputs are written to each render buffer per rendering pass. Accumulation is implemented with hardware blending by setting the blending function to (GL ONE, GL ONE). To compute the total scalar values a final reduction is performed. We choose to read the accumulation buffer to the CPU by issuing a glReadPixel call, and then sum all the pixels. Alternatively, reduction can also be implemented with a multi-pass approach using the GPU <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>To ensure the accuracy of the statistics, the slices are screenaligned and rasterized with the same eye space depth. As a result, the slices cover the same number of pixels with no perspective distortion. Perspective distortion skews the statistics, since the portion of a slice closer to the camera is weighted more. The interval among slices should be at most the lattice parameter. Thus, each FCC cell is sampled by at least one slice. Additionally, by setting the camera at a proper distance, we make sure the rasterization of the cut through a FCC cell is at least 1 pixel. Smaller slice intervals and larger screen space rasterization will generally improve the accuracy of the query. It is also worth noting that non-axis-aligned slices may lead to varying sampling frequencies in some FCC cells. This, in theory, reduces the accuracy of the query; however, our experiments indicate that this effect is insignificant.</p><p>Our system does not require the users to write queries using a grahics hardware programming API. Our approach provides the users with a set of predefined variables, e.g., s, p, d, which can be used to compose boolean expressions. These expression are subsequently embedded into a shader and dynamically loaded by the CG run-time environment using the run-time compilation features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Performance</head><p>The system performance was measured on a Windows XP PC with an Athlon 64 3400+ processor (2.2 GHz), 2GB of system memory and an Nvidia Geforce 6800 Ultra graphics adaptor with 256MB of video memory. We tested our system using multiple data sets with 2 and 21 million atoms containing 1, 4, and 8 electron orbitals. Rendering frame rates were recorded for a 512 x 512-pixel display window using the trilinear reconstruction filter, and query execution times were measured for both the whole volume and a single slice. The timing results are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 3</ref> and 4. The system performance is bound by the GPU, where the largest portion of fragment processing time is spent on texture access. This effect compounds as the number of orbitals increase. Compared to the GPU work load, CPU processing time is negligible. The newest class of programmable graphics hardware is much more efficient in optimizing branching in the fragment shader. Thus, by utilizing if-branches to avoid unnecessary computations on orbital scalars below a certain threshold, we can achieve the equivalent effects of skipping empty volume regions, which leads to a significant performance gain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Discussion</head><p>Prior to the implementation of our system, the scientists in our team primarily used atom or iso-contour plots of the data slices to study the simulation data. These slice-based methods are necessary because they define smaller domains for the scientists to verify the correctness of the simulation, identify problems and study the properties of the physical model. However, operating on just slice data without a convenient tool was extremely time-consuming. Moreover, 2-D methods offer no simple way to perceptualize the overall structure and composition of the electron cloud. The value of our system lies in offering efficient ways to understand mesoscale electron cloud structure, while catering to modes of study with which the scientists are most familiar. When data exploration and quantitative information acquisition can be performed interactively and conveniently with visualization at each level of granularity, the ef-  In a typical visualization session, the scientists start by rendering the electron orbitals using the transfer function widgets (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12a</ref>). With the help of the visual information, the user can quickly determine the region of interest, and subsequently specify a sub-volume to further explore. Statistics may be generated at this stage or further exploration of the volume slices may occur (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 12b, c, and d)</ref>. The statistics for the sub-volume and the three slices inside is shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 5</ref>.</p><p>Our system has enabled the scientists to discover some unusual spatial patterns of the orbital distributions within the wave function computation domain. In particular, the distribution of s, p, d, and s* orbital weights in a given wave function has a spatial dependence, which is visualized in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>. Statistical gathering of this data can make this insight quantitative (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 5</ref>). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref> and 9 demonstrate extreme cases, where the s, s* and p, d orbitals show different nodal symmetries, i.e. the s and s* wave function component looks significantly different from the p and d component. These new insights provoked a high degree of interest, and the physical explanation behind them could lead to new publications in the nanoelectronics domain. Additionally, by imposing the geometry of the InAs/GaAs boundary to the electron orbital rendering, our system helps the scientists study the electron leakage from the InAs QD to the GaAs barrier material (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1)</ref>, and thus gain insights into the device performance characteristics. Our system also enables the scientists to study the effects of magnetic or electrical fields on the device electronic properties through comparison of electron orbitals under varying magnetic or electrical conditions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>In this work, we presented the VolQD system for interactive visualization of multivariate wave functions in semiconducting quantum dot simulations. We have demonstrated the compact representation technique for FCC lattices using PC graphics texture memory and novel multi-field rendering techniques utilizing logarithmic scale transfer functions. Additionally, we proposed an efficient separable trilinear reconstruction method, and nonseparable linear and cubic order high quality reconstruction filters for the FCC lattice. We also demonstrated the interactive drill down data exploration, and presented statistical query execution techniques using general-purpose computing on the GPU.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The schematic view of a dome-shaped InAs QD (solid geometry) embedded in a GaAs barrier material (translucent region). The inner box defines the wave function computation domain.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Quantum dot FCC lattices: (a) single FCC cell, (b) two interpenetrating FCC cells (zinc blende).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Decomposition of a FCC lattice: (a) is the base cubic cell composed of corners; (b), (c) and (d) are cubic cells composed of opposing face centers shown in relation to the base cell.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3a )</head><label>3a</label><figDesc>. Each of the opposing face center pairs belongs to a separate Cartesian grid identical to the base grid, only with a displacement of 1/2 of the lattice parameter in two of the three major axes (seeFigure 3b, 3c, and 3d). Thus, a FCC lattice comprises 4 interpenetrating Cartesian grids, and the whole QD zinc blende can be viewed as total of 8 displaced Cartesian grids.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Atom quadruple stored in a RGBA texel. Each member of the quadruple is from a Cartesian grid shown inFigure 3. A FCC lattice is a collection of these atom quadruples.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :Figure 6 :</head><label>56</label><figDesc>FCC's Voronoi cell (a) is a rhombic dodecahedron, and the first neighbor cell (b) is a cuboctahedron. Note that only relevant atoms are shown. Quality comparison of trilinear (a) and cubic (b) reconstruction schemes applied to a hole excited state QD simulation data set. The reconstructed scalars are linearly mapped to gray-scale colors. The result of the trilinear kernel shows the grid structure, while the cubic kernel achieves smooth interpolation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Multi-channel transfer function editor interface: channels are organized in a tabbed format.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Data drill down from volume to sub-volume and to slice. Statistics are generated on each level.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>The electron orbitals of a two million atom InAs QD device in the second excited state: (a) s and s* orbitals with up and down spins, (b) p and d orbitals with up and down spins, (c) all orbitals combined.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>The electron orbitals of a two million atom InAs QD device in the third excited state: (a) s and s* orbitals with up and down spins, (b) p and d orbitals with up and down spins, (c) all orbitals combined.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 11 :Figure 12 :</head><label>1112</label><figDesc>The electron orbitals of a 21 million atom InAs QD device in the first excited state: (a), (b), (c) and (d) are up and down spins combined s, p, d and s* orbitals, respectively, and (e) is the overall electron cloud. Interactive data exploration and statistics generation. (a) is the volume of interest, (b), (c) and (d) are sample slices, for which statistics are computed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The ten orbitals of a spin domain.</figDesc><table><row><cell>orbital class</cell><cell>orbitals</cell></row><row><cell>s</cell><cell>s</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Texture coordinates transformation. The dimensions of the texture are n x , n y , n z . Texture coordinate r ∈ [(2n r</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Frame rates in frames per second for rendering QD simulations with 2 and 21 million atoms.</figDesc><table><row><cell>no. atoms</cell><cell>no. orbitals</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>2, 048, 000 18.6</cell><cell>13.5</cell><cell>9.6</cell></row><row><cell>21, 069, 312 11.3</cell><cell>9.3</cell><cell>5.2</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Query execution time for quering 4 orbitals in seconds.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">n. atoms query class</cell><cell>time</cell></row><row><cell>2, 048, 000</cell><cell>a</cell><cell>0.025</cell></row><row><cell>slice</cell><cell>b</cell><cell>0.110</cell></row><row><cell>21, 069, 312</cell><cell>a</cell><cell>0.035</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>b</cell><cell>0.120</cell></row><row><cell>2, 048, 000</cell><cell>a</cell><cell>0.185</cell></row><row><cell>volume</cell><cell>b</cell><cell>0.185</cell></row><row><cell>21, 069, 312</cell><cell>a</cell><cell>0.317</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>b</cell><cell>0.358</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ficiency of scientific discovery is greatly improved.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The percentage contributions of s, p, d and s* orbitals for the domains defined inFigure 12.</figDesc><table><row><cell>query domain</cell><cell></cell><cell>orbital contribution</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>s</cell><cell>p</cell><cell>d</cell><cell>s*</cell></row><row><cell>(a)</cell><cell>73.13%</cell><cell>1.08%</cell><cell cols="2">0.39% 25.68%</cell></row><row><cell>(b)</cell><cell>74.81%</cell><cell>0.64%</cell><cell cols="2">0.14% 24.42%</cell></row><row><cell>(c)</cell><cell>73.67%</cell><cell>0.98%</cell><cell cols="2">0.29% 25.07%</cell></row><row><cell>(d)</cell><cell>72.63%</cell><cell>1.13%</cell><cell cols="2">0.49% 25.76%</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We are currently working on improving the hardware implementation of the cubic filter kernel to achieve interactive frame rates. Additionally, we hope to incorporate more optimization techniques into the rendering engine, including octrees and z-culling. In the near future, we will migrate our system to a multi-user environment. We anticipate that our system will serve remote nanoelectronics scientists as a component of the set of utilities offered by the Network for Computational Nanotechnology (NCN) at its online simulation facility nanohub.org.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>The authors would like to thank Thomas Ertl, Martin Kraus, Kirk Riley, Joshua Schpok, Nikolai Svakhine, Eduardo Tejada, Manfred Weiler, the anonymous reviewers for many helpful discussions and comments, and NVidia for their donation of hardware. This material is based upon work supported by the US National Science Foundation under grants: ACI-0081581, ACI-0121288, ACI-0196351, ACI-0222675, ACI-0328984, ACI-9978032, IIS-0098443 and EEC-0228390, and by the Indiana 21st Century Fund.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Principles that govern the folding of protein chains</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Anfinsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A generalization of algebraic surface drawing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Blinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brook for gpus: Stream computing on graphics hardware</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ian</forename><surname>Buck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tim</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Horn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeremy</forename><surname>Sugerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kayvon</forename><surname>Fatahalian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mike</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pat</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="777" to="786" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Drebin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Loren</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pat</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH 88</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH 88</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="74" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear and cubic box splines for the body centered cubic lattice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alireza</forename><surname>Entezari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ramsay</forename><surname>Dyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vmd: Visual molecular dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Humphrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Dalke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Klaus</forename><surname>Schulten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Molecular Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">NVIDIA OpenGL Extension Specifications. NVIDIA Corporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Kilgard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Curvature-based transfer functions for direct volume rendering: Methods and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gordon</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ross</forename><surname>Whitaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tolga</forename><surname>Tasdizen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization 2003</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 2003</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume rendering multivariate data to visualize meteorological simulations: A case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joe</forename><surname>Kniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michel</forename><surname>Grenier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tom</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Joint Eurographics -IEEE TCVG Symposium on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>Joint Eurographics -IEEE TCVG Symposium on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidimensional transfer functions for interactive volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joe</forename><surname>Kniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gordon</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gaussian transfer functions for multi-field volume visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joe</forename><surname>Kniss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Premoze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Milan</forename><surname>Ikits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Aaron</forename><surname>Lefohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Emil</forename><surname>Praun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization 2003</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 2003</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large scale simulations in nanostructures with nemo3-d on linux clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marek</forename><surname>Korkusinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Faisal</forename><surname>Saied</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Haiying</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Seungwon</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Sayeed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sebastien</forename><surname>Goasguen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gerhard</forename><surname>Klimeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">6th International Conference, Linux Clusters: The HPC Revolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Projecting tetrahedra without rendering artifacts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear algebra operators for gpu implementation of numerical algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rüdiger</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transaction on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="908" to="916" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computing and displaying intermolecular negative volume for docking</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chang</forename><surname>Ha Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amitabh</forename><surname>Varshney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Scientific Visualization: Extracting Information and Knowledge from Scientific Datasets</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein explorer: Easy yet powerful macromolecular visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Martz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends in Biochemical Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scout: A hardware-accelerated system for quantitatively driven visualization and analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mccormick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeff</forename><surname>Inman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ahrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Greg</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization 2004</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 2004</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Space-time points: 4d splatting on efficient grids</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Neophytos</forename><surname>Neophytou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Klaus</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2002 IEEE symposium on Volume Visualization and Graphics</title>
		<meeting>the 2002 IEEE symposium on Volume Visualization and Graphics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="106" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transfer functions on a logarithmic scale for volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Simeon</forename><surname>Potts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Graphics Interface</title>
		<meeting>Graphics Interface</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="63" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Texture based volume rendering of hexagonal data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Niklas</forename><surname>Röber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Hadwiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alireza</forename><surname>Entezari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>CMPT TR 2003-01</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Simon Fraser University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hardware-accelerated volume and isosurface rendering based on cell-projection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Röttger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="116" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rasmol: Biomolecular graphics for all</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roger</forename><surname>Sayle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E. James Milner</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends in Biochemical Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="374" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The OpenGL Graphics System: A Specification (Version 2.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Segal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kurt</forename><surname>Akeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-10-22" />
			<publisher>Silicon Graphics, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A polygonal approximation to direct scalar volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Shirley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Allan</forename><surname>Tuchman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1990 workshop on Volume visualization</title>
		<meeting>the 1990 workshop on Volume visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="70" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal regular volume sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Theußl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Meister</forename><forename type="middle">Eduard</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="98" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hardware-based view-independent cell projection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Manfred</forename><surname>Weiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Merz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="175" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficiently using graphics hardware in volume rendering applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rüdiger</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIG-GRAPH 98</title>
		<meeting>SIG-GRAPH 98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="177" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Footprint evaluation for volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lee</forename><surname>Westover</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH 90</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH 90</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="376" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">OpenGL Programming Guide: The Official Guide to Learning OpenGL, Version 1.2</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mason</forename><surname>Woo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jackie</forename><surname>Neider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tom</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dave</forename><surname>Shreiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>third edition</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
