<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Direct Volumetric Visualization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Don</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Texas Instruments Incorporated</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>MITRE</roleName><forename type="first">Fred</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wefer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Texas Instruments Incorporated</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Direct Volumetric Visualization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The need for true 30 volumetric displays derives from the fact that the human visual system has evolved to perceive and comprehend the world in three dimensions. The Texas Instruments OmniView TM display technology provides the capability to display computer graphics images in true 3 0. Viewers can see the display from all angles and change views simply by walking around the display volume. The OmniViewm device uses lasers of three different colors to project images on a moving surface sweeping through the 3 0 cylindrical display volume. The concept of operations is discussed, along with some details of the moving surface and parameters of the resulting display. The transport theory for this type of display involves only the source term in the linear Boltzmann equation. Constraints of the technology imposed by this limitation are discussed, along with discussions of image quality, current applications, and plans for improved devices.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>In the section titled "Looking Ahead in his recent book on volume visualization, [KALJF91] stated the following:</p><p>"Volume visualization has recently emerged as a key research and development area.... More specifically, the ultimate highly inspirational goal in equipment development [for volume visualization] is a novel 3D display technology or media for fast presentation of 3D volumes, as well as surfaces, from any arbitrary direction." [KAUF911 Texas Instruments' OmniViewTM display technology represents a giant step towards Kaufman's "highly inspirational goal", displaying volumetric data directly in a three dimensional (3D) volume, without having to render such spaces into a two dimensional (2D) perspective view. Volume data has been displayed in limited form via 2D flat displays using occlusion, perspective cues, and stereopsis. Considerable literature exists on the development of volume imaging algorithms for display on 2D monitors (refer to [RUSS89] for an overview). A number of situational analysis tasks, however, require group viewing of, and interaction with inherently 3D scenes where motion parallax provides important clues for understanding. Texas Instruments recently built a large prototype of their OmniViewTM direct volume visualization technology, with demonstration scenarios from air tactics analysis and satellite orbital analysis. In these scenarios one can view the aircraft and satellite maneuvers in three dimensions from all angles. This paper discusses the need for such display devices as well as some specifics of the OmniViewTM technology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Need for Volume Visualization</head><p>Spatial thinking and the need for a volumetric medium are important because people are naturally spatial thinkers. The human visual system perceives and comprehends the world in three dimensions. As has been pointed out by [KAISgl], we spontaneously encode much of the spatial layout and regularities of our environment. The importance that spatial, or visual thinking has played in gaining conceptual insight has been frequently cited in anecdotes and in systematic studies. We need a way, however, to easily share visual-spatial understanding and knowledge with others.</p><p>Advances in the computer graphics field have resulted in applications which are increasingly well-suited to spatial thinking. Most recently, discussions in the literature have turned to volume visualization, which [KAUFI)l] defines as "the representation, manipulation, and rendering of volumetric data." Unfortunately current display devices are limited. both in their ability to present volumetric data, and in their ability to share the data with groups of users. The most commonly used systems are CRT-based 2D perspective displays that provide the illusion of 3D through shadows, relative size cues, texture gradients, perspective cues, and occlusion. These images lack the visual dynamic realism and visual cues (horizontal, vertical, and motion parallax) supplied by an actual 3D object, and are limited to only a single angle of view.</p><p>These drawbacks become most pronounced when a user is asked to monitor and control the relative positions of objects in a volume of space. In a series of reports, a research team at NASA Ames Research Center characterized the errors made when observers reconstructed 3D spatial layouts from 2D perspective projections <ref type="bibr">[MCGRWI WCGR851 [GRUN86]</ref>. They reported:</p><p>1. Random variations in the estimation errors due to fixed image scaling errors, 2. An estimation bias resembling the type of errors which would result from viewing the true visual scene through a telephoto lens, and 3. Some unexplained differences.</p><p>They also concluded that the spatial reconstruction process is subject to the observer's basic assumptions about the object characteristics. Incorrect assumptions may result in substantial estimation errors</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">[GRUN88a] [GRUN88b].</formula><p>Stereo-pair displays provide parallax, the unique view each eye receives because of its physical separation from the other. Stereo displays typically provide horizontal parallax from a single view. Some display devices have implemented limited vertical parallax and others have supplied motion parallax within limited ranges. Complete motion parallax, the change in the image caused by the motion of the viewer, is difficult to simulate over wide ranges on a 2D display device, since the image would have to change rapidly as a function of the viewer's dynamic angle of view. Some research has demonstrated stereoscopic parallax which changes with inputs from a head tracking device. These display devices have promise, but currently the system lag and restraint of the head-tracking device limit the realism of the motion parallax cues they present. The computational load needed to calculate stereo pairs for the various viewpoints dynamically limits the effectiveness of this approach to supplying motion parallax.</p><p>Given this, an important question is, "How many viewpoints are needed to visualize the data for a given task?" Very little research addresses this question. After his review of the literature, <ref type="bibr">[RUSS89]</ref> concluded that a small number of 2D projections cannot represent volume medical data adequately, simply because of the quantity of information involved. This is why, for example, quality CAT scan images require X-ray data from hundreds of viewpoints. It is necessary to display space-filling medical data in a format which is naturally interpreted by vision as 3D in form <ref type="bibr">[RUSS89]</ref>.</p><p>The number of views needed for the natural interpretation by vision as 3D varies with the nature of the data and the specific requirements of the visualization task. Generally, the ability of the display to provide visualization for the viewer improves as the number of views increases. The natural access of the user to these views is an important determinant of the ability of the display system to provide insight. In his summary of the work in volumetric displays [RUSS89] suggested the need for "true 3D" perception and real-time motion under the user's control. In discussing the work of [GOLD851 and [HUNT841 he concluded that the common thread in their investigations was that to properly understand spacefilling data, one must concentrate on providing "true 3 D perception and comprehension. Emphasis is now being placed on interactive display systems which allow the user to control the display characteristics in real-time.</p><p>This emphasis on true 3D perception with real-time user-controlled motion presents a tremendous challenge for the available processors and rendering algorithms, even when the user is constrained to a single view being displayed on a 2D display device. Users must interact to choose the views they need and display them sequentially over time to build the mental model used to perceive the volume nature of the data. With scenes of complex medical data with moderate to high transparency, static stereo viewing is relatively ineffective; however, when motion and stereo viewing are used together, the stereopsis provides noticeable enhancement to the visual perception over motion alone <ref type="bibr">[RUSS91]</ref>.</p><p>A number of situational analysis tasks (e.g., air tactics analysis, satellite orbital analysis, and battle management) share the requirements of the domains described above: direct team perception of 3D volumetric data with horizontal, vertical, and motion parallax plus all-angle viewing. The ideal display device would be one which allowed the viewer to directly perceive and interact with 3D volumetric data that actually occupies a volume, providing all perspectives at once, as if the data were a physical object. The viewer would simply walk around the display to change views. This is the ultimate user control with real-time response. In many tasks such a volumetric display could be designed to complement a 2D perspective display to provide the improved performance needed on critical volume tasks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The OmniViewTM Display Technology</head><p>Over the last four years Texas Instruments has developed, patented, and is now delivering custom volumetric display devices under the trade name OmniViewTM [WILL88a] [WILL88b] WILL891. The technology allows users to directly perceive volumetric data, providing full horizontal, vertical, and motion parallax cues. The current OmniViewTM device shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> is physically large, having overall dimensions of approximately 10 x 4 x 3 feet with the cylinder removed. The cylinder on top of the device provides a display volume 36 inches (914 mm) in diameter and 18 inches (457 mm) high. A Sun 4/470 is integral to the system. Three-dimensional graphics are displayed within the cylindrical volume, auxiliary information being displayed on the Sun CRT. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Device</head><p>The OmniViewm technology has several advantages over existing 2D or 3D displays for many volume visualization tasks:</p><p>1. Large Volumes --The 36-inch diameter volume in the current prototype can be theoretically extended to very large volumes which will provide a common visual model of the task domain for efficient team interaction.</p><p>2. All-Angle View --The display can be viewed from all angles, simultaneously by many viewers. In battle management, command and control, or scientific and engineering visualization, multiple simultaneous views of 3D data provide improved task efficiency and insight.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Dynamic Resolution --</head><p>The technology is based upon laser projection onto a moving passive element. Resolution can be dynamically increased by focusing more of the available laser resources into a particular portion of the volume, or by adding more lasers and scanners.</p><p>4. True 3D Image --This display system provides a true 3D image that can be used to visually evaluate the 3D relationships of the displayed objects. The displayed image has parallax and motion parallax similar to realworld 3D objects, to overcome the problems associated with the mental reconstruction of spatial information mentioned above [MCGR841.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concept of Operations</head><p>The concept of operation of the OmniView"' device is illustrated in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. A rapidly rotating surface (disk) within the cylindrical display volume sweeps through all possible X,Y , Z coordinates twice per rotation, providing the medium on which graphics are drawn. Red (wavelength 647 nanometers, power 100 milliwatts), green (514 nm, 150 mw), and blue (488 nm, 150 mw) single line, Gaussian mode, air-cooled lasers illuminate spots on this surfacel.</p><p>As shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, the disk rotation angle is input to a Display Control Computer (DCC) which provides timing, scanning, and modulation control. The laser beams are scanned in X and Y via acousto-optic scanners.</p><p>The operation of acousto-optic scanners and some details of a parallel volumetric display device development effort currently underway at the Naval Ocean Systems Center in San Diego, CA are discussed by <ref type="bibr">[SOLl92]</ref>. Ahead of the scanners the laser beams are modulated in intensity to provide a pulse of light of the correct brightness and color at the moment the rotating surface passes through the desired 2-value. At the nominal disk rotation rate of 600 rpm all of this happens fast enough that the human visual system fuses the time sequential pulses of light into a single 3D image. lTheoretically a voxel could be any color, by illuminating the same voxel with some combination of the three lasers. In practice, we have yet to adequately solve the registration problem, and the display is "3 1/2" colors -red, green, blue and the absence of illumination (but not black). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rotating Surface</head><p>The OmniViewm disk is a non-axially symmetric double helix. A horizontal radial line in this surface sweeps upwards at a constant rate (proportional to rotation angle) during the first half rotation, and sweeps downwards during the second half rotation. We define a right-handed Cartesian coordinate system with the X,Y plane horizontal through the bottom of the display volume and the +Z axis vertically upwards along the axis of rotation. In this coordinate system the equations of the surface look rather complicated, viz:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Y = X * tan [ II: * Z / HI for 0 5 0 I n (1) Y = X * t a n [ n * ( l -Z / H ) ] for n l 0 1 2 n (2)</formula><p>where: X,Y,Z = Cartesian coordinates of a point on the H = height of the disk in the Z-dimension , and 0 = angle in the X,Y plane measured from the surface, + X-axis counter-clockwise to the X,Y point.</p><p>There are two opportunities to illuminate each voxel* during each rotation. The two times at which pulses of light are required to illuminate a voxel at a particular Zvalue are simply: t l = Z * P / 2 H </p><p>surface has at least one major disadvantage, namely that at any given X.Y the spacing in time-of voxel illuminations varies with the Z-value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5-' 1 = p * ( l</head><p>At Z = H / 2 the two illuminations are equally spaced in time resulting in an update rate of 20 Hz (at the nominal rotation rate). As the Z-value progresses away from this value the spacing becomes progressively more unequal until at Z = 0 and Z = H the two illuminations occur simultaneously, resulting in an update rate of only 10 Hz.</p><p>This causes the illumination rate to be different for different portions of the display.</p><p>A simple solution is, of course, to use a surface with axial symmetry, such as would be the case if Eq. (2) were identical to Eq. (1). Then Eq. (4) would become ' 2 = P / 2 + t 1 and the update rate would be a constant 20 Hz regardless of the Z-value of the voxel. Unfortunately such a surface suffers from serious self-occlusion, i.e., for an arbitrary 2The volume visualization literature (e.g., [KAUF91] p. 3) uses the term "voxel" to describe the unit volume cell of the abstraction known as the "3D voxel space" in which the volumetric dataset resides. Kaufman goes on to say that "A voxel is the 3D counterpart of the 2D pixel."</p><p>With the advent of volumetric display devices such as the one herein described, this statement is literally me. In this paper, we use "voxel" to refer to the actual addressable unit volume in the display and "abstract voxel" to refer to the data structure cell. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(See wlor plates, p. CP-13.)</ref> viewing direction there are rather large sub-volumes that are not visible to the viewer. The non-axially symmetric disk is also self-occluding; however, the invisible subvolumes are much smaller and tend to be limited to low viewing angles.</p><p>Both of these surfaces suffer from a progressive steepening of slope with decreasing radius. Eventually the range of Z-coordinates spanned by a single voxel greatly exceeds the voxel diameter. The resulting distortion results in an unusable cylinder of small diameter at the center of the display volume, the so called "dead zone". The dead zone diameter of the OmniViewTM device is about five inches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Display Volume</head><p>OmniViewm directly displays volumetric data into a roughly ten cubic foot volume. The electronics use 32 bits to control the aiming and intensity of the lasers (12 bits X, 12 bits Y, and 8 bits intensity), which results in an addressability of 4096x4096 in X and Y. The Zcoordinate information is contained in the timing signals. The speed of the DCC and associated components results in a time between individual voxel updates of approximately 13 ps. The addressability of the system in the Z-dimension is approximately 4000. Given the volume dimensions of 36 inches in diameter and 18 inches high, the resulting 67 billion addressable voxels (of which roughly 50 billion are inside the cylindrical display volume and outside the dead zone) are separated by step sizes of 0.22 mm horizontally (in X and Y) and 0.11 mm vertically (in 2).</p><p>This display addressability is much more than is currently necessary. The spots created by the lasers are 2.5 mm in diameter with a luminance of approximately 40 cd/m2, creating a nominal sphere three orders of magnitude larger in volume than the voxel being addressed. Approximately 2000 to 4000 spots per laser can be displayed during the 0.1 seconds necessary for one full rotation (depending on the actual positions of the targeted voxels within the display). These figures represent a trade-off between spot size, number of spots, and brightness. The limiting factor is the response time of the current acousto-optic scanners.</p><p>In practice, 6000 to 12000 voxels 2.5 mm in diameter in a ten cubic foot display volume are adequate for many applications.</p><p>Required values of the volume addressability, percentage of addressable voxels illuminated during a single rotation, and spot size are open areas of research. Constraints set by the human visual system remain to be explored.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transport Theory Model</head><p>Given a technology like OmniViewTM to directly display volumetric data in three dimensions, the question becomes how to present information in the display volume. The basic problem of volume rendering on a 2D display device is, given a 3D array of data points representing the variations of one or more variables across the space encompassed by the array, construct a 2D rendition on the computer graphics screen showing what that data would look like if it were directly viewable. The situation is different with a true 3D display. For example, it is no longer necessary to remove "hidden" lines or b compensate in any way for a given perspective. The OmniViewm display presents whole new challenges to the field of volume rendering.</p><p>As has been discussed by <ref type="bibr">[KRUEgO]</ref>, 2D rendering techniques are often based on an evaluation of the linear transport equation. A very simplified form of this equation suitable for this discussion is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(3 &amp;/as= A -B * I + C + D</formula><p>where: I = intensity, s = direction of (position along) the ray, A = intensity source, B = opacity (absorption plus total scattering), C = particle energy changing interactions, and D = particle direction changing interactions.</p><p>The terms A. B, C, and D describe the physics of the particles being transported. These terms (and the intensity) are typically functions of position in the volume, position along the ray, and particle energy.</p><p>Volume rendering on a 2D display device involves integrating Eq. (7) through the abstract voxel space3, along the ray through each pixel on the screen, to the eye of the viewer. Proper manipulation of the terms on the right-hand side of Eq. (7) can result in effects such as: transparency, clouds, dust, shadows, glints from light sources, etc.</p><p>In many applications, the variable of interest is not a visible quantity, e.g., it might be magnetic field strength. Rendering then involves the mapping of variables in the abstract voxel space onto the various parameters we have hidden by the simplicity of Eq. (7). and then integrating the equation along the ray paths. A discussion of one such unique application can be found in [HECK881 The equivalent linear transport equation for volumetric displays is simply Abstract voxel refers to the unit cell in the 3D voxel space in which the volumetric dataset resides.</p><p>The OmniViewm device performs the integration of Eq. (8) by "nature", at the speed of light, simultaneously for all rays going to both eyes of the viewer. including perspective projection, and simultaneously for multiple people viewing the same display. As viewers change their positions, their views are all automatically simultaneously updated in real time. The OmniViewm technology, however, provides no capabilities at all for terms B, C, and D of Eq. <ref type="formula">7</ref>. The point is that the OmniViewm technology can generate light in a voxel, but cannot absorb, scatter, reflect, or refract light in a voxel.</p><p>Even with the limitations of Eq. (8) it is still possible to simulate some of the effects of light sources, e.g., geometric shadows and diffuse lighting via Lambert's law. This requires first ray tracing from light sources to surfaces in the abstract voxel space, then mapping the results of the surface brightness computations to the source term A. Surfaces can be displayed by detecting them in the abstract voxel space (see, for example,</p><p>[LORE87], [CLIN88], and [DREB881) and then mapping surface voxels to the source term A. Any visual effect which involves the missing terms in Eq. (8), or requires knowledge of the position of the viewer relative to the display volume, however, cannot be produced. This includes almost all hidden surface/hidden volume representations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Image Quality in the Display</head><p>Current research at Texas Instruments is focused on improving the quality of the volumetric display, specifically on reducing the spot size, on increasing the number of available spots, and on addressing the voxel illumination rate problem mentioned above. In addition, the current disk has refraction problems. In illuminating a voxel, the laser projects a spot of light on the frosted bottom surface of the plastic disk. The light then passes up through the disk and out the top surface where it is refracted, causing the apparent position of the voxel to be slightly different from its true position. Because the OmniViewTM surface is non-axially symmetric, the angle that the light ray makes with the top surface of the disk is different for the two illuminations performed during each rotation. The result is that the two illuminations appear to not quite coincide in space. Further, because the voxel illumination rate is low enough to be seen, the voxel appears to jump back and forth (to jitter) between the two apparent positions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Applications</head><p>We have generated a number of displays, both static and dynamic, to demonstrate the potential of the OmniViewm technology. Examples of static displays include: simple geometric shapes, concentric spheres of different colors, aircraft icons/models, satellite icons/models, a fractal volume, corporate logos, human heads, a section of a DNA molecule, and grids of topographic data. Examples of dynamic displays include: text, rotating earths with satellites in various types of orbits, aircraft flying through and around microburst meteorological conditions, aerial bombardment, and air combat maneuvers. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows a photograph of the OmniViewm device displaying a four satellite Molniya constellation. The Molniya orbit produces a ground trace very different from the usual sinusoidal curve. The satellite moves from west to east during part of its orbit, reverses direction, then reverses again and continues moving to the east. How this motion results is difficult to understand in 2D but becomes obvious when viewed in 3D. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Future Volumetric Displays</head><p>The goal of volume visualization is to provide the user insight into complex computer models, space-filling data, and spatial imagery. Achieving this goal requires appropriate display devices for the given task. Future display systems should, therefore, leverage a vast array of display technology to provide critical information in a natural and usable format to the viewers. The system designer of the future will be able to choose from a variety of display technologies that will provide the basis for these custom display systems. Display options, once dominated by the home television market, have recently seen dramatic advances. Sizes now range from small wrist mounted displays, to laptop flat panels, to largegroup projection displays. Resolution and color capability have also seen dramatic improvements, supplying other options for the designer to meet the specific needs of the customer.</p><p>The use of 2D perspective cues such as shading, texture gradients, occlusions, contours, size constancy, and optical flow with standard flat-panel or CRT displays will provide important insights for many tasks. Stereoscopic displays have consistently improved over the years and will be an important option for tasks needing parallax cues of binocular disparity and binocular depth.</p><p>Volumetric display technology will provide an important option for team tasks and those tasks needing many simultaneous views of real-time or multidimensional data. The advantage of this technology is that it provides dynamic animation with walk-around viewing. Volumetric displays give the viewer motion parallax cues (both vertical and horizontal parallax) for all angles of view. Many applications have the requirement for this type of complete all-angle viewing. With the proper software support tools (including an appropriate real time data interface), this display technology can be leveraged to solve many complex and spatial data intensive problems. This technology could greatly improve the way we view results from medical research, improve the safety of the skies, communicate complex flow models, and help us to better understand the world we live in.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The current OmniViewm Volumetric Display</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>See color plates, p. CP-13.) Figure2: Concept of Operation of the OmniViewTM Display Device</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>at the start of the current rotation, P = rotation period of the disk (0.1 s), and Z = desired Z-value for the voxel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure3:</head><label></label><figDesc>Example of a true 3D volumetric display showing a Molniya four satellite constellation orbiting the earth. (Seewlorplates, p. CP-13.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Design and prototype work currently underway at Texas Instruments addresses all these issues. Image quality metrics for volumetric display devices are an open research area. Methods for measuring image quality are being developed at Virginia Polytechnic Institute &amp; State University by Robert Beaton. For a detailed discussion of image quality issues see WILL911.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two Algorithms for the Three-Dimensional Reconstruction of Tomograms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ludke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Crawford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Teeter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="327" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume Rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Drebin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">C o m p u t e r Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988-08" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physician&apos;s Workstation With Real-Time Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goldwasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Al</forename><surname>Et</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>CGA- 00</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">44</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial Orientation From Pictorial Perspective Displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Grunwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 22nd Annual Conference on Manual Control</title>
		<meeting>the 22nd Annual Conference on Manual Control<address><addrLine>Dayton, Ohio</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Orbital Proximity Operations Planning System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Grunwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1988 IEEE Conference on Systems Man and Cybernetics</title>
		<meeting>the 1988 IEEE Conference on Systems Man and Cybernetics<address><addrLine>Peking, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial Orientation by Familiarity Cues</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Grunwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Training</title>
		<editor>J. Patrick and K.D. Duncan</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Elsevier Science Publishers B.V</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Human Decision Making and Control</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ray Tracing Jell-0 Brand Gelatin</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Heckbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3-D Frame Buffers for Interactive Analysis of 3-D Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc</title>
		<meeting>null</meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc. Photo-Opt. lnstrum. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">507</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Part 11: Knowing,&quot; in Pictorial Communication in Virtual and Real Environmenrs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>S . Ellis</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<publisher>Tay Francis Ltd</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chapter 1: Introduction to Volume Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>A. Kaufman</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Los Alamitos, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume Rendering and Data Feature Enhancement</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">C o m p u t e r Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-11" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="26" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching Cubes: A High Resolution 3D Surface Construction Algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>&amp;ore871 Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direction Judgment Errors in Perspective Displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lmcgr841 Mcgreevy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">20th Annual Conference on Manual Control</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Ames Research Center, Moffett Field, Ca</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="14" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual Space and Two-Dimensional Effects in Perspective Displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mcgr851 Mcgreevy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ratzlaff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">21 st Annual Conference on Manual Control, NASA CP-2428</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Volumetric Visualization of Scientific Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Princeton University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chapter 8 in Pictorial Communication in Virtual and Real Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>S. Ellis</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<publisher>Tay Francis Ltd</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Volumetric Visualization of 3-D Data</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laser Based 3D Volumetric Display System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Soltan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Trias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dahlke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SPIEiIS&amp;T Symposium on Electronic Imaging Science and Technology, High-Resolution Displays and Projection Systems</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-02" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="14" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Real-Time Auto-stereoscopic Multiplanar Three-Dimensional Display</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">R D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988-05" />
			<publisher>Society for Information Display</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Anaheim, Ca</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume Visualization Displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Dispfay</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image Quality Metrics for Volumetric Laser Displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donohm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SPIEIIS&amp;T Symposium on Electronic Imaging Science and Technology</title>
		<editor>J.O. Merritt and S.S</editor>
		<meeting>SPIEIIS&amp;T Symposium on Electronic Imaging Science and Technology</meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Stereoscopic Displays and Applications 11</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bellingham, WA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SPIE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991-02" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1457</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="220" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Wl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Search of a True 3-D Image</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>NovemberDecember</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
