<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Four-Dimensional Views of 3D Scalar Fields</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">CN/AS Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CERN CH-1211</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Geneva 23</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indiana University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47405</postCode>
									<settlement>Bloomington</settlement>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Four-Dimensional Views of 3D Scalar Fields</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Scalar functions of three variables, w = f (z , y , z) , are common in many types of scientijic and medical applications. Such JD scaiar fields can be understood as elevation maps in four dimensions, with three independent variables (2, y , z) and a fourth, dependent, variable w that corresponds to the elevations. We show how techniques developed originally for the display of 3-manifolds in 4 0 Euclidean space can be adapted to visualize 3 0 scalar fields in a variety of ways.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>We examine the problem of visualizing scalar functions of three variables, or 3D scalar fields. We adopt the point of view that, just as scalar functions of one and two variables can be viewed as elevation maps in 2D and 3D Cartesian coordinate systems, scalar functions of three variables are elevation maps in a 4D coordinate system, where the value of the function is identified with the fourth dimension.</p><p>That is, if we can visualize y = f(z) as a curve in a 2D Cartesian plane, and z = f (2, y ) as a 3D surface viewable from oblique angles in 3D space, then the function w = f (2, y , z ) should be representable as a 4D volume (technically, a 3-manifold embedded in 4D Euclidean space) viewable from oblique angles in 4D space.</p><p>Previous Work. Surfaces of the form z = f (2, y ) in 3D space may be represented graphically in a variety of ways, including contour plots in a plane, elevationkeyed pseudocolor plots in a plane, oblique views of rectangular grids projected onto the surface, oblique views with elevation-keyed surface pseudocolors, and shaded surface rendering. For volume data of the , Pheng A. Heng</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Department of Computer Science</head><p>Indiana University Bloomington, IN 47405 form w = f(z, y , z), extensive attention has been paid to the 3D analogs of 2D contour plots and pseudocolor maps: see, for example, various methods for constructing isosurfaces <ref type="bibr">[ll,</ref> 11, viewing color-coded density data <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12,</ref><ref type="bibr">61</ref>, making easily visible pseudocolor maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>, and exploiting transport theory <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>. However, except for some exploratory efforts (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">9]</ref>), the analogs of elevation maps for 3D scalar fields have not been pursued to their logical completion.</p><p>The purpose of this paper is to extend methods developed for the rendering of mathematical 3-manifolds embedded in 4D Euclidean space <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr">81</ref> to create a more complete family of volumetric analogs of the standard elevation map techniques used for surface representation. Approach. We suggest that new insights into the properties of 3D scalar fields can be achieved by utilizing the information redundancy present in 4D-rotated pseudocolor volume grids, and by rendering the corresponding 3-manifolds using 4D lighting and shading rules. In particular, the following features of the 4D treatment of 3D scalar fields do not seem to have been fully exploited previously: 0 Grid Planes. Grid lines in 3D plots correspond to the lines (z = constant, y = constant) that divide the surface z = f (2, y ) into square patches. The 3-manifold w = f (2, y, z ) is analogously divisible into cubic patches by the grid planes, (z = const, y = const, z = const).</p><p>Just as tilted grid lines are useful in standard 3D grid plots to give depth cues in 3D, the distortions of the grid planes resulting from 4D rotation of the viewpoint provide strong geometric cues.</p><p>0 Hidden Volume Removal. Clarity is enhanced in 3D by removing hidden surfaces, so that surfaces nearer to the viewpoint occlude those farther away. This is equivalent to making the surface stretched between grid lines opaque and carrying out z-buffered rendering. In 4D, the grid planes enclose volumes rather than areas. Thus, the equivalent procedure in 4D is to use 4D depth buffering (w-buffering) relative to a 4D viewpoint to carry out hidden volume removal. This will cause various pieces of volumes to disappear from the voxel array after 4D rotation because they become occluded by nearer neighbors.</p><p>0 Shading Using 4D Light. There is intrinsic information present in a 3D scalar field viewed as a 4D elevation that is not revealed by projecting level sets to 3D and using 3D lighting. By applying 4D lighting, shading, and specularity algorithms in the manner of [7, 81 while projecting to the 3D voxel array, we can produce a uniquely informative set of shading patterns. In particular, portions of the hypersurface that face in similar directions in 4D can be clearly perceived, so information about derivatives can be visualized more readily.</p><p>In the remainder of the paper, we first give graphical examples of a number of standard methods for handling 2D scalar fields that we will refer to when constructing analogies for 3D scalar fields. We then describe 4D analogs of 3D methods for viewing elevation grids, outline 4D shading methods, and show some examples.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Three-Dimensional Shape Plots</head><p>Functions of the form z = f(x, y) can be displayed using standard software packages such as NCSA Image, Mathematica, gnuplot, etc., to show the shape of the function. Here, by way of introduction to the 4D methods, we show a family of standard 3D plotting methods generated by the PAW package [2].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Let us take as examples the equations</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">z = Jmax(0,l-x2 -y2) (1)</formula><p>for a hemisphere plotted in the range -1 &lt; x &lt; 1 and -1 &lt; y &lt; 1, and</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">1 z = exp(-x2 -y2) + ;z exp(-(z +3)2 -(~+ 3 )~) (2)</formula><p>for a double Gaussian bump plotted in the range -5 &lt; x &lt; 2 and -5 &lt; y &lt; 2.</p><p>Then, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1, 2</ref>, and 5 , we can plot the hemisphere (Equation (1)) in the following ways: 0 Contours and Icons. In <ref type="figure">Figure l</ref>(a), we show the "straight-down" view of the hemisphere contour plot. The only cues we have for the depth are the labels or styles of the contour lines. A related method, shown in l(b), plots icons (e.g., squares) whose size is keyed to the z-value at equally spaced (2, y) grid points. which has no occlusion, to a very oblique viewpoint <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(d), we see the hemisphere "rising out of the background," in a manner of speaking. The most oblique view has the most occlusion, and also shows the profile of the highest elevation points dramatically. The regions with high specular reflection give additional cues about surface orientation.</p><p>Next, we show in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> a similar sequence of displays for the double Gaussian bump, Equation (2). 0 Grid. As shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>(a), we can get a very good image of the 3D structure using just the oblique perspective of the bare grid with hidden surfaces removed.</p><p>Figures 1(a), l(b), 2(a), 5(a), and 5(c) are the simplest examples of 2D scalar field representations. The data plots were generated by looking "straight down" at the data and visualizing the values of the elevations in various ways with this constraint. Analogs of each of these depictions can be constructed for 3D scalar fields as well. For example, contour lines for 3D scalar fields are basically nested shells produced by an isosurface construction algorithm <ref type="bibr">[ll,</ref> 11. If we add pseudocolor to indicate where the level sets are located within the volume, we can use the "tiny cubes" algorithm of <ref type="bibr">Nielson et al. [13]</ref> to make the interior voxels of the cube visible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Pseudocolor 4D Hemisphere</head><p>we used for illustration in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1, 2</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>, and 5 as</head><p>We can easily define a 4D analog of the hemisphere w = Jmax(0,l-2 2 -yzz 2 ) .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(3)</head><p>The 4D analog of the 3D method used to produce <ref type="figure">Figure 5(c)</ref> gives the cubic representation of the "hemispherical" 3D scalar field shown in the upper left of <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>. Here the pseudocolored cubic latticework is an undistorted "3D checkerboard," just as the straight-down view of the square checkerboard grid is undistorted in <ref type="figure">Figure 5(c)</ref>. We may of course choose to alter the 3D viewpoint, but this does not alter the actual lattice geometry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">4D "Transparent" Volume Grids</head><p>If we now rotate in 4D before projecting to 3D, we introduce a distortion in the apparent form of the cubic lattice that persists regardless of how we change the 3D viewpoint. The image in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows this effect without attempting to distinguish whether one <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>: Four 3D viewpoints of the hemispherical 2D scalar field given by Equation (1). (a) is straight down, and has no occlusion. (b) and (c) show the hemisphere as it rises from the background as we rotate the 3D viewpoint; we begin to see some occlusion. Finally, in (d) we see a very oblique view with extensive occlusion and a profile explicitly showing the elevation of the hemisphere above the background. <ref type="figure">(PAW images [2]</ref>.) lattice cube hides another in 4D. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> treats the small 4D cubes making up the grid volume as transparent in 4D, but opaque once projected to 3D; this makes the resulting image easier to interpret as a 3D structure. This image is the analog of <ref type="figure">Figure l(d)</ref> if we displayed the surface using small tilted quadrilaterals with open space around the edges and did not remove back-facing surfaces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">4D Pseudocolor Grid</head><p>By assigning a pseudocolor map to the values in the voxel array, we can generate a volume image with scalar values coded by color. Rotating the grid in 4D causes these colored regions to shift in such a way that a redundant value cue is produced, as we show in <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>. The pseudocolor attached to any particular volume element remains fixed to a particular element, just as it did when we rotated in 3D to make the transition from <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>(c) to <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Hidden Volume Removal in 4D</head><p>The grid can now be rendered using 4D depth buffering to eliminate confusion between overlapping volumes, just as we used hidden surface elimination in 3D to make the image of <ref type="figure">Figure l(d)</ref>. A typical result from a 4D viewpoint is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref>. Now we see a very strange phenomenon from the point of view of an observer accustomed to 3D mesh plots: instead of having tilted rectangles hidden by other tilted rectangles in the foreground, we have distorted cubes that are truncated by other opaque distorted cubes that sit in front of them in 4D.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">4D Illumination and Shading</head><p>Our final method is the 4D analog of the 3D shading method used in <ref type="figure">Figures 2 and 6(d)</ref>. We use lighting and shading in four dimensions to reveal geometric characteristics of the 3D scalar field's elevation map. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>: An image of a 4D hemisphere represented as a bare grid without removing hidden 4D volumes, but treating solid cubes in the 3D projection as opaque. We show four stages in the 4D rotation.</p><p>In particular, this method provides a quick insight into regions of the elevation map that have similar 4D normals. The details are given in Hanson and Heng <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(7,8]</ref>; we provide a brief overview here for completeness.</p><p>Four-dimensional shading models with specularity can be introduced by computing the normals at each vertex, either by taking the gradient of the equation defining the 3-manifold, taking the cross-product of the three tangents to a grid point on the 3-manifold in 4D, or averaging the normals to the volumes surrounding the point. For parametric volumes, this computation i ?v$v: s computing the three tangent fourvectors <ref type="figure">( P , Q , R )</ref> emerging from the grid point in "right-handed" order. The four-vector that is perpendicular to this family of tangents has components that are the cofactors of the first column of the following determinant, which is the generalization of the crossproduct to 4D:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">Det (4)</formula><p>To compute the n o r m 4 at the grid point, we normalize the four-vector N given by the coefficients of <ref type="figure">( 2 , $ , 2 , &amp; )</ref> in Equation (4) and call that N . If all we know are the tangents to the volumes surrounding the vertex, we compute all the volume normals using a determinant of this same form, normalize the resulting normals, average them, and normalize again to get the grid-point normal I?.</p><p>However one finds the normal at each 4D vertex point, the result is then used in the standard shading equations (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> for <ref type="bibr">3D and [7]</ref> for additional 4D discussion). The smooth shaded term with normalized lighting vector L, is added to the specular term,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">I p = I1 ( B . NIk ,</formula><p>where B is the normalized average of the direction to the camera and the direction to the light source. The intensity in either term is generally set to zero if the corresponding dot product is negative.</p><p>One then projects volume elements from the tessellated 3-manifold in 4D space to a 3D view volume of voxels, interpolates the normals from voxel to voxel, applies the selected shading algorithm, and renders the resulting intensity into the voxel array. Such view volume images are 4D analogs of the 3D view plane images in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. The voxel data must itself be volume rendered to produce an ordinary image. In <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>, we apply this approach to render the hemisphere-like 3-manifold given by Equation <ref type="formula">3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Example Applications</head><p>To illustrate the application of some of our methods to real data, we first show in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 9</ref> a comparison between two ways of rendering a set of astronomical binary star density data. On the left is a standard volume rendering produced by the AVS "tracer" module <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>. On the right, we show a shaded rendering of the same data using our 4D lighting technique. Note that our actual rendering is a volume image, which must itself be volume rendered to produce this 2D image; a rotating animation or a stereographic image would show the internal structure of our depiction more clearly. Previously invisible features, basically corresponding to regions with similar 4D gradients, are revealed by our approach.</p><p>Next we repeat the same comparison for a data set describing the electron density of the hydrogen molecule. The left image in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> shows a standard AVS volume rendering. On the right, we show for comparison a 4D shaded rendering of the density elevation plot. Again, we see suggestive additional structure in our 4D rendering. We have proposed many other related 4D visualization methods as well, but cannot present further examples of them all here; the fundamental feature of our other methods is the systematic exploitation of redundant geometric cues in four dimensions, as exemplified by Figures 7 and 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Remarks: 3D Fields as 4D Images</head><p>Since one of the main techniques introduced in this paper was the creation of a volume image from 3D scalar field elevation maps using 4D lighting and shading methods, one might imagine reversing the process. That is, one might consider the 3D scalar field data itself to be the result of a 4D imaging process. Given some reasonable assumptions about what 4D lighting parameters produced the data, one could in principle reconstruct some information about what sort of 4D object could have produced the observed image.</p><p>Unfortunately, just what constitutes a "reasonable" assumption is extremely ambiguous, so that we have not been able to systematically deduce relevant interpretations of 3D scalar fields as images of 4D objects (unless, of course, the fields happen to be derived from a 4D imaging process). This nevertheless remains an intriguing additional approach related to the ones presented in this paper, and one which might be of use in some special circumstances.    </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>0Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Surface Grids. In Figures l(c) and (d), we show oblique views of a block or "lego" representation and of a grid-line plot with hidden surfaces removed. These approaches provide additional clarity to the viewer because only the nearest block tops or patches of the tilted checkerboard pattern are visible; areas lying on the grid behind a foreground patch are hidden from view. In l(d), the distorted projections of individual outlines that are perfect squares in the straight-down view (see 5(c)) also give additional depth information.0 Pseudocolor Contours. Representing the contours as color areas instead of grid lines, as in Figure 5(a), makes it easier to distinguish limited ranges of elevation if the color map is carefully chosen. No geometric cues are present.0 Oblique Pseudocolor Contour. InFigure 5(b), we combine the information in the pseudocolor contour plot with the geometric cues of an oblique view of the colored surface without a grid. This provides very useful redundant cues for the function values, since both the color and the 3D aspect of the image contain similar information about t. Line-drawing approaches to displaying the 3D structure of a hemisphere, a simple example of a 2D scalar field given by Equation (1).(a) Straight-down contour map. (b) Straight-down variable-size icon map. (c) Oblique block or "lego" map. (d) Oblique grid line elevation map. (PAW images [2].)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(d). The lower right image in Figure 7 is similar in spirit to Figures 5(d) and 6(c) due to the three-fold redundancy of the in-formation display.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 5 :Figure 6 :Figure 7 :</head><label>567</label><figDesc>2-D scalar field of equation (1): (a) straightdown pseudocolor map; (b) oblique view; (c) with grid lines; (d) oblique view. (PAW images (21.) Oblique views of 2-D scalar field of equation (2): (a) grid lines alone; (b) pseudocolor alone; (c) both; (d) shaded 3-0 rendering. (PAW images (21.) 4-D rotations of pseudocolored 4-D hemisphere. The color of each small cube remains fixed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Oblique view of 4-D hemisphere with pseudocolor grid and hidden volume elimination.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>(Left) volume rendering of binary star density data using the AVS tracer' module. (Right) our 4-D shaded rendering of the data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>(Left) AVS volume rendering of the electron density field of a hydrogen molecule, (Right) our 4-D shaded rendering of the same data.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="0">Pseudocolor Straight-Down Grid. In Figure 5(c), we superimpose a straight-down view of the grid outline, seen obliquely in Figures l(d) and 5(d), on the pseudocolor contours. Again, no geometric cues are present.0 Pseudocolor Oblique Grid. However, if we make an oblique view, as inFigure 5(d), we get additional information, now triply redundant: the color, the hidden surface effect, and the distortion of the grid lines. This image is the richest we can construct because it exhibits the shape information to the viewer in multiple modes with little ambiguity.0 Shaded Specular Surface. InFigure 2, we show how the shaded hemisphere would appear from an assortment of viewpoints. As we move from the straight-down viewpointFigure 2(a),</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="0">Pseudocolor. Adding pseudocolor to a perspective view with no grid structure as in Figure 6(b) gives dual cuesthe oblique view of the elevation with hidden surfaces removed, and the redundant color assignment of each elevation contour. 0 Pseudocolor Grid. The distortion of the grid squares in the oblique projection adds a third cue, as shown in Figure 6(c).0 Shaded Specular Surface. InFigure 6(d), we assume a reflective surface, introduce 3D lighting, and use standard shading techniques<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> to create a shaded scene rendering. This image has a very natural aspect, and contains information about the shape of the surface that is compelling for most viewers. This shaded view contains information about the surface orientation that is more explicit than in the other methods.3 Four-Dimensional Shape Plots</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">(See color plates, p. CP-1 1 .)</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>We gratefully acknowledge the support of the staff and the use of the facilities at CICA, the Indiana University Center for Innovative Computer Applications. We are indebted to Brian Kaplan and Peter Shirley for suggestive remarks and for access to the volume data used in the application figures. A.J.H. thanks RenC Brun and the CN/AS group at CERN for their patience in revealing the workings of the PAW system.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building surfaces of evolution: the weaving wall</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Computer Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">PAW -Physics Analysis Workstation, The Complete Reference</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Couet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vandoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Zanarini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1.07</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989-10" />
			<pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CERN</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shades of a Higher Dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics World</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing n-Dimensional Virtual Worlds with n-Vision</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Beshers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics: Principles and Practice</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Addison Wesley, Reading, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Visualization of 3D Medical Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing the Fourth Dimension Using Geometry and Light</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization 91</title>
		<meeting>Visualization 91<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA; Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="328" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Figure 4: 4D lighting and shading applied to the hemispherical 3D scalar field of Equation (3). The four different 4D viewing angles shown here exhibit the 4D analog of the 3D view-dependent shading effects in Figure 2</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illuminating the Fourth Dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Comp. Graphics and Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Displaying Manifolds in Four-Dimensional Space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hoffmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<pubPlace>Lafayette, IN</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Purdue University Computer Science Department Report: Computing About Physical Objects, Purdue University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Application of Transport Theory to Visualization of 3-D Scalar Data Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching Cubes: A High Resolution 3D Surface Construction Algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH 87</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH 87</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing and Modeling Scattered Multivariate Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Comp. Graphics and Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Techniques for the Interactive Visualization of Volumetric Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization 90</title>
		<meeting>Visualization 90<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA; Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="50" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Polygonal Approximation to Direct Scdar Volume Rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shirley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tuchman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hidden Volumes: The 4th Dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics World</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Application Visualization System : A Computational Environment for Scientific Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Upson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Faulhaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kamins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Laidlaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schlegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vroom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Comp. Graphics and Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
