<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Color, Change, and Control for Quantitative Data Display</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Penny</forename><surname>Rheingans</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>27599-3175</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Color, Change, and Control for Quantitative Data Display</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Color is used widely and reliably to display the value of a single scalar variable. It ismore rarely, and far less reliably, used to display multivariate data. Calico, a dynamic tool for the creation and manipulation of color mappings, adds the element of dynamic control over the color mapping to that of color itselffor the more efsective display and exploration of multivariate spatial data. Using Calico, a one-or twovariable color mapping can be created using parametric equations and a variety of color moakls. This mapping can be manipulated by moving input devices referenced in the parametric expressions, by applying afine transform. or by performing free-form deformations. As the user changes the mapping, an image showing the data displayed using the current mapping is updated in real time, along with the images describing the mapping. This paper presents an empirical study investigating the effects of user control and smooth change in the display of quantitative data on user accuracy, confidence, andpreference. While the user control did not quite produce a significant effect on accuracy, it did produce significant increases in user preference and confidence.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Commonly, a researcher wishes to explore a large set of data in order to develop an understanding of the structure and relationships within the data. She may have informal or incomplete hypotheses about that data that she wishes to develop further. This sort of exploratory process differs from more formal hypothesis testing in that specific beliefs about the precise meaning of the data have not yet been formed. Representing the data visually for this exploratory process is appealing because it allows viewers to harness the powerful processing capabilities of the human visual syslem. Some structures in the data, especially those involving complex spatial relationships and patterns, are easy to detect visually, but difficult to specify for computational detection.</p><p>This work is intended to aid researchers whose primary interest is in the spatial structure of the variables under study, in particular, in the spatial structure of the interrelationships between the variables. A researcher interested in understanding the spatial distribution and pattern of a data set might explore whether two variables seemed to be related over a data space, how the geometry of the data space affects such a relationship, and whether isovalue points form some sort of structure. Dynamic representations enable the researcher to explore the temporal consistency of a pattem over a manipulation, providing more insight into the nature of the spatial distribution of the variables. Where spatial correspondence between the variables is important, a representation with both variables displayed in the same image is preferable to a representation where each variable is displayed in its own image. Displaying both variables on the same map can show subtle differences between spatial pattems such as spatial offsets or shape differences.</p><p>Representing multivariate data using color is attractive because the human visual system is capable of differentiating easily among hundreds of colors. Data values can also be displayed using color in a smaller area than they could be using parameters such as texture or shape. Selecting a onevariable color mapping which shows, or can be manipulated to show, thedata effectively can be a difficult task. Selecting an effective two-variable color mapping is even more difficult. Although some study has been given to evaluating the effectiveness of one variable-color or discrete two-variable mappings [for example, Pizer and Zimmerman 83; Ware 88; Levkowitz 88; Wainer and Francolini 801, almost none has been given to the experimental evaluation of continuous twovariable mappings. This sort of experimental evaluation is an important part of research into the effective display of multivariate data. This paper presents a tool for the selection and manipulation of two-variable color mappings along with an experimental evaluation of a family such mappings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Related Work</head><p>A number of systems have been developed for the interactive design of one-variable color mappings. Some of these systems appear as parts of commercially available visualization packages; a few which haveappeared in theliteratureare described below. Robertson built a system which interactively displays color gamuts of display devices to help data analysts visualize perceptual color spaces and understand their components <ref type="bibr">[Robertson 881</ref>. Cox developed a tool for the interactivedesign of single variablecolor mappings using spatially periodic, functional control over the red, green, and blue components <ref type="bibr">[Cox 881</ref>. Guitard and Ware built a similar tool wherecolor sequences weredescribed by curves for their hue, saturation, and value components <ref type="bibr">[Guitard and Ware 901</ref>. An earlier version of Calico allowed for the dynamic manipulation of one-variable color mappings using either RGB or HLS space Fheingans and Tebbs 901. None of these systems allowed for the design of two-variable color mappings and none seem to have been evaluated experimentally.</p><p>Other researchers have established a theoretical basis for the design of bivariate color sequences. <ref type="bibr">Trumbo [81]</ref> presented aconceptual h e w o r k for the selection and evaluation of bivariate color sequences. He proposed four basic criteria for effective displays. Order : if data values are ordered, the colors chosen to represent them should be perceived as ordered. Separation : significantly different levels of variables should be represented by distinguishable colors. Rows and Columns : if preservation of univariate information is important, then display parameters should not obscure one another. Diagonal : if detection of positive association of variables is a goal, then the displayed colors should be easily identified as belonging to one of three classes : those near the major diagonal, those above it, and those below. Trumbo uses these principles to develop a number of color sequences. <ref type="bibr">Robertson and O'Callaghan [86]</ref> address the problem of realizing Trumbo's color sequences in a perceptually uniform color space. In a perceptually uniform color space, equal Euclidean distances within the space correspond to equal perceptual differences. The LUV and LAB spaces developed by CIE are examples of perceptually uniform color spaces. <ref type="bibr">Pham [90]</ref> proposed the use of spline-based curve, surface, and subspace generation to implement the concepts of <ref type="bibr">Trumbo [81]</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Robertson and O'Callaghan</ref>  <ref type="bibr">[&amp;I,</ref><ref type="bibr">and Ware I881</ref> for the design of color sequences for univariate, bivariate,andtrivariatedatamappings. B-splinesprovidedamechanism for the interactive creation of color sequences through a set of key colors and local sequence modifications, Although sequences were created interactively, no immediate display of data using those sequences seems to have been implemented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Color Mappings</head><p>A mapping from data variable values to display colors is composed of a color space which defines the components of color itnda curve or surface through that space. A color space is tht space spanned by three orthogonal basis vectors. Each basis vector correwonds to one component of a color model. For example, the KGB color space is cube-shaped and the basis vectors correspond to the red, green, and blue components.</p><p>The color path is a one-dimensional parametric curve in the color space which defines the color gamut of the mapping. As the path curves through the color space it completely describes the sequence of colors used in a mapping f " a set of values of a single scalar variable to a set of colors (f(s), s = distance along the path). For example, if median family income for U.S. counties is mapped to a combination of hue and lightness using a rainbow scale in the HLS model, the color path runs through the hues in an ascending spiral from black to white. See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 1</ref>. Counties with a low median family income would be displayed in dark reds, those with an average median income in medium greens and blues, and those with a very high median income in pale purples.</p><p>The color gamut for a mapping from the values of two scalar variables to a single color is described by a surface through the color space. At each point, this color sheet shows the color used to represent a particular combination of the values of the two data variables. When all combinations of values are considered, a surface is formed. For example, a color scheme might map mean education level to hue and median income to brightness (using an I U S space). See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 2</ref>. Areas with low education levels wouldbereds, dark when median income is low and pale when it is high. Areas with a relatively average education level would be blues, dark when median income is low and pale when it is high.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Calico</head><p>In order to create useful color representations, a user must have a view of the entire gamut of representation colors and a view of the data displayed using this mapping. Additionally, a view of the color gamut in context, for example within a color space, can help the user better understand the source of the mapping. If the user can also manipulate the mapping directly and in real-time, he or she can more easily explore the data by watching how the data image changes as the color mapping is changed.</p><p>In Calico, the color space appears in the center of the screen, with the color gamut (path for one variable or sheet for two variables) represented by a curve or surface within the space. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 2</ref> shows the Calico display for a mapping of two scalar variables. The color gamut appears in the lower right of the screen. The upper left portion of the screen contains the image space showing how a 2D data set is represented using the current color scheme. Changes to the mapping are made in the color space and reflected in realtime in the image space.</p><p>A color space is represented by colored samples scattered through the portion of the space which is displayable on the current display. These samples are regularly spaced in the underlying coordinate system of the space. In Calico, color mappings can be created, viewed, and manipulated using any one of the RGB, Smith's HLS <ref type="bibr">[Smith 781,</ref><ref type="bibr">or CIELW color models.</ref> In Calico, color paths and sheets are implemented using splines through a set of control points. Color sequence control points are generated from parametric expressions which specify the color component values in terms of data variable values and input device positions. The parametric expressions can contain symbolic data variables (u,v), dynamic input device variables (S for slider position; TX, TY, and TZ for joystick deflection), arithmetic operators, and built-in function calls. The color mapping shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 2</ref> would be specified by the equations :</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Hue - U Lightness = v Saturation = 1.0 -</formula><p>In the same example, the saturation can be tied to a slider by changing the third equation to :</p><p>Saturation = S Now when the slider is moved to its maximum position, the representation shows saturated colors of varying brightness. When the slider is moved to its minimum value, the saturation is reduced to zero and the representation reduces to a grey scale showing median income as lightness; no information about education level is visible in the example image. As the slider is moved slowly up from minimum, the hues representing education level gradually fade back in Expressions containing input device variables are reevaluated when the corresponding input device is moved. A color sheet can be edited by affine transformations or by grabbing and dragging control points of the sheet. During such freeform deformations, a slider controls the degree to which nearby conuol points are dragged along with the grabbed point. Both the example image and the geometry of the color sequence change in real-time as the user manipulates the input devices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Experimental Design</head><p>An empirical study was conducted to investigate the roles of user control of the color mapping and smooth change between images in the exploration of quantitative multivariate data. Specifically, it was hypothesized that dynamic control over the representation would increase subject accuracy and confidence in a data comprehension task. Additionally, it was expected that smooth change between representations would also increase subject accuracy and confidence. In order to make mining and testing times manageable, subjects were limited to a single type of manipulation of a particular family of color mappings.</p><p>Design. This experiment employed a two-factor, wilhinsubject, partially-counterbalanced design. This design balanced the effects of both mal order and data sets. The two factors determining the type of representation were the degree of control over one representation parameter (the balance between the two colors representing the two data variables) and the smoothness of change between levels of that parameter. Three levels of the control factor and two levels of the smoothness factor were presented. See <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Representations provided either no control over the balance parameter, control only over pacing of different views, or complete control over the balance between the two colors. Additionally, representations displayed either discontinuous uansitions between parameter levels or relatively smooth change between levels (approximately 10 frames per second of user motion). Generally, a subject requested that the space and/or sheet be tumedoff for either all or none of the trials. Since a within-subject design compares a subject's score under one test condition to that subject's score under other test conditions, this should have little or no effect on the experimental results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Display</head><p>Thematic maps were displayed using one of the six representations shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. In each representation, one data variable was mapped to levels of green and the other to levels of purple. See Figure4. This family of mappings was chosen because it satisfies Trumbo's criteria of order, separability, preservation of univariate information, and diagonality. Specifically, the use of complementary colorsas the display parameters ensures the displayed colors resolve into three basic classes : roughly equal magnitudes of the two variables (greys), U &gt; v (purples), and v &gt; U (greens). In each trial, many images were shown, each with a different balance between the relative contributions of the two variables, ranging from only one variable to only the other.  shows three images of the data, each with a different balance between the relative contributions of the two variables. The representations differed in how the subject controlled the relative contributions and how often updates occur. The six representations were :</p><p>1. Slide Show Representation : Subjects viewed multiple static images of the data, with varying relative contributions of the two parameters. Five unique images were shown in a repeating loop. A new view appeared every 5 seconds. The subject had no control over the content or pacing of the images.</p><p>2. Slide Projector Representation : Subjects viewed multiple static images of the data, with varying relative contributions of the two parameters. Five unique images were shown in a repeating loop. A new view appeared when the subject pressed a button. The subject had control over the pacing, but not the content, of the images. 3. Interactive Representation : Subjects viewed multiple static images. Subjects interactively manipulated the representation by selecting values for the balance between the two parameters using a slider valuator and pressing a button to generate the new representation. The subject had control over both the pacing and content of the images.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Constant Loop :</head><p>Subjects viewed a single precomputed film loop. This film loop showed the effects of smoothly varying the relative contributions of the two parameters, but did not allow the subject to control the manipulation. The loop contained 34 unique images with a full cycle completing every 3.5 seconds. Procedure. Each subject participated in two sessions. The first session consisted of an introduction to the representations and their manipulation followed by six trials, one trial using each representation. The introduction consisted of a written, tutorial-like presentation of each type of representation for data similar to, but not the same as, that used in the rest of the experiment. In each trial, subjects were given a written description of the data and representation for that trial and asked to explore the data set while filling out a worksheet of questions about the data. The worksheet in each trial was the same except for references U, the particular variables presented in that trial. See the appendix for an example worksheet. After all trials were complete the subject fded out a final questionaire comparing the representations. The second session consisted of six additional trials, one trial using each representation, followed by another final questionaire.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Multispeed Loop</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Results</head><p>In all analyses, a within-subjects analysis was used; that is, the scores of a subject using one representation method were compared with the scores of that same subject using other representation methods. The analyses performed were comparison of percentage error difference between representations for a single-variable question, comparison of percentage error difference between representations for a two-variable question, two factor analysis of variance (ANOVA) of accuracy attributable to manipulability and smooth change of a representation, and two factor ANOVA of confidence data. Additionally, subjects' preferences for representations were examined. In the sections below, mean values for preference, percenterror, andconfidencearegiven to convey a sense of the direction and pattern of differences.</p><p>Subject Preferences. Subjects were asked to rank the representations from 1 to 6 (1 is most preferred; 6 is least preferred). Almost without exception, subjects ranked the dynamic representation as the most preferred, usually followed by the interactive representation. Subjects almost always ranked either the slide show or constant loop as the least preferred representation. Representations were usually ranked in order of increasing control. Within a pair of representations with the same amount of control, for example Slide Projector and Multispeed Loop, some subjects usually ranked the representation with smooth change higher, while other subjects usually ranked it lower. <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> shows the pattern of preference means. Most subjects gave identical rankings after the two sessions. There was no clear pattern of change among those subject who changed their rating between the sessions.</p><p>In comments about why they ranked the representations as they did, most subjects mentioned that they liked having control over the representation. Accordingly, many subjects found the interactive representation to be almost as good as the dynamic. Some subjects also mentioned liking smooth change between parameter balance levels. On the negative side, many subjects mentioned that they were most frustrated by representations where they had to wait for the image they wanted or where they could not freeze the display on a particular view.</p><p>Error Diflerences. For each data set, subjects answered questions about the value of a variable in an area (onevariable questionsee question 1 on the sample worksheet in the appendix) or about the value of a variable in areas wherethevalueoftheothervariablemetsomecriterion(twovariable questionsee question 2 on the sample worksheet). On one-variable questions, there were small, almost significant (p&lt;O.lOusingStudent's t-test)differencesinerrorrates betweenrepmentations.Figure7 showsthepattemofmeans. <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> shows the analysis of variance. On this question, subjects had lower emor rates using manipulable representa- also had slightly lower e m r rates using representations which did not provide smooth change. There was no real coherent pattem of differences in accuracy on the twovariable question. This does not necessarily mean that there was no difference in accuracy, but does mean that any such difference was dwarfed by the variability in error rates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>Conj?dence. Subjects were asked to rate their confidence in their answers on a scale from 1 to 10. In general, subjects were significantly more confident (p &lt; 0.01 and p &lt; 0.025, respectively for the one-and two-variable questions) about their answers using manipulable than using nonmanipulable representations. This means that there is less than a 1 or 2.5 percent chance that the observed difference is the result of normal variation. The two-factor ANOVA also shows an effect of the interaction between degree of control and smoothness of change that approaches significance. Specifically, control was even more important in representations that were changing smoothly. <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref> shows the pattem of means whileFigures lOand 11 show theanalysisof variance. Results suggest that subjects used their control over the representationspartly toremove unwantedinformation. This was most apparent on the single-variable question where subjects manipulated the representation to show only the desired variable. Accordingly, the answers to this question wcre slightly more accurate when the subject could manipulate the representation. A few subjects manipulated the representation this same way when answering the twovariable question, first viewing one variable, then the other, with few or no intermediate steps. This strategy was less successful on this question, resulting in answers that were no more accurate than using nonmanipulable representations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Discussion</head><p>Subjects found that different representations and manipulations were best suited for answering different types of questions. 146.47 71 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 1</ref> 1. Two -factor ANOVA for twevariable confidence, is because control was important for isolating one variable, but smoothness was not helpful. When looking at relationships between variables, control was still important, but smoothness mattered as well. Another subject observed that slow changes were good for examining detail while fast changes were useful for gaining an overall feel for the data. During the exploratory phase of dataanalysis, the researcher may ask a wide range of questions about the data. A tool providing multiple representations and a variety of manipulations can help the researcher gain insight into the answers to these questions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Conclusions</head><p>Calico, a dynamic tool for the creation and manipulation of color mappings for the exploration of multivariate, quantitative data, was used to study theeffects of user control and smooth change on user preference, accuracy, and confidence. The results of the study, as well as other user experiences with Calico, support the hypothesis that dynamic manipulation of color mappings is a useful feature of systems for the exploration of quantitative data using color. The main effect observed so far is a clear user preference for representations providing control over the mapping, a small but significant increase in accuracy, and greater confidence in information gleaned from manipulable displays. A smaller and less consistent effect showed greater user preference for and confidence in representations which provided smooth change between images.</p><p>More experimental study is needed to more comprehensively evaluate the effectiveness of data display techniques.</p><p>Two important directions are the study of actual researchers in more natural data exploration situations and the consideration of more qualitative aspects of data analysis. While it is easier to judge the accuracy of quantitative questions like those asked in this experiment, insight into the qualitative nature of the pattems and interrelationships within the data is probably a more important product of data exploration.      </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>.</head><label></label><figDesc>Stimulus images were displayed on a 512 X 512 Tektronix model 690SR monitor driven by the pixel-Planes 4graphicssystem [Fuchs,et.al.85].SeeFigure4.Athematic map of the continental United States occupied the upper left quarter of the screen.The thematic map showed two socioeconomic variables collected by the 1980 Census. Each county was colored to display the value of the variables using a particular representation scheme. A legend showing the range of colors used to represent each data variable occupied the lower right section of the screen. The center of the screen contained a wire-frame sheet showing the location of the color gamut in the HLS color space. The color space and sheet were tumed off if the subject wished.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 5</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>:</head><label></label><figDesc>Subjects viewed a single precomputed film loop showing the effects of smoothly varying the relative contributions of the two parameters. Subjects controlled the speed of the loop using a slider valuator. The speed selected ranged from full stop to a complete cycle each half second.6. Dynamic Manipulation : Subjects dynamically manipulated the relative contributions with a slider valuator. The displayed image changed dynamically in response to these manipulations.Subjects. The 12 subjects were volunteers recruited from among the graduate students and staff of the UNC Computer Science Department. All subjects were found to have normal color vision by the North Carolina Department of Motor Vehicles.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Color path.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 5a.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Calico displa Median famil income is dis la ed using hue, wkle average edrucation level is cfsphed using brightness.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Sample stimulus Image. Income is displayed by levels of green, while education i s displ ed by levels of purple. The mapping i</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 5c.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>(a-c): Four levels of relative variable contribution: a) shows just the contribution of education level, b) balanced contributions of education and income, c) just the contribution of income level. (See wiorplates, p. CP-28.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Pattem of means : Dercent error, Error means for each representation as a percentage of the range of that data variable. The upper table shows error means for one-</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Control</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>None</cell><cell></cell><cell>Pace</cell><cell>Complete</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Slide</cell><cell></cell><cell>Slide</cell><cell>Interac tive</cell></row><row><cell>Jerky</cell><cell>Show</cell><cell></cell><cell>Projector</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Change</cell><cell>7.63</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>8.04</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Constant</cell><cell>M u l t i s p</cell><cell>Dynamic</cell></row><row><cell>Smooth</cell><cell>LOOP</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>7.25</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>8.42</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Slide</cell><cell></cell><cell>Slide</cell><cell>Interactive</cell></row><row><cell>Jerky</cell><cell cols="2">Show</cell><cell>Projector</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Change</cell><cell>5.42</cell><cell></cell><cell>6.21</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Constant Multispeed</cell><cell>Dynamic</cell></row><row><cell>Smooth</cell><cell cols="2">Loop</cell><cell>Loop</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>5.29</cell><cell></cell><cell>6.00</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>I Subject confidence</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ipper tableon shows</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>.ions; the lower table</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>le questions. In both</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>whereas 10 shows</cell></row><row><cell>source</cell><cell>SS</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>MS</cell><cell>F</cell></row><row><cell>subjects</cell><cell>34.34</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>3.12</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>control</cell><cell>9.08</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4.54</cell><cell>6.38 ~~0 . 0 1</cell></row><row><cell>dynamic</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>1</cell><cell cols="2">0.03 0.07</cell></row><row><cell>CxD</cell><cell>1.75</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0.88</cell><cell>1.20</cell></row><row><cell>c x s</cell><cell cols="2">15.67 22</cell><cell>0.71</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>DXS</cell><cell>4.59</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0.42</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CxDxS</cell><cell cols="2">16.00 22</cell><cell>0.73</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>81.47</cell><cell>71</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">One subject commented that the interactive and</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Figure 10. Two-factor ANOVA for one-variable confidence</cell></row><row><cell>source</cell><cell>SS</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>MS</cell><cell>F</cell></row><row><cell>subjects</cell><cell>56.68</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>5.15</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>control</cell><cell>13.00</cell><cell>2</cell><cell cols="2">6.50 4.41 ~~0 . 0 2 5</cell></row><row><cell>dynamic</cell><cell>0.42</cell><cell>1</cell><cell cols="2">0.42 0.32</cell></row><row><cell>CxD</cell><cell>3.69</cell><cell>2</cell><cell cols="2">1.85 1.57 p &lt; 0.25</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">c x s D~S C~D~S Fipure 7. Total c x s DxS Total 32.42 22 1.47 14.37 11 1.31 CXDXS 25.89 22 1.18</cell><cell>0.07 0.05 0.33 0.15</cell><cell>22 11 71 22</cell><cell>0.00 0.00 0.01</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>I am grateful for the valuable contributions of many people to this research. Brice Tebbs supplied the initial inspiration for Calico and some key parts of its implementation. The software efforts of the whole Pixel-Planes team made the implementation of Calico possible. Greg Turk, Frederick P. Brooks, Jr., and various anonymous reviewers provided insightful suggestions about both this research and this paper. Terry Yoo contributed constant encouragement and truly heroic photography.</p><p>This work has been supported in part by grants from the NIH Division of Research Resources (#5-R24-RR-02170) and the Office of Naval Research (#NOOO14-86-K-0680).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix : Sample Worksheet</head><p>The images that you will see show two socioeconomic variables : median age and percentage of workers who drive to work. As in the tutorial, these variables are represented by levels of green and purple. Specifically, Green = median age Purple = percentage of workers who drive to work Each image shows a different balance between the two variables. Each will be shown for a few seconds. When all images have been shown, the display will go back to the beginning of the series. How confident are you about this figure?</p><p>Not 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 1OVery confident confident 3. How correlated do the variables appear to you?</p><p>Negatively Not Positively correlated correlated correlated 5 4 3 2 1 0 1 2 3 4 5</p><p>How confident are you about this judgement? Not 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 1 0 V e r y confident confident 4. Point out aplace that seems interesting to you. Why does it seem interesting?</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using the Supercomputer to Visualize Higher Dimensions: An Artist&apos;s Contribution to Scientific Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Donna</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science, andTechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Journal ofArt</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Henry</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Goldfeather</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeff</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hultquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Susan</forename><surname>Spach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Austin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Frederick</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brooks</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Eyles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Poulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fast Spheres, Shadows, Textures, Transparencies, and Image Enhancements in Pixel-Planes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AColor SequenceEditor</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Richardandcolim</forename><surname>Guitard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="338" to="341" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Color in Computer Graphic Representation of Two-Dimensional Parameter Distributions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Haim</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="19881" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ph.D. dissertation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spline-based Color Sequences for Univariate, Bivariate, and Trivariate Mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Binh</forename><surname>Pham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings: Visualization &apos;90</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;90</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color Display in Ultrasonography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ultrasound in MedicineMdBiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Tool for Dynamic Explorations of Color Mappings</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Penny</forename><surname>Rheingans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brice</forename><surname>Tebbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compuhzr Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Color Gamuts : A User Interface for the Effective Use of Perceptual Color Spaces in Data Displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Philip</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applicatwns</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TheGenera-tionofColor Sequencesfor UnivariateandBivariateMapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Philip</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>O'callaghan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1986-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alvy</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Color Gamut Transform Pairs</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Theory for Coloring Bivariate Statistical Maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Trumbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bruce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Statistician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Empirical Inquiry Concerning Human Understanding of Two-Variable Color Maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Howard</forename><surname>Wainer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Carl</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Francolini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Statistician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color Sequencesfor UnivariateMaps :Theory, Experiments and Principles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Colin</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">4149</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
