<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Accurate Interactive Visualization of Large Deformations and Variability in Biomedical Image Ensembles</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Max</forename><surname>Hermann</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anja</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schunke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Reinhard</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Accurate Interactive Visualization of Large Deformations and Variability in Biomedical Image Ensembles</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467198</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Statistical deformation model</term>
					<term>stationary velocity fields</term>
					<term>image warping</term>
					<term>interactive visual analysis</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Fig. 1. Interactive visual reconstruction of two rodent mandible anatomies using previous (linear) and proposed SVF approach. Linear reconstruction fails at A-C w.r.t. global structures while, even more severe for interpretation, at D-F artifacts that resemble anatomical features are introduced. Both kinds of error are remedied by our approach, decreasing the RMSE by about a factor of 2 on average.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Only recently the potential of interactive visual analysis for understanding anatomic variability by interpolating shapes or images has been recognized <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. In these works, the visualization itself becomes an analytical tool enabling targeted inspection of different aspects of variability. Navigating the space spanned by an ensemble of anatomies via interpolation serves as an initial exploration vehicle before applying quantitative analysis, e.g. for feature selection or hypothesis generation.</p><p>To this end non-linear deformations are quintessential that describe the morphological differences in a biomedical image ensemble. An intuitive and widely used visualization of these differences (and the induced variability) is achieved by interpolation. Unfortunately, inter- <ref type="bibr">Hermann</ref> polation between 3D images at a high quality requires computationally expensive algorithms. Therefore, to be sufficiently fast, previous interactive applications resort to a heuristic <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> whose error grows quadratically with deformation magnitude. A severe drawback of this heuristic is that it produces visual artifacts that unfortunately are similar to plausible anatomical structures. This impedes the interpretation and the usefulness of the visual analysis to a great extent as is confirmed by a morphometric expert we collaborated with. <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> shows a typical example. The key to accurately represent large deformations as well as avoid mentioned artifacts is a non-linear deformation model. Inspired by the great success of diffeomorphic transformations in computational anatomy, in this paper we describe a fast and accurate image warping algorithm based on the theory of stationary velocity fields (SVF) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, tailored for interactive visualizations. The SVF based approach has shown to successfully model variability of anatomies as different as human brain <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref> and femur bone <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, but so far it has not been applied in an interactive application. A huge benefit is that it provides a sound tangent space, the log-domain, for the group of diffeomorphisms whose elements are lifted onto the non-linear group structure by simple integration. This does not only allow us to trivially carry over classical, linear shape statistics, but also extends the design space of visual analysis methods. In particular, the below presented tech-  niques take advantage of the following properties, not available in any previous interactive system: 1) linear combinations of deformations are robust to evaluate and artifact free, 2) stable extrapolation is possible as well and 3) for each deformation an inverse mapping exists and its computation comes at no extra cost. The last property is pivotal for fast and accurate image warping, while the conceptual importance of the first two properties is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">• M.</formula><p>A great motivation for our research is rooted in the emerging application area of population imaging <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, where large deformations are inherent. Recent advances in image registration now permit the creation of detailed models for inter-subject and population studies and we expect to see many more of these in the future. We designed our methods with the complexity of such studies in mind, leading to tools for rapid investigation of complex shape variation in dependence of various influencing factors. To that effect the high degree of image detail in our visualizations nicely complements the elaborate integrated visual analysis pipeline of existing approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Overview and contributions</head><p>To the best of the authors' knowledge, the presented methods comprise the first interactive system for visual analysis of a non-linear volumetric deformation model. The work at hand is split into two parts. The first part introduces our novel image warping method and showcases four visualizations taking explicit advantage of the SVF model (Sec. 3). One novel and three established techniques are described, adapted and extended in several ways to perform interactive visual analysis of shape variability:</p><p>• Group browsing is a novel technique to render mean shapes of subgroups of the ensemble, that are interactively selected to facilitate comparison of shape difference between different classes related to extrinsic factors.</p><p>• Volumetric reformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref> enables investigation of variation on complex morphologies in a single view.</p><p>• Likelihood volumes <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref> display the probability of shape variation along principal modes for an overview.</p><p>• Projected streamlines visualize details of shape variation, paying special attention to its component tangential to a surface.</p><p>The picked visualizations are not exhaustive, but each highlights one of the new design possibilities gained through using the SVF model.</p><p>Using the methods in combination allows us to perform visual analysis of shape ensembles containing large deformations. This is demonstrated on two datasets of rodent skull anatomy, investigating influence of phylogeny, diet and geography on shape (Sec. 5).</p><p>The second part of this work is devoted to an in depth evaluation of the introduced methods (Sec. 4). A thorough benchmark on a real world dataset confirms that in fact a higher visual quality is achieved. Furthermore, a detailed comparison substantiates that artifacts of the linear method are actually remedied.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK AND PRELIMINARIES 2.1 Preliminaries</head><p>Throughout the paper we will treat an image I as a scalar function I : Ω → R representing intensity over a compact domain Ω ⊂ R 3 , that is discretized via regular sampling. In case of CT data, intensity maps to Hounsfield units measuring x-ray density, from which bone anatomy can be classified.</p><p>A deformation of an image will be represented by a mapping ϕ : Ω → Ω. When analyzing several mappings, they all have to share the same source domain, which will be that of some template image I. Starting from I, each voxel is mapped forward to its corresponding position in another image I of the ensemble. This can be described via a displacement vector field u :</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Ω → R 3 as ϕ(x) = x + u(x).<label>(1)</label></formula><p>In order to avoid scattered data interpolation when computing a deformed image, an established procedure in image warping is to iterate over the target domain of I instead of the template parameterization as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Thereby, for each voxel in I a corresponding position in the templateĪ is found, where standard interpolation techniques can be applied. This is realized by the backward or inverse mapping ϕ −1 , i.e.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I(x)</head><formula xml:id="formula_2">= (I • ϕ −1 )(x) = I(ϕ −1 (x)).<label>(2)</label></formula><p>A heuristic to approximate ϕ −1 that is commonly used in interactive systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> is to simply negate the displacement field</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ϕ −1 (x) ≈ x − u(x).<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Note that the error of this heuristic grows quadratically with the (maximum) displacement magnitude <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. This makes it suitable only for very smooth and overall small deformations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Image registration with diffeomorphisms</head><p>Variation between two shapes can be understood as the difference in location between corresponding (homologous) points, which are usually unknown in the first place. For images, this difference is assessed using registration algorithms, establishing correspondences via transforming the image domain Ω via a non-linear mapping ϕ, superimposing one image onto the other. For a wide overview of current techniques we refer to the survey of Sotiras et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. In general, image registration is an ill-posed problem and a well defined solution is achieved by regularization, restricting the set of allowed transformations to the problem at hand <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. When no additional a-priori information is available, as in our case, choosing a set of diffeomorphisms are considered a "good working framework" <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. Because of their definition as smooth mappings with a smooth inverse they exhibit no singularities, i.e. no holes are created nor do folds occur and thus anatomy is kept intact. In fact, many successful image registration algorithms rely on the theory of large deformation diffeomorphic metric mapping (LDDMM) that is well established in computational anatomy <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref>, not only for registration, but also for statistics on deformation features; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> and references therein.</p><p>In the LDDMM framework a diffeomorphic mapping ϕ is constructed as a time-varying flow φ (x,t), x ∈ Ω, t ∈ [0, 1] with ϕ(x) = φ (x, 1). The flow is given as a solution to the transport equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">d dt φ (x,t) = w(φ (x,t),t)<label>(4)</label></formula><p>with initial condition φ (x, 0) = x, parameterized over vector fields w in the tangent space of the Riemannian manifold of diffeomorphisms. Integrating (4) over time yields the final mapping. This theory has turned out to be very powerful and versatile in many applications. However, computations based on time-varying flows are quite expensive and memory intensive and thus this setting is not suitable for interactive visual analysis. Fortunately, interesting alternatives using a stationary, i.e. time independent, parameterization are available <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref> that admit fast synthesis with low memory footprint, as is demonstrated here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Stationary velocity fields</head><p>Arsigny et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> propose a Log-Euclidean framework for diffeomorphisms in which Eq. (4) is treated using a stationary vector field</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">v(x) ≡ v(x,t)</formula><p>instead of a time-varying one,</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">d dt φ (x,t) = v(φ (x,t))<label>(5)</label></formula><p>with φ (x, 0) = x and the final mapping ϕ(x) = φ (x, 1) achieved by integration to time t = 1, as before. Interestingly, (5) covers (almost) the entire space of diffeomorphisms and is thereby deemed as expressive as (4), improving performance of registration algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref> and also proved successful in modeling the variability of a range of different anatomies <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref>. The term Log-Euclidean alludes to the fact that v is considered the logarithm of ϕ, and integration now takes the role of an exponential map of v <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Considering an analogy to the group of rotations SO(3) should give some intuition. There, the matrix logarithm provides a so called infinitesimal generator. Using generators, interpolation of rotations reduces to simple algebraic manipulation (component wise addition and scaling) of their logarithms, retrieving the final rotation via matrix exponential. In this spirit, the exponential of the vector field v defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">ϕ(x) = exp(v)(x) := φ (x, 1) = 1 0 v(φ (x,t)) dt<label>(6)</label></formula><p>will always produce a diffeomorphism. One can imagine that integrating (5) describes the trajectory of a particle traveling according to the velocity v prescribed at each location. So far, SVFs have not been used for interactive visualization. Amongst other things we show how existing systems, that work with displacements (1), can be extended to handle SVF's by simply integrating (6) in the rendering stage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Statistical deformation model</head><p>Let the shape ensemble be given by a set of images {I 1 ,...,I n }. For second order statistical analysis, the variability in the ensemble has to be described with respect to a mean shape. To this end a group wise registration is performed that estimates a template imageĪ together with a set of deformations {ϕ 1 ,...,ϕ n } that encode the difference between each individual and the template. Since position and attitude of shape structure in the image is arbitrary and uniform scale is not of interest in our study, those transformations are factored out beforehand by superimposing the images via similarity alignment. The resulting aligned images are denoted I i . <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref> shows an example. Alignment and registration are done to approximately match intensities I i (x) ≈ I(ϕ i (x)) for each individual i = 1,...,n such that the set {ϕ i } describes spatial variation. The purpose of a statistical deformation model is to provide a compact, linear representation of variation <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. This requires at some point a linearization of the group of deformations. The usual choice is to simply treat displacement fields linearly, i.e. ϕ a (x)</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">• ϕ b (x) ≈ x + u a (x) + u b (x) for ϕ X (x) = x + u X (x).</formula><p>Note that this is a reasonable approximation only for small deformations. Under this assumption, analysis of the vector field data {u i } can be reduced to multivariate statistics by treating each vector field as a long column vector u i ∈ R <ref type="bibr">3N</ref> where N denotes the number of voxels in the discretized image domain Ω. Using this notation, the first moment is the arithmetic average u = 1 n ∑ n i=1 u i and the second moment is given as 3N × 3N sample covariance matrix <ref type="bibr">T</ref> . To ease interpretation of S, a principal component analysis (PCA) is applied that provides a decorrelated basis B for the vector field data, i.e. in this basis the covariance matrix becomes unit diagonal, and u i = Bc i for i = 1,...,n. The coefficient vectors c i give the coordinates of each sample u i in PCA space. Note that there exist only n = dim(S) &lt; n 3N many basis vectors and c i ∈ R n . The n pairwise orthogonal columns of B are ordered descending according to their variances σ <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> i , given by their length. Each column represents a deformation encoded as displacement vector field and is also termed mode of (shape) variation. The modes provide a generative model of shape variability</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">S = 1 n−1 ∑ n i=1 (u i − u)(u i − u)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">u = Bc with p(c) = (2π) −n /2 e − 1 2 c 2 .<label>(7)</label></formula><p>From this, novel shapes can be synthesized for visualization. The model considers coefficients c as random variable that follow a centered normal distribution of unit variance. In Sec. 3 we will use the log-domain as an alternative linearization that renders multivariate analyses like PCA to be consistent with the group properties of diffeomorphisms and thereby also suitable for large deformations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Visualization of image deformations</head><p>Several GPU raycasting methods have been proposed to render deformed images <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>, all based on the paradigm of direct space warping <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. The general idea is to not trace straight rays through a deformed image, but rather deform the traced rays via the inverse deformation, reading the intensity information from the original, undeformed image. In that way, the rendering will display the correctly deformed image, while the image data itself stays unchanged in memory and interpolation capabilities of graphics hardware can be exploited. Based on this technique, Kurzion and Yagel <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> propose a set of analytical, invertible local mappings which can be combined to achieve volumetric deformations. A fast implementation for texture based volume rendering was introduced by Rezk-Salama et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, deforming a coarser proxy geometry gained by subdivision of the volume into piecewise linear patches with subsequent interpolation. In Brunet et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> a modern, single pass raycasting solution is devised to enable interactive image manipulation via freely movable control points. The costly computation of the inverse mapping is deferred in their approach to the CPU and thus does not scale to complex deformation models. More similar to our approach, Correa et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> derive a deformation by linearly combining (inverse) displacement maps, well designed to enable illustrative volume rendering by introducing cuts <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. However, the algorithm they describe can only combine two such maps on the GPU. Our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> is most closely related, because it also synthesizes deformations from a PCA model on the GPU. Unfortunately, it is based on a linear model that limits applicability to small deformations.</p><p>Caban et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> presented a comprehensive review of visualization techniques for statistical deformation models and also introduced likelihood volumes, that are integrated into our interactive system in Sec. 3.6. Kindlmann et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> applied superquadric glyphs to visualize anatomic covariance in a very concise way. This technique is ideal for an overview but does not give access to individual modes of variation and navigation techniques as presented in the work at hand.</p><p>Another class of approaches is based on visualizing deformation properties derived from a displacement vector field. These in-clude color-coding the determinant of the Jacobian <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>, revealing growth and atrophy, or displaying critical points <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. On top of this, our ODE approach admits further flow visualization techniques like streamline integration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">VISUAL ANALYSIS METHODS 3.1 A log-domain approach</head><p>The basis of our work is, that we do not consider displacement vector fields to capture shape variation, but choose a SVF representation ϕ = exp(v) instead. A key advantage of this approach is that the log-domain, where velocity fields live, offers a natural linearization</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ϕ a • ϕ b = exp(v a ) • exp(v b ) = exp(v a + v b )</formula><p>that is lifted to the diffeomorphic group structure by integration. As a consequence, the exact inverse mapping is found by simply integrating −v, i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">ϕ −1 (x) = exp(−v)(x).<label>(8)</label></formula><p>We also take advantage of the robust extrapolation possible in the SVF model. Considering an arbitrary deformation given as velocity field v, an extrapolation is achieved by evaluating exp(λ v) for a scale factor λ &gt; 1, resulting in an exaggerated deformation that can be used for caricaturistic visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Non-linear SVF model and its navigation</head><p>An overview of the processing pipeline is given in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>. Similar to previous work, we use a group wise image registration to estimate a template imageĪ and a set of deformations. But this time, the latter are given in terms of velocity fields {v i } such that ϕ i (x) = exp(v i ) describe non-linear trajectories from the template to each individual anatomy. During registration, the templateĪ is estimated so that the set of velocity fields is centered in log-domain, i.e.v = 1 n ∑ n i=1 v i = 0. When computing the template image, all images of the ensemble are deformed into the template domain and their intensities are averaged</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">I = 1 n n ∑ i=1 I i • exp(v i ).<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Individual images I i can thus be reconstructed from the template as</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">I i ≈Ī • exp(−v i ).<label>(10)</label></formula><p>Exploiting the linearity in log-domain, the same linear PCA statistics as described in Sec. 2.4 can be applied on the set {v i }, resulting in a generative model vĉ =Bĉ (11) with a basisB of principal velocities. Shape variability is explored by synthesis of novel deformations from this model by choosing a coefficient vectorĉ and integratingφ = exp(Bĉ). For visualization the template image is warped according toφ −1 and displayed. Interpolation along a specific directionĉ in PCA space can be shown in an animation, for instance to inspect a particular mode as illustrated in <ref type="figure">Fig.</ref> 14. Alternative visualizations to this include the below presented likelihood volumes and projected streamlines.</p><p>Previous navigation strategies based on choosingĉ can directly be applied to the SVF model as well. A very common way to assess principal modes of variation is to interpolate a single entry inĉ over the range [−3, +3] <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. Another technique applies a support vector machine to identify a directionĉ in PCA space, that describes the shape difference between two classes of the dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, and interpolate along this direction. Recently, a technique for analysis of covariation between structures on the same shape was introduced <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. There, the user prescribes a local shape deformation manually and the most likely coefficient setĉ according to the model is computed, revealing correlated shape changes. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Browsing group mean shapes</head><p>A common task for exploratory analysis is to disentangle the factors that determine shape variation. Categorical factors decompose the shape ensemble into subsets, for instance into several phylogenetic or dietary groups as in our mouse mandible ensemble. In order to unveil the impact of each factor on shape variation, we derive mean shapes of the corresponding subsets, enabling interpolation in-between group means and the ensemble template. This way it is possible to investigate the difference between particular groups defined by their associated factor while considering their distinctiveness within the shape ensemble by comparison to the template. Precomputing mean shapes of all possible (in the worst case exponentially many) subsets is not practical and thus we opt for an online computation, allowing the user to flexibly define groups on the fly. An example of browsing group means, in combination with extrapolation, is given in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>.</p><p>We define a group meanĪ G for a particular subset G ⊆ {1,...,n} of the ensemble in the same way as the templateĪ for all individuals. The characteristic property of a group mean is that it has on average a zero deformation to all other images in its group, like a barycenter of mass points. We thus have to find a set of velocity fields {v i } i∈G that is centered and mapsĪ G to each group individual I i∈G . This is achieved by subtracting the (non-zero) averagē</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">v G = 1 |G| ∑ i∈G v i (12) from the available v i , leading to v i = v i −v G .</formula><p>It is easily confirmed that the average of v i∈G is zero. From this centered set of velocity fields we can now define the group mean similar to (9) as</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">I G = 1 |G| ∑ i∈G I i • exp(v i −v G ).<label>(13)</label></formula><p>Unfortunately, a naïve evaluation ofĪ G would require |G| image warps, which is not feasible for interactive exploration. However, by sacrificing the correct intensity average of the group (but not its shape!) a more efficient computation can be devised. To this end we replace each individual image I i occuring in (13) by its reconstruction (10), leading to the following approximation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">I G ≈ 1 |G| ∑ i∈GĪ • exp(−v i ) • exp(v i −v G ) = 1 |G| ∑ i∈GĪ • exp(−v G ) =Ī • exp(−v G )</formula><p>With that we arrive at an estimate for the group mean that requires only a single image warp based on the velocity fieldv G . Note that here the expensive multiple image warps of (13) are exchanged with a simple arithmetic average over velocity fields included in the group G, providing a deformation that is subsequently removed from the ensemble templateĪ via a single integration of the sum given in (12). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Volumetric reformation</head><p>Instead of showing anatomical structures in their original spatial configuration, in a reformation the shape is purposefully deformed to aid interpretation. A classical example is curved planar reformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> where tubular structures, like blood vessels and colon, are "unrolled" by resampling the input image onto curved planes following the centerline of the particular structure. The thus reformed image provides a more concise visualization and minimizes camera interaction. In our work we do not use planar but volumetric reformation targeting the same goal. Inspired by the work of Kretschmer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> our reformation approach is based on local, volumetric deformations of structures of interest. But instead of using an as-rigid-as-possible deformation model like they do, we derive velocity fields for local transformations, that are blended. In spirit, this is very similar to the original approach by von Funck et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> for mesh editing based on integration of divergence-free vector fields. The application we demonstrate is to reform a complex anatomy such that otherwise occluded structures become visible and can be investigated in a single view. This particularly reduces cognitive load in dynamic displays of shape variability, where one can stay focused on the information encoded in the animation without having to adjust camera or synchronize (mentally) between multiple views. See Figs. 6 and 14 for an example. Since the reformation should be applicable in combination with our other visualizations, we will represent it via a SVF that can be added to any further deformation. To this end an arbitrary diffeomorphic transformation can be deduced via the scaling and squaring method <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> or, more efficiently, we could make use of a polyaffine deformation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. In order to preserve spatial context, we restrict ourself in this showcase to stiff transformations and choose to setup our reformation from local rotations in a region of interest (ROI). Consider that a rotation of angle θ &lt; π around an arbitrary axis is given as a 3 × 3 matrix R together with its center of rotation x pivot ∈ R 3 . In order to incorporate this transformation into the integration (5) we take the matrix logarithm L = log(R), yielding an anti-symmetric matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, commensurate with the log-domain representation. With that, the velocity field of the local rotation is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">v rot (x) = w(x)L(x − x pivot )<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where w : Ω → [0, 1] is a weighting function that smoothly interpolates between w(x) = 1 inside the ROI, and w(x) = 0 outside of it. In the resulting deformation the ROI is rotated, while w ascertains a continuous transition between the rotated ROI and the non-rotated remainder of the volume. Note that eventually the rotation v rot is added to a deformation v for combined visualization.</p><p>Simple and efficient choices of ROI weights w include spheres and bounding boxes. For these geometries the weights can be trivially parameterized over 1D functions, either based on the distance to the rotation center or to the planes of the box. Let t in and t out denote the distance range for the transition between inside and outside of the ROI, for instance 0 &lt; t in &lt; t out ≤ r for a spherical ROI with radius r. For smooth interpolation a standard cubic function is used, i.e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">w 1D (t) = 1 − t − t in t out − t in 2 3 − 2 t − t in t out − t in for t in ≤ t ≤ t out</formula><p>while weights interior t &lt; t in are set to 1 and exterior t &gt; t out to 0. The choice of t in and t out controls the extent of the transition area. Its particular choice is a trade off between global and local spatial context. Choosing a large area increases smoothness of the transition, providing global context, but disturbs local structures, since angle and volume preservation are abandoned in the transition area. In our experience, the choice depends on the complexity of the structure. For a structure exhibiting local variations, like for instance the ear bulla of a mouse skull, a sharper transition is advised than for reforming structures with large scale variation, like the incisor of the mouse skull. A complex volumetric reformation is realized by adding several user specified rotations and their ROIs as in Eq. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>. For m such rotations {v </p><formula xml:id="formula_20">(1) rot ,...,v</formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">rot + ••• + v (m) rot .<label>(15)</label></formula><p>After choosing axis and center for a single rotation, the rotation angle can be tuned by just scaling the logarithm L → λ L where λ ∈ R controls the interpolation from no rotation (λ = 0) to the specified rotation (λ = 1) and can even be extrapolated (λ &gt; 1) or inverted (λ &lt; 0) robustly. Together with the presented raycasting procedure, this facilitates a user interface for interactive volume editing, where every aspect of the reformation is adjustable in realtime. Interestingly, being able to interpolate from normal to reformed anatomy turned out to be quite useful in establishing ("learning") the mental mapping between the two, which is essential to interpret this kind of visualization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Projected streamlines</head><p>A natural new opportunity for analysis of variation arises from the chosen representation (5) of deformations as ODE, for which a rich set of vector field and flow visualizations are available. A particular method, nicely displaying the now curved trajectories, is streamline integration, that can readily be applied to our data and has been already used for static illustration of SVFs <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. In order to convey specifically the surface parallel component of shape variation, we describe an extension of streamline integration that computes a projection onto an isosurface of the template. Displaying tangential variation in this way provides an advantage over direct visualization of a deforming shape that is affected by the aperture problem, i.e. that motion can only be perceived in direction perpendicular to contours. An example of our final visualization is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 7</ref>. Streamlines are generated by evaluating the integration of a velocity field at a monotone sequence of time points t 1 &lt; ... &lt; t k resulting in a trajectory of positions x 1 ,...,x k , that are connected with lines for final display. The projection of the streamline onto an isosurface S is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 8</ref>. We assume that the seed point x 1 already lies on the surface. For each subsequent point x i , i &gt; 1 on the original trajectory a projected point x i lying on the surface S has to be found. We found a projection via gradient descent to be unstable on our CT images, because intensity variation outside the anatomy is not smooth and contains singularities. Therefore we propose a more robust two step procedure. In the first step, x i is projected onto the tangent plane of its (projected) predecessor, defined by the normal at x i−1 . This yields an intermediate point x , already closer to S, but still an unsatisfying approximation in areas with local curvature. Therefore, in the second step, a normal direction n is estimated and a Newton iteration on the intensity function along −n is executed to find x i as the closest point on S. Normal estimation n = ∇I(x )/ ∇I(x ) is stabilized in the vicinity of S by operating on a prefiltered (smoothed) image. Let S be defined by the isovalue γ, then a Newton iteration on f (α) = I(x i + αn i ) can be formalized as</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">α n+1 = α n − f (α n ) − γ f (α n ) .</formula><p>It will eventually end up in a zero-crossing converging after say l steps, defining the projected point x i = x i + α l n i . In our implementation we choose a fixed number of l = 10 steps to avoid conditional branching in the shader program. In the example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 7</ref> seed points are chosen uniformly sampled over a mesh, corresponding to an outer isosurface of the template. Projection is done onto a surface with slightly lower isovalue, resulting in a small offset of the trajectories from the rendered mesh surface, enhancing visibility. Streamlines are color coded according to integration time, while the projection is shown in a desaturated gradient, evoking the impression of a shadow. Note that the projection remains visible also in areas where streamlines penetrate the surface and get occluded. This is a desirable feature when investigating the tangential component of shape variation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Likelihood volumes</head><p>Likelihood volumes were previously used by Jiao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> to visualize uncertainty of orientation distribution functions in HARDI. Caban et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> introduced a similar technique to display the probabilistic properties of a shape ensemble in a single, static visualization. To this end they sample images according to the probability density of the PCA model and integrate them in a single volume. More precisely, their likelihood volume counts for each voxel how many times it was covered by the deformed anatomy, classified by thresholding the sample images. The result of a direct volume rendering of this is reminiscent of a motion blurred picture, where areas of higher shape variability appear smoothed out. While the original likelihood volume is precomputed once offline, our SVF model allows an online evaluation. This enables to interactively derive displays of variability in user chosen subspaces of the PCA model. <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref> displays for instance the principal modes of variation for an overview.</p><p>In order to derive a likelihood volume, we synthesize a discrete sample of k velocity fields from our model along a particular direction c, c = 1 in PCA space and average the correspondingly warped images. For a uniform sampling γ 1 ,...,γ k of the domain [−3, 3], covering three times standard deviation, this yields a likelihood image</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">I likelihood = 1 k k ∑ i=1Ī</formula><p>• exp(γ i Bc). <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> Considering that the integration exp() dominates GPU runtime, k should be small, especially for non sparse coefficient sets that require additional texture lookups in computing Bc d . In our experiments already a minimal sampling using k = 6 produced informative summaries at interactive framerates, without requiring any preprocessing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7">Implementation and workflow</head><p>Each described visual analysis method prescribes a different velocity field v, based on user input. But instead of being restricted to deploy one method at a time, the log-domain representation enables seamless integration of several methods at once by simply adding their corresponding velocities. In this way, algorithm 1 comprises either PCA navigation or group browsing, both combined with a reformation that is specified in advance; likelhood volumes are treated separately via <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_24">x = ϕ −1 (x) = exp(−v f used )(x).</formula><p>The remaining implementation is that of a standard raycaster for direct volume rendering, with the only difference that instead of reading intensity information fromĪ(x) it is now read fromĪ(x ). We use a single pass fragment shader implementation, similar to Brunet et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Vertex displacement. An alternative to the described direct space warping in volume rendering is to apply the forward deformation ϕ(x) = exp(v f used )(x) on 3D point samples x, either representing vertices of a precomputed isosurface mesh or seed points for streamline integration. This can be efficiently realized by implementing algorithm 1 and numerical integration in a geometry shader, either displacing mesh vertices resulting in a deformed surface, or outputting a line strip connecting intermediate positions of the integration, resulting in a streamline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">EVALUATION</head><p>In order to assess visual quality of SVF and linear approach we consider PCA reconstruction results of the mouse mandible dataset, because these represent real shapes with known anatomical structure, aiding the discussion. Since direct space warping is employed, final renderings have to be compared. We benchmark on four different views, that are typical choices in exploration and expose variation in several directions. A baseline is created for each specimen using a high quality image warping algorithm in advance, that is subsequently rendered with exactly the same raycaster and transfer function as the online reconstruction. The error of a particular rendering is measured as intensity difference to the baseline, accumulated over all views. The root mean square error (RMSE) is calculated over renderings of size 512×512, yielding a single number measuring the overall visual quality, with higher values indicating stronger deviations from the baseline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Visual quality</head><p>A summary of our benchmarks is given in <ref type="figure">Fig. 10</ref>, comparing different SVF integration methods to solve <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> against the heuristic inverse (3) of the linear model. The selected integration methods all provide interactive performance; see Sec. 4.3. Apparently the Runge-Kutta 4 scheme with two steps (RK4-2) produces the best results while the linear method performs worst. Choosing more steps and/or a higher order scheme than RK4-2 does not lead to a noticeable increase in quality, probably because of the used quantization; see Sec. 6. Overall one can observe that increase in error in dependence of the deformation magnitude has a substantially lower slope for RK4-2 than for the linear method, leading to the assumption that also datasets with even larger deformations than the chosen one can be treated with the proposed method. Notably a single Euler step outperforms the linear method, even though both have identical computational complexity.</p><p>Discussion of artifacts Detailed examples of the benchmark are shown for Mer-Ger and Pachyuromys in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> and Oxy-Sca and Deo- <ref type="figure">Fig. 11</ref>. Additional examples of apparent anatomical artifacts produced by the linear method that are successfully resolved in the proposed SVF approach. Heat maps tell the absolute 8-bit intensity difference to the baseline, inset numbers denote RMSE. <ref type="figure">Fig. 11</ref>. On a first glance the figures illustrate that both, linear and SVF method, produce renderings matching the baseline at coarse scale, although the RMSE shows about a factor of 2 increased quality of the SVF over the linear method. Closer examination in the areas of higher local error in the linear reconstruction reveals apparent anatomical differences in the depiction. We can distinguish between two typical kinds of errors in the linear approach. In <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> at locations B and C approximation errors are visible prominently on contours of shape structures, that do not match the ones of the baseline. This can partly be attributed to the errors accumulated in the linear combination of the displacement fields in the PCA reconstruction, similar to the motivating example in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 2</ref>, and partly to the approximation error of the heuristic inverse. Another, even more severe class of error occurs in areas of locally varying deformation, as shown in the closeups at locations D-F in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> and in additional examples in <ref type="figure">Fig.11</ref>. In such less smooth areas of the deformation the heuristic inverse produces severe artifacts that, although locally confined, unfortunately resemble plausible (but non-existent) anatomical structure, as confirmed by the morphometric expert of our team. One could say that the linear method "hallucinates" virtual anatomical structures that render any analysis based on this visualization at least uncertain. Even datasets not exhibiting strong, global deformation may still feature locally varying changes, that lead to the second class of errors when rendered using the linear approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ura in</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Comparison of PCA spaces</head><p>By replacing the usually employed displacement vector fields with velocity fields in statistical analysis, the impact on the particular PCA space is of interest. In general, different PCA spaces are not compatible, but nevertheless we can observe that in our case the PC coordinates of both models are very close, as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12</ref>. This of course results from the fact, that both inputs, displacement and velocity fields, encode the same deformation. Actually the displacements are gained by integrating the corresponding velocity field. Conse- quently it is not surprising that the principal modes of variation match each other closely. In a scatter plot matrix, the greatest difference is visible in mode pair PC4/5, that is explainable by very close eigenvalues leading to a rotation, as shown in the inset in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12(b)</ref>. Overall, the two models differ only marginally in their PCA spaces, but much more in their visualization of synthesis results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Performance</head><p>Since we aim at an interactive system, performance is obviously a critical point. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 13</ref> shows an evaluation in this regard for navigating the PCA shape model. Because integrating a linear combination of principal modes requires many texture lookups, the navigation scenario is a computationally representative test case. The diagram shows that even in the worst case, all integration methods (taking always two steps in this evaluation) provide interactive performance at a minimum of 4 frames per second (FPS). In order to achieve higher framerates during user interaction and animation, for instance when manipulating coefficients or adjusting camera, we switch in this situations to a preview rendering at a lower resolution of 256×256. Please note that the just described worst case behaviors only occur when considering all modes of our dataset at once. For many relevant application scenarios much fewer modes are sufficient, because most of the variability is concentrated on few modes, e.g. in the rodent mandible dataset 90% of variability is explained by the first six modes. In some situations, when dealing with moderate variations, the Midpoint scheme is an acceptable trade off between efficiency and quality. The dominating factor on performance is the number of integrations (with according texture lookups) executed per fragment, illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 13</ref> on the right hand side. A potential optimization would be to avoid tracing most of the empty space by replacing the currently used very coarse bounding box by a much tighter bounding geometry, say a precomputed isosurface mesh of the template, that is warped very efficiently in the geometry shader as described in Sec. 3.7.</p><p>All tests were undertaken on a GeForce GTX 780 graphics card, rendering to a framebuffer texture of size 512×512, averaging FPS over 10 seconds for each integrator / number of modes combination to reduce CPU and operating system side effects, limited at 50Hz marking realtime performance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CASE STUDY: VISUAL ANALYSIS OF RODENT ANATOMY</head><p>In order to evaluate the usefulness of the presented visual analysis methods, a small case study was performed with a morphometric expert of our team. In advance, two ensembles of rodent anatomy were chosen, both with extrinsic factors with partly known and partly unknown impact on shape. One is a set of mandibles, a morphologically relatively simple structure, from diverse rodents, e.g. old and new world mice, gerbils etc., displaying a great variability based on different degrees of relationships and diet types. The other comprises a set of skulls from a single species, with the skull having a considerably larger complexity than the mandible. The two ensembles were analyzed in two separate sessions of each about 30 minutes, not including time for explaining the visualizations and user interface. Overall, the visualization used most of the time was to navigate single modes of variation. This is not surprising since it comes closest to the usually employed static illustrations of mode extrema. In comparison, the dynamic visualization was described to provide a "better understanding" in the sense that the particular variation becomes more obvious, especially for smaller structures. For the mandible ensemble, most of the time was spent browsing group means, which was directly accessible to the expert, who appreciated that groups could be defined interactively and used this feature intensively. A small hindrance was that group selection required to manually look up additional information on phylogeny. A linked view showing a taxonomy tree for interactive selection would provide a more intuitive browsing interface, but is outside the scope of our present work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Inspection of skull ensemble</head><p>For exploration of the skull ensemble, no hypotheses were assumed apriori, and only PCA navigation was employed, illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 14</ref>. The first mode was quickly related to shape variation due to size (allometry), observing the typical difference in proportions between extent of brain case and length of snout, i.e. larger brain case and shorter snout for smaller specimen and vice versa. Further exploration revealed eventually a geographic signal in third and fourth mode, after switching back-and-forth between different modes. In advance of the session, the anatomic reformation was shown to the expert who found especially the animated interpolation between normal and reformed anatomy helpful to understand how to read the latter. The reformed view was mostly used for overview, for instance to decide upon which structures to consider for further inspection. It served well to detect presence of variation at relevant structures like the two ear bullae, that otherwise would have required at least two different camera views. For final inspection an unreformed view was preferred, providing the correct morphological context required for interpretation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Analysis of mandible ensemble</head><p>The aim of the mandible case study was to verify if known hypotheses about impact of diet and phylogeny could also be observed in our volumetric model, which could actually be confirmed by browsing group means as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>. Differences in the respective signals are clearly visible for the two phylogenetic groups. While the Gerbillinae (Phylo 1) are known to have a unique manidble morphology (see also <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 12(a)</ref>, Mer-Ger and Pachyuromys) and thus display a stronger phylogenetic signal (greater similarity along the row), the second group (Phylo 2) shows a stronger dietary signal (stronger similarity along the columns). Between carni-and omnivore group mean, one can see the characteristic difference in height of the central structure, potentially attributed to different mechanical demands in chewing different kinds of food. At the beginning of the session likelihood volumes as in <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref> were shown as overview. Even though not being accustomed to this kind of visualization, the expert could directly relate to it, and discovered an interesting correlation at the three rear processes in PC2, closely related to the dietary signal. While the overview does not inform on the direction of the observed correlation, this becomes apparent when displaying streamlines as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 7</ref>. Noteworthy, the expert recognized candidate regions for morphological modules <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>, delineated by areas of different flow characteristics in tangential variation. This is a promising insight that awaits further investigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Datasets and pre-processing</head><p>Preprocessing of both CT ensembles consisted of an automatic segmentation, separating skull and mandibles <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>, followed by a custom group wise image registration based on intensity-based similarity alignment <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and symmetric log-domain diffeomorphic demons <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> resulting in velocity fields and a template image. All images were resampled to 200 2 ×400 isotropic voxels.</p><p>The rodent mandible dataset is compiled from 48 specimen in order to investigate and compare influence of diet and phylogeny (on a genus level) on mandible shape. To alleviate a bias due to different number of samples in the phylogenetic groups, one representative mandible is considered per genus, averaged over all of its specimens. Left and right mandible of each specimen were averaged in advance to remove asymmetric effects. Eventually, 16 representatives are analyzed, 8 omnivorous and 8 carnivorous. The closest omni-and carnivore relatives supply 8 diet/genus pairs. The skull ensemble consists of 22 specimens of the species Apodemus flavicollis, sampled throughout Europe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">DISCUSSION</head><p>Limitations. Two main limitations of the presented approach arise with respect to scalability and representation of discontinuous mappings. Sec. 4.3 shows that our current implementation stays interactive when combining up to 15 velocity fields during integration. The factor limiting GPU performance here are the number of texture lookups involved. To circumvent this bottleneck, additional strategies are required; for instance based on a multi-pass approach or sets of precomputed sums. GPU memory can become another limiting factor in the view of large population studies that cover several hundred individuals. However, thanks to smoothness of velocity fields and lower dynamic range compared to displacements, downsampling in resolution and quantization can be effectively applied to reduce memory consumption. In our experiments velocity fields were reduced from 200 2 ×400 at 32-bit (183MB/field) to 100 2 ×200 at 8-bit (6MB/field) without significant loss in quality. Still, further investigation of optimal interpolation schemes for downsampling and additional compression methods is appropriate. For compression it should be possible to exploit the fact that most of the ensemble variance is concentrated on a few principal modes, irregardless of sample size. A limitation inherent to the SVF approach is that it can not model discontinuous mappings nor changes in topology. For that purpose a combination of our approach with the discontinuity maps of Correa et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> seems a promising endeavor.</p><p>Future directions. The presented work provides a starting point for interactive analysis of shape variation in presence of large deformations. So far the focus was on efficient synthesis of deformed images and the shown visualizations are prototypical and can be improved in many regards. Subject to future work are custom-tailored adaptions that guide the user to deformations of interest and convey specific local aspects of variability. A related issue in this regard is to assess model quality. To this end it is planned to enhance the presented visualizations to explicitly take registration uncertainty into account. For instance, the streamline visualization could help to uncover tangential drift that indicates a suboptimal group wise registration result <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Another aspect not considered in this work is that variation occurs at different scales. In this regard it would be interesting to see our methods extended to the hierarchical polyaffine model of Seiler et. al <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Due to the complexity inherent in such a hierarchy, interactive displays of variability at multiple scales provide an ideal exploration vehicle.</p><p>For group browsing an efficient computation of group averages has been devised. It is yet unclear how this procedure can be generalized to also estimate group covariances on the fly; that would allow to interactively browse complete PCA spaces of each and every group.</p><p>We also see potential applications of our work beyond shape analysis. For instance, image registration algorithms could be monitored during runtime using our fast image warping method, enabling debug visualizations for parameter tuning in the spirit of Registra-tionShop <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, adding diffeomorphisms to its class of transformations. Concerning 3D modeling it would be interesting to see if the easy and efficient modeling of weighted local rotations, used in our reformation technique, does provide benefits for interactive editing of 3D volumes <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref> and meshes <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this work we presented an efficient algorithm for 3D image warping in a GPU raycaster, applied to visualize statistical deformation models, based on the theory of stationary velocity fields. Albeit simple in implementation, it improves visual quality significantly compared to previous work, that relies on a linear model of displacements and a heuristic algorithm for image warping. In our approach, image warping is naturally combined with a non-linear deformation model of diffeomorphisms, linearized in log-domain via SVFs. We showed that this combination extends the design space for visual analysis of anatomic variability and introduced a novel technique for targeted browsing of subgroups of an ensemble in relation to extrinsic factors. A comparative study on rodent mandibles and a population study on mouse skulls, performed by a morphometrics expert of our team, attested the applicability of the presented methods.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Transforming a rectangular grid by a displacement field (top) and a velocity field (bottom) representing each a clockwise rotation R around θ = 60 • (center). Arrows indicate vector fields and deformation trajectories are shown in blue. Evaluating scaled versions of the vector fields demonstrate inter-and extrapolation. While displacements follow linear paths, resulting in shrinkage and expansion of the transformed grid, integrating in log-domain leads to curved trajectories that perfectly reproduce each expected rotation of 0.5θ = 30 • and 1.5θ = 90 • .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Superimposition of the rodent mandible ensemble consisting of 16 images aligned via similarity transforms. The display illustrates the shape variability investigated with the presented visualization methods.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Outline of processing pipeline.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Browsing mean shapes of different phylogenetic and dietary groups allows comparative analysis of the impact of these factors onto anatomy. The template is highlighted. Note that dietary mean shapes, shown in color, are extrapolated to emphasize difference (see video).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Volumetric reformation of five regions on a mouse skull to assess otherwise occluded structures in a single view. Efficient image warping enables realtime manipulation and simultaneous browsing of PCA space (seeFig. 14). Top: Isosurface and DVR rendering from top view without and with reformation. Bottom: Alternate views.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Streamline visualization of PC2. Shown are the mean shape in blue, a displaced version in yellow and streamlines color-coded according to integration time [t 0 ,t max ]. Top: t max = 1.5 and t max = 3.0 respectively. Bottom: Projection onto mean shape (grayscale) provides additional information about the tangential component of shape variation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>rot } the final reformation velocity field reads v re f orm = v<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Streamline projection onto an isosurface (see text for details).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .Fig. 10 .</head><label>910</label><figDesc>Likelihood visualization. The motion of a particular variation mode over[−3σ , +3σ  ] is accumulated in a single likelihood volume, color coded from blue to yellow. Top: Direct volume rendering of likelihood function. Bottom: Alternative visualization that provides context via contour lines and isosurface. The transfer function is adjusted to bi-partition areas of low (yellow) and high (blue) variability more clearly. Evaluation of visual quality between linear and SVF model using different integration schemes. (See text for details.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Comparison between PCA spaces for SVFs and linear displacement fields shows only a marginal difference for rodent mandible dataset. (a) Scatter plot of first two modes, where same shapes in both models are connected by a line and the region covering two standard deviations is marked. (b) Difference measured as rotation angle between PC basis pairs. The average rotation angle of 3.04 • reflects high agreement. Inset scatter plot shows PC pair with greatest discrepancy.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Rendering performance for quality and preview framebuffer size, plotted against number of terms in linear combination (measurement limited at 50Hz). Heat map shows number of integrations per pixel.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 14 .</head><label>14</label><figDesc>Browsing PCA shape space. Columns show the mean shape (center) deformed according to the principal mode of variation (PC1) synthesized for different standard deviations σ 1 . Color coded is deformation strength perpendicular to the surface where blue/red indicates shrinkage/expansion. Note that reformation and PCA synthesis are applied simultaneously, while only the latter is color coded. (a) Reformed anatomy, (b) original anatomy, (c) alternate view on original anatomy.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Manuscript received 31 Mar. 2015; accepted 1 Aug. 2015; date of publication 20 Aug. 2015; date of current version 25 Oct. 2015. For information on obtaining reprints of this article, please send e-mail to: tvcg@computer.org. Digital Object Identifier no. 10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467198</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>For direct volume rendering backward integration is performed during raycasting at each sample position x along a ray, resulting in a displaced position</figDesc><table /><note>. Navigation in shape space is facilitated by choosing a direc- tionĉ using one of the methods from Sec. 3.2 or interactive selection of a group G. The corresponding animation is controlled via a scalar parameter λ , mapped for instance to a GUI slider. On camera or pa- rameter change, a deformation is computed via numerical integration of velocities v f used , as detailed next. The impact of different integra- tion schemes on quality and performance are compared in Sec. 4.3. Algorithm 1 Linear fusion of velocity fields Input: Position x ∈ Ω. Output:Velocity v f used ∈ R 3 . 1. Evaluate reformation v re f orm at x via (15). 2. Evaluate v model at x by interpolating......using (11) along directionĉ in PCA space with λ ∈ [−3, 3]: v model = λBĉ ...using (12) betweenĪ and mean of group G with λ ∈ [0, 1]: v model = λv G 3. Return v f used = v re f orm + v model . Direct volume rendering.</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>This work was supported in part by Deutsche Forschungsgesellschaft within the priority program SPP1335. The authors thank Rainer Hutterer, Zoological Research Museum Alexander Koenig, Bonn, for loan of specimens and Krishna P. Soundararajan for image pre-processing.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fast and logeuclidean polyaffine framework for locally linear registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Arsigny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Commowick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayache</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Pennec</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Mathematical Imaging and Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A log-euclidean framework for statistics on diffeomorphisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Arsigny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Commowick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Pennec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayache</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. MICCAI&apos;06, Part I</title>
		<meeting>MICCAI&apos;06, Part I</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="924" to="931" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A fast diffeomorphic image registration algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ashburner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="113" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Neuroimage</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global and local deformations of solid primitives</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Barr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In ACM Siggraph Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computing large deformation metric mappings via geodesic flows of diffeomorphisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Beg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Trouvé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Younes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of computer vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contributions to 3d diffeomorphic atlas estimation: application to brain images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bossa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Olmos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. MICCAI&apos;07</title>
		<meeting>MICCAI&apos;07</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="667" to="674" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From individual to population: Challenges in medical visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Botha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ynnerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1206.1148v1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Scientific Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="282" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploded views for volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization &amp; Computer Graphics (TVCG)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1077" to="1084" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating dynamic deformations into interactive volume visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brunet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Eurographics/IEEE VGTC conference on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics/IEEE VGTC conference on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="226" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visualization of Variation and Variability</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Busking</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-12" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Delft University of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct visualization of deformation in volumes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Busking</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Botha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic multi-view exploration of shape spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Busking</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Botha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="973" to="982" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An evaluation of visualization techniques to illustrate statistical deformation models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Caban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rheingans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="821" to="830" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial transfer functions: a unified approach to specifying deformation in volume modeling and animation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Winter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cornea</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2003 Eurographics/IEEE TVCG Workshop on Volume graphics</title>
		<meeting>the 2003 Eurographics/IEEE TVCG Workshop on Volume graphics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="44" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Programmable shaders for deformation rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Correa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM Siggraph/Eurographics symposium on Graphics hardware</title>
		<meeting>ACM Siggraph/Eurographics symposium on Graphics hardware</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="96" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discontinuous displacement mapping for volume graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Correa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eurographics/IEEE VGTC Workshop on Volume Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A minimum description length approach to statistical shape modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Twining</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cootes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Waterton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="537" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Medical Imaging</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ill-posed medicine -an introduction to image registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Modersitzki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inverse Problems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34008</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantically steered visual analysis of highly detailed morphometric shape spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schunke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">1st IEEE Symposium on biological data visualization (BioVis)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="158" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A visual analytics approach to study anatomic covariation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schunke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE PacificVis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functions of Matrices: Theory and Computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Higham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uncertainty visualization in hardi based on ensembles of odfs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pacific Visualization Symposium (PacificVis)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="200" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CPR-curved planar reformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kanitsar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fleischmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Felkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of anatomic covariance tensor fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Toga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (IEMBS &apos;04)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1842" to="1845" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">elastix: A toolbox for intensity-based medical image registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Staring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Viergever</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pluim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Medical Imaging</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visual analysis of image-centric cohort study data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Klemm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oeltze-Jafra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hegenscheid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Volzke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Transactions on Visualization &amp; Computer Graphics (TVCG)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1673" to="1682" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cranial integration and modularity: insights into evolution and development from morphometric data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klingenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hystrix, the Italian Journal of Mammalogy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kretschmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Soza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tietjen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Suehling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stamminger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ADR -Anatomy-Driven Reformation. IEEE Transactions on Visualization &amp; Computer Graphics (TVCG)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2496" to="2505" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive space deformation with hardwareassisted rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kurzion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of the variability of 3d statistical shape models by animation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lamecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Seebaß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-C</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Deuflhard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Studies in health technology and informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the metrics and euler-lagrange equations of computational anatomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Trouvé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Younes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annual review of biomedical engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Caricaturistic visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rautek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Viola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization &amp; Computer Graphics (TVCG)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1085" to="1092" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast volumetric deformation on general purpose hardware</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rezk-Salama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scheuering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Soza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Greiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM Siggraph/Eurographics workshop on Graphics hardware</title>
		<meeting>the ACM Siggraph/Eurographics workshop on Graphics hardware</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing changes in MR images with color-coded Jacobians</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Riddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Donlevy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dawant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic resonance imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="777" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic construction of 3d statistical deformation models using non-rigid registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rueckert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Frangi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schnabel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. MICCAI&apos;01</title>
		<meeting>MICCAI&apos;01</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capturing the multiscale anatomical shape variability with polyaffine transformation trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Seiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Pennec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Image Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1371" to="1384" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Femur specific polyaffine model to regularize the log-domain demons registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Seiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Pennec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ritacco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SPIE Medical Imaging, pages 79620G-79620G. International Society for Optics and Photonics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Registrationshop: An interactive 3d medical volume registration system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Smit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Klein Haneveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Staring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eisemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Botha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vilanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="153" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deformable medical image registration: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sotiras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Davatzikos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Paragios</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1153" to="1190" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Medical Imaging</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated visual analysis for heterogeneous datasets in cohort studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Steenwijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Milles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buchem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Botha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE VisWeek Workshop on Visual Analytics in Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visualising deformation fields computed by non-linear image registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tittgemeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wollny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kruggel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="51" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Computing and Visualization in Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistics on diffeomorphisms via tangent space representations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vaillant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Younes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Trouvé</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetric logdomain diffeomorphic registration: A demons-based approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vercauteren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Pennec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perchant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayache</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. MICCAI&apos;08</title>
		<meeting>MICCAI&apos;08</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="754" to="761" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffeomorphic demons: Efficient non-parametric image registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vercauteren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Pennec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perchant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ayache</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector field based shape deformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Funck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Theisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Seidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1118" to="1125" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volumetric segmentation of complex bone structures from medical imaging data using reeb graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wiens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Central European Seminar on Computer Graphics for Students</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="120" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
