<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Feature-Based Tensor Field Visualization for Fiber Reinforced Polymers</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Valentin</forename><surname>Zobel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Stommel</surname></persName>
							<email>markus.stommel@tu-dortmund.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gerik</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Leipzig University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">TU Dortmund University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Leipzig University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">IEEE Scientific Visualization Conference</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2015 October 25-30</addrLine>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>Il</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Feature-Based Tensor Field Visualization for Fiber Reinforced Polymers</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>tensor visualization</term>
					<term>feature-based visualisation</term>
					<term>composite materials</term>
					<term>structural mechanics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Virtual testing is an integral part of modern product development in mechanical engineering. Numerical structure simulations allow the computation of local stresses which are given as tensor fields. For homogeneous materials, the tensor information is usually reduced to a scalar field like the von Mises stress. A material-dependent threshold defines the material failure answering the key question of engineers. This leads to a rather simple feature-based visualisation. For composite materials like short fiber reinforced polymers, the situation is much more complex. The material property is determined by the fiber distribution at every position, often described as fiber orientation tensor field. Essentially, the material&apos;s ability to cope with stress becomes anisotropic and inhomogeneous. We show how to combine the stress field and the fiber orientation field in such cases, leading to a feature-based visualization of tensor fields for composite materials. The resulting features inform the engineer about potential improvements in the product development.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The design of components is a central task in mechanical engineering. Nearly all modern products consist of several components that were subject to an engineering design process. Of course, aesthetics and usability play often an important role. Also, many components have to resist one or several predefined mechanical load conditions. Besides these constraints, the engineer tries to minimize an overall cost function which often includes production cost, production speed and component weight. Essentially, the engineer has to optimize the component design under a number of constraints. Besides the geometry, he has to select a material and to define the production process. Eventually, an engineer has a rather strict time budget to carry out the task.</p><p>In this paper, we consider a specific, but frequent case of engineering design. We assume that the design aims at a component with a predefined static load condition. Furthermore, we assume that weight and production cost play a major role. Therefore, a lightweight composite material, specifically a short fiber reinforced polymer, is selected which allows for cheap mass production using injection molding. There is a very large number of different components with these specifications on the market at the moment, and this number is increasing rapidly. Hundreds of mechanical engineers carry out this task every day. Consequently, there is a strong interest in computational methods that support this design process.</p><p>One important step during the design process is a virtual test of the design with respect to the load condition. A structural mechanics simulation using the finite element method (FEM) is the standard choice for this task. The system computes the stress and strain tensor field together with other field information. From there, the engineer tries to answer his major questions:</p><p>1. Does the current design fulfill the load condition? 2. If the design fails the virtual test, where does it fail?</p><p>To get answers to these questions, the engineer reduces the tensor field information usually to a scalar field using a so called yield criterion. By a threshold for the admissible strain, the field is further reduced to a boolean field. The development of yield criteria for short fiber reinforced polymers is still in its infancy, so criteria for homogenous materials like the von Mises criterium <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> are often used despite their serious limitations in this context. There are more involved yield criteria like the Tsai-Hill <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> or the Tsai-Wu <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> criterion that use the anisotropic material properties in their evaluation. To obtain the anisotropic, inhomogeneous material properties, the injection molding process is simulated. This results in a fiber orientation function for every finite element which defines the local material properties which are used in the yield criteria. However, it is very difficult to find the thresholds for these yield criteria for arbitrary fiber orientations.</p><p>Moreover, all these criteria are used to reduce the whole field information to a simple boolean field that says if the material fails at a certain position. The resulting visualization is rather simple and has two variants. First, the boolean criterion is shown directly. Second, since these criteria create a scalar field and define a threshold, the scalar field may be shown, usually by color coding or isosurfaces. From an engineer's point of view, there are actually additional questions. If the component fails the virtual test, he needs to improve the design. A typical question is:</p><p>3. Can the material properties be changed (by changing the injection molding process) to pass the test with the current geometric design?</p><p>Depending on the answer of question 3 the engineer might further ask:</p><p>4. If the geometric design has to be changed, how should it be changed? 5. If the component copes with the load condition, can the costs be reduced without violating the constraints?</p><p>Regarding questions 4 and 5, we refer the reader to another recent article <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. In this article we focus on question 3. Current systems do not give visual support regarding this question. Our goal is to demonstrate that additional analysis and visualization allow to derive more helpful information from the data than just a boolean or scalar field. From a visualization researcher's point of view, we have clearly stated questions to derive a suitable visualization solution. Therefore, we propose a feature-based approach that allows to focus the engineer's attention to the critical regions and present detail information on the problems or chances of the current design on demand. As two tensor fields, a tensorial approximation of the fiber distribution field and the stress tensor field, are at the center of the idea, we call it a feature-based tensor field visualization for fiber reinforced polymers.</p><p>A feature is defined as "data that are important or relevant in some respect (features)" <ref type="bibr">[15, sec. 3]</ref> in the visualization literature. In our case, with respect to question 3, we distinguish three cases: (R) Red feature: it is a region of the component where a change of the local fiber distribution will not allow to pass the test. Such a feature in the component forces the engineer to change the geometric design. (O) Orange feature: This is a region in the component where the current fiber orientation fails under the local stress condition. However, a change in the fiber orientation may lead to a positive test. The engineer may try to change the injection molding process to get a valid design without geometric changes that usually require more material and increase production cost. (Y) Yellow feature: This is a region where the current fiber orientation sustains the local stress, but a change in fiber orientation may lead to failure. If the engineer wants to remove an orange feature, he has to keep the yellow features in mind.</p><p>The remaining case is called "green": These are regions where any fiber orientation allows to cope with the local stress.</p><p>Our visualization tries to concentrate on the engineer's questions. As an initial overview, we show graphs which give the number of red, orange and yellow elements for the single time steps of the simulation. A time step in the simulation reflects a certain load. This helps the engineer to select a load where the stress becomes critical. Now a time step can be selected from the graph interactively and we present the most critical features in the data. If there are red features, we show only them. The engineer knows now that his geometric design should undergo a change. If there are orange features but no red features, we show only the orange features. The engineer knows that his current design fails, but he may try to change the injection molding process to solve the problem. If there are neither red nor orange regions, we show the yellow regions and the engineer knows that the fibers improve the stability of the component. If there are neither red, orange nor yellow features, then the engineer knows that the component is stable enough for any fiber orientation. In the last case, he might consider to use the plain polymer without reinforcement. A further reduction of material volume using a different geometric design is another option.</p><p>In a second step, we give detail information on the local situation in the orange and yellow regions. We use a glyph to indicate the current local fiber distribution and a double cone to illustrate the suitable fiber directions for the current stress. This allows the engineer to get an idea on how the fiber direction needs to be changed in the orange regions and which change he has to avoid in the yellow regions. Of course, this is far from solving the question of how to change the injection molding, but it is very valuable information that other approaches miss.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>Tensor fields arise in most FEM simulations performed in engineering. However, as mentioned above, they are mostly considered as intermediate results. Usually the focus is on the derivation of scalar quantities without fully utilizing the tensor information. As a consequence, most visualization methods used in engineering are limited to basic visualizations of scalar fields, often restricted to 2D slices. Sometimes also the major eigenvectors are plotted on grid points.</p><p>More advanced visualization methods for stress tensor fields from structure simulations are used in recent work <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. The objective of this work is also to improve the stability of a component without changing its weight and hence production cost. However, this is achieved by optimizing the geometry of the component, not the fiber orientations. Tensor lines are considered as major load paths and rib structures are constructed along tensor lines. These rib structures outperform the rib structure that was constructed according to best practice in mechanical engineering.</p><p>We state some publications where related applications or methods are considered. For an overview on visualization methods for indefinite tensor fields we refer the reader to a state of the art report <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and the references therein. Additionally, we list some work where tensor fields are used in a similar context, or where related methods are used. Stress tensor fields are considered in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> in a geomechanical context. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> they are used for implant planning in orthopedics. Glyphs are widely used for the visualization of tensor fields. Different types of glyphs are compared in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The use of superquadrics as tensor glyphs is proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. General design guidelines for glyphs and strategies for glyph placement are described in the state of the art report <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. A placement strategy similar to the method we use in this article is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Another approach for the visualization of stress tensor fields is the computation of the tensor field topology. The computation of the topology for 2D tensor fields is described for example in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, for 2D time dependent tensor fields see <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. 3D tensor field topology is treated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Although tensor field topology is sometimes applied to stress tensor fields, its meaning seems unclear in our case. To our best knowledge there is no direct relation of the tensor field topology to material failure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">APPLICATION</head><p>The example considered in this work is a metal triangular wrench, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, which has to be replaced by a lightweight version. The design of the wrench has to fulfill certain constraints. As the wrench has to fit to the intended nut, a part of the geometry is predefined. In addition, the use by a human hand determines part of the surface geometry. This resulted in a CAD model, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. To reduce the weight we selected a short fiber reinforced polymer as material. Specifically, we selected PBT (polybutylene terephthalate) material reinforced by 20% short glass fibers. This material allows to use injection molding for cheap mass production.</p><p>The next step was a virtual test using the commercial FEM software package ABAQUS (Dassault Systèmes Simulia Corp., Providence, RI, USA). We assumed an anisotropic elasto-plastic material model. The dimensions of the component are 148x56x44 mm and the mesh resolution is 1 mm edge length of the finite elements. This results in a medium sized mesh of approximately 170,000 elements. The used finite elements are 10-node second-order quadratic tetrahedra, which enable a detailed geometrical representation and provide accurate simulation results.</p><p>While the previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> aimed at optimizing the geometric design using tensor visualization methods, we look for visualizations that lead to an improvement of the injection molding process in this article. Therefore, we need to simulate this process. We used the commercial tool MOLDFLOW (Moldflow Corporation Framingham, MA, USA) for this purpose. The resulting field is mapped to the Abaqus mesh using the tool CONVERSE (Simcon GmbH, 52146 Würselen, Germany). This defines a fiber orientation tensor for each element. From this field, an inhomogeneous and anisotropic mechanical behavior can be derived, which is the basis of our visualization effort.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">FUNDAMENTALS</head><p>In this section we give a short overview over the foundations necessary for our method described in Section 5. First, we give a short introduction to tensor fields and explain the stress and fiber orientation tensors used in this work. For more details on tensor fields we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and the references therein. The yield criteria used in this work, i. e. the Tsai-Hill and the Tsai-Wu criterion, are described in Section 4.2. Section 4.3 explains the reconstruction of a fiber distribution function from the fiber orientation tensor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Tensor Fields</head><p>By the general mathematical definition, a tensor on a real vector space V is a multilinear map</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T : V × • • • ×V ×V * × • • • ×V * → R</formula><p>taking n copies of V and m copies of the dual space V * of V to a real number. The numbers n and m are called the covariant and contravariant order of the tensor field, respectively. In this work we are mostly concerned with three-dimensional tensors of covariant order two, i. e. maps of type T :</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">R 3 ×R 3 → R. T is called symmetric if T (v, w) = T (w, v) for all v, w ∈ R 3 . If T satisfies also T (v, v) &gt; 0 for all v = 0</formula><p>, it is called positive definite. By choosing a (usually orthonormal) basis e i of V and setting T i j := T (e i , e j ) we can write the tensor component-wise or as a matrix.</p><p>A tensor field on a subset U of R 3 is a map assigning a threedimensional tensor to each point of U. It is called symmetric, positive definite and so forth if this condition holds pointwise. In this work, we deal with virtual testing of technical components. So U is given by the shape of the component, and the tensor field is some quantity simulated at each point of the component, in our case the stress or the fiber orientation.</p><p>Stress Tensor The question whether a material can resist a certain load depends on the stresses arising inside the material. To answer this question we need to know about the stresses in each point of the component. The complete state of stress is given as a symmetric tensor field</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">σ =   σ x τ xy τ xz τ xy σ y τ yz τ xz τ yz σ z  </formula><p>where σ and τ are the normal and shear stresses, respectively. Given a unit normal vector n the stress vector σ n describes the forces acting on a plane perpendicular to n. The stress vector σ n can be decomposed into a component acting normal to this plane, the normal stress, and a component acting tangential to the plane, the shear stress. Due to the symmetry of σ there is a basis of eigenvectors of σ . The eigenvectors, usually denoted by n 1 , n 2 , n 3 , are called principal directions. The corresponding eigenvalues are called principal stresses and commonly denoted by σ 1 , σ 2 , σ 3 , not to be confused with the normal stresses σ x , σ y , σ z in an arbitrary coordinate system. On the planes defined by n 1 , n 2 , n 3 there are acting only normal stresses and no shear stresses. Positive values for the eigenvalues σ x , σ y , σ z indicate tensile stresses, negative values compressive stresses. For more details on stress tensors, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</p><p>Fiber Orientation In this work we are interested in the stability of technical components made of short fiber reinforced polymers by injection molding. In contrast to homogeneous materials, it is much more difficult to decide if the material can resist local stressing conditions. The admissible stresses vary from point to point and depend on the fiber orientation. In each point the distribution of the fiber directions is given by a probability density function ψ defined on the unit sphere S 2 . The output of an injection molding simulation performed with MOLDFLOW, however, is not a fiber distribution function ψ but a fiber orientation tensor a i j of order two. The relation between ψ and a i j is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">a i j = S 2 p i p j ψ(p) d p ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where p = (p 1 , p 2 , p 3 ) is a point on the sphere. From the properties of the probability distribution follows that a i j is a symmetric positive definite tensor of second order with trace(a i j ) = 1. While a i j gives a rough approximation of the fiber distribution function ψ, a more precise approximation of ψ can be obtained using also the fourth order fiber orientation tensor a i jkl which is defined similarly by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">a i jkl = S 2 p i p j p k p l ψ(p) d p .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>The reconstruction of ψ from a i j and a i jkl is briefly described in Section 4.3, for more details on the relation between fiber orientation tensors and the fiber distribution function see <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Yield Criteria</head><p>Yield criteria are used to predict if a material can resist a local stressing condition. For the sake of completeness we first introduce the well-known von Mises stress, which is a suitable choice for predicting failure of isotropic materials. Since fiber reinforced polymers show a anisotropic behavior we need more intricate criteria like the Tsai-Hill and the Tsai-Wu criterion. The latter is even more complex, since it considers a different tensile and compressive strength, which are assumed to be equal in the Tsai-Hill criterion. Von Mises criterion One widely used failure criterion is the von Mises stress <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">σ v = (σ x − σ y ) 2 + (σ x − σ z ) 2 + (σ y − σ z ) 2 − 6(τ 2 xy + τ 2 xz + τ 2 yz ) 2 .</formula><p>The material is assumed to fail if σ v exceeds a certain value which has to be determined experimentally. This criterion is only meaningful for isotropic materials, i. e. it is independent of the orientation of the material with respect to the stress. Tsai-Hill Criterion A more advanced criterion is the Tsai-Hill criterion <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> which is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">F(σ y − σ z ) 2 + G(σ x − σ z ) 2 + H(σ x − σ y ) 2 +2(Lτ 2 12 + Mτ 2 13 + Nτ 2 23 ) ≤ 1 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>while the constants F, G, H, L, M, N are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">F = 1 2 1 Y 2 + 1 Z 2 − 1 X 2 , G = 1 2 1 Z 2 + 1 X 2 − 1 Y 2 , H = 1 2 1 X 2 + 1 Y 2 − 1 Z 2 , L = 1 2S 2 12 , M = 1 2S 2 13 , N = 1 2S 2 23 .</formula><p>The numbers X,Y, Z denote the tensile/compressive strength in x-, yand z-direction, while tensile and compressive strength are expected to be equal. S 12 , S 13 , S 23 denote the shear strength in the xy-, x-z-, y-z-plane, respectively. These values have to be determined by tensile and shear testing, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>.</p><p>Because there are six material constants in the model, six experiments are necessary for calibration. For isotropic materials this criterion reduces to the von Mises stress. In case of transversal isotropy the number of experiments reduces to three. Transversal isotropy means that the material does not change its properties with arbitrary rotations around a particular axis. A fiber reinforced polymer with an unidirectional fiber distribution, that is all fibers are pointing in the same direction, fulfills this property. Here, the axis of symmetry is given by the direction of the fibers. If we choose a coordinate system where the x-axis coincides with the axis of symmetry, we have Y = Z and S 12 = S 13 . Additionally the rotational symmetry implies N = 2F + G which replaces S 23 . Consequently, we need experimentally determined values for X,Y, S 12 .</p><p>Tsai-Wu Criterion The Tsai-Hill criterion does not distinguish between tensile and compressive stresses. A criterion incorporating this is the Tsai-Wu failure criterion given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">b 1 σ x + b 2 σ y + b 3 σ z + F 11 σ 2 x + F 22 σ 2 y + F 33 σ 2 z +2F 12 σ x σ y + 2F 13 σ x σ z + 2F 23 σ y σ z (4) +F 44 τ 2 12 + F 55 τ 2 13 + F 66 τ 2 23 ≤ 1 .</formula><p>The b i and F i j are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">b 1 = 1 X t − 1 X c , b 2 = 1 Y t − 1 Y c , b 3 = 1 Z t − 1 Z c , F 11 = 1 X t X c , F 22 = 1 Y t Y c , F 33 = 1 Z t Z c</formula><p>,</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">F 44 = 1 S 2 12 , F 55 = 1 S 2 13 , F 66 = 1 S 2 23 , F 12 = − 1 2 √ X t X c Y t Y c , F 13 = − 1 2 √ X t X c Z t Z c , F 23 = − 1 2 √ Y t Y c Z t Z c .</formula><p>Here the indices t and c for X,Y, Z indicate tension or compression.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Reconstruction of the Fiber Distribution Function</head><p>Fiber orientations computed during the simulation of the injection molding process are represented as fiber orientation tensors.</p><p>In some cases, we are interested in the fiber distribution function rather than the fiber orientation tensor, the relation between them is explained in Equation (1). A fiber distribution function can be approximately reconstructed from a given fiber orientation tensor. One such reconstruction, which is widely used in the context of short fiber composites, is briefly discussed in this Section, for details we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and the references therein. The fiber distribution function ψ can be expressed by the series expansion</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">ψ(p) = f 0 V 0 + f i j (p)V i j + f i jkl (p)V i jkl + . . .</formula><p>The basis functions f 0 , f i j , f i jkl , . . . have values in the space of tensors of order zero, two, four and so on. Similarly, the coefficients</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">V 0 , V i j , V i jkl , .</formula><p>. . are zero order, second order, fourth order tensors and so forth. Truncation after the fourth order term yields a fourth order reconstruction of the fiber distribution function. The basis functions up to order four are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">f 0 = 1 f i j = p i p j − 1 3 δ i j f i jkl = p i p j p k p l − 1 7 (p i p j δ kl + p i p k δ jl + p i p l δ jk + p j p k δ il + p j p l δ ik + p k p l δ i j ) + 1 35 δ i j δ kl + δ ik δ jl + δ il δ jk</formula><p>where δ i j denotes the Kronecker delta. The coefficients can be computed from the basis functions by</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">V i j... = 1 4πN! = N ∏ x=0 (2x + 1) S 2 ψ(p) f i j... d p .<label>(5)</label></formula><p>For V i j the integral in Equation 5 can be rewritten to</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">S 2 ψ(p) f i j d p = a i j − 1 3 δ i j ,</formula><p>by S 2 ψ(p) d p = 1 and the definition of the fiber orientation tensor (1). Consequently it is easy to compute V i j for a given fiber orientation tensor. The computation of V i jkl is more difficult, since the integral becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">S 2 ψ(p) f i jkl d p = S 2 ψ(p)p i p j p k p l d p − . . . = a i jkl − . . . ,</formula><p>i. e. the fourth order fiber orientation tensor a i jkl is involved here.</p><p>Since a i jkl is not an output of the injection molding simulation, it is a common practice to approximate it from the second order fiber orientation tensor a i j . Several so-called closure approximations have been proposed to approximate a i jkl , see for example <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. One of the simplest closure approximations is the quadratic closure which is given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">a i jkl = a i j a kl .</formula><p>The linear closure is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">a i jkl = − 1 7 (a i j δ kl + a ik δ jl + a il δ jk + a jk δ il + a jl δ ik + a kl δ i j ) + 1 35 δ i j δ kl + δ ik δ jl + δ il δ jk .</formula><p>While the quadratic closure is exact for unidirectional fiber orientations, the linear closure is exact for uniform (random) fiber orientations. In our work we use the so-called hybrid closure approximation, which is basically a combination of the quadratic and the linear closure. For details, we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">METHOD</head><p>With our method we want to find out whether a component can be improved by a modified fiber orientation, and if so, we want to indicate possible improvements of the fiber orientation. To do this we have to be able to predict potential failure in dependence of a fiber orientation. This allows us to distinguish four simple cases:</p><p>The material fails in case of any fiber orientation (red), the material never fails (green), or it depends on the fiber orientation. The latter case also considers whether the actual fiber orientation fails (orange) or not (yellow). Using glyphs visualizing admissible fiber directions alongside the given fiber orientation, we show possible improvements of the fiber orientation. Since common tensor glyphs are not directly usable for visualizing fiber orientation tensors, we propose an adapted version of superquadrics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Predicting Failure</head><p>Short fiber reinforced polymers produced by injection molding are inhomogeneous materials, i. e. the fiber distribution varies from point to point. Thus, in each point, the constants of the yield criteria (3) and (4) have to be defined differently. It would be necessary to perform tensile and shear testing for every possible fiber distribution. This would not only be a big effort, it would also be necessary to produce specimen with specific fiber orientations, which is not possible. Only the production of specimen with unidirectional fiber orientations is feasible, i. e. only in case of unidirectional fiber orientations failure can be predicted precisely. In order to guess failure for an arbitrary fiber orientation, we propose the following heuristic. In a first step we assume different unidirectional fiber orientations and compute whether the material would fail under the given stress. In a second step, the fiber distribution function is employed to compute the percentage of fibers pointing in failing directions. If this value exceeds a predefined value, the material is assumed to fail.</p><p>For the first step we need to apply the Tsai-Hill (3) or the Tsai-Wu criterion (4) on unidirectional fiber orientations. Unidirectional fiber orientations result in a transversal isotropic material, and we assume that the constants in (3) or (4) are chosen for fibers pointing in x-direction. Instead of changing the constants for other fiber directions, we rotate the given stress tensor σ . If p is the fiber direction, we just need a rotation matrix R which maps the first unit vector e 1 on p, i. e.</p><p>Re 1 = p .</p><p>By applying the Tsai-Hill criterion or the Tsai-Wu criterion on</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">σ = R T σ R</formula><p>we can compute if a material with fibers pointing in direction p can resist a local stressing condition σ . Due to the transversal isotropy the result of the yield criteria is invariant under rotations of σ around the x-axis. This explains why it is only necessary that R maps e 1 to p. The mapping of e 2 and e 3 is arbitrary. Now we divide the set of all fiber directions into bundles of similar fiber directions. This is equivalent to a partition of the sphere into small regions A i ⊂ S 2 . The fiber directions represented by A 1 , . . . , A n are approximated by a single direction p 1 , . . . , p n ∈ S 2 . Next, we evaluate a yield criterion for each direction p i as described above. In this way, we can compute all unidirectional fiber directions p i which cause failure.</p><p>For rating arbitrary fiber orientations, we make use of the fiber distribution function ψ which can be approximated from the fiber orientation tensor a i j . The reconstruction of ψ is briefly discussed in Section 4.3, for details on the implementation of this method we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. With the help of ψ we are able to rate the fiber orientation by computing</p><formula xml:id="formula_20">f (ψ) = ∑ i∈I f A i ψ(p i )</formula><p>while the sum runs over the set of indices i ∈ I f for which the fiber directions p i fails. This gives the percentage of fibers pointing in directions where unidirectional fiber orientations would cause failure. Now, a fiber orientation is assumed to fail if this percentage exceeds a predefined threshold t.</p><p>We have chosen to construct the function f in a discrete way for a more vivid presentation and since this reflects the implementation. Alternatively, we can define f continuously. Let F ⊂ S 2 be the set of fiber directions p for which the material fails, then</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">f (ψ) = F⊂S 2 ψ(p) d p</formula><p>is again the percentage of fibers causing failure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Classifying Regions</head><p>In order to show the potential of possible optimizations of the fiber orientation, we want to partition the component into four different regions, colored green, yellow, orange, and red. Green regions classify parts where the failure criterion indicates that the material resists, independent of the fiber orientation. Yellow and orange regions mark parts where the fiber orientation influences the result of the yield criterion. If the actual fiber orientation indicates failure it is colored orange, otherwise yellow. Regions where no local fiber orientation can prevent failure are colored red.</p><p>From a theoretical point of view, a point with a set of failing fiber directions F and fiber distribution ψ is However, in case of orange F might cover almost the whole sphere, leaving just a small area uncovered. Then a specific, almost unidirectional fiber orientation would be necessary which might be impossible in practice. The reconstruction of the fiber distribution function reflects this fact, i. e. the reconstructed fiber distribution functions, as described in Section 4.3, are rather smooth. In particular, unidirectional fiber orientations are excluded, since the corresponding fiber distribution function is a Dirac delta function. Thus we want to consider only regions as orange if there is a real chance that a reconstructed fiber distribution function ψ fulfills f (ψ) ≤ t. Since it is very costly to compute if there exists a reconstructed ψ for an arbitrary F satisfying this condition, we define a global maximum for the area of F on S 2 . For this we consider the sharpest possible reconstructed ψ, which is the reconstruction from the fiber orientation tensor a i j representing an unidirectional fiber orientation. Lets assume fibers pointing in x-direction, i. e. a 11 = 1 and a i j = 0 for all other components. Now we want to compute the maximal area of F which allows that ψ fulfills f (ψ) ≤ t. Due the spherical symmetry of our ψ around the x-axis the desired F covers the whole sphere with the exception of spherical regions around the poles of S 2 on the x-axis. Thus we can find an upper bound for the area of F by integrating ψ over increasing regions around the pole. If this integral exceeds 1 − t, the complement of the domain of integration is the desired F.</p><p>The upper bound we compute this way is precise if F is a circular region, otherwise it serves as an approximation. Similarly, we compute a lower bound for the area of F in case of yellow. If F is small enough that even the worst reconstructed fiber distribution satisfies f (ψ) ≤ t, then we want to consider these regions as green.</p><p>In this case we proceed as above, but here F is given as the spherical region around the poles for which the integral is equal to t.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Visualization using Glyphs</head><p>We have distinguished four different regions of a component in the last section, where orange regions are especially interesting. In this regions an optimization of the component might be possible by modifying the fiber orientation. To indicate improved fiber orientations we use two kinds of glyphs. The first glyph is designed to show the preferred directions for the fibers. Moreover we use a modified version of superquadrics to visualize the current fiber orientation. Using the function f (ψ), which gives the amount of fibers pointing in disadvantageous directions, we can easily place the glyphs at the crucial points.</p><p>Visualizing Preferred Fiber Directions In Section 5.1 we have defined a set F as the directions where unidirectional fiber orientations would cause failure. We want a fiber distribution with as few as possible fiber directions contained in F, thus it is comprehensible to visualize the directions F. For this we consider the boundary points of F and connect them with the origin, this results in a cone separating fiber orientations causing failure from those that do not. This new kind of glyph makes it easy to identify the desired fiber orientations. We show some examples of this glyphs in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> alongside with the glyphs for the fiber orientation described in the next paragraph.  <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>: Glyphs visualizing the desired fiber directions and the fiber orientation tensor. Admissible fiber directions lie on the green side of the cones, directions causing failure are located on the red side. These directions depend on the stress tensor. For the visualization of the fiber orientations superquadrics are used. The color indicates if the fiber orientation causes failure (orange/red) or not (yellow), while red means that every other fiber orientation would also fail.</p><p>Visualizing Fiber Orientation Tensors In our case we are mostly interested in the fiber distribution function which is associated with the fiber orientation tensor. Thus a visualization of the reconstructed fiber orientation function ψ, as described in Section 4.3, might be a solution. This could, for exmaple, be achieved by altering the radius of a sphere according to the function values. However, as mentioned above the reconstructed ψ is rather smooth, moreover it can have small negeative values. Due to such artifacts this does not result in an easily understood visualization. Instead we consider the precise reconstruction of the fiber distribution function for an unidirectional fiber orientation. This is represented by a fiber distribution tensor with eigenvalues λ 1 = 1, λ 2 = λ 3 = 0, and the precise reconstruction would yield a Dirac delta function. Of course, it is also not possible to properly visualize a Dirac delta function but one would expect a rod-shaped glyph in this case. Similarly, for a planar distribution, which corresponds to eigenvalues of λ 1 = λ 2 = 1/2, λ 3 = 0, one would expect a disk-shaped glyph, and for a uniform distribution with eigenvalues λ 1 = λ 2 = λ 3 = 1/3 a sphere is preferable. These three cases are also denoted as linear, planar and spherical, respectively. Superquadrics, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> for details, are quite close to what we want here, but some adjustments are needed to meet our requirements. Like many other tensor glyphs superquadrics vanish when an eigenvalue of the tensor is zero, and this is the case for unidirectional and planar fiber distribu-tions. To avoid this, we shift zero eigenvalues slightly in the positive range. Furthermore, since the fiber orientation tensor has a trace of one, the spherical glyph has a radius of 1/3, a disc-shaped glyph has a radius of 1/2 and a rod-shaped glyph has length one. This makes the spherical and the disc-shaped glyph to look rather small. So we adjust the radius of these glyphs to create glyphs which appear to be equally sized. This is achieved by an affine linear transformation of the eigenvalues of each fiber orientation tensor</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">λ → m + M − m λ 1 λ ,</formula><p>where M is the desired maximal radius and m the desired minimal radius, i. e. the largest eigenvalue is mapped to M and an eigenvalue of zero is mapped to m. We choose M and m separately for the linear, planar, spherical case, and interpolate between the three cases using the anisotropy metrics c l , c p and c s by Westin <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Now, if  Glyph Placement Our goal is to place glyphs preferably at points where the current fiber distribution is disadvantageous. We use the value f (ψ) for this purpose. The higher the value, the more disadvantageous the fiber distribution is. This allows an easy approach for placing glyphs on all relevant positions. We compute f (ψ) for all data points and sort it in decreasing order. Then, we choose the first point, i. e. the point with the highest value. Subsequently, we remove all points within a neighborhood of predefined size. This procedure of choosing the first point and removing all points within a neighborhood is repeated until there are no points left. The size of the neigbourhood has to be chosen carefully, if the size is too large important fetaures can be missed, a small size results in a high number of glyphs and produces clutter. To find the proper value easily, the user can interactively control the size of the regions, as well as the size of the glyphs.</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">M l , M</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head><p>We evaluate our method with two datasets. The first is a tensile bar, a specimen used to perform experiments as depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  3</ref>. Such specimen can be produced with an almost unidirectional fiber orientation in tensile direction, so we know that the fiber orientation is satisfactory here. This allows us to check if our method works properly. As a second example we use the triangular wrench described in Section 3, and we compare three different fiber orientations here.</p><p>As failure criterion we use the Tsai-Wu criterion. Due to its ability of distinguishing tensile and compressive stresses, it is the more advanced one. For the calibration of this failure criteria we need the constants X t , X c , Y t , Y c , S 12 . The material used in our simulations is PBT GF 20, a polybutylene terephthalate with 20% short glass fibers. This material is considerd also in <ref type="bibr">[11, p. 91]</ref> where the values X t = 102.54, X c = 140.30, and S 12 = 57.87 are measured experimentally. Furthermore, Y t = 52 and Y c = 72 are determined virtually by simulation since it is not feasible to perform the necessary experiments, see <ref type="bibr">[11, p. 105]</ref>.</p><p>We also have to choose the threshold t which defines the maximum percentage of fibers allowed to point in directions where unidirectional fiber distributions would cause failure. Obviously, it would make not much sense to choose t &gt; 0.5, since this would allow that a majority of fibers points into directions causing failure. In contrast, a very strict choice, e. g. t = 0.1 or less, would make it rather hard for a fiber distribution to meet this requirement in many situations. Defining a precise value for t would certainly need a thorough investigation including experiments which is beyond the scope of this work. For our experiments we decided to use t = 0.2, which is a cautious choice but not too restrictive.</p><p>Tensile Bar A stretching of 1 mm is simulated for the tensile bar, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>. During the simulation process the stretching is increased progressively, which leads to a time parameter ranging from 0 to 1. At first we compute the red, orange and yellow regions for all time steps and show its temporal development in a graph, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 7</ref>. The graph shows the number of elements of the respective regions during the simulation process. We can observe here that the first yellow elements arise after a stretching of about 0.27 mm and increase rapidly. However, the first orange elements appear much later when the stretching reaches 0.64 mm. Shortly after, at about 0.68 mm, the first elements turn red. This indicates that the fiber orientation is really good here and there is not much to optimize. And this is exactly what we expect here, since the fibers are almost perfectly aligned in the direction of stretching.</p><p>Now we can select a time step from the graph and have a closer look at the colored regions for a stretching of 0.64 mm, 0.68 mm and 0.75 mm, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref> top. Considering our glpyhs showing preferred fiber directions and the current fiber distribution, we can also see that the fibers are pretty much aligned in stressing direction, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref> bottom. Moreover we observe that the cones are diminishing with increasing stretching. This indicates that decreasing variations of the fiber orientation are allowed for increasing stresses.  Triangular wrench As a second example we consider the triangular wrench. We investigate the fiber orientations produced by three different gates, i. e. three different points of injection, see <ref type="figure">Figure</ref> 9. An increasing force of up to 200 N acting on the wrench is simulated. We start with a fiber orientation produced with a gate on the side, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 9a</ref>. The first orange elements occur after a time of 0.4 which corresponds to a force of 80 N, i. e. the force becomes critical here. The orange region is shown in the upper image of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10a</ref>. The glyphs for this region (lower image) reveal that the fiber orientation is very inadequate to sustain the load. Many fibers point in directions which are on the red side of the cone, so the fiber orientation is obviously responsible for the material failure here. This is clearly a result of the chosen gate on the side, since the fibers are aligned with the flow of the melt. Next we move the gate   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 9b</ref>. This brings a significant improvement, the number of orange elements for 80 N is reduced from 362 for case (a) to 47 for case (b). Consequently the orange region <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 10b</ref> top) is much smaller. The corresponding glyphs show that the fiber orientation is much better and even in the orange regions a large number of fibers points into admissible directions. Consequently the glyphs also show if the fiber orientation in an orange region might still be acceptable or if it is inappropriate. Unfortunately, a new orange region arises at the end of the wrench for case (b).</p><p>Moving the gate to the front of the wrench (9c) reduces the number of orange elements further to 41. As we can see in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure (10c)</ref>, the orange region at the end of the wrench disappears almost completely, while the fiber orientation in the middle of the wrench is very similar to case (b), i. e. we have no significant loss in this region.</p><p>Discussion As we have seen it is possible to achieve a better fiber orientation by modifying the gate. There are also other parameters in the injection process, like the injection direction, the temperature or the pressure, which can influence the resulting fiber orientation. However, there is no way to precisely control the fiber orientation in an injection process. Moreover, it is possible that even the best parameters for the injection process lead to a fiber orientation which is still not perfect. However, an experienced engineer will be able to guess reasonable injection parameters much better if he knows about the desired fiber orientation. Thus our glyphs give helpful information for the engineer in order to improve the injection process. Naturally, the question arises whether an automatic optimization of the injection parameters is possible. The computation of the stresses with regard to the fiber orientation takes several hours. Thus very few simulation runs are possible within an acceptable amount of time. This makes an automatic or even semi-automatic optimization not practical with current simulation methods and computing power, though this is a desirable goal for the future.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>The design of components is a central task in mechanical engineering. Essentially, the engineer is solving an optimization problem with constraints. After an initial design, a virtual test using structural simulations is performed. This results in a stress tensor field besides other field information. The central question is the potential failure of the design under the predefined load. This question is answered by a failure criterion suitable for the chosen material. This results usually in a simple boolean or single scalar field visualization with fixed threshold.</p><p>However, we have shown in this paper that after the virtual test, there is always the question of potential improvement. This is not really supported by current visualization methods besides indicating the failure region. The engineer can always change the geometric design. In case of composite materials, he can also steer the material properties in a certain region by changing the production process, in our case injection molding. This opens an interesting way of improvement because it typically won't change production cost, production speed, or component weight, i. e. the overall cost function. Our new feature-based visualization does not only inform the engineer where his design might fail, we also show how far failure is caused by a disadvantageous fiber orientation and how it can be improved. We assume that this information is very useful for changing the production process in order to obtain a fiber orientation which leads to a more stable component. Our visualization gives a simple, efficient overview and presents details in the critical parts of the design. This includes a new type of glyph showing the admissible fiber directions, as well as modified superquadrics for visualizing fiber orientation tensors. We demonstrate in the results section how this visualization can be interpreted.</p><p>Regarding our future work, there are several aspects of this work that we would like to improve. So far, we have only given informal evidence for the use of our method. Therefore, we want to check in how far our hypothesis is suitable to predict failure in dependence of arbitrary fiber distributions. This includes also a proper investigation of the threshold t. We will also study the influence of the fiber orientations in the structure simulation. Modified fiber orientations can have an effect on the stresses. Currently, we ignore this effect but we need to check its influence, especially in the context of optimizing the injection molding process. Finally, we hope to stimulate other groups to join our effort of deriving better visualization tools for the design in mechanical engineering, especially for composite materials.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Original metal version of the triangular wrench</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Full CAD model of new plastic design</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Illustration of tensile and compressive testing in x direction (left) and shear testing in the x-y-plane (right). Testing S xy or S yx yields the same result.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>red, if F = S 2 , • orange, if / 0 = F S 2 and f (ψ) &gt; t, • yellow, if / 0 = F S 2 and f (ψ) ≤ t, • green, if F = / 0.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) Stress is constant while the fiber orientation tensor rotates (b) Stress is constant while the fiber orientation changes from a rather aligned to a rather planar distribution (c) Fiber orientation is constant while the stress in z-direction increases (d) Fiber orientation and stress in z-direction is constant while additional stress in ydirection is added</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>p , M s and m l , m p , m s are the maximal and minimal radii for the planar, linear and spherical case, respectively, we set M = c l M l + c p M p + c s M s , m = c l m l + c p m p + c s m s . We have chosen M l = 1.0, M p = 0.75, M s = 0.6 and m l = 0.1, m p = 0.05, m s = 0. The resulting glyphs are shown in Figure 5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Superquadrics adapted for the visualization of fiber orientation tensors. The tensors are interpolated over a triangle with vertices representing the linear, planar and spherical case.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Geometry of the tensile bar</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Graph showing the number of red, orange and yellow elements over time</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>The tensile bar for a stretching of 0.64 mm, 0.68 mm and 0.75 mm (from left to right). Red, orange and yellow regions are shown in the upper row, glyphs visualizing fiber orientations and admissible fibers are shown in the lower row.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Different gates for producing the wrench by injection molding to the top, see</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Orange regions and glyphs for the wrench at a force of 80 N</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank Michael Stanko and Marc Schoeneich for creating the dataset of the triangular wrench and the tensile bar, respectively, and providing all necessary information about the data.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glyph-based visualization: Foundations, design guidelines, techniques and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Borgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kehrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Maguire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Laramee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eurographics State of the Art Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated multi-aspect visualization of 3d fluid flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brambilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ø</forename><surname>Andreassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of VMV 2013: Vision, Modeling &amp; Visualization</title>
		<meeting>of VMV 2013: Vision, Modeling &amp; Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-09" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orthotropic closure approximations for flow-induced fiber orientation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cintra</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Rheology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1095" to="1122" />
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The topology of symmetric, secondorder tensor fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Delmarcelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hesselink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the conference on Visualization&apos;94</title>
		<meeting>the conference on Visualization&apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="147" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stress tensor field visualization for implant planning in orthopedics. Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Georgii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Burgkart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1399" to="1406" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Micromechanics of inelastic composites with misaligned inclusions: numerical treatment of orientation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Doghri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tinel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer methods in applied mechanics and engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">195</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1387" to="1406" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glyph and hyperstreamline representation of stress and strain tensors and material constitutive response</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hashash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wotring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal for numerical and analytical methods in geomechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="626" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The mathematical theory of plasticity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1950" />
			<publisher>Oxford university press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing the use of tensor closure methods with orientation distribution reconstruction functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of composite materials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1851" to="1871" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tensor visualizations in computational geomechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jeremić</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Joy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal for Numerical and Analytical Methods in Geomechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="944" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Beitrag zur mikromechanischen Berechnung kurzfaserverstärkter Kunststoffe-Deformation und Versagen</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Universität des Saarlandes</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Superquadric tensor glyphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixth Joint Eurographics-IEEE TCVG conference on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>the Sixth Joint Eurographics-IEEE TCVG conference on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="154" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization and Analysis of Second-Order Tensors: Moving Beyond the Symmetric Positive-Definite Case</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kratz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Auer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stommel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum -State of the Art Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tensor visualization driven mechanical component design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kratz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schoeneich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Zobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Burgeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stommel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. PacificVis</title>
		<meeting>PacificVis</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE. IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iconic techniques for feature visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Van Walsum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 6th conference on Visualization&apos;95</title>
		<meeting>the 6th conference on Visualization&apos;95</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page">288</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Superquadric glyphs for symmetric second-order tensors. Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1595" to="1604" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tensor topology tracking: A visualization method for time-dependent 2d symmetric tensor fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tricoche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general theory of strength for anisotropic materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of composite materials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1971" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanik der festen Körper im plastisch-deformablen Zustand</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mises</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nachrichten von der Gesellschaft der Wissenschaften zu Göttingen, Mathematisch-Physikalische Klasse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="582" to="592" />
			<date type="published" when="1913" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Geometrical diffusion measures for mri from tensor basis analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-F</forename><surname>Westin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Peled</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gudbjartsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jolesz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1742</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topological lines in 3d tensor fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="320" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
