<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Graphic Data Display for Cardiovascular System</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date>October 22 -October 23, 2001</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Case</forename><surname>Study</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Agutter</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>March</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Graduate School of Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">Noah</forename><surname>Syroid</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Drews</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Dwayne</forename><surname>Westenskow</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Bioengineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Julio</forename><surname>Bermudez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Graduate School of Architecture</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Strayer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<address>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Graphic Data Display for Cardiovascular System</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published">October 22 -October 23, 2001</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T18:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Our multidisciplinary group has developed a visual representation for cardiovascular physiological variables. This enhances a clinician&apos;s ability to detect and rapidly respond to critical events. The integrated and intuitive display communicates a patient&apos;s cardiovascular state so that it is easily and quickly understood without prior training. The display is designed to show patterns of functional relationships that aid in the detection, diagnosis, and treatment of a critical event.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Background of Problem</head><p>Medical errors have cost tens of thousands of lives in United States hospitals each year-a number greater than deaths from highway accidents, breast cancer, and AIDS combined. The Institute of Medicine (IOM) in its landmark report "To Err is Human," (released in November 2000 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>), estimates the number of deaths due to medical mistakes to be from 44,000 to 98,000 annually Many of those errors occur in anesthesia, where it has been estimated that human error is associated with more than 80% of critical anesthesia incidents and more than 50% of anesthetic deaths. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> This data is consistent with other complex work environments involving humanmachine interactions such as aviation and process control. Critical incident studies report that an adverse outcome frequently became a catastrophic "evolving chain" of subtle incidents, which alone might not have lead to a disaster. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> Many of these errors can be directly traced to erroneous, or misleading information from patient monitors or in the physician's failure to recognize a pattern in the data that would have led to a correct diagnosis of the problem. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> By optimizing the content and organization of graphical displays, clinicians would likely detect, diagnose and treat critical anesthesia events more effectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Traditional Anesthesia Displays</head><p>Anesthesia display design has primarily been bound by tradition as opposed to helping clinicians detect critical events. They still look like the strip chart recorder output Sir Thomas Lewis used in 1912 to record the first ECG.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1.Traditional Display (Datex-Ohmeda)</head><p>These monitors use a "single-sensor-single-indicator" display paradigm ( <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> That is, a single variable is displayed for each sensor used. As a result, clinicians must observe and integrate information generated by the independent sensors. This process of sequential, piecemeal data gathering makes it difficult to develop a coherent understanding of the interrelationship between the presented information of physiological processes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> An alternative to traditional SSSI displays is to develop displays that integrate data at a higher level, provide the user with graphic representation and present information in a way that is consistent with the cognitive representation of that user.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Display Design Background</head><p>It is well known that humans are largely visual creatures. Throughout time humans have used pictures to communicate difficult concepts quickly and effectively. These pictures, like the ancient pictographs found in the Lascoux caves, help us make inferences that lead to a better and quicker understanding of the message behind the picture. Recent cognitive research has indicated that the human mind is better able to analyze and use complex data when it is presented graphically, rather than textual or numerical formats <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Research in thinking, imagination and learning has shown that visualization plays an intuitive and essential role in the association, correlation, manipulation and use of information. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> The more complex and critical the information, the more imperative it is to communicate the information effectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> When the information is consistent with cognitive representation, performance is often more rapid, accurate, and consistent. Conversely, a failure to use perceptual principles in the appropriate ways can lead to erroneous analyses of information. Therefore, it is imperative that information be presented in a manner that facilitates the user's ability to process the information and minimize any mental transformations that must be applied to the data. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> It is this essentially qualitative filtering and depiction of information towards achieving a clear end that constitutes representation design. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> Providing information in an integrated way should increase the anesthesiologist's situation awareness, and thus reduce the risk of patient injury.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Display Description</head><p>To monitor an anesthetized patient the anesthesiologist watches over 30 interrelated variables. This task is very demanding, as it requires the clinician to keep a high level of situational awareness while performing other duties, such as caring for the patient, filing out patient record etc. Current displays sub-optimally show the information as waveforms and numerics.</p><p>Our research group has designed an innovative, detailed, cardiovascular display for anesthesiologists that aids in the detection, diagnosis and treatment of critical cardiovascular events during anesthesia. The display organizes measured and modeled physiologic information, into relevant data sets or critical functions. These data sets are mapped as graphical objects (e.g., cubes, spheres, cylinders, prisms) that work as metaphors of the critical functions of the system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Design Process</head><p>We began by examining other cardiovascular displays and generating a list of cardiovascular variables that have important clinical information about the patient's cardiovascular state: Central venous pressure (CVP, mmHg) measures the blood pressure after gas exchange in the systemic tissues and organs. Mean pulmonary artery pressure (PAP, mmHg) is the blood pressure in the lungs. When PAP is high, such as in right heart failure, fluid tends to cross the pulmonary-capillary membranes and collect in the lung's alveoli. The pulmonary vascular resistance (PVR, dynes/sec/cm 5 ) indicates vasoconstriction or vasodilatation of the pulmonary vasculature. Mean left arterial pressure (LAP, mmHg) in the pulmonary vein is an indicator of left heart preload. Cardiac Output (CO, ml/min) is the blood flow through the heart and is a function of heart rate (HR, beats/min), and stroke volume (SV, ml):</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">SV HR CO u</formula><p>. Mean arterial pressure (MAP, mmHg) is a primary clinical monitoring variable. The systemic vascular resistance (SVR, dynes/sec/cm 5 ) is an indicator of arterial vessel constriction or dilation. Blood is the substrate for oxygen transport. SaO2 is the ratio of oxygen saturated hemoglobin in the arterial system Using this set of variables, many preliminary ideas were explored through the use of digital sketches. <ref type="figure">(Figure 2</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Design Principles</head><p>After numerous discussions, we simplified and distilled the ideas down to one design using design principles that suggest normal uniform, regularly spaced elements to create a smooth balanced design when variables are normal that includes a reference frame. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> The use of these principles for designing clinical monitors allows for <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. Preliminary Sketches rapid detection of change, which is consistent with the ideas behind an artificial horizon and the symmetrical polygon displays. When the patient status is abnormal, deviations from a smooth balanced design occur they are perceived very quickly because the normal shapes are preattentively processed <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. That is to say that the objects "pop out" from their surroundings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Display Organization</head><p>The objects in the display are spatially located to show a diagrammatic organization of the flow of the blood. From the left, venous blood returning from the systemic capillaries flows into the vena cava (a). The right heart (b) pumps the deoxygenated blood through the pulmonary arteries (c) to the lungs (d), the site of gas-exchange. Oxygenated blood in the pulmonary veins (e) flows to the left heart (f) where it is pumped via the aorta (g) to the systemic tissues. This arrangement places all relevant measurements together and contextulized, to allow rapid understanding and diagnosis. This organization also highlights important concepts such as left heart preload, afterload and cardiac output. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Figure 3</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Display Metaphors</head><p>The display conveys the look of a 3-D pipe and is a geometric graphic metaphor for a blood vessel. Vertical movement of each part of the pipe represents a change in blood pressure. In the cardiovascular system, blood pressure is often used as a surrogate for a patient's volume status. As the blood pressure increases for a portion of the cardiovascular system, the corresponding object becomes larger by increasing in the vertical direction. Thus, the objects' movement provides a dual notion of the patient's pressure and volume status. In addition, abnormal changes in pressures can have clinical meaning. For example, abnormally high LAP (or preload) could mean that the left heart is not functioning optimally. The outline of the pipe represents normal pressure for each cardiovascular object. The object's size in relation to the reference pipe conveys whether blood pressure is normal, high or low with respect to a standard physiology.</p><p>Vascular tone in the pulmonary and systemic cardiovascular systems is shown as circles and represented as a cross-section of the pipe. When resistance is high, the vessels are constricted and the circle is filled. When resistance is low, the vessels are dilated and the circle is expanded. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Figure 4)</ref> The left heart is responsible for delivering blood to the vital organs and the tissues represented simply as a sphere. Its visual dominance is purposely stated due to the severe consequences of heart failure. The diameter of the sphere is proportional to the stroke volume. When stroke volume is low (poor contractility), then the heart object becomes small, and a large heart object represents a large volume of blood ejected during each heartbeat. Again, a gray circle around the object reference frame indicates the standard physiology. Animated "beating" of the sphere indicates heart rate. Furthermore, if the heart is not receiving adequate oxygen (myocardial ischemia, computed by ST segment analysis of the ECG), then it changes shape drastically in order to elicit prompt attention. <ref type="figure">(Figure 5</ref>) An object for the right heart is intentionally missing because sensors that distinguish between left and right cardiac output continuously do not exist.</p><p>Finally, the color of the LAP, left heart, and MAP objects is proportional to SaO2. Brain and vital organ damage rapidly ensues if the patient has even short durations of arterial blood desaturation. If the arterial blood is well oxygenated (SaO2 &gt; 93%), then the objects' color will be bright red. As arterial blood begins to desaturate, when the patient has no ventilation for example, the color rapidly changes from red to purple (87% &gt; SaO2 &gt; 93%) to blue (SaO2 &lt; 87%). ( <ref type="figure">Figure 6)</ref> In addition, the emergent shapes invoke a diagnosis by the clinician because the objects look similar to the way an anesthesiologist envisions them. For example, during hypervolemia, blood pressure, systemic vascular  resistance, cardiac output falls which shows up as smaller objects narrowed down like a nozzle with SVR increased to compensate for hypotension. The hypovolemic patient is referred to as a dry patient and the resultant graphic shows an image that looks dry or like an empty pipe. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Figure 7</ref>)</p><p>These emergent features significantly supported naturalistic decision-making by providing patterns that are readily learned and applied to rapid diagnosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Iterative Design Evaluation</head><p>Each design iteration was evaluated using a 4-step usability testing protocol. This shows how design changes impact the intuitiveness (ability to recognize the general organizational aspects, the ability to easily map specific data to the general organization), and usability (ability to recognize appropriate patterns). By maximizing the ease of use we anticipate that acceptance of the display will be greater.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1)</head><p>Intuitiveness -Are the visual objects in the designed metaphor easily recognizable? -Do the data clearly associate with the information to be presented by the designed elements in the metaphor? 2) Usability -Is the metaphor effective for visualizing the pertinent patterns of information? Changes in design are made by using the evaluation protocol for each design iteration. The results direct which portions of the design need refinement. The protocol is presented as static images on paper or on a computer.</p><p>To assess the effect of changes in design on intuitiveness and the confusion matrices for the original and the new designs are compared. An improvement in intuitiveness, for example, should show in a reliable increase in correct judgments about the anatomical features and the physiologic structures in the display.</p><p>Original Design Modified Design Anatomical 57% 62% Measurement 48% 85% Diagnosis 61% 67%</p><p>A simple approach to obtain an impression about the participants' performance is to calculate the percentage of correct answers. <ref type="table">(Table 1</ref>) Calculating the percentages does not correct for chance level performance; however, such an analysis is appropriate for evaluating the design using experts, as the possibility of chance performance is less likely.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Future Work</head><p>We are planning on proving the efficacy of the cardiovascular display by creating a realistic surgical environment using the METI simulator. We will be using a between subject test protocol that will test detection time and situation awareness with subjects using the traditional display only or using the traditional with the new cardiovascular display.  <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. Usability Testing Results</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. Cardiovascular Display</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Resistance States</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Hypovolemia</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">M: To Err is Human Building a Safer Health System. Institute of Medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Corrigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Donaldson</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>National Academy Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Errors, incidents and accidents in anaesthesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Runiciman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sellen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anaesth Int. Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="506" to="519" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anesthetic mishaps: breaking the chain of accident evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gaba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maxwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Deanda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anesthesiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="670" to="676" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Human</forename><surname>Reason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Error</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Cambridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Discriminative display support for process operators, Human detection and diagnosis of system failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goodstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Rasmussen, J Rouse WB</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="482" />
			<pubPlace>New York Plenum</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supporting operator problem solving through ecological interface design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vicente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cristoffersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pereklita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transaction on Systems, Mass and Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5529" to="5574" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer-aided fighter pilots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Rouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Geddes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Spectrum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supporting operator problem solving through ecological interface design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vicente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Christoffersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pereklita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transaction on Systems, Man and Cybernetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Engineering Data Compendium: Human Perception and Performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Boff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lincoln</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Wright-Patterson AFB, Harry G. Armstrong Medical Research Laboratory</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tufte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Visual Display of Quantitative Information</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Connecticut</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Graphics Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graphical Displays: Implications for Divided Attention, Focused Attention, and Problem Solving Human Factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Flach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="533" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Graphics; Innovative Solutions in Contemporary Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wildbur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Burke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Thames and Hudson</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preattentive processing in vision</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Triesman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Vision, Graphics and Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
