<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Shape Of Shakespeare: Visualizing Text Using Implicit Surfaces</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Randall</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rohrer</surname></persName>
							<email>rohrer@seas.gwu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of EECS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The George Washington University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of EECS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The George Washington University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20052</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>DC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ebert</surname></persName>
							<email>ebert@cs.umbc.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland Baltimore County CSEE</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">CSEE Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland Baltimore County</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1000 Hilltop Circle</addrLine>
									<postCode>21250</postCode>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sibert</surname></persName>
							<email>sibert@seas.gwu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of EECS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The George Washington University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of EECS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The George Washington University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20052</postCode>
									<settlement>Washington</settlement>
									<region>DC</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Shape Of Shakespeare: Visualizing Text Using Implicit Surfaces</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T18:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>information visualization</term>
					<term>text visualization</term>
					<term>procedural visualization</term>
					<term>implicit surface modeling</term>
					<term>blobby models</term>
					<term>document clustering</term>
					<term>information retrieval</term>
					<term>graphics</term>
					<term>user interfaces</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Information visualization focuses on the use of visual means for exploring non-visual information. While free-form text is a rich, common source of information, visualization of text is a challenging problem since text is inherently non-spatial. This paper explores the use of implicit surface models for visualizing text. We describe several techniques for text visualization that aid in understanding document content and document relationships. A simple method is defined for mapping document content to shape. By comparing the shapes of multiple documents, global content similarities and differences may be noted. In addition, we describe a visual clustering method in which documents are arranged in 3D based upon similarity scoring. Documents deemed closely related blend together as a single connected shape. Hence, a document corpus becomes a collection of shapes that reflect inter-document relationships. These techniques provide methods to visualize individual documents as well as corpus meta-data. We then combine the two techniques to produce transparent clusters enclosing individual document shapes. This provides a way to visualize both local and global contextual information. Finally, we elaborate on several potential applications of these methods.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Information visualization provides a tool for exploring and understanding information. While some information is inherently spatial (e.g. atmospheric temperature samples), much is not. Visualizing the non-visual requires mapping the abstract to the physical. Perhaps, the most common and widely-used form of abstract information is free-form text. From the earliest days of human writing, through the popular plays of Shakespeare, to the current Information Age, freeform text is integral to human communication. Text is among the richest and largest sources of information consumed, produced, and analyzed by humans. Hence, text is a prime potential source for applying visualization techniques. Text visualization uses visual metaphors for analyzing and understanding content and relationships in text documents. For example, document or corpus content might be mapped to shape, and inter-document relationships might be represented as a network graph. By specifying and controlling a useful visual mapping, text visualization can be used to better understand document content and relationships.</p><p>In this paper, we describe several new techniques for text visualization. First, we define a simple method for mapping document content to shape. By comparing the shapes of multiple documents, global content similarities and differences may be noted. In addition, we describe a visual clustering method in which documents are arranged in 3D based upon similarity scoring. Documents deemed closely related blend together as a single concept shape. Hence, a document corpus becomes a collection of concept shapes. These techniques provide methods to visualize individual documents as well as corpus meta-data. We then combine the two techniques to produce transparent clusters enclosing individual document shapes. This provides a way to visualize both local and global contextual information ("focus+context"). In addition to describing these visualization techniques, we briefly discuss several applications that seem useful for these methods.</p><p>Our visualization methods use underlying implicit surface models to generate flexible, procedural shapes. We believe that procedurallygenerated shapes pose an interesting and useful alternative for representing abstract spaces such as text. By procedural modeling, we mean techniques that use algorithms and code segments to dynamically generate, abstract, and encode model detail <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. Such approaches provide a flexible, dynamic framework in which a small set of parameters may be used to control the generation of detailed models. The domain of text visualization entails a very large multidimensional space. Appropriate selection of a small set of representative parameters of this large space can be used to procedurally control the dynamic generation of very complex, detailed models and shapes without an unwieldy, many-to-many parameter mapping. In addition, since visualizing text requires mapping the abstract to the physical, procedural modeling provides a nice interface for provid-ing this layer of abstraction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Text Visualization</head><p>Even though text-based information is ubiquitous, a limited number of text visualization approaches have proven useful. Problems stem from mapping a non-spatial entity into an artificial physical space. Meaningful mappings often are domain and application dependent. To be useful, text visualization must provide superior ways for humans to analyze and understand large document sets. As corpus size grows, visual clutter produced by visualization often confuse and obscure meaning. Such general issues make effective text visualization difficult but intriguing. Given the large, rich abundance of textbased information, finding effective visualization methods is important.</p><p>Several text visualization systems are particularly interesting. Themescapes presents corpus themes in the form of geographic terrain or mountains (literally, a landscape of themes) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Text documents are analyzed to produce a theme summary that is mapped to peaks and valleys of a 3D terrain. The DEPICT system visualizes text documents using underlying context vectors and Kohonen Self Organizing Maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>. It uses neural networks for learning context of word usage and how regions of high-dimensional space map into projected 2D regions. Visually, the clustered document space is represented as a 2D grid of circular nodes with color and size used to show document properties. Acquaintance/Parentage uses n-gram analysis for language-independent categorization of text documents and arranges them as a 2D proximity graph to show document relationships <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. Stereo Field Analyzer (SFA) has been used to show a clustered document space as a 3D scatterplot using stereo <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The VIBE system also visualizes document similarities by arranging nodes in measured proximity to fixed spatial reference points <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. MIT's Galaxies of News provides a rich 3D information space in which to navigate, explore, and find news items within a thematically clustered space <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>These examples of text visualization use shape and spatial arrangement for depicting document content and relationships. Corpus analysis yields pertinent information that is organized and presented as visual and spatial representations. Interaction with the resulting visualizations allow further exploration and understanding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Implicit Surface Modeling</head><p>Implicit surface modeling is a flexible, procedural approach to shape generation. It uses an underlying density field to represent volumetric information that can be modeled as a collection of procedurallygenerated density field sources. Using procedural control, this density field can be evaluated to produce amorphous, generalized shapes that exhibit interesting animation and blending effects. These "organic" shapes may be viewed volumetrically (volume rendering) or by finding an iso-surface of interest. Implicit surface models are also known as blobby models, metaballs, or soft objects. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref> for further details. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows several examples of shapes produced by implicit surface models. Any information that can be mapped to a density field may be modeled using these techniques. A nice property of these models is that the underlying source fields may be simply summed and blended without detailed knowl-edge of the processes that generated them. In this way, very desperate entities can be combined using a common density field model. (If desired, complex warps, blends, and constructive solid modeling operations can also be used when combining field sources.) <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>: Shapes produced by implicit surface models</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">BLOBBY TEXT VISUALIZATION</head><p>Using ideas from text visualization and implicit surface modeling, we have developed several technique for visualizing text by mapping document content and relationships to blobby models. We sometimes refer to the resulting visualizations as blobby text. Implicit surface models are attractive since they use a generalized, procedurally-generated 3D density field to represent shape. Shape modeling is achieved by controlling the generation and evaluation of these density fields. To visualize text, we map text document and corpus characteristics to a density field representation. From this density field, we can generate generalized shapes.</p><p>Humans are quite adept at perceptual visual cues and recognizing subtle shape differences. In fact, it has been shown that humans can distinguish shape during the pre-attentive psychophysical process <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. (Humans are pre-wired for understanding and visualizing shape. Visualization is based upon harnessing these skills of shape perception.) We hope to take full advantage of these perceptual skills by generating shapes in a dynamic manner. Hence, we chose to use implicit surface modeling for shape generation. While mapping selected characteristics of text documents to simple density field representations may seem arbitrary and simple, its simplicity provides for flexible shape generation. Since text is abstract and inherently non-spatial, a simple arbitrary spatial mapping results in no inherent loss of meaning. However, it is incumbent upon the visualization designer to provide, reveal, or reinforce some meaning.</p><p>In the following sections, we describe two visualization methods that use implicit surfaces for representing text. These blobby text methods are used to visualize document content and document relationships. We then combine the two techniques to visualize both local and global contextual information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Document Visualization</head><p>Since text documents have no inherent spatial properties, visualizing the content of documents requires a spatial mapping. We have defined a simple mapping in which significant word occurrences in a document correspond to a representative 3D shape. By comparing the shapes of multiple documents, a high-level overview of document similarities and differences may be noted. Resulting document shapes may be further explored and compared by direct manipulation and "spread-sheet" interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, researchers report using superquadric ellipsoid surfaces for mapping multivariate data to representative glyphs and shapes. They control shape generation by interpolation. Our approach is related in concept. However, we use implicit surfaces for shape generation which provides a more flexible, procedural approach using volumetric density fields.</p><p>Like others, we use an underlying vector-space model to represent document content. Our document vectors summarize word occurrence in documents and how these words relate to other documents in the corpus. While n-gram analysis has the advantage of languageindependence, we feel there are many advantages of using linguistic-based analysis (i.e. semantic meaning). Since we wish to apply our document model to applications in information retrieval, word "chunking", rather than pattern "chunking", seems more useful and meaningful. In analyzing document content, we ignore "stopwords" that provide little contextual meaning and do not currently use word stemming. In fact, we view our document analysis process as minimal and choose to concentrate on the visualization aspects. (A better document analysis engine could easily be substituted.) Given a corpus, we generate representative document vectors for each document as well as an overall corpus vector. The dimensionality of this vector space corresponds to the total number of unique words occurring in the entire text corpus. (Hence, it is a very high dimensional space that is commonly greater than 1000 dimensions.) Each document vector is specified in terms and dimensionality of the overall corpus vector. The document vectors are normalized with respect to the corpus vector to provide a correlation with the overall corpus content. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows an example document vector of N dimensions. (This document has 202 occurrences of the word "hamlet" and 0 occurrences of "java".)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2: Document vector</head><p>After generating document vectors for the entire corpus, we perform a shape mapping for each document. One of the common problems in visualization is how to project meaningful information from highdimensional space into a manageable, meaningful display space (i.e. 2, 3, or perhaps as many as 7 dimensions). Techniques like multi-dimensional scaling, metric scaling, and factor analysis can be used to help guide this projection. In our current system, we simply sort our document vectors in descending order of word occurrence. We se-lect the top N occurring words in the corpus and use this as the basis for sorting document vectors. (Here, for example, statistical analysis could be applied to determine the N most influential or "best" occurring words as opposed to the N "most" occurring words.) At this point, the sorted document vectors reflect the relationship and weighting of how each dimension contributes to the overall corpus content. The chosen N dimensions are then mapped to N equally spaced directions in 3-space emanating from the origin of a sphere <ref type="figure">(Figure 3a</ref>). (The top N document dimensions correspond to these N directions in 3D.) In practice, we typically choose 14 principal directions in 3D: the 6 main orthogonal 3D directions (+X, -X, +Y, -Y, +Z, -Z axis) and also the 8 directions that bisect each of the main axis quadrants. While any value of N may be chosen, as N grows, less spacing occurs between these principal directions. We define the magnitude of the N spherical direction vectors to be linearly proportional to the document's normalized word count for the corresponding dimension. At the end of each one of these N direction vectors, we place a spherical source field function which partially defines an implicit surface model <ref type="figure">(Figure 3b</ref>). The N source fields populated about the sphere define a 3D density field. We treat this procedurally defined density field as an implicit surface model which can visualized using standard methods for implicit surface rendering. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> shows a possible shape generated by evaluating the implicit surface model of <ref type="figure">Figure 3b</ref>. (Note that we show our examples in 2D for clarity but in practice use 3D.) Experience and intuition dictate that 14 directions may be nearing the upper limit of practicality for arrangement of spherical source fields (depending on the extent of the arrangement space). However, using greater than 14 principal directions may be quite possible using alternatively shaped density functions (i.e. skeletal bones). Currently, we use identically sized spherical source functions at the end of every vector. We could vary the radius of these source functions as well. In ordering the principal directions, we currently use a fixed layout algorithm that attempts to spread high frequency words evenly about the sphere. However, one could use an alternative layout algorithms that attempt to use words semantics to guide this arrangement.</p><p>This process of mapping document vectors to spherically arranged density field sources is repeated for each document of interest in the corpus. Evaluating each document's 3D density field results in 3D blobby shapes that are based upon the content of the underlying document. Each shape uses the same scale and modeling space and is based on the same N-dimensional vector space model. For example, an upward bulge in the "hamlet" direction on one shape corresponds to the same upward "hamlet" direction on other shapes.</p><p>In our implementation, we choose to use a blobby potential field function derived by Blanc and Schlick that is flexible, efficient, and has fixed decay distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. (This function generate densities ranging from 1.0 at its center to 0.0 at its boundary of influence.) To visualize, we evaluate the overall density field and compute an isosurface (0.5 iso-surface) using Jules Bloomenthal's polygonization method <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. We currently render the iso-surface polygons using VRML and display within VRML-enabled web browsers. Navigation and interaction with the resulting visualization is primarily performed through browser-supplied functionality. (This typically includes direct manipulation as well as common metaphors such as "fly-through" and "go-to".) In addition, VRML provides a broad set of sensor capabilities that allow one to define and add more interesting navigation and interaction aids. <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> shows a single text document visualized as blobby text. The underlying document is a paper titled "Web-based Information Visualization". Consistent with the title, the most frequently occurring words are "web", "visualization", and "information". These terms correspond to the three main, extruding bulges that appear on the top, left, and right portions of the shape. We may optionally choose to display the corresponding terms at each end of the direction vectors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 5: Blobby text document ("Web-based Information Visualization")</head><p>Extending this approach to a set of documents, we can compare document content by comparing a resulting set of shapes. To better inspect and compare multiple shapes, we use a spread-sheet style interaction method in which manipulating one shape (document) triggers corresponding changes (i.e. transformations) in all other shapes <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. That is, if one selects a single document shape and rotates it using standard browser interaction tools, all other documents rotate in a corresponding, synchronized manner. This insures that all shapes maintain a consistent information space. (Spread-sheet interaction is currently implemented using VRML sensors and routes.) <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 6 and 7</ref> show examples of multiple text documents represented as a collection of blobby text shapes. Documents with similar content will tend to have generally similar shape. Documents with bulges or troughs in the same direction exhibit common word usage. (For example, in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">figure 6</ref>, the shapes in the upper left corner and upper right corner, each have a protruding bulge to the right which corresponds to the word "information".) While precise, detailed analysis may not be possible with this method, we see this visualization approach as a broad overview for comparing document content. We envision families of shapes that correspond to families of document themes. Such families may have overall similar shape but small local differences. In addition, these initial views might be used to initiate visual queries or to link to underlying or related information.</p><p>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Corpus Visualization</head><p>A second text visualization method has been developed for understanding and visualizing an entire corpus and associated meta-data such as inter-document relationships. This technique employs a common document clustering algorithm and uses implicit surfaces to represent clusters of documents deemed to be similar. Our approach is similar in concept to the blobby clustering method reported by Gross and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. We use blobby clustering as a visual technique for representing clusters (relationships and hierarchies) of related documents. Spatial proximity of documents is used to show similarities. Documents deemed to be very closely related are shown as a cluster or connected shape that we call a concept shape. Underlying implicit surface models automatically blend related documents as connected components.</p><p>We use the same document vectors described in section 3.1 to represent a collection of text documents. A document similarity matrix is computed by finding the dot-product between each pair of corresponding document vectors. This normalized similarity score provides a scalar value that represents how closely related each document is to the others. This completely connected relationship graph of documents is mapped to a corresponding mass-spring model in which particle locations correspond to document locations. Initially, the particles (documents) are randomly distributed throughout a specified arrangement region. A spring, representing a document relationship, is placed between each document pair. We use the pair's similarity score as a guide to establish the physical properties of the spring and make the spring rest length proportional to the similarity score. Documents deemed to be very similar will have spring properties that attempt to attract each other while springs of dissimilar documents will attempt to repel each other. Using this physically-based model with random initial mass locations, we allow the physical simulation to run to completion or to a sufficiently stable configuration. During this process, documents are pushed and pulled into a relative configuration that satisfies the physical properties of the mass-spring model. The final particle locations of the simulation correspond to document locations with distance being inversely proportional to similarity score. This physically-based clustering method is a common approach used by others. An incremental method that is suitable for interactive drawing is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Once the physical simulation moves documents into a meaningful arrangement, each document's position is treated as a location of a point source field of an implicit surface model. A corpus of N documents will have N source fields representing its corresponding blobby model. Using standard implicit surface rendering, an iso-surface is found within the global density field defined by the collection of N field sources. A natural visual clustering of closely related documents is automatically created by the blobby model. Documents that are closely related, and hence closely located, are blended together as a single connected component of the implicit surface model. We often think of these connected components as concept shapes, concepts or themes shared by related documents. An entire corpus becomes a collection of concepts represented with these connected components. <ref type="figure">Figures 8 and 9</ref> show examples of using this blobby clustering technique to visualize document relationships in two different corpuses. In each example, the concept clusters are easily visible. However, 3D interaction may be needed for full examination. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 10</ref> shows a close-up view of <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>. The three documents clustered together in the foreground of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 10</ref> all discuss issues of nuclear energy. This automatic blobby clustering approach highlights documents with similar concepts and reduces the visual clutter of individual document glyphs. Another advantage is that humans are much more adept at seeing continuous connected components as opposed to evaluating distance relationships between disconnected objects. This method provides a global view of a corpus and associated meta-data. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Focus + Context</head><p>Local and global context is very important in producing effective visualizations. We need to see and understand local detail (focus) in context of global information. This desired effect is known as "fo-cus+context". Distortion viewing (i.e. fish-eye lens) is a popular ap-proach to addressing this issue <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. We addresses it by combining our reported techniques of document and corpus visualization (section 3.1 and 3.2) to produce semi-transparent clusters enclosing individual document shapes. The clustered concept shapes produced in corpus visualization are rendered as semi-transparent shells surrounding individual documents. The shapes of the individual documents within each cluster are based on their relative content using the shape-generating method described in section 3.1. <ref type="figure">Figure 11</ref> shows a clustered collection of documents shown with semi-transparent cluster shells and individual document shapes. <ref type="figure">(Figure 12</ref> is a zoomed view of <ref type="figure">Figure 11</ref>.) <ref type="figure">Figure 13</ref> shows a detailed example of 3 documents. The two that are clustered together are Shakespeare's plays Richard II and Richard III while the solitary document within its own cluster is a document on information visualization (two vastly different concepts from vastly different ages). By providing both semi-transparent cluster shells as well as individual document shapes based on content, we achieve both local and global context within the entire information space.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">APPLICATIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>We view these early experiments in blobby text visualization as very promising and are exploring numerous applications for these methods. The visualization components that we describe can be used as a visual interface for underlying information retrieval engines as well as for visualizing the results of such systems. Queries might be constructed and executed simply by marking, selecting, or brushing parts of a blobby document surface. Results of such queries might be visually highlighted across the corpus by using color, shape, or texture changes in the surface. As information volumes grow, data mining tools will likely need to rely on visualization for supplying global context and will require tighter coupling between query en-gines, knowledge bases, and visualization. We think that visualization through procedural, implicit surfaces may be suitable and attractive for such applications. While clustering and multi-dimensional scaling are often used to help visualize very large information spaces, visualization techniques themselves may be used to help explore and understand new clustering and scaling algorithms.</p><p>Because implicit surface models exhibit interesting and useful animation effects such as blending and deformation, they seem conducive for visualizing time-varying information. In fact, it would be interesting to visualize how a text corpus and its relationships change over time. Since we are currently using VRML for rendering, we can also embed appropriate web hyperlinks throughout our blobby surfaces which can serve as a very simple but useful information retrieval mechanism. (In fact, we currently use a limited number of hyperlinks in our current implementation to link to underlying documents.)</p><p>While blobby text visualization poses some interesting possibilities, there are some important questions left to be explored. To date, we have not performed a formal evaluation or user study to determine how meaningful and useful these techniques are. Blobby text needs to be compared with competing analysis and visualization techniques to determine its applicability, utility, and scalability. As we refine and improve our visualization and document analysis components, we will perform a much more rigorous evaluation of these techniques.</p><p>Perhaps, the most interesting direction for future work is to compute a hierarchy of document clusters (concept shapes) that map to multiple semantic layers of the information space. In this approach, multi-resolution visual components correspond to multi-resolution semantic concepts. By changing the granularity of clustering or changing the iso-surfaces (concepts) computed, a nested, multi-level, hierarchy of related concepts could be created. From the highestlevel view, the overall corpus would be seen with its main concept shapes. As one dives in closer to specific clusters, more detailed views of sub-clusters (sub-concepts) would be revealed. An appropriate viewing scheme could be devised such that one always sees two levels deep into the nested hierarchy while simultaneously seeing the current level ( <ref type="figure">Figure 14</ref>). If each of these nested shape layers correspond to nested semantic information layers, information query tools could adapt to appropriate levels of information detail at each level. A hierarchical, multi-resolution clustering approach such as this would be very useful for providing "focus + context".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 14: Nested cluster hierarchy</head><p>While iso-surface evaluation may still be appropriate with these methods, volumetric visualization of hierarchical concept layers may be a better approach. In visualizing, hierarchical layered structures, combinations of transparency, texture, and multiple iso-surfaces may be appropriate. Techniques for effective display of such layered volumetric information is addressed by Interrante <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. We plan to further expand our current work using these ideas and exploring these applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have explored the use of implicit surface models for visualizing text. The power and flexibility of these underlying procedural models provides strong support for visualizing abstract, non-spatial information such as text. Using these models, we have developed techniques for visualizing the content of individual documents and for visualizing corpus meta-data. To visualize document content, we devised a simple, but representative, mapping from content to shape. By comparing the shapes of multiple documents, overall content similarities and differences may be noted. In addition, we developed a visual clustering method in which documents are arranged in 3D based upon similarity scoring. Documents deemed closely related blend together as single concept shapes that are easily observed. This provides a way of visualizing an entire corpus and its meta-data relationships. By combining these methods, a third visualization technique is produced that provides both local and global context of documents within a corpus. We are continuing to explore these techniques for text visualization, will expand their application to information retrieval and data mining, and will perform a rigorous evaluation of these techniques. While visualizing text (visualizing the non-visual) remains a challenging problem, new approaches like blobby text appear promising for providing insight and better understanding of large text corpuses. To this end, the "shape" of Shakespeare may be significant.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 3 :Figure 4 :</head><label>34</label><figDesc>a) N principal directions b) implicit surface model with N source fields Implicit surface generation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Multiple documents shown as blobby text</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>"Spreadsheet" of blobby text documents</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 8 :Figure 9 :</head><label>89</label><figDesc>Clustered documents (blobby clusters) Clustered documents (blobby clusters or concept shapes)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Close-up view of clustered documents inFigure 9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 11 :Figure 12 :Figure 13 :</head><label>111213</label><figDesc>Semi-transparent clusters enclosing document shapes Zoomed view of figure 11 clusters Information visualization cluster and Shakespeare cluster (Richard II, Richard III)</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>Thanks to Jules Bloomenthal for making his implicit surface polygonizer available for all.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extended Field Functions for Soft Objects</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Carole</forename><surname>Blanc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><surname>Schlick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Implicit Surfaces `95, (Ed.) B.Wyvill and M.P. Gascuel</title>
		<meeting>Implicit Surfaces `95, (Ed.) B.Wyvill and M.P. Gascuel</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="32" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Generalization of Algebraic Surface Drawing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Blinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Implicit Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chandrajit</forename><surname>Bajaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jim</forename><surname>Blinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marie-Paule</forename><surname>Cani-Gascuel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alyn</forename><surname>Rockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brian</forename><surname>Wyvill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Geoff</forename><surname>Wyvill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1- 55860-233-X</idno>
		<editor>Jules Bloomenthal</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>San Francisco, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Implicit Surface Polygonizer</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jules</forename><surname>Bloomenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Graphics Gems IV</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chestnut Hill, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="349" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extending Distortion Viewing from 2D to 3D</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sheelagh</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Carpendale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cowperthwaite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">David</forename><surname>Fracchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Spreadsheet Approach to Information Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ed</forename><surname>Huai-Hsin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chi</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Phillip</forename><surname>Barry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Riedl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><surname>Konstan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Information Visualization Symposium &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>Information Visualization Symposium &apos;96<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drawing Graphs to Convey Proximity: An Incremental Arrangement Method</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gauging Similarity with n-Grams: Language-Independent Categorization of Text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marc</forename><surname>Damashek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">267</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="843" to="848" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-02-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic Shape Interpolation for Glyph-based Information Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kukla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amen</forename><surname>Zwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ian</forename><surname>Soboroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Aaron</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Late Breaking Hot Topics Proceedings, IEEE Visualization Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="59" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Computer Science and Engineering Handbook</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Jr. Allen Tucker</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Advanced Geometric Modeling</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimally-immersive Interactive Volumetric Information Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amen</forename><surname>Zwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ethan</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Aaron</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Information Visualization Symposium &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>Information Visualization Symposium &apos;96<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="67" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">S K</forename><surname>Ebert ; F</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Musgrave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Peachey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Perlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Worley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>0-12- 228760-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Texturing and Modeling: A Procedural Approach</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Information on a Sphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sprenger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Finger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Information Visualization Symposium &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>Information Visualization Symposium &apos;97<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illustrating Surface Shape in Volume Data via Principle Direction-Driven 3D Line Integral Convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Victoria</forename><surname>Interrante</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Proceedings, Annual Conference Series 1997, ACM SIGGRAPH</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Los Angeles, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="116" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings of SIGGRAPH 97</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illustrating Transparent Surfaces with Curvature-Directed Strokes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Victoria</forename><surname>Interrante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Henry</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Pizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization 96</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 96<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="218" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Self-Organizing Maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kohonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">To See or Not to See --Is That the Query?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Korfhage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 14th Annual ACM SIGIR Conference</title>
		<meeting>14th Annual ACM SIGIR Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="141" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Object Modelling by Distribution Functions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nishimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hirai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kawai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kawata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shirakara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Omura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electronics Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="718" to="725" />
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of Document Collection: the VIBE System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Olsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Korfhage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sochats</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Spring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Processing &amp; Management</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Christou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bruce</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cumming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Hawken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Zisserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Analysis of 3D Shape: Psychophysical principles and neural mechanisms</title>
		<editor>Glyn W. Humphreys</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Blackwell</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Understanding Vision</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Earl</forename><surname>Rennison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Galaxies of News: An Approach to Visualizing and Understanding Expansive News Landscapes</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Marina Del Ray, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings of UIST 94</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DEPICT: Documents Evaluated as Pictures, Visualizing Information Using Context Vectors and Self Organizing Maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marc</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rushall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ilgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Information Visualization Symposium &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>Information Visualization Symposium &apos;96<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="107" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><surname>Shakespeare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1600</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Hamlet, Act II, Scene ii</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing the Non-Visual: Spatial analysis and interaction with information from text documents</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pennock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lantrip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pottier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Crow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Information Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>Information Visualization &apos;95<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Animating Soft Objects</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wyvill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mcpheeters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wyvill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="242" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data Structures for Soft Objects</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wyvill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mcpheeters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wyvill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="234" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
