<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Choosing Effective Colours for Data Visualization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Healey</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of British Columbia</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Choosing Effective Colours for Data Visualization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>H.5.2 [Information Interfaces and Presentation]: User Interfaces -ergonomics</term>
					<term>screen design (graphics</term>
					<term>colour); I.3.6 [Computer Graphics]: Methodology and Techniques -ergonomics</term>
					<term>interaction techniques</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>In this paper we describe a technique for choosing multiple colours for use during data visualization. Our goal is a systematic method for maximizing the total number of colours available for use, while still allowing an observer to rapidly and accurately search a display for any one of the given colours. Previous research suggests that we need to consider three separate effects during colour selection: colour distance, linear separation, and colour category. We describe a simple method for measuring and controlling all of these effects. Our method was tested by performing a set of target identification studies; we analysed the ability of thirty-eight observers to find a colour target in displays that contained differently coloured background elements. Results showed our method can be used to select a group of colours that will provide good differentiation between data elements during data visualization.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Scientific visualization in computer graphics is a rapidly expanding area of research. This is due in large part to the dramatic increase in both the size and the number of datasets that need to be visualized <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. To date, many application-specific tools have been built to help analyse individual datasets. Much less work has focused on developing guidelines for the design of visualization techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Our work is intended to address one aspect of this more general question.</p><p>A typical method of visualizing a dataset involves mapping data attributes to visual features (e.g., shape, size, spatial location, and orientation). Colour is an important and frequently-used feature. Examples include colour temperature gradients on maps and charts, colour-coded vector fields in flow visualization, or colour icons displayed by real-time simulation systems.</p><p>If we use colour to represent our data, an important question to ask is: "How can we choose effective colours that provide good differentiation between data elements during the visualization task?" We address this problem by trying to answer three related questions:</p><p>How can we allow rapid and accurate identification of individual data elements through the use of colour?</p><p>What factors determine whether a "target" element's colour will make it easy to find, relative to differently coloured "nontarget" elements? How many colours can we display at once, while still allowing for rapid and accurate target identification?</p><p>Previous work has addressed the issue of choosing colours for certain types of data visualization. For example, Ware and Beatty describe a simple colour visualization technique for displaying correlation in a five-dimensional dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. Research on the design of military systems sometimes quotes anecdotal evidence that suggests ": : : the general guideline for computer-generated images is no more than five to seven colours at a time: : : " <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, although they offer no explanation for why this might be the case. Robertson, Ware, Rheingans and Tebbs, and Levkowitz and Herman discuss various methods for building effective colour gamuts and colourmaps <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. Recent work at the IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center has focused on a rule-based visualization tool that considers how a user perceives visual features like hue, luminance, height, and so on <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>.</p><p>None of these techniques were designed to investigate the rapid and accurate identification of individual data elements based on colour. Also, since the colour gamut and colourmap work uses continuous colour scales to encode information, they do not address the question of how many colours we can effectively display at once, while still providing good differentiation between individual data elements.</p><p>An intuitive first step to gaining more control over colour would be to use a perceptual colour model like CIE LUV, CIE Lab, or Munsell <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Unfortunately, fixing the colour distance in a perceptual colour model to a constant value does not guarantee that each colour will be equally easy to detect. Other factors can affect how groups of coloured elements interact with one another.</p><p>Our technique does, in fact, use the CIE LUV colour model to provide control over colour distance and isoluminance. We also exploit two specific results related to colour target detection: linear separation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1]</ref> and colour category <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. These effects are controlled to allow for the rapid and accurate identification of colour targets. Target identification is a necessary first step towards performing other types of exploratory data analysis. If we can rapidly and accurately differentiate elements based on their colour, we can apply our results to other important visualization techniques like detection of data boundaries, the tracking of data regions in real-time, and enumeration tasks like counting and estimation <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">BACKGROUND</head><p>Before we describe our technique in detail, we provide a brief overview of the CIE LUV colour model, as well as a description of the linear separation and colour category effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">CIE LUV</head><p>The CIE LUV colour model was proposed by the Commission Internationale de L'Èclairge (CIE) in 1976 <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Colours are specified using the three dimensions L (which encodes luminance), u , and v (which together encode chromaticity). CIE LUV provides two useful properties for controlling perceived colour difference.</p><p>First, colours with the same L are isoluminant. Second, Euclidean distance and perceived colour difference (specified in E units) can be interchanged, since the colour difference between two colour stimuli x and y is roughly:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">E xy = p L xy 2 + u xy 2 + v xy 2 (1)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Linear Separation</head><p>The linear separation effect was originally described by D'Zmura <ref type="bibr">[1991]</ref> . He was investigating how the human visual system finds a target colour in a sea of background non-target colours. D'Zmura ran experiments that asked observers to determine the presence or absence of an orange target. Two groups of differently coloured non-target elements were also present in each display (e.g., in one experiment half the non-targets in each display were coloured green and half were coloured red). Results showed that when the target could be separated by a straight line from its non-targets in colour space <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1</ref>, target T and non-targets A and C), the time required to determine the target's presence or absence was constant, and independent of the total number of elements being displayed. This suggests detection occurs in parallel in the low-level visual system. When the target was collinear with its non-targets ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, target T and non-targets A and B), the time required to identify the target was linearly proportional to the number of elements being displayed. Observers had to search serially through each display to determine whether the target was present or absent. colour model, notice that target T is equidistant from all three nontargets A, B, and C; in Case 1, target colour T is collinear with the non-target colours A and B; in Case 2, target T is linearly separable from its non-targets A and C Work by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Bauer [1996]</ref> provided a number of results that strengthen D'Zmura's hypothesis. First, he showed that perceptual colour models cannot be used to overcome linear separation. In his experiments the target-non-target distance was fixed to a constant value in CIE LUV <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1</ref>). In spite of this, the target required serial searching when it was collinear with its non-targets, but was significantly easier to detect when it was separable. Bauer replicated his initial findings in three additional colour regions: green, blue, and green-yellow. This suggests linear separation applies to colours from different parts of the visible colour domain. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Kawai [1995]</ref> reported results that suggest that the time required to identify a colour target depends in part on the named colour regions occupied by the target and its non-targets. If target identification depended only on the colour distance between a target and its nontargets, the time taken to detect presence or absence of the target should decrease uniformly as target-non-target distance increases. Kawai ran a set of experiments that showed this was not true. <ref type="bibr">Kawai</ref>   <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>: A target T and two non-targets A and B shown in a j;g slice from the OSA colour model; the boundaries of the blue, green, and purple colour regions are shown as thick lines; T and B occupy the same named colour region "blue", but A does not an isoluminant colour slice used during his experiments into named colour regions. His results showed that search times decreased dramatically whenever the non-target was moved outside the target's colour region. For example, finding a target coloured T in a set of non-targets coloured B was significantly more difficult than than finding T in a set of non-targets coloured A ( <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>). The targetnon-target distances TAand TBare equal; Kawai suggests the difference in performance is due to the fact that both T and B are located in the blue colour region, but A is not. Similar search time asymmetries for separate experiments testing green, purple, and red targets were also explained by a difference in colour regions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Colour Category</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">COLOUR SELECTION TECHNIQUE</head><p>Results discussed in the background section suggest that choosing effective colours for data visualization depends on at least three separate criteria: We began our investigation by controlling colour distance and linear separation, but not colour category. We proceeded under the assumption that the user might choose to search for any one of the available data elements at any given time. This is typical during exploratory data analysis; users will often change the focus of their investigation based on the data they see as the visualization unfolds. Our requirement meant that the colour selection technique had to allow for rapid and accurate identification of any of the elements being displayed.</p><p>We ran four studies to investigate the tradeoff between the number of colours displayed and the time required to determine the presence or absence of a target element. Each study displayed a different number of unique colours, which we identify using the names red, yellow-red, yellow, green-yellow, green, blue-green, blue, purpleblue, purple, and red-purple (or R, YR, Y, GY, G, BG, B, PB, P, and RP):</p><p>three-colour study: each display contained three different colours (i.e., one colour for the target and two for the nontargets) which we named R, GY, and PB five-colour study: each display contained five different colours: R, Y, GY, B, and P seven-colour study: each display contained seven different colours: R, Y, GY, G, BG, P, and RP nine-colour study: each display contained nine different colours: R, YR, Y, GY, G, BG, PB, P, and RP Every colour in a given study was tested as a target. For example, the three-colour study was run three times, first with an R element acting as a target (and GY and PB elements acting as non-targets), next with a GY target (and R and PB non-targets), and finally with a PB target (and R and GY non-targets). Faster search times for certain targets would have to be explained in terms of colour distance, linear separation, or colour category. Each of the four studies were themselves divided in the following manner: elements in each display were drawn as coloured squares, and were randomly located on an underlying 99grid that covered the entire viewing area of the monitor half of the displays were randomly chosen to contain an element that used the target colour; the other half did not one-third of the displays contained a total of 17 elements (one target and 16 non-targets if the target was present, or 17 nontargets if the target was absent); one-third of the displays contained a total of 33 elements; one-third of the displays contained a total of 49 elements Colours for each of the four studies were chosen such that the colour distance between pairs of colours and the linear separation for each colour were fixed to constant values. Our results showed that detection was rapid and accurate for all colours from both the three-colour and five-colour studies. Results from the seven-colour and nine-colour studies were mixed; some colours gave better performance than others. This difference was explained when we examined the colour regions occupied by each of the colours.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Method</head><p>We began the colour selection process by obtaining the chromaticities of our monitor's triads. We also measured the luminance of the monitor's maximum intensity red, green, and blue with a spot photometer. These values were needed to convert colours from CIE LUV into the monitor's RGB gamut.</p><p>We wanted to ensure that the colours we chose had the same perceived intensity. Previous research has suggested that random variation in intensity can interfere with an observer's ability to perform visualization tasks based on colour <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. In order to guarantee isoluminance, all the colours were chosen from a single u ; v -slice through the CIE LUV colour space at L = 6 7 : 1 . We wanted to maximize the number of available colours, while still maintaining control over colour distance and linear separability. To do this, we computed the boundary of the monitor's gamut in the L = 6 7 : 1 slice. We then found the largest circle inscribed within the gamut <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Figure 3a)</ref>.</p><p>Given the maximum inscribed circle, we chose colours that were equally spaced around its circumference. For example, during the five-colour study we chose colours at positions 14 , 86 , 158 , 230 , and 302 counterclockwise rotation from the x-axis <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Figure 3b)</ref>. This method ensured that neighbouring colours had a constant colour distance. It also ensured that any colour acting as a target had a constant linear separation from every other (non-target) colour. A similar technique was used to select colours for the threecolour, seven-colour, and nine-colour studies. This gave us the fol-  Thirty-eight users with normal or corrected acuity participated as observers during our studies. After ensuring they were not colour blind, each observer was asked to complete one or more target blocks. A target block consisted of 360 displays testing a single colour target from one of the four studies. A total of 66 target blocks were completed. We used a Macintosh computer with an 8-bit colour display to run our studies. Responses (either "target present" or "target absent") and the time to respond for each display an observer completed were recorded for later analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Results</head><p>Observers had very little difficulty identifying targets during the three-colour and five-colour studies. Graphs of mean response time across display size were relatively flat for every colour (Figures 4a and 4b; note that the y-axis ranges from 400 msec to 800 msec in these graphs). Mean response times ranged from 459 msec to 549 msec during the three-colour study, and from 508 msec to 661 msec during the five-colour study. Mean response error during both studies was approximately 2.5%. We concluded that users could accurately identify the target in all cases, and that the time required to do so was relatively independent of display size. This suggests that, even when using five different colours, the visual system can search for any one of the colours in parallel.</p><p>Target identification became significantly more difficult for certain colours during the seven-colour and nine-colour studies <ref type="figure">(Figures 4c and 4d</ref>; note that the y-axis ranges from 100 msec to 3500 msec in these graphs). Mean response error during the sevencolour study was still low, at approximately 3.3%. The P, Y, R, BG, and RP targets all exhibited relatively flat response time graphs. Mean response time for these elements ranged from 611 msec to 870 msec. The G and GY targets, however, gave response times typical of serial search. An increase in the number of elements being displayed brought on a corresponding increase in response time. The increase for target-absent displays (approximately 19 msec per additional element for GY, and 17 msec per element for G) was roughly twice that for target-present displays (7 msec and 8 msec  <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>: Response time graphs for the four studies, the graph on the left represents displays where the target was absent, while the graph on the right represents displays where the target was present: (a) response time as a function of display size (i.e., total number of elements shown in the display) for each target from the three-colour study; (b) response times for each target from the five-colour study; (c) response times for each target from the seven-colour study; (d) response times for each target from the nine-colour study per element for GY and G, respectively). Observers had to search through, on average, half the elements before they found the target in target-present displays. In target-absent displays, however, they had to search through all the elements to confirm that no target existed. This explains why per item search time increased roughly twice as fast for target-absent displays. A similar set of results was obtained during the nine-colour study. Overall mean response error increased to 8.1%; it was lowest for the P, Y, and PB targets (approximately 3.4%), and highest for the G, GY, and RP targets (approximately 14%). The P, Y, and PB targets displayed relatively flat response time graphs during target-present displays. The remaining targets showed some form of serial search. The effect was weakest for the R and YR targets, and strongest for the G and GY targets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Colour Category Integration</head><p>Results from our four studies showed that controlling colour distance and linear separation alone is not enough to guarantee consistently good (or consistently bad) target identification for every colour. Results from Kawai suggest that colour category can also have a strong effect on the amount of time required to identify a colour target. We decided to see whether colour category results could explain the asymmetric response times we observed during the seven-colour and nine-colour studies.</p><p>In order to do this, we needed a method of placing individual colours within a named colour region. We used a simple technique described by Healey and Enns <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. This technique places individual colours within user-named colour regions as follows:</p><p>Step 1:</p><p>Individual colours are mapped into the Munsell colour model. Colours are specified in the Munsell model using the three dimensions hue, chroma (which controls saturation), and value (which controls luminance) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>; the hue dimension is divided into ten regions that are identified using the ten names R, YR, Y, GY, G, BG, B, PB, P, and RP. A colour is assigned the name of its hue dimension in Munsell space.</p><p>Step 2:</p><p>The above technique is used to subdivide all or part of a colour space into named colour regions. We wanted to divide our maximum inscribed circle into named colour regions. Healey and Enns divided a similar circle at L = 7 1 : 6 (this corresponds closely to our circle from the L = 6 7 : 1 slice), as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref>.</p><p>Step 3:</p><p>Observers are asked to name representative colours from each colour region. This converts Munsell names into user-chosen names; it also provides a way of measuring how strongly a particular name represents a given colour region. Healey and Enns used the colour at the middle of each colour region in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> to represent the region. <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 1</ref> shows the names chosen for each of the ten representative colours. For example, 5.3% of the observers called the YR region's representative colour "red", 86.8% called it "orange", and 7.9% called it "brown".</p><p>Each of the colours from our four studies was assigned a name using the method described in Step 1 above; this also placed each colour within one of the ten named colour regions. The user-chosen colour names shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 1</ref>  As an example, consider the P and R regions, which have ranges:</p><p>purple magenta pink red P 86.9%</p><p>2.6% 5.2% R 26.3% 71.0%</p><p>Colours from P and R overlap only at the "pink" name. Their overlap is not that strong, since neither P nor R are strongly classified as pink. The amount of overlap is computed by multiplying the percentages for the common name. This gives a P-R overlap of 5:2 26:3 = 0:014. A closer correspondence of user-chosen names for a pair of regions results in a stronger category similarity, for example, G and GY have an overlap of 97:3 100:0 = 0:973. Categories that overlap over multiple names are combined using addition, for example, YR and Y overlap in both the "orange" and the "brown" name, giving a YR-Y overlap of 86:82:6+ 7:9 44:7 = 0 : 058. These overlap values can be used to explain why certain colours were difficult to use for target identification.</p><p>During the seven-colour study the P, Y, R, BG, and RP targets gave good performance. The G and GY targets gave poor performance. An examination of <ref type="table">Table 2 suggests the following explanation:</ref> targets R, Y, P, and RP have a weak category similarity to the other colours used during the study; Y has no category similarity to the other colours, R and RP have a category similarity (i.e., an R-RP overlap) of 0.145, and P and RP have a category similarity of 0.173 target BG has a moderate category similarity to GY and G (0.256 and 0.263, respectively) targets G and GY have a moderate category similarity to BG, and a very strong category similarity (0.973) to one another For each target in the seven-colour study, an increase in its category similarity to the other colours corresponded closely to an increase in its mean response time. We can measure this correspondence by computing Spearman's correlation coefficient on the rank  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">.3%  --------R  --26.3% 71.0%  ------2.6%  YR  ---5.3%  86.8%  7.9%  -----Y  ----2.6%  44.7% 47.4%  ---5.2%  GY  -------97.3%  --2.6%  G  -------100.0%  ---BG  -------</ref>  <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>: Similarity table, showing individual and total category similarity values for each of the colours used during the seven-colour study <ref type="table">Table 2</ref> sums the category similarity measures for each of the seven colours we used. The rank order of total category similarity from lowest to highest is Y, R, P, RP, BG, GY, and G. Ranking our colours based on total mean response time (including both present and absent trials across all three display sizes) from smallest to largest gave an order of P, R, Y, BG, RP, GY, and G. The Spearman correlation between these rankings is r = 0 : 821, confirming that higher mean response times for a given target correspond to a higher category similarity.</p><p>A similarity-response time correlation can also be observed during the nine-colour study. Targets P, Y, YR, and PB had a weak category similarity to other colours used during the study. Targets R, RP, and BG had a moderate category similarity to each other and to G and GY. Targets G and GY had a moderate category similarity to BG, and a strong category similarity to one another. The Spearman correlation between the colours' total similarity and mean response time ranking was r = 0 : 762. Results for YR and BG are somewhat anomalous; category similarity values suggest we should have observed better performance for the YR target, and worse performance for the BG target. Results for the other colours correspond closely to their category similarity measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Colour Category Study</head><p>Results from investigating colour category integration might imply that effective colours can be selected by controlling colour category alone. This was tested by selecting seven colours from colour regions that had low category similarity with one another. An examination of observer responses in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 1</ref> shows that colours chosen from the R, YR, Y, G, B, P, and RP regions satisfy our restriction; the largest category overlap occurs between RP-R (0.145) and RP-P (0.173). The colours we used were exactly those chosen by Healey and Enns to represent the above seven regions. Seven observers with normal or corrected acuity participated as observers during the colour category study. A total of 360 displays for each target were completed by the observers. Mean response error was 3.4%, which shows responses were accurate. The pattern of response times, however, was similar to the original seven-colour study. Several colours (in particular R and YR) exhibited poor search performance. This can be explained by examining the distance between neighbouring pairs of colours, and the linear separation for each colour when it acted as a target (Table 3). Colours that gave the worst search performance (R, YR, and RP) had the smallest neighbour distances and linear separation; in fact, the R, YR, and RP targets had a linear separation that was smaller than the one used during the nine-colour study. Colours that gave the best search performance (Y, G, B, and P) had the largest neighbour distances and linear separation.</p><p>From these results we concluded that colour category alone can-  . Results from displays using these colours as targets are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7</ref>. Mean response error was 5.2%. Response time graphs for all seven colours are much flatter than in the original seven-colourstudy, although G and Y still gave mixed results during target-absent displays. We could have further differentiated these elements by choosing a yellow from the center of the Y colour region (rather than at the GY-Y border). This might have resulted in poorer performance for the other targets due to the reduction in colour distance and linear separation between our Y, YR, R, RP, PB, and BG colours, however. It appears that seven isoluminant colours is the maximum we can display at one time, while still allowing rapid and accurate identification of any one of the colours.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">VISUALIZING MEDICAL IMAGES</head><p>As we discussed in the introduction, our long-term goal is a set of guidelines that help users maximize the total number of colours available during visualization, while still allowing for the rapid and accurate detection of any one of the given colours. Experimental results showed how we can control colour distance, linear separation, and colour category to pick seven isoluminant colours that satisfy our requirements. Extending these results to a practical application is a non-trivial problem. However, even the specific results reported here can help to design useful visualization applications. To this end, we discuss how colours from our experiments were used to visualize slice data from a Computerized Tomography (CT) scan.  We began by displaying slices as greyscale images ( <ref type="figure">Figure 8a</ref>); values in each slice had been scaled to range from 0:::255 for exactly this purpose. Higher values in a slice correspond to denser material detected during the CT scan. Greyscale images are a standard method for displaying medical slice data <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>, since they allow a user to easily locate individual regions of similar density. Through consultation we identified seven intensity ranges that corresponded to seven individual regions of interest. Slices were then viewed using seven different colours. <ref type="figure">Figure 8b</ref> displays the slice using colours from our original seven-colour experiment. <ref type="figure">Figure 8c</ref> displays the slice using colours from our final colour category experiment. There are three important points to note. First, as with the greyscale representation, it is easy to locate individual regions in both colour slices. The densities (and therefore the intensity values) of different regions of interest are consistent across slices. Therefore, our colour displays work well for any individual slice chosen by the user.</p><p>Second, as predicted by our experiment results, the colours used in <ref type="figure">Figure 8b</ref> do not always provide good differentiation between regions, compared to the colours used in <ref type="figure">Figure 8c</ref>. Consider the region reference by the arrow. In <ref type="figure">Figure 8b</ref>, it appears to made up of a single type of element. In fact, it is made up of two types of elements; this is clear when examining the same region in <ref type="figure">Figure 8c</ref>. Notice there is no corresponding tradeoff between <ref type="figure">Figure 8c</ref> and <ref type="figure">Figure 8b</ref>, that is, there are no pairs of elements that are difficult to differentiate in <ref type="figure">Figure 8c</ref> but easy to differentiate in <ref type="figure">Figure 8b</ref>.</p><p>Finally, colour images can provide visual cues that might not be immediately apparent in a greyscale display. For example, consider  <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>: Examples of a single CT slice (note that printed colours do not match exactly the colours shown on the monitor): (a) the slice displayed using a greyscale intensity ramp; (b) colours from the original seven-colourexperiment, although the location and borders of each region are clearly visible, the makeup of certain regions is difficult to determine, compared to; (c) colours from the final seven-colour experiment, which show clearly that the region referenced by the arrow is made up of two different groups of elements the small spots of purple at the top of the region in the center of the image. These spots represent areas of high relative density, and are quickly identified as different from the surrounding material. The same information is present in the greyscale image, but the visual system is not immediately drawn to it, since the contrast between the region and its neighbours is not as pronounced. One method of visualizing slice data is to "fly" through the slice stack, rapidly displaying individual slices one after another in a movie-like fashion <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. In this context, we expect users could more accurately detect areas with a specific density range using colour rather than greyscale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION</head><p>This paper has presented a simple method for choosing effective colours for use during data visualization. We accomplish this by controlling colour distance, linear separation of colours, and colour category similarity during colour selection. We found that an isoluminant slice through a monitor's gamut yielded up to seven different colours, any one of which could be rapidly and accurately detected, even in the presence of all the others. Each colour needed a minimum colour distance, linear separation, and colour category differentiation to guarantee good performance. One of our future goals is a set of investigations that explicitly measure the tradeoff in observer performance when these effects are varied. This will also allow us to identify the minimum required value for each effect. The perceived intensity of each colour was held constant during our studies to eliminate the potential for visual interference. It might be possible to use intensity in a controlled manner to increase the number of colours we can display simultaneously. For example, we might be able to choose multiple groups of colours, with each group being restricted to an isoluminant slice through the monitor's gamut. A colour group would be assigned to a conceptually related set of attribute values in the dataset to be visualized. Proper division by intensity might allow a user to select individual colours either from within a group (e.g., a dull red element or a bright green element) or across groups (e.g., all red elements). This type of technique is not possible if colours of varying intensity are chosen from the monitor's gamut in an ad hoc fashion.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Example of a target with both collinear and separable nontargets, the colours are shown in a u ; v -slice from the CIE LUV</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>colour distance: the Euclidean distance between different colours as measured in a perceptually balanced colour model linear separation: the ability to linearly separate targets from non-targets in the colour model being used colour category: the named colour regions occupied by both the target and non-target elements</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>lowing colour distances d and linear separations l: L* = 67.1 (67.1, 21.1, 11.2) Choosing colours from the monitor's gamut: (a) the boundary of the gamut at L = 6 7 : 1 , along with the maximum inscribed circle centered at L ; u ; v = 67:1;21:1;11:6, radius 75.0 E ; (b) five colours chosen around the circle's circumference; each element has a constant colour distance d with its two neighbours, and a constant linear separation l from the remaining (non-target) elements Study d l</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>allow us to measure the similarity of different colour regions. This category similarity is dependent on: the range of user-chosen colour names assigned to a given region Example of segmenting the circumference of a maximum inscribed circle from a u v -slice through CIE LUV at L = 7 1 : 6 ;ticks along the the circle mark the boundaries between the ten named regions, points are the representative colours for each region how "strongly" a region covers any user-chosen name in its range how the ranges of the two regions overlap</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Response time graphs for the first colour-category study: (a) target absent displays; (b) target present displays</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Response time graphs for the second colour-category study: (a) target absent displays; (b) target present displays The scan was taken to locate an aneurism in a patient's brain. This resulted in 116 individual slices, each of which had a 512 512 resolution.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Responses for the representative colours from the ten named regions, shown as the percentage of observers who chose a given name</figDesc><table><row><cell>26.3%</cell><cell>57.8% 15.8%</cell><cell>-</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>E 42.0 E 12.2 E YR 42.0 E 49.8 E 14.6 E Y 49.8 E 112.6 E 39.0 E G 112.6 E 67.5 E 52.9 E B 67.5 E 63.2 E 29.1 E P 63.2 E 48.6 E 20.4 E RP 48.6 E 42.0 E 14.2 E</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>CW d</cell><cell>CCW d</cell><cell>l</cell></row><row><cell>R</cell><cell>42.0</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The exact distance in CIE LUV between a colour, its clockwise neighbour (CW d), and its counter-clockwise neighbour (CCW d), as well as the linear separation from the other colours when it</figDesc><table><row><cell>acted as a target</cell></row><row><cell>not be used to ensure consistently good identification based on</cell></row><row><cell>colour. Colour distance and linear separation need to be considered,</cell></row><row><cell>since they have an effect on search performance. We used a more</cell></row><row><cell>systematic colour selection technique to choose another set of seven</cell></row><row><cell>colours:</cell></row><row><cell>a single green was chosen from the combined G-GY colour re-</cell></row><row><cell>gion; observers see the entire region as green, which means it</cell></row><row><cell>can be used for only a single colour</cell></row><row><cell>the clockwise neighbour of our green was a yellow, chosen to</cell></row><row><cell>lie on the border between the GY and Y colour regions</cell></row><row><cell>the counterclockwise neighbour of our green was a blue-green,</cell></row><row><cell>chosen to lie in the center of the BG colour region (we did not</cell></row><row><cell>use the colour from the border between G and BG, because it</cell></row><row><cell>was too difficult to differentiate from our green)</cell></row><row><cell>the remaining four colours (chosen from the YR, R, RP, and</cell></row><row><cell>PB colour regions) were at equal steps between our yellow and</cell></row><row><cell>our blue-green</cell></row><row><cell>This gave us a constant neighbour distance d and linear separa-tion l (59:4 E and 24:6 E , respectively) between the Y, YR, R, RP, PB, and BG colours (G had a larger d and l than the other</cell></row><row><cell>colours)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Department of Computer Science, University of British Columbia, 2366 Main Mall, Vancouver, British Columbia, V6T 1Z2, Canada</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>I would like to thank Dr. Kellogg S. Booth and Dr. James T. Enns for the technical advice they offered during my research. I would also like to thank Ms. Jeanette Lum for coordinating and running the most of the experiment sessions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual search for colour targets that are or are not linearly-separable from distractors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jolicoeur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vision Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A rule-based tool for assisting colormap selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bergman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rogowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;95<address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Munsell: A Grammar of Color</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Birren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1969" />
			<publisher>Van Nostrand Reinhold Company</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dimensional interaction of hue and brightness in preattentive field segregation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Callaghan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perception &amp; Psychophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adding intelligence to scientific data management</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cambell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Short</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color in visual search</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D'zmura</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vision Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="951" to="966" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time multivariate data visualization using preattentive processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Healey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Booth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Enns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Modelling and Computer Simulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-speed visual estimation using preattentive processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Healey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Booth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Enns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A perceptual colour segmentation algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Healey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Enns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer Science, University of British Columbia</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep. TR-96-09</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Retrofit of flat panel color displays in the F-16A/B</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE/AIAA 11th Digital Avionics Systems Conference</title>
		<meeting>IEEE/AIAA 11th Digital Avionics Systems Conference<address><addrLine>Seattle, Washington</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="328" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of color category on visual search</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kawai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Uchikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ujike</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Annual Meeting of the Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Fort Lauderdale, Florida</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page">2991</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color scales for image data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics &amp; Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tool for dynamic explorations of color mappings</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rheingans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tebbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing color gamuts: A user interface for the effective use of perceptual color spaces in data displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics &amp; Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An architecture for rule-based visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rogowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Visualization &apos;93</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;93<address><addrLine>San Jose, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="243" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research issues in scientific visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rosenblum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics &amp; Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effective software systems for scientific data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Haber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gurwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Search, similarity, and integration of feature between and within dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Triesman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Psychology: Human Perception &amp; Performance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="652" to="676" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Judgments of proportions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Varey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mellers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Birnbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Psychology: Human Perception &amp; Performance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color sequences for univariate maps: Theory, experiments, and principles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics &amp; Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using colour dimensions to display data dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Beatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Factors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wyszecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Stiles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Color Science: Concepts and Methods, Quantitative Data and Formulae</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
