<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Visualization of Laser Confocal Microscopy Datasets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Georgios</forename><surname>Sakas</surname></persName>
							<email>gsakas@igd.fhg.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Vicker</surname></persName>
							<email>vicker@zfn.uni-bremen.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Plath</surname></persName>
							<email>plath@zfn.uni-bremen.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Fraunhofer IGD University of Bremen University of Bremen</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Fraunhofer Institute for Computer Graphics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Wilhelminenstr. 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>64283</postCode>
									<settlement>Darmstadt</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology, Leobenerstr</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>28359</postCode>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>NW2, 28334</postCode>
									<settlement>Bibliothek, Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Visualization of Laser Confocal Microscopy Datasets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper presents an example of how existing visualization methods can be successfully applied-after minor modifications-for allowing new, sometimes unexpected insight in scientific questions, in this case for better understanding unknown, microscopic biological structures. We present a volume rendering system supporting the visualization of LCM datasets, a new microscopic tomographic method allowing for the first time accurate and fast in-vivo inspection of the spatial structure of microscopic structures, especially important in (but not restricted to) biology. The speed, flexibility and versatility of the system allows fast, convenient, interactive operation with large datasets on small computers (workstation or PC). By testing different datasets we have been able to significantly improve the performance of understanding the internal structure of LCM data. Most important, we have been able to show static and dynamic structures of cells never seen before and allowing significant insight in the cell movement process. Therefore we regard our system as a universal tool for the visualization such data.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In recent years the efforts of the major tomographic techniques (CT, MR, PET/SPECT etc.) have been focused on the acquisition of slices from organs within the human body. The size of such organs is typically several centimeters and the resolution of the acquisition techniques has been improved down to the order of magnitude of a millimeter. After several years of research and development major advantages in both, hardware and software have been achieved and the techniques of understanding complex topologies in the macroscopic scale are now considered to be well established. However, the structures in the microscopic scale show an even higher complexity than those of organs. As examples one can list structures of nerve cells, tissue and muscles, blood vessels etc. showing beautiful, complex, and mostly still unexplored patterns. In order to understand the spatial relationship and internal structure of such microscopic probes, tomographic series of slices are required in analogy to the tomographies used for organs and other macroscopic structures. The first method for gathering such tomographs is based in microtomic cutting and inspection of each slice using traditional microscope methods. However, this procedure shows a long list of drawbacks: the probe must be fixed, the slices can not be arbitrarily thin, the registration of slices after cutting is very difficult and often impossible, the procedure is extremely time consuming and the probe is destroyed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1: Principle of Laser Confocal Microscopy</head><p>Visible or ultra violet laser emission is focused on the first confocal pinhole and then onto the specimen as a diffractionlimited light spot, see <ref type="figure">fig. 1</ref>. The primary incident light is then reflected from particular voxel elements or emitted from fluorescent molecules excited within it. Emissions from the object return along the primary laser light pathway and depart from it by lateral reflection from (or passage through, depending on the instrument) a dichroic mirror onto the second confocal pinhole. This aperture is confocal with the infocus voxel elements in the specimen. The virtual elimination by defocusing of all distal and proximal flanking emissions at this physical point assures that the light passing onto the detector, a sensitive photodetector or camera, is specifically derived from in-focus object voxels with a resolution, e.g. in the Leica instrument, approaching 200 to 400 nm in the x/y and z directions, respectively. In order to image the entire object, the light spot is scanned by a second mirror in the x/y plane in successive z sections by means of a precision stage motor. Rapid scanning preserves fluorescent intensity but must be reconciled with image quality. The storage, retrieval and manipulation of light intensity information from the object makes static and dynamic 3-D imaging possible. Although not perfect, the new method shows several significant benefits as compared to the traditional procedures. The most important of them are: true tomographic method, significant freedom in choosing slice thickness and size, trivial registration of slices, very fast and easy in operation, capable of acquiring in-vivo cells as well as static or dynamic structures, non-destructive. Lastly, by using different types of laser and fluorophore materials, different spatially overlapping structures can be visualized and superimposed within the same probe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">The Visualization Problems</head><p>The data acquired with Laser Confocal Microscopy (LCM) show several characteristics requiring specialized treatment in order to make the method applicable:</p><p>1. Large data size. Typical datasets have a resolution of 512 2 64 pixels. These pixels are colored, thus a typical RGB dataset requires some 50 Mbytes of memory. Obviously, datasets of this size require efficient processing methods.</p><p>2. Low contrast, low intensity gradients, bad signal to noise ratio. These characteristics make a straight-forward segmentation between the structures of interest and the background (e.g. by using thresholding, region growing, homogeneity, color differences etc.) impossible. All the methods listed above apply more or less binary decision criteria if a pixel/voxel belongs to the structure or not. Such criteria typically fail when used with signals showing the characteristics listed above.</p><p>3. Unequal resolutions in the plane and the depth directions. Thus, a visualization method has to be able to perform with "blocks" or unequal size lengths instead with cubic voxels. Re-sampling of the raw data to a regular cubic field will further reduce the signal quality, introduce interpolation artifacts and generate an even larger dataset, probably too large to be handled with conventional computers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref>. In general the examined structured is unknown. This has several implications on the quality and the speed of the visualization method:</p><p>Regarding the quality, artifacts have to be avoided as far as possible. Introducing artifacts in an unknown structure will often have fatal effects on their interpretation, since the human observer does not always have the experience for judging the correctness or the fidelity of the presented structures. As an example, an obvious artifact caused by bas parameter settings of the software during the visualization of human anatomy (e.g. of a head) is immediately detected by the observer, since the human anatomy is well known and such artifacts are trivially detected. This is not the case when inspecting an unknown dataset.</p><p>Choosing the "correct" illumination model (e.g. MIP, semi-transparent, surface etc.) has a significant impact on the clarity and information content of the visualization. Again, due to the lack of experience such a decision is typically much more difficulty than in the case of anatomic tomographic data.</p><p>The speed of visualization becomes the most crucial issue. The visualization parameters have to be adjusted in an interactive, trial-and-error procedure. This can take a very long time if, e.g., after an adjustment the user has to wait for several minutes to see the new result. Furthermore, inspection of new, unknown structures require rapid changing of directions, illumination conditions, visualization models, etc.. Looping and stereo images are of enormous importance for understanding unknown, complicated spatial structures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Volume Rendering LCM Data</head><p>The term "volume rendering" refers to techniques for direct visualizing measured or simulated, discrete or continuous, scalar or vector data distributed over 3-D space, i.e., without mapping the data on intermediate representations <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Volume rendering is the method of choice for visualizing LCM fields since it works directly on the raw data without requiring a pre-processing or segmentation step introducing artifacts. Furthermore, all parameters of visualization can be adjusted on-the-fly at will. Volume rendering is a long established, well understood research topic for a rather long period of time, and a rich literature exists here. Therefore in this Case Study we skip most of the technical details and focusing on the application of using volume rendering for LCM data visualization. For the shake of competence we only resume the very basic milestones of volume rendering. For more details the interested reader can refer the original literature (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>).</p><p>The visualization pipeline consists of three stages, as presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">fig. 2</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The 3D data are initially represented as a cube. During the "geometric transformation" stage the data are transformed, (perspectively) projected, and scan-converted using usual scanline techniques before the visible portion is clipped. In the "traversing" step the volume data are traversed using a ray-marching scheme similar to the well-known ray tracing. Different methods (e.g. splatting, shear-warp etc.) are also possible. During traversing the densities along the eye-ray are "sampled", i.e. properly weighted and accumulated. In the next "illumination" stage mapping of the data to visible primitives is performed. The three most frequently used techniques in volume rendering include (a) the reconstruction of the appearance of surfaces, used widely for the visualization of medical data like CT or MRI <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> (b) the maximum or minimum intensity projection (MIP), <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> or (c) the visualization as semitransparent gels having frequently the appearance of clouds or X-rays <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Each of these representations possesses advantages when used with particular types of data. The result of this stage is an RGB-color and transparency stored in the frame buffer. Before the picture is displayed, 2-D image processing ("imaging") may be applied on the frame buffer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Implementation and Results</head><p>For the visualization of LCM data we used our volume rendering system InViVo (Interactive Visualizer of Volume data) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Visualization of Static Probes</head><p>Under the term "static" we understand microscopic structures which in general do not change shape rapidly as compared to the observation time. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Visualization of Dynamic Cell Structures</head><p>Laser confocal microscopy plays a fundamental role for gathering in-vivo data about not only static, but also dynamic structures, i.e. structures existing typically only within living cells and for a very short period of time (e.g. for a few seconds.). Such structures are common in several biological applications. In the case studied here we focus on temporary structures formed by polymerized actin, a structure necessary for cell movements. For locomotion cells like Dictyostelium amoebae (see <ref type="figure">fig 5)</ref> forms pseudopodia by changing their shape. The changes in the cell shape are caused by the polymerization of actin. In contrast to monomeric G-actin, polymeric (filamentous) F-actin can be "colored" with fluorescence makers <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. In this way the dynamics of the formation of short living polymerization structures can be detected. The complex dynamic of the three-dimensional periphery can be studied by means of LCM data visualization. Analyzing the temporal changes of the three-dimensional cell periphery -for example by the Karhunen-Loeve method <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>-allow us to estimate the essential data for the cell mobility. This will enable us to classify possible cell decreases by means of the cell mobility. This is important not only for Dictyostelium amoebae. but for all cells, which move around, for example white blood cells. Furthermore, the formation of the pseudopodia is strongly correlated with the structure formation during the polymerization of actin inside the cell. There are complex threedimensional structures like spiral and scroll waves, which can be realized for short periods of time. By means of LCM visualization such structures can be studied in detail. The "life-time" of the different temporary structures inside the cells will give another possibility to classify .deseasethological conditions at the cellular level <ref type="figure">Figures 3, 4</ref> and 5 demonstrate the importance of LCM data visualization for detecting unknown structures. In this case, we studied actin filaments in Dictyostelium amoebae. This cell is a model of phagocytosis and chemotaxis, behaving much like the neutrophil leukocytes in our own blood. It also passes through a developmental phase in which about 100,000 cells aggregate and differentiate into 3 or 4 cell types which form a little slug that may crawl off to sporulate, partly modeling our own development. New research using this cell has shown that, contrary to earlier assumptions, cell movement in amoeboid cells is not a random process. To describe the pericellular spatio-temporal extension of pseudopodia which drive the locomotion of these cells one normally thinks of the incoherence movement of a sack containing 5 playful kittens. But upon closer inspection, the cell surface decomposes into the oscillating product of superimposed, rotating waves <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The origin of these waves lies in the highly dynamic assembly and disassembly of actin proteins into short filaments in alternate corners of the cell with time periods ranging from 10 to 100 s. All 3 figures show fluorescently stained actin filaments (Factin) building larger patterns in fixed cells. The structure and dynamics of these patterns have not yet been studied in detail. F-actin appears to assemble into small structures or, at other intervals, more evenly as a cortex under the cell surface membrane, as in figs. 3 and 4. Here, F-actin molds the cell surface into an highly irregular pattern. This particular type of pattern is not revealed by using any other visualization method (slices, MIP or transmission ray). <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> shows Factin structures with a size aof about 10-20 micrometers The data resolution is 512 484 43 voxels = 10 Mbytes. Note the structure of the surface visible in the "surface volume rendering" image. <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> shows similar structures from a different cell. Note that the surface of the actin block is not flat but shows a complicated structure with several spikes and "antenas" (pseudopodia). These structures are hardly visible and therefore difficult to detect when regarding individual slices. <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> shows close-ups of the structure in an active pseudopodium in the upper-left hand corner of one slice, i.e., a "pretzel-like" pattern. Close examination indicates a wavefront of F-actin filament assembly. By using the volumetric methods presented here, a complete investigation of this structure (rotation, measurement, volumetry, etc.) could be produced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>We presented a volume rendering method supporting the visualization of LCM datasets. The speed and versatility of our implementation allows for a convenient, fast, interactive examination of unknown cell structures even on small, of-theself computer such as PC or PowerPC. By testing different datasets we have been able to significantly improve the task of understanding the internal structure of LCM data. In addition to the static images we have been able to also visualize dynamically changing temporary structures of polymerized actin. Furthermore, for the first time we have been able to present the complicated surface of such structures, allowing insight in a process of great biological importance not completely understood yet. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The visualization pipeline.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :Figure 4 :Figure 5 :Figure 6 :Figure 7 :Figure 8 :</head><label>345678</label><figDesc>F-actin structures in Dictyostelium amoebae, Resolution 51248443 voxels = 10 Mbytes. Upper left a single slice, right surface reconstruction; lower left MIP, right transmission illumination models F-actin structures. Resolution 51248470 voxels = 16.5 Mbytes. Upper left a single slice, right surface reconstruction; lower left MIP, right transmission illumination models Close inspection of a "pretzel-like" structure located in the upper left area (pseudopodium) of the slice. Total dataset resolution 512 484 60 voxels = 14 Mbytes The complicated topology of nerve cells networks. Resolution 512 2 x100 voxels = 25 MBytes. Upper left a single slice, right surface reconstruction; lower left MIP, right transmission illumination models The wire-like structure of the astrocyte cytosceleton of the same probe. Resolution of 335 306 67 voxels with a size of 0:16 2 0:2m. Upper left a single slice, right surface reconstruction; lower left MIP, right transmission illumination models The extra-cellular component of a retina blood vessel of a cat. Resolution of 335 306 67 voxels with a size of 0:16 2 0:2m. Upper left a single slice, right surface reconstruction; lower left MIP, right transmission illumination models</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Typical examples of static structures are cells, bones, muscles etc. etc. In general the vast majority of microscopic probes can be considered as to be static structures. An important reason for this is that preparation and observation of rapidly changing, dynamic structures, shows usually significantly difficulties.Figures 8 and 7present a microscopic preparation of the tubular structure of a cat retina. The used microscope was able to detect two different fluorophore types separately, thus acquiring two different tissue types simultaneously. The dataset consist of 335 306 67 voxels, each with a dimension of 0:16 2 0:2m. The first image presents the extracellular component of the blood vessel. The vessel diameter before the branch point is 19 m.</figDesc><table><row><cell>The second image shows</cell></row><row><cell>the wire-like structure of the astrocyte cytosceleton. Both</cell></row><row><cell>datasets originate from the same probe. In all subsequent im-</cell></row><row><cell>ages the difference of the visualization between slicing, MIP,</cell></row><row><cell>surface and semi-transparent methods is shown.</cell></row><row><cell>The next dataset 6 shows the complicated structure of nerve</cell></row><row><cell>cells networks. The resolution of the dataset is with 25 Mbytes (512 2 100 voxels) large. As one can see on image</cell></row><row><cell>6 upper left, single slices are not able to provide full under-</cell></row><row><cell>standing of the complicated topology. The three other im-</cell></row><row><cell>ages show in much better detail the internal structure of the</cell></row><row><cell>cell network.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Volume Visualization</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Los Alamitos/CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press Tutorial</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The locomotion, shape and pseudopodial dynamics of unstimulated Dictyostelium cells are not random</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Killich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Plath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bultmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rensing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Vicker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cell Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1005" to="1013" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell movement and shape are non-random and determined by intracellular, oscillatory, rotating waves in Dictyostelium amoebae</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Killich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Plath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E.-C</forename><surname>Hass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bultmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rensing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Vicker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BioSystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Display of Surfaces from Volume Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics &amp; Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient Ray-Tracing of Volume Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Visualization of Large Scalar Voxel Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hartig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization&apos;92 conference</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization&apos;92 conference<address><addrLine>Boston-MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10-22" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Volume Rendering of Large Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-08" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="438" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Optimized Maximum Intensity Projection (MIP)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grimm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Savopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>P. Hanrahan, W. Purgathofer</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Springer Verlag Wien</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="63" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rendering Techniques &apos;95</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confocal scanning optical microscopy and its applications for biological specimens</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shotton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cell Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
