<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The definition of consonance as the ability to resolve a sound into the pitch categories is introduced.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>Consonance in music has been a scientific issue ever since the pythagorean idea of scales with ratios of small whole numbers has been suggested. Rameau's famous "Traité de l'Harmonie" <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr">1721]</ref> is the first to emphasize the importance of the harmonic series. However, its failure to explain consonant chords such as the minor triad led Helmholtz <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">1863]</ref> to develop a physical explanation of consonance in terms of beats. Two tones within a certain critical bandwidth show the phenomenon of "roughness", which can be attributed to dissonance.</p><p>Pierce <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and Terhardt <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> have pointed out that an explanation of consonance with roughness and beats disregards the musical meaning of the interval between the notes of the chord in question. Other criteria, such as context, familiarity <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, prenatal conditioning and cultural conditioning <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> have been suggested to account for the subjective decision of "what goes well". A seventh of two sinusoidal tones displays no roughness.The dissonant effect might then be attributed to our familiarity to its dissonant role in Western music.</p><p>Krummhansl and Kessler <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">1982]</ref> have determined "key profiles" which encompass these criteria by an experimental method in which musicians were asked to judge how well each probe tone went with the tone or chord before. They used a multidimensional technique to produce maps of rela-tionships between chords, as well as predictions of corresponding keys to passages. It is shown that for a given major triad, the dominant, subdominant and parallel minor chord is detected as being related.This paper suggest a way to produce the key profiles theoretically:</p><p>The characteristic curve for roughness is obtained by the measure of how well the given chord resolves into the pitch categories.</p><p>This is not to be confused with the spectral resolving power of the ear! Pitch categories are about a semitone wide. and present the elements of the 12-tone scale to which people on the Western hemisphere are familiar. The categorical perception enables the listener to assign any audible harmonic to a complex tone. This freedom or lack of resolution power accounts for the chromatic scale being able to serve as a substitute for the diatonic scale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Consonance in terms of Helmholtz roughness</head><p>The phenomenon of the perception of beats of two sinusoidal tones which differ in frequency by a factor of about 22:21 give rise to the definition of "dissonance". The characteristic as shown in Pierce <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Alternative definition of Consonance</head><p>Sounds are perceived by the ear by some kind of spectral analysis ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>). Sano and Jenkins presented a connectionist model due to which the local information of the analysis on the basilar membrane ("transducer layer") is passed to a scale of pitch categories ("note layer") in the brain. "The motivation for the model derives from the fact that the inner hair cells in the cochlea, the primary transducers in the auditory system, respond to a range of frequencies".</p><p>In optics, one is confronted with the question of when two close spectral lines are to be called separate. The unability to make this decision shall be used here to define dissonance. Two closely neighboured pure tones display an overlap of the corresponding response distributions on the transducer layer. As an alternative approach to the roughness-theory, dissonance shall be viewed as the uncertainty in deciding which pitch category the particular harmonics belong to. The situation in figure 2 corresponds to two partials from different fundamental tones in a chord. They generally have different amplitudes. Usually these distributions are modelled by Roex-filters. In the present context Gaussian approximations are sufficiently exact. The uncertainty in distributing the peaks into the pitch categories will here be modeled by U(1-U), such that the consonance reads U is one when two fundamental distributions overlap completely, so 0&lt;K&lt;1. The Definition coincides with the experimental fact that the dissonance of two pure tones decreases when one of their amplitudes lessens. The resulting characteristic for two peaks (K 0 (f,f0) resembles h(f,f0): </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Consonance of a chord</head><p>From this characteristic, a composite function for the "consonance of a chord" can be derived. A natural approach is to examine the weighted sum of the pair consonancies appearing in the chord. The weighting (F(k)) occurs via the loudness (in sone) of the corresponding partial, which is proportional to the logarithm of the Fourier power spectrum.It measures the amplitude of the response distribution.</p><p>Summing the pair consonancies corresponds to with and U(kf i ,lf j ,k,l), a measure for the overlap,</p><p>If in addition a vector space of chords is defined by assigning one dimension to each pitch category with n=88 for 88 piano-keys, for example, then the coordinates of c give the amplitudes of the complex tones involved in the chord.</p><p>Then the consonance becomes a scalar product. The diagonal elements can now be increased by the magnitude of the lowest eigenvalue, to make this scalar product positive definite. Physically this corresponds to shifting the consonance upward on the scale, without disturbing the hierarchy of the measure. An interpretation would be the "self-consonance" of the single complex tone.</p><p>Renormalizing this extended quadratic form yields(λ min &lt;0) a norm for a Hilbert space, in which the set of all chords are embedded in the first quadrant (. The renormalized coordinates for measuring the consonance reads:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Ĉ f i { }     1 N 2 ------ K 0 f n α f n b ,     k 1 = N ∑ α 1 = N ∑ = K 0 f f' , ( ) 1 M 2 ------- 1 4U 1 U - ( ) - ( ) l 1 = M ∑ k 1 = M ∑ = U kf lf' , ( ) F k ( ) F l ( ) f″e f″ kf i - ( ) 2 2 σ k i , 2 -------------------------- - e f ″ lf j - ( ) 2 2 σ l j , 2 ------------------------- - d 0 ∞ ∫ = c R n ∈ c i 1 N ---- δ i n α , k 1 = N ∑ = = Ĉ c ( ) c i K 0 f i f j , ( )c j j 1 = n ∑ i 1 = n ∑ c 〈 |K 0 c | 〉 = = C c ( ) c 〈 |K 0 λ min - c | 〉 c 〈 |K c | 〉 c K 2 = = = c i 1 N N λ min - ( ) ---------------------------------- δ i n α , α 1 = N ∑ =</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Metric, Correlation</head><p>With the obtained norm, a metric is induced by with the Correlation &lt;a|K|b&gt;. These seemingly sporadically defined measures are able to distinguish the familiar harmonic relationships.</p><p>The matrix elements of K are dependent on the weighting function F(k) of the k'th partial, and in so far on the instrument.</p><p>They also have the interpretation of how well a single complex tone of the instrument sounds together with another complex tone (=fundamental including partials). The matrix elements are therefore also obtainable from a psychoacoustical experiment in which people give their judgement on how well they perceive pairs of tones. This supports the subjective idea of musical taste.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Results</head><p>For the case of a (Yamaha DX 11) synthesizer version of a cello the power spectrum has been recorded. In the following calculation of the matrix K the first eight partials will be considered.</p><p>The peakwidth of the gaussian distributions is obtained by fitting K 0 (f,f0) into h(f,f0) (minima equal!). The resulting value is 2σ κ,ι =0.31m(kf i ), (m=interval of one minor third) which corresponds to about one half-tone. This stands in contrast to the value of the band pass measure Q=10 given by Sano&amp; Jenkins <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> for the Rounded Exponential Filter where g=|f-f0|/f0, which is usually used to model the response distribution on the basilar membrane. The value obtained here would approximately be Q=6.</p><p>and U(kf i ,lf j ,k,l) can be evaluated with extending the integration range over the whole frequency axis(-inf,+inf).</p><p>A typical weighting functions F(k), with P(k)={1,0.81,0.7,0.71,0.51,0.59,0.5,0.4,0.3}(Cello). A and B are determined by maximizing the contrast of the norm. If the consonance is shown over the frequency difference, the values for the matrix K can be extracted, as in figure 4. The chord, and therefore the consonance is then detemined by keynumbers of the tones within: The result points to the following rule:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">{n α }. d a b , ( ) a b -K a K b K 2 a b 〈 | 〉 K - + = = Roex g ( ) 1 4Qg + ( )e 4 Qg - = F k ( ) A B P k ( ) 0.3 -------------     log + =</formula><p>Given a consonant chord, among all other consonant chords, the ones "closest" typically appear together in music of Western culture.</p><p>Since the choice of F(k) is not obvious, different results for the key profiles are obtained. However, the characteristic peaks at the fourth, the fifth, the third, and the sixth are always present and make the harmonically related chords detectable by certain "windows" in a consonance over distance diagram.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Analysis of Music</head><p>Here, the Fourier spectra (F(i)) which are used in an arithmetic mean: F(i,j)=0.5(F(i)+F(j)). Again, this is an approximation. Parncutt <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> points out that roughness of a pair of tones may diminish if one tone is played louder. Here, the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Note: C# D D# E F F# G G# A A# B C'</head><p>Consonance: .01 .1 .5 .6 .8 .1 .9 .35 .7 ..5 .3 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chord</head><p>Consonance spectra have been taken of a synthesizer-version of a grandpiano (Yamaha DX 11). The first four bars of Bach's well known "Preludium" are subject to the analysis. The beginning of the piece is characterized by <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>: The 48 first chords of Bach's "Preludium" in C-Maj from "Das Wohltemperierte Klavier I" (c.:consonance, D.distance) two base-notes and a pair of three subsequently played "right-hand" notes. The higher notes are not sustained and can therefore be considered to fit into the harmonic context laid out by the introducing lower notes, which are sustained. The progression of these triads can be traced with the diagram of figure 7.</p><p>C stands for consonance, and c 1 ,c 2 are the number of semitones from the base tone. The first three chords have the coordinates (c 1 ,c 2 )=(4,7),(4,12),(4,16) at which the consonance clearly shows extremal values. The second progression of three chords belongs to (c 1 ,c 2 )=(2,9), <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2,</ref><ref type="bibr">14)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7)</ref>, and the third to (c 1 ,c 2 )=(3,7), <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr">14)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr">17)</ref>. All appearing consonancies show a value of C&gt;0.4. As a result one can say that Bach seems to have picked chords with especially little roughness in the introduction of his "Preludium".   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">Conclusion</head><p>Visualization of consonance and correlation between chords serves as a useful tool to overlook harmonic relationships. Typically related chords are distinguishable in relevant diagrams ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 8</ref>).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure. 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Characteristic roughness curve of two sinusoidal pure tones: h(f,f0). The normalization value m(f0) = f0*(2^(3/12)-1) corresponds to the interval of three semitones. (f0 &lt; f; Valid for approximately f0&gt;500Hz.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure . 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Two overlapping response distributions on the basilar membrane corresponding to the sinusoidal pure tone components of a chord.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Consonance in terms of overlap of response dis-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :Figure 5 :</head><label>45</label><figDesc>A typical key profile7. Problem solving in musicGiven a chord (say C,E,G), what are its closest neighbours? Using the Keyprofile the norm and the metric give the following closest chords above C=0.824, which is the consonance of (C,E,G): The closest chords to (CEG) within the first octave with consonance greater or equal to 0.84</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Tracing chords in a consonance diagram</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>All triads as seen by the C E G. In the window, C E A, C F C', C F A, and D G H can be found.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">On the sensation of tone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L F</forename><surname>Helmholtz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1863" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Harmonic resolution, neural resonance, &amp; positive affect</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Connection Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracing the dynamic changes in perceived tonal organization in a spatial representation of musical keys</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Krummhansl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Psychol.: Human Perc. Perf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="579" to="594" />
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Harmony: A psychoacustical approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Parncutt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Springer Series in Information Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Auditory filters and excitation patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Patterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Frequency selectivity in hearing</title>
		<editor>B.C.J. Moore</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attaining consonance in arbitrary scales</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Pierce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Acoustical Society. Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">249</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1966" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The science of musical sound</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Pierce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific American Library</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rameau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1721" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Traité de l&apos;harmonie</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A neural network model for pitch perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Music and connectionism</title>
		<editor>P.M. Todd &amp; D.G. Loy</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pitch, consonance and harmony</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Terhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Acoust. Soc. Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1061" to="1069" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Consonance</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
