<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Anchoring Effect in Decision-Making with Visual Analytics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Isaac</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ryan</forename><surname>Wesslen</surname></persName>
							<email>rwesslen@uncc.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alireza</forename><surname>Karduni</surname></persName>
							<email>akarduni@uncc.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sashank</forename><surname>Santhanam</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Samira</forename><surname>Shaikh</surname></persName>
							<email>sshaikh2@uncc.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">¶</forename><surname>Wenwen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dou</forename><surname>||</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Charlotte</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">IEEE Conference on Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>October 1-6, Phoenix</addrLine>
									<postCode>2017</postCode>
									<region>Arizona</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Anchoring Effect in Decision-Making with Visual Analytics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:10+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Visual Analytics</term>
					<term>Anchoring Effect</term>
					<term>Sense Making</term>
					<term>Cognitive Bias</term>
					<term>Interaction Log Analysis K.6.1 [Management of Computing and Information Systems]: Project and People Management-Life Cycle; K.7.m [The Computing Profession]: Miscellaneous-Ethics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Anchoring effect is the tendency to focus too heavily on one piece of information when making decisions. In this paper, we present a novel, systematic study and resulting analyses that investigate the effects of anchoring effect on human decision-making using visual analytic systems. Visual analytics interfaces typically contain multiple views that present various aspects of information such as spatial, temporal, and categorical. These views are designed to present complex, heterogeneous data in accessible forms that aid decisionmaking. However, human decision-making is often hindered by the use of heuristics, or cognitive biases, such as anchoring effect. Anchoring effect can be triggered by the order in which information is presented or the magnitude of information presented. Through carefully designed laboratory experiments, we present evidence of anchoring effect in analysis with visual analytics interfaces when users are primed by representation of different pieces of information. We also describe detailed analyses of users&apos; interaction logs which reveal the impact of anchoring bias on the visual representation preferred and paths of analysis. We discuss implications for future research to possibly detect and alleviate anchoring bias.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Researchers in multiple fields, including psychology, economics and medicine have extensively studied the effect of cognitive biases on decision making <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. Cognitive biases are rules of thumb or heuristics that help us make sense of the world and reach decisions with relative speed <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. Decision making, the process of identifying solutions to complex problems by evaluating multiple alternatives <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> has been increasingly exacerbated due to explosion of big data <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. To facilitate human decision-making processes on large and complex datasets, Visual Analytics (VA) combines automated analysis techniques with interactive visualizations to increase the amount of data users can effectively work with <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. Evidently, the effectiveness of VA to support decision making is an area that warrants study. Our goal in this work is therefore to conduct a study which incorporates three complementary strands of research, given the premises that VA supports decision making, and that decision making is impacted by cognitive biases. Specifically, we investigate how users' decision making processes are impacted by cognitive biases when using VA systems to analyze large and complex datasets. Moreover, we explore if and how cognitive biases are reflected in the way that users interact with visual analytic interfaces.</p><p>In the context of VA research, many recent VA systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref> designed to facilitate the decision making on large and complex datasets contain coordinated and multiple views (CMV). By presenting different visual representations that show various aspects of the underlying data and automatically coordinating operations between views, multiple coordinated views support exploratory analysis to enable insight and knowledge discovery <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. In visual interfaces that employ CMV design, users often have choices on which views serve as primary vs. supporting views for their analysis and on the strategies to switch between different views.</p><p>The flexibility of visual interfaces with coordinated and multiple views make cognitive biases such as anchoring bias particularly relevant to study. People find cognitive biases to be useful heuristics when sorting through large amounts of information, when task constraints or instructions prime them to focus on specific types of information, or when asked to make quick decisions and analyses. This has been demonstrated for several biases and shown that biases affect decision-making processes in predictably faulty ways that can result in decision-making failures when information is discounted, misinterpreted, or ignored <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Additionally, the biases affect not only regular users, but also expert users, when thinking intuitively <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. One type of bias, the anchoring effect describes the human tendency to rely too heavily on one/the first piece of information offered (the "anchor") when making decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Research has demonstrated that individuals anchor on a readily accessible value and adjust from it to estimate the true value, often with insufficient adjustments. For instance, if a person is asked to estimate the length of the Mississippi River, following a question on whether the length is longer or shorter than 500 miles, their answer will be adjusted from the 'anchor' value of 500 miles and will underestimate the true length of the Mississippi River. The effect of such anchors have been extensively studied in multiple tasks in the laboratory and in the field (for a detailed review see <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>). However, the effect of anchoring in Visual Analytics interfaces have not been systematically studied. More importantly, the effect of anchoring bias on the strategies that users deploy to interact with the visual interface and their analysis outcomes remains an open question.</p><p>In this paper, we study the effect of anchoring on users exploration processes and outcomes. When interacting with visual interfaces employing CMV design, there is a possibility that users rely too heavily on one particular view. The reasons for such reliance include but are not limited to prior experience, familiarity with certain visualizations, and different ways they were trained to use the visual interface. The significance and impact of such anchoring is the subject of our study.</p><p>Prior work in the VA community provides empirical data on cognitive costs of visual comparisons and context switching in coordinated-multiple-view visual interfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38]</ref>. Findings from these experiments inform design guidelines of CMVs. However, there is little research on how cognitive biases transfer to visualizations, in particular to visual interfaces with coordinated multiple views. MacEachren <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> argues that prior efforts in visualization of uncertainty deal with representation of data uncertainty, but do not address the reasoning that takes place under these conditions. We therefore aim to investigate the impact of anchoring effect on human decision-making processes when using VA systems, because it has been shown to be overwhelmingly affect decision-making <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Our experiment design addresses several challenging requirements that are necessary to derive meaningful implications: first, the experiments need to be conducted using a VA system with tasks relevant to decision-making based on large and complex datasets; second, measures and experiment data that reflect users' decision making processes (beyond task completion time and accuracy) need to be collected; third, novel analyses methods need to be developed to tease out the effect of anchoring bias on decision making with VA systems. Accordingly, our work makes the following original contributions:</p><p>• To situate our study in complex decision making tasks with visual interfaces, the experiments are conducted with a sophisticated visual analytics system <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> with multiple coordinated views. The design of the visual analytics system enables the visual anchor on either geo or time related representation through tutorial/training.</p><p>• In order to study the effect of anchoring bias on the decisionmaking processes with greater nuance and granularity, we collect not only quantitative measures about users' performance, including questionnaire responses, but we also collect detailed interaction logs within the visual interface. The interaction logs capture the decisionmaking process at a action level. Significant differences in actions were found between subjects assigned to different visual anchors.</p><p>• In addition to running statistical tests on the quantitative measures collected through pre-and post-questionnaires, we apply two novel methods of analysis -graph analysis and structural topic modeling -to analyze the paths and patterns of users interactions and identify the effect of anchoring bias. Our analysis revealed that visual anchors impact users' decisionmaking processes while numerical anchors affect the analysis outcomes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">BACKGROUND AND RELATED WORK</head><p>In this section, we describe literature in the areas relevant to our study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Background on Anchoring Effect</head><p>Humans have the tendency to rely on heuristics to make judgments, which can lead to efficient and accurate decisions <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, however these heuristics may also lead to systematic errors known as cognitive biases <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Psychologists have long studied the presence of cognitive biases in human decision making process <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref>. The anchoring and adjustment bias, defined as the inability of people to make sufficient adjustments starting from an initial value to yield a final answer <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, is one of the most studied cognitive biases that can lead individuals to make sub-optimal decisions. In the classic study by Tversky and Kahneman <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, the authors found evidence that when individuals are asked to form estimates, they typically start with an easily accessible value or reference point and make adjustments from this value. While such an approach may not always lead to sub-optimal decisions, research has demonstrated that individuals typically fail to adjust their estimates away from their initial starting point the anchor. Research has shown that anchoring affects decision making in various contexts, including judicial sentencing <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, negotiations <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> and medical diagnoses <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Given this documented prevalence of anchoring bias in various contexts of decisionmaking activities, we hypothesize that such effects may also be present when individuals interact with data while using visual analytics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Visual Analytics and Cognitive Biases</head><p>Sacha et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> investigate how uncertainties can propagate through visual analytics systems and examine the role of cognitive biases in understanding uncertainties, and also suggest guidelines for the design of VA systems that may further facilitate human decisionmaking. Similarly, research in the detection of biased decision making with VA software is in the early stages <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Harrison et al.</ref> found through a crowd-sourcing experiment that affective priming can influence accuracy in common graphical perception tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. George et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> examined robustness of anchoring and adjustment effect in the context of decision support systems. Although their study revealed the presence of anchoring bias in the user's decision making task of estimating the price of house, their decision support system did not contain a highly complex visual interface consisting of coordinated multiple view. Researchers have also investigated the role of various other biases such as confirmation bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> and attraction effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> in the context of visual analytics. Dimara et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> studied attraction effect using crowdsourcing experiments to determine that attraction bias did in fact generalize to information visualization and that irrelevant alternatives may influence users choice in scatterplots. Their findings provide implications for future research on how to possibly alleviate attraction effect when designing information visualization plots but no study to date has explored the anchoring bias in visual interfaces. Additionally, no research to date has examined the interaction patterns and activities of users in decisionmaking while these users are explicitly anchored under controlled experimental conditions. In the next section, we describe a novel approach to analyzing the users' interaction patterns which is grounded in the analysis of web log data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Use of Topic Models for Analyzing Web Logs</head><p>For our analysis of the interaction logs, we employ a variant of topic models, structural topic modeling (STM), that facilitates testing the effect of document-level variables on topic proportions. By characterizing the temporal sequence of actions taken by the user during their interactions with the interface as a 'text document' and characterizing actions as 'topics', we are able to test the effects of several factors, which include not only demographic variables such as age and gender, but also the effects of anchoring bias on the user's actions, and hence their decision-making processes. Although topic models have been used to analyze web logs previously, our application of STM to user interaction logs is novel by providing a mechanism to test the effect of independent variables on actions (topic proportions). Early applications of topics models <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref> to analyze web log behavior used probabilistic latent semantic indexing (pLSI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, a predecessor model to LDA-based topic models <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. In the case of analyzing web log data, the pLSI model has been helpful in capturing meaningful clusters of users' actions, and found to surpass state-of-the-art methods in generating user recommendations for Google News <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</p><p>One limitation of this method was that it did not consider time or user-level attributes (independent variables) within the model. To address the issue of time, Iwata et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> created a LDA-based topic model (Topic Tracking Model) to identify trends of individuals' web logs on two large consumer purchase behavior datasets. In their model, they created a time component to identify the dynamic and temporal nature of topics. As we will discuss in section 5, we address the same concern by creating a time component in our STM model. Further, we employ STM's flexible causal inference framework as a mechanism to test anchor bias by treating each anchor group as additional independent variables. iment. We then describe the experiment design rationale and tasks designed to elicit and test anchoring bias, and provide details about the experimental procedures and participants next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Research Questions</head><p>Given that our research lies at the intersection of anchoring bias, decision making processes, and visual analytics systems, we designed two types of anchors, namely visual and numerical to evaluate their effects in the context of visual analytics systems. The numerical anchor is based on many psychology studies to test whether the participants can adjust away from the numerical anchor in their final answers. The visual anchor is designed specifically to prime people with different views in visual analytics interfaces with CMV design. The design of the numerical anchors is to evaluate if users are subject to anchoring bias when using visual analytics interfaces to aid decision making in a way similar to whats found by previous experiments conducted without the use of a visual analytics interface; while the design of the visual anchors is to test specifically whether users can be anchored visually and how that affects the analysis process and outcome. More specifically, we seek to answer the following research questions with respect to the impact of anchoring on decision-making activities using visual analytics systems:</p><p>• RQ1 -Visual Anchor: Can individuals be anchored on a specific view in a CMV?</p><p>• RQ2 -Numerical Anchor: Are the effects of numerical priming transferable to VA?</p><p>• RQ3 -Interaction Patterns I: How does anchoring influence the paths of interactions?</p><p>• RQ4 -Interaction Patterns II: Are there systematic differences in the interaction patterns and information seeking activities of individuals primed by different anchors?</p><p>To answer these questions, we designed and conducted a controlled experiment using a custom VA system, which is described next.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">CrystalBall -a visual analytics system used for the experiment</head><p>To study the anchoring effect during complex decision making tasks performed in a visual analytics system, we conduct the experiment with Crystalball, a visual analytics system that facilitates users in identifying future events from Twitter streams <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Detecting future events from tweets is a challenging problem as the signals of future events are often overwhelmed by the discussion of on-going events. Crystalball is designed to detect possible future events from streaming tweets by extracting multiple features and enables users to identify potentially impactful events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Analyzing large and noisy Twitter data</head><p>On average, around 500 million tweets are posted on Twitter per day by more than 300 million Twitter users <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. However, many of them discuss past and ongoing events, and news headlines. To find, identify and characterize possible future events, the Crystalball system pipeline contains multiple components, including entity extraction, event identification and a visual interface. The pipeline first extracts location and date from tweets. If the extracted date refers a future time and the extracted location is valid, then the tweet goes to the event identification component. Even if a tweet may mention a future time and valid location, it is possible that the tweet does not contain any informative content. Thus, in order to determine the quality of tweets as indicators of future events, we employ 7 measures: Normalized Pointwise Mutual Information (NPMI) of time-location pairs, link ratio, hashtag ratio, user credibility, user diversity, degree centrality and tweet similarity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Multiple Coordinated views in the CrystalBall Interface</head><p>and User Interactions <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows the Crystalball interface. The interface has 4 main views: a calendar view, map view, word cloud view and social network view. The calendar view displays a list of future events ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1A)</ref>. By default, it shows overview of future events (event overview, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1a</ref>). The event overview shows all identified events and connections among them. Circles represent identified future events. The circles are grouped by dates. Events that have a same location are connected with a solid line and events that have same keywords are connected with a dotted line. The event view shows detailed event information (event list) when the user selects a subset of the future events as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure  1b</ref>.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2A</ref>). The 5 measures are link and hashtag ratios, NPMI, user diversity and tweet similarity. Two timeline bar charts visualize distribution of tweet positing time ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2B</ref>) and the number of tweets in last 30 days ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2C)</ref>. The bottom bar chart shows average emotion scores of the tweets ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2D</ref>). Keywords that summarize tweets of the event is displayed on the right side of the view <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2E</ref>). The event can be bookmarked as favorite by clicking the star icon ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2F</ref>). The bookmarked events are stored in database so that the user can review them anytime.  The map view shows identified events on the map to indicate where they will occur ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1B</ref>). Events are aggregated based on the zoom level and are shown as rings. The color of ring proportions represent event dates ranging from tomorrow (dark blue) to more than a month (light blue). Clicking a ring will show its tweets as circles. Clicking a circle will show a tooltip showing the tweet.</p><p>There are two facilitating views to help users explore and further analyze the future events: word cloud view and social network view <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1 C and D)</ref>. The word cloud view shows keywords extracted from tweets of the identified events. The size of keywords represent frequencies of the keywords. The word cloud view is updated when selected events are changed. The social network view represents relationships between future events and Twitter users. Clusters in the view represent future events in same locations. In many cases, a cluster has several future events in a same location.</p><p>User Interactions: The highly interactive and exploratory nature of the Crystalball interface enables users to start their exploration and analysis of future events from any of the four main views present in the interface.</p><p>A user can start with the calendar view in order to know when the event will occur. Hovering the mouse over a circle in the event overview will highlight the corresponding events on the map, word cloud and social network view. The user can find events that share a same location or keywords by examining links. The user can select a particular date then the event list will be shown in the calendar view that shows all events of the date with detailed information. Other views will be automatically updated to show corresponding events in the views.</p><p>Alternatively, the user can start the analysis from the map view to make sense of where the event will occur first. The map view shows detailed evenets when zooming into a region of interest. When the zoom factor is lower than a zoom threshold, the calendar, word cloud and social network views are updated to show the events in the current map extent. The user can open the event list to show all the events in the map extent by clicking the "show events" button on the bottom right of the map view.</p><p>The interactions implemented in CrystalBall allows users to perform exploratory analysis to support decision-making tasks. Consequently, the decision making process is reflected by the actions participants take within CrystalBall. In our experiment, in order to analyze the effect of anchoring bias on a decision making task conducted in CrystalBall, we defined and logged 39 unique user interactions. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref> lists 36 user interactions, situated in their corresponding views. The rest of the 3 interactions were used rarely but our participants during their interactions with CrystalBall. The interface records all user interaction logs with a timestamp and a user's name to database which are analyzed in Section 5 in order to show users' decision making process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Design Rationale</head><p>The anchoring effect has been replicated in numerous studies in the laboratory and in the field <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. Our experiment design is thoroughly grounded in these best practices of controlled experimental studies in that we use priming to elicit the anchoring bias. First, we focused the participants experience around a well-defined cognitively engaging decision-making task -we asked participants to estimate the number of protest events in a given period of time and in a given location. We conducted our experiment with the CrystalBall interface to predict and detect protest events from Twitter data. The Calendar View and the Map View as described in Section 3.2 serve as the time and geo (visual) anchor. In order to test our hypotheses, we followed a 2×2 between-subjects factorial design with two factors (numerical and visual) and each factor had two levels as described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Experimental Stimuli</head><p>The visual and numerical anchors for the experiments were devised in order to prime the participants in two ways. The numerical anchor primed participants on a number (High or Low) and the visual anchor primed participants on a specific view in the CrystalBall interface (map view, representing geo anchor or calendar view, which represented the time anchor). The decision-making task presented to the participants is one of the four choices presented below:</p><p>Geo + high/low anchor: Do you think that the number of protest events in the state of California &lt;geo anchor first&gt; was higher or lower than 152 (or 8) &lt;high (or low) numerical an-chor&gt; between November 10, 2016 and November 24, 2016 &lt;time anchor&gt;?</p><p>Time + high/low anchor: Do you think that the number of protest events between November 10, 2016 and November 24, 2016 &lt;time anchor first&gt; was higher or lower than 152 (or 8) &lt;high (or low) numerical anchor&gt; in the state of California &lt;geo anchor&gt;?</p><p>As can be noted, the magnitude of the numerical anchor, either high or low, is subject to the experimental condition. These high and low numerical anchors were chosen based on the actual number of protest events present in the data (as determined by trained annotators). Additionally, the order of presentation of the visual anchors varies in the two questions. The visual anchors were further reinforced through custom training videos orienting the participants to the use of the CrystalBall interface. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The two training videos reinforce the visual anchors by starting and driving the analysis from either the map view (geo) or the calendar view (time).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Experiment Design</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.1">Procedures</head><p>The data collection for this study involved in-person laboratory participation. Participants were recruited via in class recruitment, email to listservs and the psychology research pool at our university. Sessions were conducted between February 10th, 2017 and March 15th, 2017. After signing up for the study, participants were assigned a unique code for secure identification. Associated with this code, was the random assignment to one of four experiment conditions (High/Geo, Low/Geo, High/Time, Low/Time). Participants were asked to come to the lab for the duration of one hour. The experimenter would first elicit their responses to informed consent. Next, the participants would view two training videos specifically designed for this experiment. The first video was a general training video (duration 5 minutes) which oriented them to the use of the Crystal Ball interface and its basic functionality (e.g., primary and  <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">High  20  21  41  Low  22  18  40  Total  42  39  81</ref> supporting interactions). This video was shown to all the participants, regardless of experimental condition. Next, the participants were shown a priming video (duration of 3 minutes) based on their visual anchoring group. The priming video was designed to guide the users through a case scenario through either Geo or Time Visual Anchors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Geo Time Grand Total</head><p>Following the training, the participants were asked to complete a pre-test questionnaire. The pre-test questionnaire consisted of questions related to participant's demographics (age, gender, education), their familiarity with visual analytics systems and social media, and Big-5 personality questions <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. The informed consent, training video and pre-test questionnaire typically took around 20 minutes to complete. The participants were then assigned the task, and asked to interact with CrystalBall for about 25 minutes. We designed and implemented interaction logging with the CrystalBall interface to capture their timestamped actions as they proceeded through the task. The interaction logging is transparent to the participants. At the end of their interaction, participants were asked to estimate the number of protest events based on their analyses within CrystalBall.</p><p>Next participants were asked to complete a post-test questionnaire. The completion of the post-test questionnaire ended their participation in the study. The post-test contained questions regarding the usability of the system (ease, attention, stimulation, likability), level of engagement during the task and questions to gauge their susceptibility to bias. The bias questions consisted of eight questions designed to measure the level of bias. Participants were compensated by either a $5 gift card or class credit assigned at the discretion of the class instructor willing to assign extra credit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.2">Participants</head><p>A total of 85 participants completed the study. We discarded the data for four participants due to usage of incorrect identification codes during the experiment. Distribution of participants across experiment conditions was relatively even and is represented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> shows a summary of the demographic characteristics of participants across factors including age, gender, education and major. We note that there is an even balance of participants across various demographic characteristics such as gender (male vs. female), age (different age ranges) and education background (computing vs. other majors), although there is some skewness in the data towards students pursuing Masters degrees. Participant demographic characteristics were also balanced across the four experiment conditions due to random assignment of participant to experiment condition. Males and females participants were uniformly distributed across experiment conditions (25% in each condition, SD = 10% for males, SD = 6% for females). Average ratio for males to females was 1.02 in each experiment condition. Average proportion of undergraduate, masters and PhD education level in each experiment condition was also 25% (SD = 13%, 10% and 24% resp.).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">EXPERIMENT RESULTS: ANALYZING QUANTITATIVE MEASURES</head><p>Two types of quantitative analyses are conducted to answer research questions RQ1 and RQ2 introduced in Section 3.1.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">RQ1 -Visual Anchor: Can individuals be anchored on a specific view?</head><p>To quantitatively evaluate whether participants can be anchored on a view in CrystalBall, we conducted two types of stastical analysis -two-way ANOVAs and Bonferroni-corrected pairwise t-tests. We extracted the overall time duration a participant spent in geo or timeoriented views from the interaction logs by taking into account the time stamp of each action occurred in a particular view. A two-way ANOVA was conducted on the influence of two independent variables (numerical and visual anchor) on the amount of time spent in different views (map vs. calendar). The main effect for visual anchor was statistically significant and had an F ratio of F(1, 78) = 11.57, p &lt; .001. The main effect for numerical anchor indicated that the effect for numerical anchoring did not significantly affect the time spent in map vs. calendar view (p &gt; 0.05). The interaction effect was not significant, F(1, 77) = 0.12, p &gt; 0.05.</p><p>Bonferroni corrected pairwise t-tests (α=0.05/4) were conducted to compare the duration of time spent in the different conditions with α=0.0125 level of significance. We found that visual anchor had significant effect on the time spent in map view vs. calendar view across both conditions (p &lt; 0.01 in both cases) whereas the numerical anchor did not (p &gt; 0.05 in both cases).</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>, we show the duration of time spent in each view for each participant across all four experimental conditions. The x-axis represents the time in minutes, with the blue bars representing duration in calender view and the black bar representing duration in map view; the y-axis are the participant ids in each condition. We see from charts labeled High/Geo and Low/Geo that participants spent significantly more time in the map view vs. the calendar view in the geo anchoring conditions. The charts labeled High/Time and Low/Time reveal that in the Time priming conditions, the time spent in each view was variable and no statistical trends can be observed. We have included four separate charts in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref> to provide sufficient comparative detail across the experiment conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">RQ2 -Numerical Anchor: Are the effects of numerical priming transferable to VA?</head><p>The effect of numerical anchor on time spent within Crystal-Ball. As reported in Section 4.1, two-way ANOVAs conducted in order to determine the effects of numerical anchoring indicated the main effect for numerical anchor did not significantly affect the time spent in map vs. calendar view (p &gt; 0.05). The interaction effect was also not significant, F(1, 77) = 0.12, p &gt; 0.05.</p><p>These findings indicate that being primed by a numerical anchor did not have an effect on the amount of time spent in map view compared to the calendar view. We discuss the implications of these findings further in the discussion section, and suggest that more investigation is needed to determine the cause of these effects.    analyzed the responses given by participants in the pre-and posttests. The participants were asked to estimate the number of protest events, before and after their interactions with the data and the interface. The findings are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>. On the x-axis we show the two groups in the numerical anchoring condition High and Low. On the y-axis are each participant's estimates regarding the number of protest events, before the interaction (in orange) and after the interaction (in red). Mean post-test responses are in black. Our findings indicate that participants were consistently anchored on initial number presented to them in the framing of the questions (p &lt; 0.05). Our findings suggest that the effects of the classic anchoring bias elicited by priming with numerical anchors in previous laboratory studies can be replicated in VA. We did not find any effects of the visual anchoring (geo vs. time) on the final outcome (t(40) = 2.02, p &gt; 0.05), suggesting that the effects of the visual anchor may be more subtle than can be determined via post-test questionnaire responses. We conducted detailed analyses to capture these effects, which we shall describe in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">EXPERIMENT RESULTS: ANALYZING INTERACTION LOGS FOR USER ACTIVITY PATTERNS</head><p>To test the hypothesis that user interaction logs reflect the participants' decision making processes, we applied two additional types of analyses on the logs in order to evaluate the impact of anchoring effect on the patterns of user interactions. The two analyses address research questions RQ3 and RQ4 (Section 3.1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">RQ3: How does anchoring effect influence the paths of interactions?</head><p>To analyze the paths users take during their analysis with Crystal-Ball and the effect of anchors on these paths, we developed a novel method to study the sequences of users interactions as a network of interaction nodes. We constructed the interaction network as follows: each interaction is logged with five attributes: time stamp of the interaction, the view it took place in, the type of interaction, and detailed description for each interaction (e.g. Each of these interactions form the nodes in a network. The edges in the network are chronological pairs of interactions. For example, if a user has zoomed on the map and then hovered on a particular location in the calendar view, this would add an edge between the Map Zoom and Calendar Location Hover nodes. The edge weight would incrementally increase for each additional observed pair. For visualization purposes, we disregarded self-loops (i.e, repeated actions) because we are more interested in the relationship between different interactions and the paths of interactions taken by our users. This method yields a weighted directed graph which enables us to cluster interactions through community detection, rank each action by multiple centrality measures and compare aggregate user path differences controlling for each anchor. The network visualizations in this section were created with Gephi <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. In this section, first we take actions of all users into account to get a complete picture of users' paths of interactions. We then analyze differences in users paths to detect different user strategies controlling for the two anchors (visual and numerical). We studied the network of all user logs, as well as our four experiment anchors. We did not find significant differences in the networks created from logs of users primed on the two numerical anchors. Hence in this discussion, we will focus on the three remaining networks: a full network (AllNetwork), a Geo-anchored network (GeoNetwork) and a Time-anchored network (TimeNetwork).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1">Analyzing the network of all interactions</head><p>By adopting an exploratory data analysis method, we started by analyzing different features of AllNetwork (39 nodes and 640 edges) ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7)</ref>. We first utilized the community detection algorithm developed by Blondel et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, which resulted in 5 different communities of interactions. Most of these communities are comprised of interactions that occur within the same view or have a close semantic relationship to each other. The community detection results allowed us to categorize nodes in our network into three main groups that were in line with our initial system design strategies: preliminary interactions, primary interactions, and supporting interactions. The primary interactions include those that users have to go through in order to find the events of interest. The supporting interactions are those that users perform in order to find supporting information to confirm the previously found events. The preliminary interactions such as login and clicking on the menu bar were used infrequently as they are not critical to the analysis process. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref> shows the network colored and annotated based on the community detection results.</p><p>In order to measure the importance of different interactions, we utilized the Pagerank algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. Since Pagerank takes into account the weight of edges between interactions, it is much more powerful than simply calculating the frequency of each interaction. Pagerank assigns probability distributions to each node denoting the importance of the node. These probability distributions are appropriate metrics for importance of the interactions in our system as they show the likelihood of a random surfer in the network to traverse to a specific end node. The top ranked interactions in our interface are all from the primary action communities with the exception of Word Hover. As seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref>, edge weights between important nodes in the same community are higher than ones between different communities. Furthermore, we can observe mutual higher weighted paths between these higher ranking interactions. Some exceptions to this observation is when the users are moving away from a view to another conduct more in depth analysis. For example, in AllNetwork, the edge between Events Location Hover to Events Location Click is weighted very strong, but the path of opposite direction is not. We can interpret Events Location Click as an interaction that drives users out of this community to others such as Word Cloud and Social Network to get complementary information of an event ( See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig 7)</ref>. The AllNetwork and the analyses resulting from it serve as a reference for the comparisons we wish to make across the GeoNetwork and TimeNetwork.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2">Comparing interaction networks of Geo-vs. Timeanchored users</head><p>To answer our research questions of whether visual anchor has an effect on the way different groups of participants interact with the visual interface, we constructed two networks based on the actions of the geo and time-anchored groups. These networks consist of the same 39 action nodes but have different edges and weights allowing us to compare the interactions of participants primed on the two visual anchors through the lens of their respective networks. Similar to our analysis of AllNetwork, we first started by detecting communities within GeoNetwork and TimeNetwork. Interestingly, the results show similar community structures to AllNetwork. However, there are subtle differences that point to the differences regarding the usage of CrystalBall between the two groups. For example, the action of Favorite Icon Click (through which users can save an event to view later in the Favorites Menu) in GeoNetwork is part of the preliminary actions community, but for TimeNetwork it is part of the Time related primary actions community. This subtle change could indicate that the time primed users had more interactions between saving an event as a favorite and then viewing the list of favorite actions in comparison to our Geo primed users.</p><p>We calculated Pagerank for interaction nodes in both these networks. Comparing these values would allow us to understand important interactions within each network and how they are affected by the visual anchor. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 8</ref> illustrates significant differences of the two networks. In the GeoNetwork, the top nodes are a mixture of interactions from the Map and Event views, with the highest ranked interaction from the Map view. This pattern is consistent with the strategies shown in the Geo priming video. In contrast, in the TimeNetwork, the top ranked nodes are interactions within the Events view and the Calendar View, which is also consistent with the strategy shown in the time-anchor video. Other important but lower ranking actions in TimeNetwork are from the Map View. Furthermore, by observing the paths between the Events community (colored purple in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 8</ref>) in both GeoNetwork and TimeNetwork, we see that weight of the edge between Events Location Hover and Events Location Click is relatively higher in the GeoNetwork in comparison to the TimeNetwork. This could indicate that our Geo primed users use maps to explore and primarily use hovering and clicking on a location together to view more details in the map, word cloud, and social network views. Our time primed users on the other hand, utilize the hovering on locations to explore events. These differences show interesting behavioral variations in sequences of interactions between our two groups. These differences show that time primed users are more likely to use the Calendar and Events view actions as their primary exploratory tool. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 8</ref> shows the comparisons between these two networks and two bar charts comparing the top 5 ranked nodes in each network.</p><p>Analyzing the interactions of our participants as a network has many benefits. It allows us to take into account the sequence of interactions, as well as the paths taken by users to arrive at the conclusion. The paths taken reflect the strategies users employ during the decision-making process. Furthermore, we can take an overview of all interactions within the CrystalBall interface and analyze what strategies need to be improved to make the interface more effective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">RQ4: Estimating the effects of anchoring bias on interaction patterns and information seeking activities</head><p>One drawback of the network analysis is that the estimated impact for each anchor is measured without standard errors to calculate the statistical significance of each result. To address this problem, we use structural topic modeling (STM) to measure the impact of the anchors and user-level attributes on users' actions <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. Originally built for text summarization, STM is a generalized topic model framework for testing the impact of document-level variables. For our model, topics are clusters of interactions measured as probability distributions over the action space. We test our hypotheses of the effect of anchoring on the topic proportions through an embedded regression-component. STM is a consolidation of three predecessor models: the correlated topic model (CTM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, the sparse additive generative model (SAGE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and the Dirichlet multinomial regression model (DMR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. The CTM model introduces a correlation structure for topic distributions while the DMR and SAGE models provide mechanisms to estimate the effect of independent variables on either topic proportions (via DMR model) or word distributions for each topic (via SAGE model). 2  the DMR (GLM regression) component. On the other hand, a disadvantage of the BoW assumption is that it ignores the order of interactions. To address this issue, we made two modifications: extracting bi-/tri-grams and creating a session time variable by interaction deciles. First, we extracted every bi-and tri-gram as chronological action pairs and triplets from the interaction logs. Including bi-and tri-grams and the single actions, we had 237 unique features after removing sparse features. Second, we created a time variable that divided each user's session into ten evenly distributed groups (interaction decile). Given that each user's session averaged nearly 800 individual actions, each decile maintained sufficient interactions to facilitate topic inference. Additionally, inclusion of the time variable had the advantage of increasing our sample size (number of documents) from 81 to 810 as the document-level went from each user to a user's interaction decile (e.g. first 10% of user X's interactions).</p><p>To test the effect of anchoring bias on users' interactions, our baseline model to explain topic proportions (dependent variable) incorporates three independent variables: the visual anchor, the numerical anchor, and time as interaction deciles. After analyzing the model, we tested other demographic attributes including gender, major, age, education level, and the Big-5 personalities. <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 2</ref> above provides a list of the independent variables tested and the categorical levels. We binned the user attributes into binary levels. Similarly, we converted the Big-5 personality results into binary levels in which users who scored above the mean were categorized as High while users who scored below the mean were categorized as Low.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">The effect of visual anchor on interaction patterns estimated by topic proportions</head><p>We find the visual anchor has a significant effect on the proportion of users' interactions as topics clustered automatically in view-based groups (e.g., map, calendar, events). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref> provides the top seven interactions for three sample topics. We observe that the interactions tend to cluster into groups related to each interaction's associated view hierarchy as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>. For example, topic 8 includes interactions related to the map view including Map Zoom, Map Pan, Map Circle Click and Map Click Cluster. Therefore, we gave topic 8 the manual label of Map View since its interactions are all related to that view. Following this approach, we created manual labels for the other seven topics. Further, we find that the topics tend to cluster in groups consistent with our network communities found in Section 5.1. For instance, the four prominent interactions of the Map View topic (by probability) have the strongest connections as well as highest PageRank in the Map View community cluster (green nodes) in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref>. Second, we find in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 9</ref> that the Map View and Flower Glyph topics had the largest topic proportions. Alternatively, the social network and word cloud were the smallest topics. To test our number of topics, we followed the procedure recommended by <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> by considering multiple topic scenarios <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40)</ref> and comparing each model's held-out likelihood and average semantic coherence. We decided on an eight topic model given a high average semantic coherence and parsimony of topics (see supplemental materials).</p><p>We observe that the visual anchor had a significant effect on the Map View and Calendar View topics. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 9</ref> provides the effect the anchors had on the topic proportions. In this plot, each dot is the estimated topic proportion difference for each topic by the two levels of each anchor. The line represents a 95% confidence interval around each estimate. From these figures, we find that the Map View and the Calendar View topic proportions have the most significant differences between the two groups. Consistent with our findings in sections 4.1 and 5.1, Geo primed users are anchored more to the view they were primed on while we see less of an effect in Time primed users. On the other hand, we found that the visual anchor had an unexpected effect with the Event List: All Tools (topic 3). Geo primed users tended to use tools like the Keyword More and Emotion Bar more than Time primed users. Alternatively, we find that the numerical anchor had only a marginal effect on two topics (Calendar View (topic 6) and Event List: All Tools (topic 3)). These results imply that the visual anchor had a more significant impact on the proportion of users' interactions than the numerical anchor. This is important as we observed opposite effect (numerical anchor was significant, visual anchor was not) in the users' estimation of the event outcome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2">The effect of visual anchor on interactions used over time estimated by topic proportions</head><p>We find evidence of a temporal effect on the topic proportions. To measure this effect, we divided each user's interaction path into interaction deciles (see Section 5.1). To aid estimation, we used a b-spline to smooth the values. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> provides the effect of the visual anchor (line color) and time (x-axis) for the Map View and Calendar View topic proportions. We observe a significant impact of the time of the user's session on this topic proportions. For example, Map View topic proportion is nearly twice during the user's first twenty percent of interactions than users' remaining 80 percent of interactions. Moreover, we see this distinct drop for both visual anchor groups. This observation implies that users tended to use the Map View more in the beginning of the session as they were getting acclimated to the interface. Alternatively, the Calendar View topic trended down resulting in much lower use by session end (15% Time, single digits Geo). We found marginal effects of time for the other six topics, with most nearly flat given already low topic proportions (less than 10%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3">The effect of demographic variables on interaction patterns estimated by topic proportions</head><p>To test other possible variables, we ran five additional model scenarios replacing the numerical anchor variable (as it showed only marginal significance) with the demographic variables (gender, major, student level and Big-5 personality). We found that none of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>: This figure provides two charts on the effect between the visual anchors (line color) and time as measured by interaction deciles (x-axis) for two topics (Map View and Calendar View). Each line is the estimated topic proportions across the session and controlling for the visual anchor. The solid line is the point estimate and the dotted line is a 95 percent confidence interval. For the interaction deciles (time), we divided users' sessions into ten evenly distributed groups. A b-spline was used to smooth the curve across the ten points.</p><p>the variables produced significant (95%) changes in topic proportions, although some produced marginally significant effects (see supplemental materials). For example, most variation occurs in the secondary view topics (Word Cloud, Social Network and an interaction topics).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">DISCUSSION AND LIMITATIONS</head><p>In this section, we provide implications of our experiment results on anchoring effect in visual analytics, and point out possible limitations related to the study design and analysis.</p><p>Experiment implications As shown by our data analysis (section 4 &amp; 5), our experimental results indicate that anchoring bias does transfer to visual analytics. Most interesting finding is that the visual anchor seems to significantly impact the decision-making process, while the numerical anchor has a significant effect on the decision-making outcome. The decision-making process reflects the way that users interact with CrystalBall; the outcome is the final answer that the participants provided at the end of the decision-making process.</p><p>Such findings have implications for user training on visual analytics systems with CMV, as well as how decision-making tasks are framed. With respect to training/tutorial, the visual analytic systems development team should provide multiple scenarios employing strategies that involve the use of different views as the primary visualization to drive the analysis. As of decision-making task framing, one should avoid accidentally anchoring the participants on an expected outcome or when possible, employ measures of cognitive bias (such as in our post-test) to evaluate the inherent cognitive bias of the users. As noted in Section §2.1, the tendency of humans to rely on heuristics to make judgments does often lead to efficient and accurate decisions. However, we need to determine when such heuristic decision-making is being applied, in order to ensure that the resulting decisions are optimal.</p><p>Experiment sample size limitation. As can be expected with any laboratory experiment, this research has limitations. One such limitation is the sample size of 81 participants in our experiment. However, the diversity of our sample with respect to gender, age, educational background and personality factors are steps we have taken to ensure the validity of our results. Our findings replicate the effects of anchoring that have been long studied in literature, further attesting to the validity of the experiment.</p><p>Experiment control limitation. Another limitation of our experiment is that we do not consider a control group , that is, participants who engage in the decision-making task without being primed by any anchors. While our initial study reported here was focused on determining whether the effects of anchoring are at all present and can be elicited in such experiments, our future work will be aimed at replicating these findings in more extensive experiments with larger sample size and will include control groups for comparison. STM analysis limitations. Fong and Grimmer <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> note that topic models are susceptible to problems in estimating marginal effects due to the zero-sum properties of topic proportions. Further, topic models cluster only based on the count and ignore interaction duration (time spent). To address such limitation, the quantitative analysis in section 4 explicitly accounted for the duration of each interaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we presented a systematic study and resulting analyses that investigate the effect of anchoring bias on decision-making processes and outcome using visual analytic systems. Our experimental results provide evidence on anchoring effect being transferable to visual analytics in that visual and numerical anchors affect the decision-making process and outcome respectively. The present study is a first step in an overarching research agenda of determining the use of heuristics in decision-making processes from the user interactions and if these decision-making processes can be reliably inferred then to automatically suggest ways in which to improve the process.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Crystalball interface: the interface has 4 main views: (A) calender view, (B) map view, (C) word cloud view, and (D) social network view. The calendar view shows the future event overview (a) by default. The event list (b) is shown when the user selects a subset of future events. The tweet panel (E) is shown when the user clicks the Twitter icon.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Event list. The flower glyph shows 5 measures of the future event and the number of tweets in the center (A). The three bar charts in the center show hourly distribution of tweet positing time (B), the number of tweets pointing to the event in last 30 days (C), and averages of emotion scores of the tweets (D). A list of keywords that summarize the tweets are displayed next to the bar charts (E). The user can bookmark the event by clicking the star icon (F).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>shows enlarged image of Figure 1b. A flower glyph visualizes 5 of 7 measures of a future events with the number of tweets in the center</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>User interaction logs: the figure displays main user interaction logs of the Crystalball interface. Each view has different interaction logs based on its visual elements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Demographic. A summary of demographic information of the participants based on gender, age, education and major.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>This figure provides a summary of the amount of time spent in calendar and map views on each of the four different conditions. The red dashed line is the mean of the amount of time spent in calendar and map view.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>The estimated number of geo-political events reported by each participant is represented by red dots. The orange line represents the anchor value and black line is the mean of estimated number of political events.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, 12:56:35.56, Calendar view, Click, Zoom 89.55 36.00). As shown in Fig 3 there are 36 main interactions as well as 3 main secondary interactions over multiple views.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>The directed network of all interactions. Nodes are interactions and edges are interactions that occur after each other. The size of nodes are proportional to Pagerank values and width of edges are proportional to the edge weights. Note, if a line is drawn between a start-node and an end-node, the outgoing edge from the start node is on the relative left side of that line.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Side by side visualization of GeoNetwork and TimeNetwork. The size of nodes is proportional to Pagerank values of nodes in each graph, the color of nodes corresponds to the detected community of each node, and the width of each edges corresponds to the weight of that edges. The bar charts show the top 5 nodes based on their Pagerank value and is color coded based the community the nodes community.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>The figure on the left provides the expected topic (action-cluster) proportions with judgmental labels to aid in interpretation. The figures on the right provide the estimated effect of the visual and numerical anchors on each of the eight topics' proportions. The dot is the point estimate and the line represents a 95 percent confidence interval. The red dots/lines are topics that are significant with 95% confidence.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Distribution of participants in 4 conditions. Row-Numerical anchor; column-Visual anchor.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The effect of numerical anchor on the decision-making outcome. To further asses the impact of numerical anchoring, we (min)</figDesc><table><row><cell>22</cell><cell cols="2">map view calendar view</cell><cell>3.87</cell><cell>8.94</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.96</cell><cell>7.23</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>6.27</cell><cell cols="2">4.88</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>4.32</cell><cell>4.46</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>s t n a p</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>i</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>c</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>i t</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>r a p</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>20</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>High/Geo</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Low/Geo</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">High/Time</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Low/Time</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Independent Variables Tested</figDesc><table><row><cell>Type</cell><cell>Independent Variable</cell><cell>Level</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>This table provides the seven actions with the highest probabilities for three sample topics: Map View, Calendar View and Event List (all tools). Action combinations (bi-or tri-grams) are denoted by the plus sign.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3">USER EXPERIMENTIn this section, we first describe our research questions and provide a detailed description of the visual analytic system used in the exper-</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Please refer to supplemental materials for the two training videos.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">We used the stm R package<ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> for our analysis. This package includes additional tools for topic modeling including a spectral initialization process that aids in addressing the multi-modality problem (stability of the results).</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Condi�on</head><p>Visual Anchor Time / Geo However, as with most topic models, STM is built from the bag-of-words (BoW) assumption that provides a key advantage and disadvantage in our analysis. The advantage is that it yields statistical properties (exchangability) that identifies topics as clusters of co-occurring interactions and facilitates statistical testing through</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.internetlivestats.com/twitter-statistics/" />
		<title level="m">Twitter usage statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2017" to="2020" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gephi: An open source software for exploring and manipulating networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bastian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Heymann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jacomy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confronting cognitive anchoring effect and blind spot biases in federal sentencing: A modest solution for reforming a fundamental flaw</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Crim. L. &amp; Criminology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">489</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A correlated topic model of science</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Blei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lafferty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Annals of Applied Statistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Latent dirichlet allocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Blei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Jordan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of machine Learning research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="993" to="1022" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast unfolding of communities in large networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Blondel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Guillaume</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lambiotte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lefebvre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of statistical mechanics: theory and experiment</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10008</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive biases and heuristics in medical decision making: a critical review using a systematic search strategy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Blumenthal-Barby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Krieger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Decision Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="557" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of anchoring bias in the equity market: Evidence from analysts earnings forecasts and stock returns</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hilary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Financial and Quantitative Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vairoma: A visual analytics system for making sense of places, times, and events in roman history</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sauda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystalball: A visual analytic system for future event discovery and analysis from social media data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">VAST</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wesslen</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">VAST</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Volkova</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">VAST</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">VAST</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">VAST</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">2017</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring context switching and cognition in dual-view coordinated visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Convertino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ryu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>North</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/CMV.2003.1215003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings International Conference on Coordinated and Multiple Views in Exploratory Visualization -CMV 2003</title>
		<meeting>International Conference on Coordinated and Multiple Views in Exploratory Visualization -CMV 2003</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human factors of the confirmation bias in intelligence analysis: Decision support from graphical evidence landscapes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Smallman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Factors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="745" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Google news personalization: scalable online collaborative filtering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Das</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Datar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Garg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rajaram</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 16th international conference on World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting>the 16th international conference on World Wide Web</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="280" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The attraction effect in information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dimara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bezerianos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dragicevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="480" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sparse additive generative models of text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Eisenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coordinated and multiple views for visualizing text collections</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Eler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Paulovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C F D</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Minghim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/IV.2008.39</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">12th International Conference Information Visualisation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="246" to="251" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Anchoring effect. Cognitive Illusions: Intriguing Phenomena in Judgement, Thinking and Memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Englich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page">223</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of treatments from text corpora</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A literature review of the anchoring effect</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Furnham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Boo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Socio-Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Countering the anchoring and adjustment bias with decision support systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Duffy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decision Support Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geovisual analytics for cyber security: Adopting the geoviz toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Giacobe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visual analytics science and technology (VAST), 2011 IEEE Conference on</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="316" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homo heuristicus: Why biased minds make better inferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gigerenzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Brighton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Topics in Cognitive Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influencing visual judgment through affective priming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Skau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Franconeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi: 10.1145/ 2470654.2481410</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, CHI &apos;13</title>
		<meeting>the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, CHI &apos;13<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2949" to="2958" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Probabilistic latent semantic indexing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 22nd annual international ACM SIGIR conference on Research and development in information retrieval</title>
		<meeting>the 22nd annual international ACM SIGIR conference on Research and development in information retrieval</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="57" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topic tracking model for analyzing consumer purchase behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Iwata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Watanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In IJCAI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1427" to="1432" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A unified approach to personalization based on probabilistic latent semantic models of web usage and content</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mobasher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AAAI 2004 Workshop on Semantic Web Personalization (SWP&apos;04)</title>
		<meeting>the AAAI 2004 Workshop on Semantic Web Personalization (SWP&apos;04)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>John</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Donahue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kentle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The big five inventoryversions 4a and 54</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A perspective on judgment and choice: mapping bounded rationality</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American psychologist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">697</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thinking, fast and slow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive coordinated multiple-view visualization of biomechanical motion data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ewert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1383" to="1390" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Görg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kohlhammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Melançon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-540-70956-57</idno>
		<title level="m">Visual Analytics: Definition, Process, and Challenges</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin Heidelberg; Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="175" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galinsky. The information-anchoring model of first offers: When moving first helps versus hurts negotiators</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Loschelder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Trötschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Swaab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Friese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">995</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visual analytics and uncertainty: Its not about the data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Maceachren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of particle interactions in granular media</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Meier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schlemmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kerren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Steinmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1110" to="1125" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Topic models conditioned on arbitrary features with dirichlet-multinomial regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mimno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mccallum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1206.3278</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for cognitive bias detection and feedback in a visual analytics environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nussbaumer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Verbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E.-C</forename><surname>Hillemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bedek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dietrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the European Intelligence and Security Informatics Conference</title>
		<meeting>the European Intelligence and Security Informatics Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The pagerank citation ranking: Bringing order to the web</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Motwani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Winograd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<pubPlace>Stanford InfoLab</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zooming versus multiple window interfaces: Cognitive costs of visual comparisons</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Plumlee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/1165734.1165736</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans. Comput.-Hum. Interact</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">State of the art: Coordinated multiple views in exploratory visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/CMV.2007.20</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fifth International Conference on Coordinated and Multiple Views in Exploratory Visualization (CMV 2007)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="71" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model of text for experimentation in the social sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Airoldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">515</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="988" to="1003" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">stm: R package for structural topic models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tingley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>R package version 1.2.1, 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural topic models for open-ended survey responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tingley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leder-Luis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gadarian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Albertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Political Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1064" to="1082" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of uncertainty, awareness, and trust in visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sacha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Senaratne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Big data: Unleashing information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Systems Science and Systems Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Judgment under uncertainty: Heuristics and biases</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Utility, probability, and human decision making</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="162" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiple-criteria decision making: concepts, techniques, and extensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-L</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Springer Science &amp; Business Media</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
