<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Usability Log Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
							<email>mark.gray@cc.gatech.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology Atlanta</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30332-0280</postCode>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Albert</forename><surname>Badre</surname></persName>
							<email>badre@cc.gatech.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology Atlanta</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30332-0280</postCode>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mark</forename><surname>Guzdial</surname></persName>
							<email>guzdial@cc.gatech.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Georgia Institute of Technology Atlanta</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>30332-0280</postCode>
									<region>GA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Usability Log Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T18:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Our approach to testing graphical user integaces involves logging large amounts of data. These logs capture information at the key press and mouse click level about how an application is used. Since the raw data is voluminous and not at a useful level of detail, we use analysis and visualization to find information that is interesting and useful to a usability analyst but was previously buried in the data. We call some of our custom visualizations &quot;contextual&quot; meaning they use key elements of the context the data was collected in as an organizing structure. We expect this type of .visualization to be easier and faster to understand and more helpful than traditional charts. We hope that our finding a natural geometry for these visualizations will inspire others whose data apparently has no inherent geometry to find natural ways to visualize their data.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction to Usability Testing</head><p>Usability testing is an attempt to discover what difficulties people will have using a new system. If testing is done well, it can suggest what parts of a system should be changed before deployment. We are trying to improve the usability testing process for computer software. Currently the testing process involves inviting or hiring people who are similar to those expected to use the software. These outside participants are usually given a set of tasks to complete that will test key parts of the software.</p><p>During the test session, participants are observed and often videotaped. Recorded video of the computer screen shows which interface events occurred and the context (the state of the program and the phase of use) in which they occurred. Adding video tape of the user expands the amount of context available and can provide more insights into the user's strategy, indicating how and why an interface is misunderstood. Serious usability problems that prevent some participants from completing the given tasks might be easily detected and understood even without viewing the recorded video, but pinpointing causes of more subtle problems that only cause minor confusion or only slow down the completion of tasks may require more careful study of the video. Whenever it illustrates any usability problem, video is valuable because it can help convince those responsible that a change is required.</p><p>Unfortunately, video tapes are cumbersome and tedious to use. Much time is wasted when a usability expert watches uninteresting parts of a video while searching for the critical parts. <ref type="bibr">[Badre 951</ref> This indicates that although context and events are both captured by video, it can be difficult to find particular events. We address this problem in two ways, both of which use automated event logs. First, we can use these logs to index video, allowing a usability analyst to find interesting footage more quickly. This paper concentrates on our other use of event logs: creating "big picture" visualizations that capture important aspects of an entire session in one image.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Logging Interface Events</head><p>Our extension to usability testing requires that a log of events occurring on the computer be capturedl in addition to normal video taping. Others have used event logging in usability testing before. <ref type="bibr">[Bleser 82,</ref><ref type="bibr">Good 85,</ref><ref type="bibr">Olsen 881</ref>  <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> is a sample from a low-level log file. With the current logging tool all interface events, or any selected set of event types, are recorded. Both events caused directly by the person (mouse movements and clicks, keyboard presses) and the computer's responses (changes occurring on the screen) can be important.</p><p>One of our visualizations, inspired by Eick et. al. in SeeSoft and pictured in figure 1, can be constructed without detailed analysis. <ref type="bibr">[Eick 941</ref> In an attempt to find usage patterns that we were previously unaware of, this visualization takes as input any log file and creates a striped bar visualization. This vertical bar is made of</p><p>We have created programs that collect such logs on Macintosh, UnidX-windows, and Microsoft Windows. Our analysis and visualization work has been done on a combination of these three platforms, but current development is mainly under Microsoft Windows '95. 0-8186-7668-X/96 $5.00 0 1996 IEEE horizontal stripes. The top stripe of the bar represents the In the example in figure 1, log files that were created by first event and lower stripes represent later events.</p><p>the application being studied are displayed. If an Stripes are colored according to any attribute of the application generates its own activity log as it runs (a events (the type of event, which window the event common practice during application development) our occurred in, etc.) By default all stripes are drawn the tools can use those logs if they contain time stamps and same height and width. Alternatively, the height of each some sort of event type. During this log, two windows were created, the second inside the first, the second was maximized (made large), then it received focus, then the user scrolled through that window copying ("C) and pasting ("V) text.</p><p>Time is how many seconds (or milliseconds) have passed since the log started. Window ID is the window system's handle for the window affected. Some events affect two windows, so Other Window is the parent window for Create events and the window losing focus for SetFocus events. Data varies by event type. X and Y are screen coordinates. Six short sessions with a key to the colors. Pattems such as "all sessions end with Logout" and "all sessions start with one or more Visits" are easy to see when viewed in color.</p><p>Once events of interest are located in a log file, the corresponding segment of video tape is known because time code recorded on the video tape is synchronized with the log file. Using a video tape machine controlled by the computer, the tape can be automatically wound to the correct time. Another option is to record the video digitally in a computer file. This option is appealing because it allows very fast random access to the video, bypassing tedious waiting for tape winding. Unfortunately, although high quality digital video will be inexpensive some day, current storage requirements (compressed video requires several megabytes per minute) and quality (not as good as high-end video tape) make it undesirable to keep only a digital copy of usability sessions, though it is certainly feasible to keep a digital copy of a session while it is being analyzed.</p><p>If it is not possible to record video of a session, the level of detail in the log file is sufficient to reconstruct an approximate image of the screen at any time during the logged session. This capability would be most useful if the monitoring software were installed on a computer outside the usability lab. In this case, a testing participant might use the software in the course of actual work, generating real-world usage information. If privacy concerns can be overcome, this method could be used to gather large amounts of useful event log data cheaply. Even with this capability it is still desirable to record actual video of sessions whenever possible because reconstructed images can, of course, never capture events occurring outside the computer such as interruptions or reading of documentation. Also, as noted above, actual video of people having trouble using software is quite helpful in convincing developers that a usability problem is serious and should be fixed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Analysis</head><p>In addition to using logged events as indices into video, we perform several analyses on the log files and attempt to visualize and understand the meaning of the results. The results of many of our analyses and visualizations can themselves be used as indices into video tape of sessions. Beyond their use as indices, analyses and visualizations are the most promising ways of bringing insight into what occurred during the test sessions because they provide useful summaries that can be viewed far more quickly than a session's video.</p><p>Numerical analyses of log files can result in numerical answers like performance time per task, mouse movement distances, command frequencies, and command pair frequencies. <ref type="bibr">[Olsen 881</ref> A simple frequency analysis calculates how many times each type of event occurred in the time period of interest. A usability analyst is likely to want to know which advanced features were ever used or such data as how many times help was requested compared with how much typing was accomplished. An analysis of which events were most common just before or just after requesting help is also possible and can be enlightening.</p><p>A pairing analysis produces a frequency-ordered list of every pair of events that occurs sequentially in the log. This shows which action combinations are most used and may suggest combining some pairs of actions into single actions or at least making sure that frequently paired actions are physically and logically near one another for efficiency and ease of use. Another analysis divides low-level user-generated events into keyboard and mouse events and notes when events from each source occur so it can find how often the user moves a hand from the keyboard to the mouse and back. Each move takes some time, so frequent moving wastes time and indicates either a poor interface design or an inefficient strategy being employed by the user.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Visualization</head><p>In our experience, visualization can summarize many numbers neatly in one picture, highlight unusual parts of the data, and sometimes show meaningful patterns in the data that would have been difficult or impossible to find without visualization. <ref type="bibr">[Guzdial 941</ref> Any results of numerical analysis can be shown as numbers, but it is often possible to improve comprehension by creating some sort of picture to display the result. For a frequency analysis, a traditional presentation is a line graph of frequency over time. This gives a quick feeling for whether the hand switching (or other behavior) is occurring only during one phase of program use or uniformly over the whole session. Any visualization that, like such line graphs, uses one axis for time, has the advantage that it can provide point-and-click indexing to the video recording.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Long-Term Visualization</head><p>For long term logging of more than a week, a calendar-oriented timeline visualization is being developed as pictured in figure 2. This view allows comparison of activity between hours of the day, days of the week, and weeks of a month all in one image. This example shows frequency of sending email for a large group of people in the College of Computing at Georgia Tech. We expect to use this tool to visualize long term logging of other applications, particularly as part of usability testing. Interesting sociological points can be found in this sort of graph. Email activity was unusually low Jan 1 and 15 (campus was closed), some activity happens even on weekends, and more email per hour is sent between midnight and 3am than between 5am and 7am. (People here are more likely to stay very January 1996</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sun</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mon Tue</head><p>Wed Thu</p><p>Fri Sat dimension to encode frequency of use, either in place of or in addition to the use of shading. In a three dimensional version, frequently used parts of the interface would become mountains protruding from the dane of the interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2: Calendar Timeline</head><p>For viewing long-term log files late than arrive very early. It is worth noting that if this type of analysis were focused on individual people, privacy would be a serious concern.) As this tool is developed further we may try to incorporate the official weekly calendar of events, increasing the amount of context available. Different types of data from the same period of time could be overlaid on the same graph. We may also explore overlaying data from more than one day, week, or month in the same space for easier comparisons. Studies of computer use over long periods of time are rare because they are typically expensive and logistically difficult. <ref type="bibr">[Kay 951</ref> We hope that providing automatic logging and useful visualization and analysis software will make such studies more possible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Contextual Visualization</head><p>Some of our contextual visualizations are inspired by thematic maps. Such maps are frequently seen displaying information such as county-by-county analyses of causes of death. Similar maps used in election coverage show at a glance which states have cast their votes for which candidate. An example of a contextual visualization in the user interface domain is figure 3 where relative frequency of use of different buttons and other GUI controls is displayed by creating a rendition of the interface where frequently used controls are colored darker. This type of visualization, including the window structure, can be rendered totally automatically from information recorded in a typical log file. If more quantitative results are important, frequency numbers can be added to the visualization. We plan to create similar visualizations that use a third Our contextual displays generally do not replicate the application interface in full color because we prefer to leave the color dimension free to encode usage information. Just as maps colored to show geographic distribution of population statistics generally eliminate unrelated information such as topological detail, we remove distracting details from the interface and use the layout to organize the presentation of information. When not using color in a visualization it is possible to use color bitmaps of the controls from the interface. It is also possible to integrate the display of relative screen position of controls with display of their pattern of use by automatically augmenting the display with arrows overlaid on the interface as shown in figure 4. The arrows in this visualization currently indicate the path followed during a particular session. In future versions they will be able to be drawn to show the most frequent transitions as in a Markov chart. Thicker or darker arrows could be used to indicate the more frequent paths found in testing with many users and/or over a long period of time. The most frequently used paths should be examined visually. Layout might need to be changed if the flow of a common path is not rightto-left, top-to-bottom. Even when a straightforward path is followed frequently, a change may be suggested by the data. If users always have to change a particular option, for example, then changing that option's default value could make the interface more efficient.</p><p>We expect that contextual visualizations will allow fast, accurate interpretation because it is easier to pick out salient features and more subtle patterns in the context of a familiar interface. Just as <ref type="bibr">Bransford and Franks (and Johnson)</ref> found that contextual knowledge is necessary for comprehending prose passages and helpful for recall, <ref type="bibr">[Bransford 721</ref> we believe that visualizations which include key elements of the context the data was gathered in should improve comprehension and memorability. Deciding what the key elements of the context are is similar to the selection of a metaphor for a new user interface. It is good to choose a representation the user will recognize from his or her present knowledge and it is necessary to choose a representation that can convey the necessary information. For usability testing the necessary information includes such measures as frequency and patterns of use as described above. The sort of pattern one is looking for greatly influences the requirements of a visualization. Looking at aggregated information about frequency and order of use of dialog box controls is supported by the type of visualization pictured in the previous two figures. Looking at menu use should be handled a little differently since menus are laid out differently than dialog boxes. Menu use statistics are displayed in the context of a reconstruction of the menu structure being tested. The application's menus are reconstructed across the top of a window to appear as they did while the application was running. Below each menu is a vertical bar whose length is proportional to the logged usage of that menu. The effect is an inverted bar chart. Additionally, each bar is divided into segments, each of which corresponds to usage of a menu item within the menu. Some of the text of each menu item can be included in the visualization and clicking on a bar segment pops up its full name and keyboard shortcut. Unused menu items can be included as small black segments with white labels. This display allows at least a qualitative comparison that shows whether items toward the top of each menu are used more than those toward the bottom as one would hope for efficiency of motion. Adding keyboard shortcuts should be considered for frequently used items without shortcuts. Menu items (or any other controls) that remain unused during extensive realworld use either indicate unneeded functionality which should be eliminated or poorly labeled controls which should be made clearer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Future Work</head><p>We have several ideas for improvements to the visualizations we have discussed, including adding three dimensional components and more interactivity. Our next major focus will be on conducting experiments comparing our contextual visualizations with standard statistical charts such as bar and line graphs. We plan to use both students and interface designers to determine which techniques are best in terms of eliciting fast and accurate interpretations of the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Our approach to usability analysis brings us a large quantity of time-varying data. From this data we want to find answers to questions posed in terms of usability. The current medium used to record usability tests, taped video, is good at providing context and details of test sessions, but it is a linear medium that does not provide for effective searching or big-picture overviews. We use event logging as an index for searching through the video and as a means of collecting data for analyses and visualizations which provide unrivaled summaries that can, at a glance, bring greater understanding of important features of the collected data. We feel that using some the context the data was collected in as a guide for creating visualizations has great promise for usability testing and for other visualization tasks.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Color Bar Visualization</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>prienlalian ....; ................... . ,......... . Grayscale Control Usage Visualization More frequently used controls are colored darker</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Arrows Showing Pattern of Use Arrows indicate the order in which controls were used during a test session.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Menu UseTaller bars indicate more frequently used menus.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Sample Log File Fragment</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This set of tools draws inspiration from CHIME developed by Paulo Santos. Jay J. Yan programmed the calendar visualization and Ken Griggs programmed the Windows '95 version of the logging tool.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Badre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guzdial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A user interface evaluation environment using synchronized video, visualizations and event trace data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Software Quality Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bleser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards Specifying and Evaluating the Human Factors of User-Computer Interfaces</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Human Factors in Computer Systems</title>
		<meeting>Human Factors in Computer Systems</meeting>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Contextual Prerequisites for Understanding: Some Investigations of Comprehension and Recall</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bransford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="743" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical Analysis of Computer Log Files</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Eick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Use of Logging Data in the Design of a New Text Editor</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Good</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
			<biblScope unit="page">85</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conference Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="97" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guzdial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analyzing and Visualizing Log Files: A Computational Science of Usability. Presented at HCI Consortium Workshop</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studying Long-Term System Use</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-07-38" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interface Usage Measurements in a User Interface Management System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Olsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Halversen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH Symposium on User Interface Software</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGGRAPH Symposium on User Interface Software</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="110" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
