<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Finding Comparable Temporal Categorical Records: A Similarity Measure with an Interactive Visualization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Krist</forename><surname>Wongsuphasawat</surname></persName>
							<email>kristw@cs.umd.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science &amp; Human-Computer Interaction</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lab University of Maryland</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20742</postCode>
									<settlement>College Park</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ben</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science &amp; Human-Computer Interaction</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lab University of Maryland</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20742</postCode>
									<settlement>College Park</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Finding Comparable Temporal Categorical Records: A Similarity Measure with an Interactive Visualization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Similan, M&amp;M Measure, Similarity Search, Temporal Categorical Records H.5.2 [Information Interfaces and Presentation]: User Interfaces-Graphical user interfaces (GUI)</term>
					<term>I.5.3 [Pattern Recognition]: Clustering-Similarity measures</term>
					<term>H.3.3 [Information Storage and Retrieval]: Information Search and Retrieval-Search process</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>An increasing number of temporal categorical databases are being collected: Electronic Health Records in healthcare organizations, traffic incident logs in transportation systems, or student records in universities. Finding similar records within these large databases requires effective similarity measures that capture the searcher&apos;s intent. Many similarity measures exist for numerical time series, but temporal categorical records are different. We propose a temporal categorical similarity measure, the M&amp;M (Match &amp; Mismatch) measure, which is based on the concept of aligning records by sentinel events, then matching events between the target and the compared records. The M&amp;M measure combines the time differences between pairs of events and the number of mismatches. To accommodate customization of parameters in the M&amp;M measure and results interpretation, we implemented Similan, an interactive search and visualization tool for temporal categorical records. A usability study with 8 participants demonstrated that Similan was easy to learn and enabled them to find similar records, but users had difficulty understanding the M&amp;M measure. The usability study feedback, led to an improved version with a continuous timeline, which was tested in a pilot study with 5 participants.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Various organizations are increasingly collecting temporal categorical data. Electronic Health Records (EHRs) are being collected by leading health organizations. These EHRs contain millions of records with patient histories. Transportation systems are being monitored at an unprecedented scope which is resulting in gigantic traffic incident logs. Academic institutes are also keeping track of educational advancement of their students. Challenges arise when there is a need to find similar records within these large-scale databases. For example, clinicians want to find patients with similar symptoms to a target patient in order to guide the treatment of the target patient. A major challenge of this problem is defining similarity measures for temporal categorical data.</p><p>Many methods for computing a similarity measure between time series have been proposed. However, modifying them to suit temporal categorical data remains an open problem. This paper presents a temporal categorical similarity measure called the M&amp;M measure, which is based on aligning temporal data by sentinel events <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, then matching events between two records. If the events are identical between records, then the M&amp;M measure is the sum of the distances (time difference) between the matched pairs. A lower distance represents higher similarity.</p><p>The problem becomes more complex when the set of events in the target record does not exactly match those in another record. To accommodate unmatched events, we convert this into an assignment problem and use the Hungarian Algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> to match events that produce the minimum distance. Consequently, the M&amp;M measure is redefined as a combination of the number of mismatches and the distance.</p><p>Furthermore, we believe that an interactive user interface will provide help in finding and understanding results. We developed an interactive interface, Similan, that allows users to adjust parameters of the M&amp;M measure and see the results in real time. (See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1.</ref>) Similan adopts the alignment concept from LifeLines2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and allows users to preprocess the dataset by aligning events by a sentinel event. Similan displays all events in a timeline for each record. Our extension to the rank-by-feature framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> allows users to select a target record and then adjust the ranking criteria to explore the impact of result order.</p><p>Records are simultaneously visualized on a coordinated scatterplot according to the number of mismatches and the distance function. The comparison panel provides more advanced exploration. When users select one record for a detailed comparison with the target record, they see links between events, enabling them to understand how close the relationship is.</p><p>This paper is organized as follows: Section 2 covers the relevant history of similarity searching, temporal data visualization and related areas. Section 3 provides a brief explanation of the M&amp;M measure. Section 4 introduces Similan and describes the user interface. Section 5 explains the M&amp;M measure in more details. Section 6 describes a usability study done to evaluate the interface. We follow by a brief discussion about the new version in Section 7, describe future work in Section 8, and conclude in Section 9.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>A growing body of recent work is focused on similarity searching, mainly in the medical domain. For example, the national health insurance system in Australia records details on medical services and claims provided to its population. Tsoi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> proposed a method to classify patients from medical claims data into various groups. Their aim is to detect similar temporal behavioral patterns among patients in the dataset. PatientsLikeMe <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> is an online community where patients with life-altering diseases share and discuss personal health experiences. Users enter their structured data on symptoms, treatments, and health outcomes into the site. This information is rendered as data visualizations on both an individual and an aggregate level. Users can also search for similar patients by specifying demographic information. Unlike PatientsLikeMe, this work focuses on a sequence of events (symptoms, treatments, and outcomes) in patient records, which is a special type of time series called temporal categorical data. Users can start by double-clicking to select a target record from the main panel. Similan will calculate a score that indicates how similar to the target record each record is and show scores in the color-coded grid on the left. The score color-coding bars on the right show how the scores are color-coded. The users then can sort the records according to these scores. The main panel also allows users to visually compare a target with a set of records. In this early prototype, the timeline is binned (by year, in this screenshot). If the users want to make a more detailed comparison, they can click on a record to show the relationship between that record and the target record in the comparison panel on the top. The plot panel at the bottom shows the distribution of records. In this example, the user is searching for students who are similar to Student 01. The user sets Student 01 as the target and sorts all records by total score. Student 18 has the highest total score of 0.92 so this suggests that Student 18 is the most similar student. Student 41 and Student 18 both have one missing paper submission but Student 41 has a lower match score so Student 18 has higher total score. . The numbers of events in each category are displayed in the label. By clicking on the colored squares users can customize color. Users can choose to align events by selecting a sentinel category (middle). Weight for calculating total score can be adjusted using sliders and textboxes (right). Links in the comparison panel can be filtered using these parameters.</p><p>A time series is a sequence of data values, measured at successive times, spaced at (often uniform) intervals. One notation is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">X = {(t, v) | t ∈ Time}</formula><p>Temporal categorical data, e.g. athlete injuries, is one type of time series. However, unlike the numerical time series, e.g. stock indices, every v is not a numerical value (1, 2.9, 3.5, ...), but a category ("Jammed finger", "Broken leg", etc.). For temporal categorical data, we will call each (t, v) an event. The i-th event in the sequence is denoted by x i .</p><p>Stock Indices (Numerical) Injuries (Categorical) (10/8/07, 540.35) (10/18/07, "Jammed finger") (10/9/07, 555.32) (11/10/07, "Broken leg") ...</p><p>... (12/1/07, 410.94) (12/31/08, "torn ACL")</p><p>Many similarity measures between numerical time series have been proposed. According to the surveys of previous methods by Ding et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and Saeed and Mark <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> , similarity measures for time series can be grouped into various types.</p><p>The first type is lock-step measures, which compare the i-th point of one time series (x i ) to the i-th point of another (y i ). The most straightforward measure is the Euclidean distance. However, since the mapping between the points of two time series is fixed, these distances measures are sensitive to noise and misalignments in time.</p><p>Second, elastic measures are distance measures that allow comparison of one-to-many points (e.g., Dynamic time warping (DTW)) and one-to-many / one-to-none points (e.g., Longest Common Substring (LCSS)). DTW <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> is an algorithm for measuring similarity between two sequences which may vary in time or speed with certain restrictions. The sequences are "stretched" or "compressed" non-linearly in the time dimension to provide a better match with another time series. DTW is particularly suited to matching sequences with missing information. However, DTW requires monotonicity of the mapping in the time dimension.</p><p>Another group of similarity measures are developed based on the concept of the edit distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, the number of operations required to transform one string into another string. The lower the number is, the more similar the strings are. Hamming distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, Levenshtein distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> or Jaro-Winkler distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> are some examples. The best known such distance is the LCSS distance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> Another related area is biological sequence searching. There exist many algorithms for comparing biological sequence information, such as the amino-acid sequences of different proteins or the nucleotides of DNA sequences. Some examples of these algorithms are BLAST <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, FASTA <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> and the TEIRESIAS algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</p><p>The transform-based techniques project time series onto a set of functions such as sinusoids or principal components. The data transformation reduces the dimensionality of the original time series and facilitates the use of machine learning techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> or other methods in matching time series.</p><p>However, most of the existing methods are designed for numerical time series and require v to be a numerical value. This motivates the need of a similarity measure for temporal categorical data (when v is a category). The M&amp;M measure is then proposed to support this type of data. The M&amp;M measure is also different from existing approaches in other aspects. It is different from lock-step measures because it does not fix the mapping of i-th events together. Unlike elastic measures, it does not allow one-to-many but allows one-to-none mapping. It is also not limited to monotonicity of the mapping as in DTW. It is different from edit distances and biological sequence searching because the data is sampled at non-uniform intervals and more than one event can occur at the same time while two characters or amino acids cannot occur at the same position in the string or biological sequence.</p><p>The first step of the M&amp;M measure is to match every event (t, v) in the target record with an event from the compared record. New challenges arise since there are many possible ways to match events but the M&amp;M measure requires matching which will yield the maximum similarity. This problem can be reduced to a problem called the assignment problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, which is described as follows <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>:</p><p>"There are a number of agents and a number of tasks. Any agent can be assigned to perform any task, incurring some cost that may vary depending on the agent-task assignment. It is required to perform all tasks by assigning exactly one agent to each task in such a way that the total cost of the assignment is minimized."</p><p>If the numbers of agents and tasks are equal and the total assignment cost for all tasks is equal to the sum of the costs for each agent, then the problem is called the linear assignment problem. When the assignment problem has no additional qualifications, the term linear assignment is used. If there are n tasks, the Hungarian algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref> can solve the assignment problem in polynomial time (O(n 3 )). The first version, known as the Hungarian method, was invented by Kuhn <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. After Munkres <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> revised the algorithm, it has been known as the Hungarian algorithm, the Munkres assignment algorithm, or the Kuhn-Munkres algorithm. Later, Bertsekas <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> proposed a new and more efficient algorithm for the assignment problem.</p><p>Using an absolute time scale alone does not address all of the tasks users face when comparing temporal categorical data. In particular, tasks that involve temporal comparisons relative to important events such as a heart attack are not supported. Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> proposed a concept of aligning temporal data by sentinel (important) events, e.g. heart attack. The time in each record is then recomputed, referenced from the time that the sentinel event in each record occurs. Making time at which the sentinel event, the events before the sentinel event and the events after the sentinel event occur become zero, negative and positive, respectively. Before applying the similarity measure, Similan allows users to preprocess the data by aligning them by sentinel events.</p><p>Seo and Shneiderman <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> presented a conceptual framework for interactive feature detection named rank-by-feature framework. In the rank-by-feature framework, users can select an interesting ranking criterion, and then all possible axis-parallel projections of a multidimensional data set are ranked by the selected ranking criterion. Similan, inspired by this rank-by-feature idea, allows users to rank the dataset by many criteria derived from the M&amp;M measure.</p><p>In order to facilitate the result interpretation, the data records should be visualized in a meaningful way. Ma et al. proposed Event Miner, a tool that integrates data mining and visualization for analysis of temporal categorical data. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> However, Event Miner was designed for analyzing only one record. Pattern Finder <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> is an integrated interface for visual query and result-set visualization for search and discovery of temporal patterns. There has been a number of published visualization works on temporal categorical data on timelines. A design using timelines for medical records was proposed by Powsner and Tufte <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, who developed a graphical summary using a table of individual plots of test results and treatment data. LifeLines <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> presented personal history record data organized in expandable facets and allowed both point event and interval event representations. Alonso et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>'s experiment to compare a tabular format and the LifeLines representation suggested that overall LifeLines led to much faster response times and can reduce some of the biases of the tabular format. However, their design does not assist comparison between records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">INTRODUCTION TO THE M&amp;M MEASURE</head><p>We define a new similarity measure for temporal categorical records called M&amp;M (Match &amp; Mismatch).</p><p>The first step of the M&amp;M measure is to match the events in the target record with events in the compared records. Since there can be many possible ways to match the events between the two records, we define an event matching process for the M&amp;M measure, which will be explained in Section 5. After the matching is done, the M&amp;M measure is a combination of two measures:</p><p>The first measure, match score, is for the matched events, events which occur both in the target record and the compared record. It captures the time difference between events in the target record and the compared record.</p><p>The second measure, mismatch score, is for missing or extra events, events which occur in the target record but do not occur in the compared record, or vice versa. It is based on the difference in number of events in each category between the two records.</p><p>Match and mismatch score are combined into total score, ranging from 0.01 to 1.00. For all three scores, a higher score represents higher similarity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">SIMILAN INTERFACE DESIGN</head><p>Given two temporal categorical records, the M&amp;M measure returns a score which represents the similarity between that pair of records. However, the score alone does not help the users understand why records are similar or dissimilar. Also, the M&amp;M measure can be adjusted by several parameters. Furthermore, one of the users' goals is to find the similar records from a database, which contains multiple records. Hence, a tool to assist the users to understand the results, customize the parameters, and perform a similarity search in a database is needed. To address these issues, Similan was developed to provide a visualization of the search results to help the users understand the results, and an interface that facilitates the search and parameter customization. Similan is written in C# .NET using the Piccolo.NET <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> visualization toolkit. The key design concept of Similan follows the Information Visualization Mantra <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> : overview first, zoom and filter, details on demand.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Overview</head><p>Similan consists of 4 panels: main, comparison, plot and control, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. Users can start from selecting a target record from the main panel. After that, the main and plot panels give an overview of the similarity search result. Filtering and ranking mechanisms help users narrow down the search result. Users then can focus on fewer records. By clicking on a particular record, the comparison panel shows relationships between that record and the target record on demand. Moreover, mouse hovering actions on various objects provide details on demand in the form of tooltips. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Events and Timeline</head><p>Colored squares are used to represent events. Each color represents a category. Users can customize the colors and check the checkboxes in the control panel ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>) to select interesting categories. The number of events in each category is displayed behind the category name.</p><p>Similan's timeline is not a continuous timeline but divided into bins. The bin interval is automatically calculated by the size of application window and total time range of the data. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, the timeline is divided into years (05, 06, 07, 08). In each bin, events are grouped by category and categories are placed in the same order. Maintaining the same order allows visual comparison between records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Main Panel</head><p>Each record is vertically stacked on alternating background colors and identified by its name on the left (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). Ranking scores (more details in Section 4.5) appear on the left hand side before the name. Events appear as colored squares on the timeline. By default all records are presented using the same absolute time scale (with the corresponding years or month labels displayed at the top) and the display is sized so that the entire date range fits in the screen.</p><p>A double-click on any record marks that record as a target record. A target mark will be placed in front of the target record instead of a ranking score. Clicking on any record selects that record as a compared record. Both the target record and compared record will be highlighted. Users can move the cursor over colored squares to see details on demand in the form of tooltips. Also, zooming on the horizontal axis and panning are possible using a range slider provided at the bottom of the main panel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Alignment</head><p>Users can select a sentinel category from a drop-down list as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>. By default, the sentinel category is set to none. When the sentinel category is selected, the time scale will change from an absolute time, i.e. real time, into a relative time. The sentinel event becomes time zero and is highlighted <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Figure 4</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Rank-by-feature</head><p>Similan is inspired by the idea of rank-by-feature from Hierarchical Clustering Explorer (HCE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. These following ranking criteria are derived from the M&amp;M measure proposed in this paper.</p><p>1. Total Score ranging from 0.01 to 1.00</p><p>Total score is the final output of the M&amp;M measure. It is a weighted sum of match and mismatch score. The weight can be adjusted and users can see the result in real-time ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>).</p><p>2. Match Score ranging from 0.01 to 1.00 This is a score derived from the distance (time difference) between matched events. We choose to display match score instead of distance because the distance is a large number, so it can be difficult to tell the difference between two large numbers and understand the distribution.</p><p>3. Number of Mismatches (#Mismatch) ranging from 0 to n This is the total number of missing and extra events compared to the target record. The #mismatch is shown instead of the mismatch score because it is more meaningful to the users. Furthermore, we break down the #mismatch into categories.</p><p>Positive and negative values correspond to the number of extra and missing events, respectively.</p><p>Users can click on the ranking criteria on the top of the main panel to sort the records. By clicking on the same criteria once more, the order is reversed. A triangle under the header shows current ranking criterion. Legends in the control panel show the range of each ranking score and how they are color-coded. (See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.6">Plot Panel</head><p>In addition to displaying results as a list in the main panel, Similan also visualizes the results as a scatterplot in the plot panel <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1)</ref>. Each record is represented by a "+" icon. Horizontal axis is the match score while vertical axis is the number of mismatches (#mismatch). Records in the bottom-left area are records with high match score and low number of mismatches, which should be considered most similar according to the M&amp;M measure.</p><p>Moving the cursor over the + icon will trigger a tooltip to be displayed. Clicking on a + will set that record to be the compared record and scroll the main panel to that record. Users can also draw a region on the scatterplot to filter records. The main panel will show only records in the region. Clicking on the plot panel again will clear the region and hence clear the filter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.7">Comparison Panel</head><p>The comparison panel is designed to show similarity and difference between the target record and the compared record. Lines are drawn between pairs of events matched by the M&amp;M measure. Line style is used to show the distance value. Strong links, or links with short distance, are shown as solid lines. Weak links, or links with large distance, are shown as dashed lines. Events without any links connected to them are missing or extra events. Users can adjust the distance threshold for strong links in the control panel. (See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2.</ref>) Moving the cursor over a link will display a tooltip showing the event category, time of both events and distance.</p><p>Furthermore, users can filter the links by using the filters <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2)</ref>. Users can filter by setting the minimum and/or maximum distance. By selecting link types, only the selected types are displayed. Strong links are links with a distance in the range specified by the slider. Forward Links are links which are not strong links and the event in target record occurs before the event in compared record while Backward Links are the opposite.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">M&amp;M (MATCH &amp; MISMATCH) MEASURE IN DETAILS</head><p>This section explains how we define the M&amp;M measure. Our base idea is that similar records should have the same events and the same events should occur almost at the same time. Therefore, the M&amp;M measure uses the time difference and number of missing and extra events as the definition of similarity.</p><p>The notation below is used to describe a temporal categorical record, which is a list of temporal categorical events (t, c). The i-th event in the record is denoted by x i or (t i , c i ). X = {(t, c) | t ∈ Time and c ∈ Categories}</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Event Matching Process</head><p>The first step of our approach is to match the events in the target record with events in the compared record. There can be many possible ways to match the events into pairs. Therefore, we define a distance function based on a sum of time difference to guide the matching. The matching which produces the minimum distance (time difference) will be selected. Note that the distance from the M&amp;M distance function is not the final result of the M&amp;M measure, but only part of it. This distance is later converted to a match score.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1">M&amp;M Distance Function</head><p>We first define a distance function between each pair of events, as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">d((t, c), (u, d)) = |t − u| if c = d ∞ if c = d (1)</formula><p>The distance is computed from the time difference if both events have the same category. The granularity of time difference (years, months, days, etc.) can be set. Currently, we do not allow matching between different categories, so we set the distance between every pair of events that comes from different categories to infinity.</p><p>Then the distance function between the target record X and the compared record Y</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">X = {(t 1 , c 1 ), (t 2 , c 2 ), ..., (t m , c m )} Y = {(u 1 , d 1 ), (u 2 , d 2 ), ..., (u n , d n )}</formula><p>is described as the following:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D(X,Y ) = min ∑ i∈[1,m], j∈ [1,n] d(x i , y j )</formula><p>each value of i and j is used exactly once.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(2)</head><p>A distance function between two records is calculated by matching events from the two records into event pairs and summing up the distances d(x i , y j ) between each pair. However, this distance function works only when m = n because it requires a perfect match between the two records. Also, even when m = n, this case can occur:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">X = {(t 1 , "A"), (t 2 , "A"), (t 3 , "B")} Y = {(u 1 , "A"), (u 2 , "B"), (u 3 , "B")}</formula><p>"A", "B" ∈ Categories</p><p>This will certainly create at least one pair of different category events, which is not preferred. Hence, the distance function fills in some null events (null, null) to equalize numbers of events between the two records in each category. The two lists above become.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">X = {(t 1 , "A"), (t 2 , "A"), (t 3 , "B"), (null, null)} Y = {(u 1 , "A"), (null, null), (u 2 , "B"), (u 3 , "B")}</formula><p>The distance function between each pair of events is revised. The null events should not be paired together so the distance is infinity. The pairs that have one null event indicate missing or extra events. The distance function does not include extra penalty for missing or extra events. Penalty for missing and extra events will be handled separately by the mismatch score (Section 5.2.2). Therefore, the distance is zero in these cases. Last, if the pair does not contain any null event, the original distance function is used.</p><p>Finally, a distance function between a target record X and a compared record Y becomes:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">D (X,Y ) = min ∑ i∈[1,m], j∈ [1,n] d (x i , y j )</formula><p>each value of i and j is used exactly once.</p><p>(4)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2">Minimum Distance Perfect Matching</head><p>The problem is how to match every event in X to an event in Y to yield minimum distance. This problem can be converted into an assignment problem. (See Section 2.) Let events from X (x i = (t i , c i )) become agents and events from Y (y j = (u j , d j )) become tasks. Cost of the assignment is d (x i , y j ). Then use the Hungarian Algorithm to solve the problem. The distance matrix between X and Y is displayed below.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">     y 1 y 2 . . . y n x 1 d (x 1 , y 1 ) d (x 1 , y 2 ) . . . d (x 1 , y n ) x 2 d (x 2 , y 1 ) d (x 2 , y 2 ) . . . d (x 2 , y n ) . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . x m d (x m , y 1 ) d (x m , y 2 ) . . . d (x m , y n )     </formula><p>The time complexity of the Hungarian Algorithm is O(n 3 ) when n is the number of events in each record. If there are m records in the database, the time to perform a matching between the target record and all records, assuming that each record has approximately n events is O(mn 3 ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Scores</head><p>Once the event matching process is completed. The match, mismatch and total score can be derived from the matching.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">Match Score</head><p>The distance from M&amp;M distance function captures the time difference between the two records. However, the distance can be a large number, which users find difficult to compare. Hence, we normalize the distance into a match score, ranging from 0.01 to 1.00. A higher score represents higher similarity. Only records with zero distance will yield a score of 1.00. Otherwise, the highest possible match score for non-zero distance is bounded to 0.99. The lowest score is bounded to 0.01 because we think that zero score may mislead the users to think that the target and compared record are not similar at all. Let n be total number of records in the dataset. X and Y are target and compared record, respectively. The match score (M(X,Y )) is calculated from the following equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">D max = Max j∈[1,n] D (X,Y j ) (5) M(X,Y i ) = 1.00 if D (X,Y i ) = 0 D max −D (X,Y i ) D max * .98 + .01 otherwise (6)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2">Mismatch Score</head><p>When the number of events in two records are not equal, there are missing or extra events. A missing event is an event that occurs in a target record but does not occur in a compared record. An extra event is an event that does not occur in a target record but occurs in a compared record. For example, imagine a target record for a patient who has chest pains, followed by elevated pulse rate, followed by a heart attack diagnosis. If the compared record has only chest pains and heart attack diagnosis, it has one missing event. We count a number of mismatches (N(X,Y )), a sum of number of missing or extra events in each category, and normalize it into a mismatch score (MM(X,Y )), ranging from 0.01 to 1.00. Only records with no mismatch events will yield a score of 1.00. Other records will have score within range 0.01 to 0.99.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">N max = Max j∈[1,n] N(X,Y j )<label>(7)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">MM(X,Y i ) = 1.00 if N(X,Y i ) = 0 N max −N(X,Y i ) N max * .98 + .01 otherwise<label>(8)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3">Total Score</head><p>The match score and mismatch score are combined into total score (T (X,Y i )) using weighted sum.</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">T (X,Y i ) = w * M(X,Y i ) + (1 − w) * MM(X,Y i ) ; w ∈ [0, 1] (9)</formula><p>Increasing the weight w gives match score more significance while decreasing w gives mismatch score more significance. The default value for weight is 0.5. (Both are equally significant.) For example, the users may not care whether there is any missing or extra event so the weight should be set to 1. Therefore, the Similan interface allows users to manually adjust this weight and see the results in real-time. (See Section 4.5.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Discussion</head><p>Our concept that the similar records should have the same events (low number of mismatches) and the same events should occur almost at the same time (low time difference) is transformed into the M&amp;M measure. Time difference and number of mismatches are two important aspects of similarity captured by the M&amp;M measure. Records with high match score are records with low time difference while records with high mismatch score are records with low number of mismatches. The M&amp;M measure can be adjusted to give significance to match or mismatch score. By default, the match score and mismatch score are assigned equally weights, so the most similar record should be the record with low time difference and also low number of mismatches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">EVALUATION</head><p>A usability study for Similan was conducted with 8 participants. The goals in this study were to examine the learnability of Similan, assess the benefits of a scatterplot, learn how the number of events and categories affect user performance, and determine if users could understand the M&amp;M measure in the context of its use. We also observed the strategies the users chose and what problems they encountered while using the tool. Synthetic data based on graduate school academic events, such as admission, successful dissertation proposal, and graduation, are used. This choice of data was intended to make the tasks more comprehensible and meaningful to participants, who were technically oriented graduate students.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Usability Study Procedure and Tasks</head><p>Two versions of Similan were used in this usability study: one with full features (S-Full) and another without a scatterplot (S-NoPlot). All usability sessions were conducted on an Apple laptop (15 inch widescreen, 2.2 Ghz CPU, 2GB RAM, Windows XP Professional) using an optical mouse. The study had two parts. In the first part, participants had an introduction to the M&amp;M measure and training with the Similan interface without a scatterplot (S-NoPlot). Then, the participants were asked to perform this task with different parameters:</p><p>Given a target student and dataset of 50 students. Each student record has x categories of events and the total number of events is between y to z events. Find 5 students that are most similar to the target student using S-NoPlot. In the second part, participants were introduced to the scatterplot and asked to perform task 4, 5 and 6 which are performing task 1, 2 and 3, respectively, but using S-Full instead of S-NoPlot. The datasets used in task 1-3 and 4-6 were the same but the students were renamed and the initial orderings were different. Task 1 and 4 were used only for training purpose. The results were collected from tasks 2, 3, 5 and 6.</p><p>In addition to observing the participants behavior and comments during the sessions, we provided them with a short questionnaire, which asked specific questions about the Similan interface. Answers were recorded using a seven-option Likert scale and free response sections for criticisms or comments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Results</head><p>For the first part of this 30-minute study, all participants were observed to use the following strategy: first select the target student, and then use the ranking mechanisms to rank students by the total score. In their first usage, some participants also selected the student who had the highest total score to see more detail in the comparison panel. Afterwards, they just studied the visualization and reported that these students with high total score are the answers.</p><p>For the second part of the study, which focused on the scatterplot, most of the participants were observed to use the following strategy: first select the target student, draw a selection in the plot panel, and then use main panels ranking mechanisms to rank students by the total score. However, a few participants did not use the scatterplot to do the task at all. They used the same strategy as in the first part.</p><p>Users spent comparable time on tasks 2 and 3 and on tasks 5 and 6. There was no difference in performance times between tasks 2 and 3 or between tasks 5 and 6, even though there were more events in tasks 3 and 6. This is understandable since participants reported that they trusted the ranking provided by the interface. However, users spent more time doing the tasks while using the scatterplot.</p><p>All of the participants trusted the total score ranking criterion and used it as the main source for their decisions. They explained that the visualization in the main panel convinced them that the ranking gave them the correct answers. Therefore, in the later tasks, after ranking by total score and having a glance at the visualization, they simply answered that the top five are the most similar.</p><p>All of them agreed that the main panel is useful for its ranking features and the comparison panel is useful in showing the similarity between the target and a compared student. However, they had different opinions about the scatterplot. Some of the participants mentioned that it was useful when they wanted to find similar students. They explained that the similar students can easily be found at the bottom left of the scatterplot. One participant said that she had to choose two parameters (#mismatch and match score) when she used the scatterplot. On the other hand, while using the main panel, she had to choose only one parameter (total score), which she preferred more. A few of them even mentioned that it is not necessary to use the scatterplot to find similar students. Although they had different opinions about its usefulness in finding similar students, they all agreed that the scatterplot gives a good overview of the students' distribution. It can show clusters of students, which could not be discovered from other panels. Also, one participant pointed out that the main and comparison panels are helpful in showing how students are similar, while the plot is more helpful in explaining how students are dissimilar.</p><p>Participants had positive comments on Similan's simple, intuitive and easy to learn interface. Most of the participants got started without assistance from the experimenter. Nevertheless, some user interface design concerns were noted. Some participants noticed that the binned timeline could be misleading in some situations.</p><p>Overall, participants liked the simple yet attractive Similan's interface and strongly believed that Similan can help them find students who are similar to the target student. Ranking in the main panel appears to be useful. By contrast, participants had difficulties in learning the M&amp;M measure, since it combines two kinds of scores. The scatterplot did not benefit the tasks in this study but we believe it may prove useful for more complex databases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">NEW VERSION</head><p>According to the user feedback, using a binned timeline can be misleading in some situations. A pair of events in the same bin can have a longer distance than a pair of events in different bins. Also, order of events within the same bin is hidden. Therefore, we develop a new prototype that adopts the continuous timeline used in Lifelines2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> and includes several improvements ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>.)</p><p>We did a pilot study with 5 participants to compare the binned timeline in original version and continuous timeline in the new version and received these comments: The continuous timeline requires more space for each record and looks more complicated. The binned timeline is more compact, simpler and therefore more readable. It gives users less detail to interpret. However, the continuous timeline does not mislead users when comparing distances or ordering. Both types of timeline have advantages and disadvantages depending on the task. The binned timeline is suitable for general tasks that do not require fine-grain information while the continuous timeline is more suitable when fine-grain information is required.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">FUTURE WORK</head><p>Currently, the M&amp;M measure takes all missing and extra events into account. In some situations, missing events are not considered important but extra events are, or vice versa. In a more complex situation, missing 1 of 2 events is not important but missing 2 of 2 events can be considered critical. Moreover, missing an event of category A may be not as critical as category B. The M&amp;M measure also does not allow matching of events between different categories. Allowing matching between different categories may make the similarity measure become more flexible.</p><p>Dealing with a large database is a challenging problem. Temporal categorical databases, e.g. EHRs, can contain millions of records. The O(n 3 ) time complexity of the Hungarian algorithm is a concern, but the number of events for each match is low, so the time to compare against a large data set grows only linearly with the number of records. Anyway, we are improving the algorithm to reduce its time complexity. A signature-based approach may also be used to reduce unnecessary computation.</p><p>More filtering mechanisms can be added to help users explore the search results. Also, records may be classified into groups or clusters according to total score, match score, #mismatch, etc.</p><p>The existing tools <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref> allow users to specify an exact query and retrieve records that satisfy the query. However, by using an exact query, some records may be overlooked because there are some minor details that make them dissatisfy the query. We propose a way to let users specify a loosely defined query by creating a custom record that contains the events that they are interested in. The M&amp;M measure then can be used to calculate the similarity score of between each record and the query record.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">CONCLUSION</head><p>Temporal categorical data are continuously being gathered by various organizations. Finding similar records within these large-scale databases is a challenging task, especially defining the similarity measure. This paper proposes the M&amp;M measure, a novel similarity measure for temporal categorical data. Briefly, the M&amp;M measure is a combination of time differences between events, and number of missing and extra events.</p><p>We also introduce Similan, an interactive tool that facilitates similarity searching and search results visualization for temporal categorical data. The alignment feature allows users to pre-process the dataset by aligning events by a sentinel category. Users are allowed to rank the temporal categorical records by many ranking criteria derived from the M&amp;M measure. The scatterplot provides an overall distribution of search results. The comparison panel provides advanced exploration of relationships between records.</p><p>A usability study had been conducted to evaluate the interface. Users found Similan to be comprehensible but they had a hard time understanding the M&amp;M measure. Users expressed strong opinions that Similan can help them find similar records from temporal categorical data. Learning from the evaluation, we developed a new prototype that has a continuous timeline and ran a pilot study to assess the benefits of the continuous timeline. The result shows that the binned timeline has advantage in its more compact and simpler look while the continuous timeline is more complex but gives the users more fine-grain information.</p><p>The M&amp;M measure can be extended further to increase the capability to handle more complex conditions and Similan can be extended into a more powerful tool that allows users to explore various temporal categorical databases using both similarity searching and loosely defined queries. For example, clinicians can use Similan to find patients with similar symptoms to a target patient in order to guide the treatment of the target patient while graduate student committees uses Similan to query for students who published a paper about three months before graduation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Users can start by double-clicking to select a target record from the main panel. Similan will calculate a score that indicates how similar to the target record each record is and show scores in the color-coded grid on the left. The score color-coding bars on the right show how the scores are color-coded. The users then can sort the records according to these scores. The main panel also allows users to visually compare a target with a set of records. In this early prototype, the timeline is binned (by year, in this screenshot). If the users want to make a more detailed comparison, they can click on a record to show the relationship between that record and the target record in the comparison panel on the top. The plot panel at the bottom shows the distribution of records. In this example, the user is searching for students who are similar to Student 01. The user sets Student 01 as the target and sorts all records by total score. Student 18 has the highest total score of 0.92 so this suggests that Student 18 is the most similar student. Student 41 and Student 18 both have one missing paper submission but Student 41 has a lower match score so Student 18 has higher total score.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Control Panel: Users can select categories of interest (left)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>(top) The M&amp;M measure (bottom-left) High time difference (low match score) but no mismatch (high mismatch score) (bottomright) Low time difference (high match score) but high mismatches (low mismatch score)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Relative Timeline: Time scale is now relative to sentinel events (blue). Time zero is highlighted in dark gray.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>d∞</head><label></label><figDesc>((t, c), (u, d)) if c and d = null 0 if c = null, d = null 0 if c = null, d = null d((t, c), (u, d)) if c and d = null (3)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Task 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>x = 2 , y = 4 and z = 6; Task 2 : x = 4 , y = 6 and z = 10; Task 3 : x = 6 , y = 8 and z = 16</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>New version: The timeline is continuous and events are split into rows by category.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank Dr. Samir Khuller for his guidance regarding the algorithms, Dr. Amol Deshpande for his guidance on the similarity measures, Dr. Catherine Plaisant, Taowei David Wang and Darya Filippova for their thoughtful comments, and our usability study participants for their time. We appreciate the collaboration and support from physicians at Washington Hospital Center.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viewing personal history records: A comparison of tabular format and graphical presentation using lifelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Alonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behaviour and Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Altschul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lipman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using signature files for querying time-series data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>André-Jönsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Badal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 1st European Symp. on Principles of Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery</title>
		<meeting>1st European Symp. on Principles of Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery<address><addrLine>London, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="220" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toolkit design for interactive structured graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bederson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grosjean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Software Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using dynamic time warping to find patterns in time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Berndt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Clifford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AAAI-94 Workshop on Knowledge Discovery in Databases</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="248" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new algorithm for the assignment problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bertsekas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mathematical Programming</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981-12" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="152" to="171" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Burkard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mauro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Martello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Assignment Problems. Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Querying and mining of time series data: Experimental comparison of representations and distance measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Trajcevski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Keogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the VLDB Endowment Archive</title>
		<meeting>of the VLDB Endowment Archive</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-08" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1542" to="1552" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A visual interface for multivariate temporal data: Finding patterns of events across multiple histories</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fails</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karlson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shahamat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Symp. Visual Analytics Science and Technology</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Symp. Visual Analytics Science and Technology</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social uses of personal health information within patientslikeme, an online patient community: What can happen when patients have access to one another&apos;s data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Frost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Massagli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Internet Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Error detecting and error correcting codes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hamming</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Bell System Technical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="1950" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The hungarian method for the assignment problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Naval Research Logistics Quarterly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="1955" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binary Codes Capable of Correcting Deletions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Levenshtein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Insertions and Reversals. Soviet Physics Doklady</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">707</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1966-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time series similar pattern matching based on empirical mode decomposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 6th Int. Conf. Intelligent Systems Design and Applications</title>
		<meeting>6th Int. Conf. Intelligent Systems Design and Applications<address><addrLine>CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="644" to="648" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progressive and interactive analysis of event data using event miner</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hellerstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Perng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grabarnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Int. Conf. Data Mining</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Int. Conf. Data Mining<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">00</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">661</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithms for the assignment and transportation problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Munkres</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="1957" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved tools for biological sequence comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pearson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lipman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the National Acad</title>
		<meeting>of the National Acad</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2444" to="2448" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lifelines: using visualization to enhance navigation and analysis of patient records</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mushlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. AMIA Symp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical summary of patient status</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Powsner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tufte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="386" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial pattern discovery in biological sequences: the TEIRESIAS algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Rigoutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Floratos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BIOINFORMATICS OXFORD</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning string-edit distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ristad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yianilos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="522" to="532" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel method for the efficient retrieval of similar multiparameter physiologic time series using wavelet-based symbolic representations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Saeed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mark</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AMIA Annual Symp. Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="683" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A rank-by-feature framework for interactive exploration of multidimensional data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Seo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The eyes have it: a task by data type taxonomy for information visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Symp. Visual Languages</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Symp. Visual Languages</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-09" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="343" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pattern discovery on australian medical claims data-a systematic approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tsoi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hagenbuchner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1420" to="1435" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aligning temporal data by sentinel events: discovering patterns in electronic health records</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Quinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stanchak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 26th Annual SIGCHI Conf. Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>26th Annual SIGCHI Conf. Human Factors in Computing Systems<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="466" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The state of record linkage and current research problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Winkler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<pubPlace>U.S. Census Bureau</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
	<note>Statistical Research Division</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
