<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Geovisual Analytics for Self-Organizing Network Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ho</forename><surname>Van Quan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Visual Analytics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dept. of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><surname>Åström</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Visual Analytics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dept. of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mikael</forename><surname>Jern</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Visual Analytics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dept. of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Geovisual Analytics for Self-Organizing Network Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Geovisual analytics</term>
					<term>visualization</term>
					<term>self-organizing network</term>
					<term>multi-layer</term>
					<term>multi-dimensional</term>
					<term>time-varying</term>
					<term>geospatial data sets H.1.2 [User/Machine Systems]: Human Information Processing -GeoVisual Analytics; I.6.9 [Visualization]: Information Visualization</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Cellular radio networks are continually growing in both node count and complexity. It therefore becomes more difficult to manage the networks and necessary to use time and cost effective automatic algorithms to organize the network&apos;s neighbor cell relations. There have been a number of attempts to develop such automatic algorithms. Network operators, however, may not trust them because they need to have an understanding of their behavior and of their reliability and performance, which is not easily perceived. This paper presents a novel web-enabled geovisual analytics approach to exploration and understanding of self-organizing network data related to cells and neighbor cell relations. A demonstrator and case study are presented in this paper, developed in close collaboration with the Swedish telecom company Ericsson and based on large multivariate, time-varying and geospatial data provided by the company. It allows the operators to follow, interact with and analyze the evolution of a self-organizing network and enhance their understanding of how an automatic algorithm configures locally-unique physical cell identities and organizes neighbor cell relations of the network. The geovisual analytics tool is tested with a self-organizing network that is operated by the Automatic Neighbor Relations (ANR) algorithm. The demonstrator has been tested with positive results by a group of domain experts from Ericsson and will be tested in production.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>In parallel with the 3G Long Term Evolution (LTE) specification and development <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>, the Next Generation Mobile Network (NGMN) association of operators brings forward requirements on management simplicity and cost efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The vision is that algorithms automate tasks that currently require significant manual effort. One part of LTE that benefits from selforganization is automatic neighbor relation support. There are some attempts to develop such automatic algorithms. For instance Ericsson has developed an algorithm, called Automatic Neighbor Relations (ANR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, which automatically creates and updates neighbor cell relation (NCR) lists based on measured network data. Furthermore, each cell is also assigned a physical cell identity (PCI), which is intended to be locally unique. The goal is to automatically reassign PCIs to avoid local conflicts.</p><p>Network operators, however, may not trust automatic algorithms because they need to have an understanding of their behavior, reliability and efficiency, which is not easily perceived. To enhance confidence and understanding of automatic algorithms such as ANR, we propose that an automatic algorithm should come with observation possibilities. For example, it must be possible to observe the outcome; what cell relations are added or removed, when in time this is happening etc. It must also be possible to understand the algorithm behind; why a cell changes its PCI, how a PCI conflict is detected etc. For these purposes, a geovisual analytics approach should be useful to show how such an algorithm works and to support examining various aspects of the network.</p><p>Visual presentation and exploration of geospatial network data can provide analysts and operators with strategic and sometimes competitive advantage. Integrated information and geovisualization methods, here referred to as geovisual analytics, focus on finding location-related patterns and relationships. Geovisual analytics (GVA) tools are designed to support highlyinteractive explorative spatial data analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref> of large temporal geospatial data. In this paper we introduce a demonstrator and case study for Adobe Flash called VoSON (Visualization of Self-Organizing Network) allowing the operators to follow, interact with and analyze the evolution of a self-organizing network under the operation of an automatic algorithm such as ANR.</p><p>VoSON increases comprehension of the behavior of a selforganizing network and supports network examination by visualizing counts and attribute values of cells and cell relations over time. It further gives possibilities for filtering and highlighting extreme values. With this demonstrator, it is possible to examine and gain insight into the problem that may have caused a situation. The following GVA methods were regarded by the domain experts as most important tasks in VoSON:</p><p> Interactive dialogue between the operator and cell data and cell relation data -PCI conflicts can be analyzed and managed;  Large-scale cell data and cell relation data are simultaneously analyzed through the use of dynamic linked views by the operator to efficiently comprehend complex situations;  Spatial and multivariate cell data and cell relation data are analyzed and animated in a temporal context;  Key information for the operator e.g. visual representations are combined with textual labels and symbols placed in separate map layers to avoid overwhelming the display.</p><p>The remainder of the paper is organized as follows. Section 2 gives an overview of related work. Section 3 presents the data description. Section 4 presents our GAV Flash framework. Then the approach is presented in section 5. Self-organizing network in geovisual analytics is presented in section 6. Finally the user feedback is presented in section 7 and the conclusion in section 8. 1 {ho.van.quan, tobias.astrom, mikael.jern}@itn.liu.se</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.1</head><p>Visual exploration of spatial-temporal data Visual exploration of spatial-temporal data has been the subject of many research papers, see <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> for an overview. Andrienko and Andrienko have illustrated several motivating approaches in earlier papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. Many papers <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>, emphasize the advantages of and need for multiple linked views (MLVs) for dynamically exploring time-varying, geographically referenced and multivariate attribute data. As a response a generic "GeoAnalytics" visualization (GAV) tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> was introduced and similar methods are employed in this case study. The extended parallel coordinates plot (PCP) with embedded statistical filtering methods serves as a visual control panel linked to the choropleth maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, and is a central component in this project. GeoVista <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and VIS-STAMP <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> are other examples of a general system with functionalities that support exploration tools that leverage visual and computational methods to search for space-time and multivariate patterns.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.2</head><p>Communication network visualization Communication network visualization is not new. There have been a number of attempts to visualize networks for various purposes as summarized in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>. Most previous work on visualizing communication network data has been based on measuring performance or bandwidth characteristics. Some work is applied to network traffic monitoring, some is applied to intrusion detection and some is applied to network behavior monitoring.</p><p>Becker et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref> presented the SeeNet environment that uses three graphical tools, 'Link map', 'Node map' and 'Matrix display' to visualize network data, analyze network traffic, and study overloads. Koutsofios et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref> also introduced SWIFT-3D that incorporates interactive 3D maps, statistical displays, network topology diagrams, and pixel-oriented displays for interactive exploration of large-scale network data. Nevertheless, in their work the network is not a self-organizing network and their goals are also different from our goal therefore we are not sure their visualization techniques can well suit our needs. In our work we develop and use different visualization techniques such as cell maps, cell relation maps, PCPs, time sliders, time-graphs and various types of glyphs to serve our needs.</p><p>To our best knowledge, there has been no work published in literature that visualizes a self-organizing network to illustrate how an algorithm such as ANR configures a radio network.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DATA DESCRIPTION</head><p>We start by introducing a number of basic concepts in a radio network. In this context, a radio network includes three major objects: base station, its cells and cell relations. A base station is the physical entity with radio transmitters and receivers and constitutes one or more cells covering a geographical area. A cell supports mobility by knowing its close neighbors to which it can handover calls; i.e. cell relations (or shortly relations in the context of this paper). To help mobile terminals identify a cell, all cells broadcast two identifiers: a globally unique cell identifier (CGI) and a physical cell identity (PCI). CGIs are unique and constant over time but are more difficult and time consuming to detect for the mobile terminals. In contrast, PCIs are easier to detect but they are not unique since there are only 504 different PCIs in LTE. The PCI of a cell can vary over time since it needs to be unique in a region and may need to change.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.1</head><p>Data generation ANR is chosen as a case study for this paper. A simulator has been built by Ericsson and a number of simulation cases are selected to reflect the behavior of the algorithm. In each simulation case, a number of cells are prepared. In each interval of 15 minutes, the data generation script generates a number of mobiles in handover locations between cells where the serving cell and target cell are determined from the radio conditions at the mobiles' locations. Then events are recorded together with their time-stamp. The basic events include  calls dropped  handover successes or handover failures  relations added or removed  PCI conflicts detected, and  cells changing PCIs The events are divided into two groups. The first group includes the events that reflect how the algorithm works and how the network is configured such as PCI conflicts detected, cells changing PCIs and relations added or removed. The second group includes the events that reflect the network performance such as handover successes, handover failures, and calls dropped. The events in the first group are then stored, and the events in the second group are counted over each time interval and are stored by counts to save storage space. From these counts, a number of other counts are computed to support data analysis.</p><p>The counts mainly belong to one of two types: cell counts and relation counts. The number of call drops, and the number of outgoing handover failures are examples of cell counts; and the number of handover successes and the number of handover failures are relation counts. The counts and events are then used to visualize for each time interval to reflect the way the algorithm configures the network.  The GAV Flash includes a collection of common geovisualization and information visualization components, data analysis algorithms, tools that connect the components to each other and data providers that can load data from various sources. Interactive features that are needed to support a spatial and temporal <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> analytical reasoning process are available, such as tooltips, brushing, highlight, visual inquiry, conditioned filter mechanisms that can discover outliers and methods supporting time-linked multiple views. The GAV architecture allows new or existing components/classes to be incorporated with the already existing components, e.g. special GVA methods used in VoSON such as the glyph layer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Simulation cases</head><p>In figure 3, spatial-temporal and multivariate self-organized network data are simultaneously explored through the use of dynamic linked views to detect complex patterns and problems in cellular radio networks as described in more detail in sections 5 and 6. The views are coordinated using the GAV data linking method based on the same data cube model and colouring scheme. Any filtering or highlighting made in one of the linked functional components propagates to all the others.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">GAV Map Layers</head><p>The choropleth map component facilitates a layered architecture. It means that each class of spatial information is represented by its own layer, e.g. shaded map, glyph, Google map. These layers then can be combined and controlled to be displayed, hidden or transparent depending on the needs of the user. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">APPROACH</head><p>To  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Selection of visual representations</head><p>Network data in the context of this paper mainly belongs to one of two types: cell data and relation data. The data include geographical data, attribute data, events and counts that are timevarying. In order to enable efficient interaction with and analysis of the data we need to select different visual representations so that each best suits a certain type of data. Furthermore, they should also be arranged in a well-designed layout. To meet these requirements, we suggest the following layout that includes seven dynamic linked visual representations (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">figure 3)</ref>:  a cell map, a cell-based PCP and a cell graph for visualization and analysis of cell data,  a relation map, a relation-based PCP and a relation graph for visualization and analysis of cell relation data, and  a time slider for time control and analysis. The following parts will describe these in more detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Cell map</head><p>The cell map is one of our central views. It is used to:  Visualize, interact with (e.g. multi-selection, zoom, pan, highlight), and analyze cells and events relating to cells,  display cell data such as CGI, PCI, and  highlight notable cells such as ones having an extreme value or having the same PCI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">Cell visualization</head><p>To be able to achieve the goals above, we first need to have a good visual representation of cells. Cells have their geographical positions (the position of antennas) and their own best-served areas, called "coverage areas" that normally do not have a clear shape as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">figure 4(a)</ref>. Nevertheless, an accurate representation of them is not necessary for the purpose of this project. Therefore we have represented cell coverage areas as polygons to simplify the visualization of and interaction with cells. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4(b)</ref> shows an example of these approximations achieved by applying a number of morphological operations such as removing isolated parts, dilation and erosion to cell coverage areas.  In addition, a color map is used to color cell coverage areas according to the attribute or count being selected in the cell-based PCP. A tooltip displays information about cell data (see figure 3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.2.3</head><p>Cell  The cell map allows the visual analysis of various types of cell events such as cells changing PCI, PCI conflicts detected, cells changing relations. For each type of events there is a layer which can be controlled to be displayed, hidden or transparent depending on the task to be focused upon. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref> illustrates the visualization of several cell events occurring in interval 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Relation map</head><p>The relation map is used to  visualize, interact with and analyze cell relations and events relating to cell relations such as relations added, relations removed,  display cell relation data, and  allow the operator to highlight notable cell relations such as relations in black lists or white lists. To visualize a relation that is a directed connection from a cell to another cell, a simple and straightforward solution is to use an arrow. Nevertheless, there are several different types of relations that should be distinguished such as relations being selected, relations added, relations removed, or relations in black lists. To be able to visualize, interpret and make sense of them, we use arrows with glyphs and colors as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">figure 7</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 8</ref> shows an example where various types of relations of cell 605 in the interval 6 are analyzed.</p><p>The relation map also uses a color map to color relations according to the selected attribute/count in the relation-based PCP and a tooltip to show relation data.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Cell-based PCP and relation-based PCP</head><p>Cells and relations have many variables and counts. To explore them and understand correlations between them, PCPs are good choices due to their ability to explore multiple variables using interactive features such as highlighting and filtering. Furthermore, when linked with the cell and relation maps the PCPs facilitate important analytics reasoning of network data as described in section 6.</p><p>We use two PCPs: 1) a cell-based PCP that explores cell attributes and counts in each time interval and 2) a relation-based PCP that explores relation attributes and counts in each time interval (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">figure 3)</ref>. Furthermore, to avoid analysing a large number of variables and counts of cells and relations that would result in very high data density we use the filter mechanism to help the operator to select variables and counts to focus upon.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Cell graph and relation graph</head><p>Cell counts and relation counts are time-varying. To see how they change over time, time-graphs should be useful. Therefore, we use two time graphs: one, called cell graph, to visualize and explore an attribute or count of cells over time and a second, called relation graph, to visualize and explore an attribute or count of relations over time (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">figure 3)</ref>. These graphs, when combined with the maps and the PCPs above, can provide a better view of the network data and at the same time support better analysis of the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6">Time slider</head><p>The time slider is a key component used to control selection of time, animation and especially to highlight intervals of change (i.e. intervals in which cells change their PCIs or relations) of cells or the whole network. This can help the operators to follow the changes in the network more easily and support them in analysis of changes in the network as presented in section 6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.7">Dynamic linked views and zoom in on focus</head><p>Spatial-temporal and multivariate data are effectively analyzed through the use of dynamic linked views <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. VoSON supports this by inheriting from the GAV Flash framework the ability to dynamically link views to each other through selection, color mapping and filtering. When one or more cells are selected (through the cell combo-boxes on the menu bar or the cell map or the cell-based PCP etc.), the cell map will highlight them and their neighbors with different colors and levels of transparency; then the cell-based PCP will highlight these cells (but not their neighbors), and the cell graph will visualize cell values of a selected variable or count over time. The relation map then highlights and zooms in on these selected cells and their neighbors. Then only relations relating to the selected cells in the cell map can be selected and interacted with in the relation map. Similarly, when one or more relations are selected (through the relation map or the relation-based PCP), the relation map will visualize them, the relation-based PCP will highlight them and the relation graph will visualize relation values of a selected variable or count over time. If relations are selected by the cell-based PCP, then their source-cells (or target-cells) will be selected and visualized in the cell map and so on. In linking by filtering, when cells are filtered in the cell-based PCP they will also be immediately filtered in the cell map. In linking by color mapping, one color map is shared by all three views: the cell map, cellbased PCP and cell graph and another color map is shared by the relation map, relation-based PCP and relation graph.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">SELF-ORGANIZING NETWORK IN GEOVISUAL ANALYTICS</head><p>The goal of this paper is to use a geovisual analytics approach to self-organizing network data related to cells and neighbor cell relations to show how an automatic algorithm such as ANR works. To achieve this goal, VoSON provides abilities to follow and analyze the changes in the network, examine cell and relation data, find extreme cells and relations, and determine cells having potential problems such as PCI conflict.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Supervision and analysis of changes in the network</head><p>Changes in the network include two types: (1) changes of cells in a time interval that can help to answer questions such as where PCI conflicts are, which cells change their PCIs, and which cells add new relations or remove relations; and (2) changes of cells over time that can allow answering questions such as when PCI conflicts relating to the cells are detected, when cells change their PCIs, and when they add new relations or remove relations. Therefore, supervision and analysis of both types of changes can help the operators to better understand how the algorithm works and, if needed, intervene in the system. Then when the user selects a number of cells or relations, changes related to those cells and relations will be shown. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 9</ref> shows an overview of changes occurring in the network in time interval 1. In case 1 there are no PCI conflicts and only two new relations added. In case 2 there are no PCI conflicts, but many new relations added. In case 3, there are many handover failures, PCI conflicts and new relations added.</p><p>To supervise changes of concerned cells over time, the time slider plays an important role. It marks time intervals in which cells change PCIs and time intervals in which they add or remove relations. The time graphs show their values of a concerned attribute or count over time.</p><p>By examining events occurring in a time interval and exploring related data such as the number of calls dropped and the number of handover failures of cells and cell relations in several previous time intervals, the operators can understand why a cell changes its PCI in that time interval, why a PCI conflict happens, and how a PCI conflict is detected etc. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> shows changes of cell 210 over time. Cell 210 changes its relations in intervals 1, 2, 8 and 12 and changes PCI from 210 to 64 in interval 8 after a PCI conflict between itself and cell 225 is detected. The PCI conflict is detected by cell 224 by the method of CGI report <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>    <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12(a, b, c)</ref> shows intervals of change of all cells for cases 1, 2, and 3 respectively. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref> shows an overview of changes occurring in interval 20 in cases 2 and 3 respectively. From VoSON, as illustrated in the above figures, we found that in case 1 there are few intervals of change at the beginning, and from interval 12 there is no change. In cases 2 and 3, adding new relations happens continuously in the first intervals and less often in the later intervals. This is also true for cells changing PCI in case 3. All these facts make sense and agree with the initial configurations of the network in each case.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Finding notable cells and relations</head><p>There are a number of cells and relations that have an abnormal attribute value or count or have a potential problem of PCI conflict. Finding these cells and relations is important since it can help the operators focus on them and follow and analyze them. VoSON provides several ways to accomplish this. The first way is to use the ability of PCPs to filter and find cells and/or relations having extreme values for example a large number of calls dropped or large number of handover failures in a certain time interval. Then the time graphs and the time slider can be used to see how they change over time. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> shows an example of finding a notable cell. In this figure, the cell-based PCP is used to find out that cell 659 has 7 call drops in interval 1. The time slider shows that this cell changes PCI in interval 2. It changes PCI from 14 to 485 after a PCI conflict between itself and another cell in its vicinity detected by itself by the method of transmission gap <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. The cell graph shows that after changing PCI, it has no call drop. Another alternative is to use a search tool that allows the user to specify search conditions through a graphical user interface and then flag the resulting cells and relations in the cell map and relation map. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 14</ref> shows an example of using the search tool to find the top 3 cells having a large number of call drops and the top 3 relations having a large number of handover failures in interval 1. The search results show that cell 670 relates to both results. A further analysis shows that there is a PCI conflict between it and another cell in its vicinity detected in interval 2. After the PCI conflict is resolved cell 670 has no call drops. Nevertheless, it is discovered that there are still handover failures from it to cell 672 that occur repeatedly. This phenomenon raises a question that might need more information to answer.</p><p>To identify cells having a potential PCI conflict, the simple way is to highlight cells that have the same PCI. Then cells that are in the vicinity of each other and use the same PCI would have a high potential of PCI conflict. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 15</ref> shows cells having the same PCI (3) in interval 5. Then a PCI conflict between cells 453 and 468 is detected in interval 6 and cell 453 changes its PCI to 471.</p><p>VoSON also provides the ability to find notable relations that have a long distance between their source and target cells. These relations should be supervised to answer questions such as when they were added, why and if they work well. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 16</ref> shows several long-distance relations: (1) relation from cell 659 to cell 575 and (2) relation from cell 670 and cell 661. A further analysis shows that both relations have a number of handover failures that occur repeatedly. This also raises another question that might need more information to answer. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">USER FEEDBACK</head><p>Our partner, Ericsson, has been using the prototype during the cycle of its development and has provided us with highly valuable feedback regarding its advantages and disadvantages. Five domain experts in radio network area participated with the objective to assess usability issues such as advantages and disadvantages in the prototype's visual representations, interaction mechanisms and, its support of visual explorative data analysis. They were also encouraged to give their opinions for further development of VoSON.</p><p>The feedback shows that the users like the concept of the time line and the ability to see the network changing "-I like the concept and the view of changes over time, really good". The ability to find 'problem' cells and relations were also considered as highly positive "-it looks useful and very good to me".</p><p>On the negative side we have realized that several users start with the flagging feature rather than using filters to find the starting point for the search. It seems that the amount of information in the PCPs or other complications hindered them. But after a while, 'playing' with the PCPs, they learned this new way of finding interesting patterns -which results in a greater acceptance of the PCPs. The feedback has also included a number of expected features to be considered for further development; for example the ability to pick lines on time graphs and link them to other views, and the ability to find extreme values in all time intervals instead of only one interval.</p><p>Finally, the tool now consists of a balanced subset of possible counts and parameters from the radio network. In many situations, it is enough to explain how ANR works; however, there are some situations that need more information especially to explain call drops that are not dependent on ANR.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>We have developed a geovisual analytics tool that supports analysis of the way an automatic algorithm such as ANR configures a self-organizing network in collaboration with Ericsson. The tool is based on the GAV Flash framework. It combines interactive visual displays, a multi-layer approach and the ability to work with multi-dimensional, time-varying, and geospatial data sets. It allows the operators to follow events happening in the network, supervise and analyze changes in the network over time and answer various types of questions such as why a relation is added or removed, why a cell changes its PCI, or how a PCI conflict is detected that can help them to better understand how the algorithm works. The tool can also support the operators to examine and intervene in various aspects of the network, find existing problems as well as potential problems. The tool has been used and tested by a group of relevant domain users and the findings from these efforts has been highly positive and in favor of the tool. Our next steps are to <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> find out what information should be added and how it is used, (2) further improve the interaction and performance of the tool, (3) apply it to massive data from a real environment, and (4) finally perform a thorough evaluation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>VoSON is developed with the web-compliant GAV Flash framework and its class libraries</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>GAV layered map technique with Google, shaded, symbol and glyph maps with user opacity controls.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Seven main views of VoSON: two maps are used to visualize, interact with and analyze cells and relations; two PCPs are used to explore and examine cell and relation attributes/counts in each time interval; two graphs are used to explore and examine cell and relation attributes/counts over time; a time slider is used to move back and forth and highlight "intervals of change" of selected cells.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>(a) cell coverage areas; (b) cell coverage areas simplified into polygons that allow easier interaction with cells 5.2.2Visually exploring cell information and data In order to enable the exploration of various types of cell information and data we extend the simplified polygons to polygons having multiple borders and divided into several subareas as shown in figure 5(a). By combining these multi-border and multi-sub-area polygons with glyphs, texts and colors we can display fifteen different pieces of cell information and data at the same time.Figure 5(b) shows an example where the red border represents a cell being selected as a serving-cell. The green border represents a target-cell of a serving-cell being selected. The red circle represents a cell changing PCI. The orange flower represents a cell adding or removing relations. The red flag represents an extreme cell (i.e. a cell having an extreme value). The green flag represents a serving-cell of an extreme relation (i.e. a relation having an extreme value). The yellow flag represents a target-cell of an extreme relation. The texts present CGI and current PCI (and last PCI if the cell changes its PCI from previous interval).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>(a) an illustration of a multi-border and multi-sub-area polygon; (b) a multi-border and multi-sub-area polygon is used to display various types of cell information and data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>An illustration of cell events occuring in interval 8</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Arrows (with border), glyphs and colors are combined to represent various types of relations</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>An illustration of using arrows with borders together glyphs and colors to represent various types of relations</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>An overview of changes occurring in time interval 1 VoSON provides several abilities to supervise and analyze both types of changes. To supervise changes in each time interval, the cell map shows all cell events occurring in that time, highlight cells changing PCIs and changing relations; the relation map shows relations added and removed in that time; the cell based-PCP displays attribute values and counts of all cells, and the relation based-PCP displays attribute values and counts of all relations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(CGIR) after 3 handover failures in interval 5 from it (cell 224) to cell 225.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 10 .Figure 11 . 3 Figure 12 .</head><label>1011312</label><figDesc>(a) Intervals of change of cell 210; (b) after 3 handover failures in interval 5 from cell 224 to cell 225, a PCI conflict between cells 210 and 225 detected in interval 8 by cell 224 Changes occurring in time interval 20 for cases 2 and (a, b, c) Intervals of change of the case 1, 2, 3 respectively;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>cell 659 has 7 call drops in interval 1 (left) and it changes PCI after a PCI conflict between itself and another cell in its vicinity detected in interval 2 (right)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 14 . 6 Figure 16 .</head><label>14616</label><figDesc>An illustration of using the finding tool to find noticeable cells and relations Figure 15. (a) cells having the same PCI (3) in interval 5; (b) cell 453 change its PCI from 3 to 471 in interval Long-distance relations</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>There are three cases that are selected to simulate the behavior of the algorithm, each includes 225 cells prepared. Furthermore, all cells are initiated with empty neighbor cell lists. The simulation is done for one day, including 96 intervals of 15 minutes.</figDesc><table /><note> In case 1, cells are sequentially assigned to CGIs from 1 to 225. Then each cell is initially assigned to a non- conflict PCI except two cells, 210 and 225, which have the same PCI, 210. Each cell is also initiated with a well- planned neighbor cell list. Furthermore, all cells that ideally would have both cells 210 and 225 in their neighbor cell list only have cell 225. In case 2, cells are sequentially assigned to CGIs from 226 to 450. There is no PCI conflict, but there are only the most important neighbors in the neighbor cell lists. In case 3, cells are sequentially assigned to CGIs from 451 to 675 but there are only 15 PCIs initially assigned to cells by the following formula PCI = ((Cell CGI -1) mod 15) + 14 GAV FLASH FRAMEWORK The VoSON demonstrator was developed and customized using our new GAV Flash framework. A previous version for Microsoft's .Net and DirectX is described in [8]. Our geovisual analytics methods have now been adapted for the Web 2.0 using Adobe's Flash basic graphics and Flex for user interfaces. Programmed in Adobe's object-oriented (OO) language ActionScript, the GAV Flash (figure 1) and VoSON facilitate 100% deployment to the Internet -a requirement from our partner and network domain expert Ericsson.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>develop VoSON, we follow a human-centered approach enabling deployment of a demonstrator that puts the emphasis on tasks defined by the Ericsson domain expertise and needs of the target-groups. Each GAV Flash component performs a specific task in the overall GVA process. Customizing the VoSON application we have, for example, the GAV Flash implementation of a Parallel Coordinates Plot (PCP) and the layered map component. Other new domain-related components are the relation map, extended 2D-graph and extended time slider.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>event visualizationThe network events (e.g. cell events and relation events) reflect how the algorithm works. Visualizing them can help the operators to observe how the network evolves, interpret and get answers to various questions such as</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>What relations are added or removed? When? Why?</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Which cells change their PCIs? When? Why?</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>How are PCI conflicts detected?</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">and therefore facilitate analysis and understanding of how the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">algorithm works.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>This applied research study was supported, in part, by Ericsson AB, Sweden and by funding from the Visualization Program managed by the Swedish Knowledge Foundation (KK-Stiftelsen).</p><p>We would like to thank researchers Johan Moe, Fredrik Gunnarsson, Harald Kallin, Thomas Rimhagen, and Kristina Zetterberg at Ericsson for providing data for our case study and ideas during the evaluation stage of the tool. Many thanks to our colleagues at the National Center for Visual Analytics NCVA (http://ncva.itn.liu.se) at ITN, Linkoping University.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dahlman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parkvall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sköld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Beming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">3G Evolution: HSPA and LTE for Mobile Broadband</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Technical specification group radio access network; requirements for evolved UTRA (E-UTRA) and evolved UTRAN (E-UTRAN)</title>
		<idno>3GPP TR 25.913</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Release 7</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Operator use cases related to self organising networks</title>
		<idno>ver. 1.53</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2007" to="2011" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>NGMN</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neighbor cell relation list and physical cell identity selforganization in LTE</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Amirijoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Frenger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gunnarsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kallin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zetterberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2008 IEEE International Conference on Communications Workshops</title>
		<meeting>the 2008 IEEE International Conference on Communications Workshops</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariate analysis and geovisualization with an integrated geographic knowledge discovery approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gahegan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Maceachren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cartography and Geographic Information Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visual tools to explore spatio-temporal variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces</title>
		<meeting>the Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="420" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual exploration of spatial distribution of temporal behaviors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Information Visualisation (IV05)</title>
		<meeting>the 9th International Conference on Information Visualisation (IV05)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="806" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeoAnalytics tools applied to large geospatial datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Åström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 12th International Conference Information Visualisation (IV08)</title>
		<meeting>the 12th International Conference Information Visualisation (IV08)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="362" to="372" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual data mining in large geospatial point sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Panse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>North</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization methods for timedependent data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2003 Winter Simulation Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 2003 Winter Simulation Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="737" to="745" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exploratory visualization with multiple linked views</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Exploring Geovisualization, J. Dykes, A. M. MacEachren, and M.-J. Kraak</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Pergamon</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="180" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeoAnalytics -Exploring spatio-temporal and multivariate data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Franzén</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 10th International Conference on Information Visualisation (IV06)</title>
		<meeting>the 10th International Conference on Information Visualisation (IV06)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="31" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The GAV toolkit for multiple linked views</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Franzén</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Coordinated and Multiple Views in Exploratory Visualization</title>
		<meeting>the 5th International Conference on Coordinated and Multiple Views in Exploratory Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="97" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeoAnalytics visual inquiry and filtering tools in parallel coordinates plots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 15th Annual ACM International Symposium on Advances in Geographic Information Systems</title>
		<meeting>the 15th Annual ACM International Symposium on Advances in Geographic Information Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Geovista</forename><surname>Studio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.geovistastudio.psu.edu" />
		<title level="m">Available</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A visualization system for space-time and multivariate patterns (VIS-STAMP)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Maceachren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-11" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1461" to="1474" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network visualisation: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Withall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Parish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IET Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing network data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Eick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and ComputerGraphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Network Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Eick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R K</forename><surname>Wilks ; S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Readings in information visualization: Using vision to think</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Fransisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufman</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="227" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing large telecommunication data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Koutsofios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>North</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing large-scale telecommunication networks and services</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Koutsofios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>North</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Truscott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;99</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;99</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="461" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactions to geovisualization: an experience from a European project</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mues</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schuck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Geographical Information Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1149" to="1171" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
