<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Shape coding of multidimensional data on a microcomputer display</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeff</forename><surname>Ekddow</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Microsimulations Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Chateau Place Minneapolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>5321, 554 17</postCode>
									<region>MN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Shape coding of multidimensional data on a microcomputer display</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The visual representation of data from complex systems, whether databases, measured scientific data, or simulation output, holds the promise of discovering patterns in the data that will increase its management efficiency while revealing relationships invisible to numeric methods. In this paper we present a simple and flexible method of shape coding for higher dimensional data sets that allows the database o p erator or discipline scientist quick access to promising patterns within and among records or samples. The example used is a thirteen parameter set of solar wind, magnetosphere, and ground o b servation data collected hourly for twenty-one days in 1976. Backaround There is currently a great deal of interest in understanding the topology of higher dimensional data sets. Applications for methods developed in this area encompass a broad range of computer-related fields, including ma* agement of extensive databases, scientific visualization, and complex p r o cess control. Visual methods in this field seem promising and are the subject of extensive research at this time1. One McCormick, B., DeFanti, T. &amp; Brown, M., &quot;Visualization in Scientific Computing&quot;, Reuort to the National Science Fou ndation bvthe Panel on Grauhics, Image Processine and-1987 2 Littlefield, Richard J., &quot;Using the glyph concept to create user-definable display formats&quot; Proceed&apos; i~lgs of the</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>visual method involves mapping data values to a compound graphic object, usually called a "glyph" and occasionally called an "icon."2 The precedent for this approach is to be found in advanced statistical methods. 3 ,4 During the 60's and 70's several methods were p r o posed for projecting complex data sets onto graphic surfaces. Most of these efforts were ignored or sank into obscurity at the time because of the diffi culty of creating and interpreting them. 5 Current interface and computing technology eliminates the drudgery of successive iterations of design, allowing the researcher to seek optimum display parameters in fairly short sessions. A greater commitment to the process is required, however, as perception of the salient features of complex glyph surfaces can usually require much more time than the inspection of histograms, draughtsman's arrays of scattergram's box and whisker charts, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The svstem to</head><p>The solar wind and the Earth's m a g netic field have an interesting relationship which is being studied from many perspectives. The plasma, or ionized gas outflow from the Sun, consists of both positively and negatively charged particles. When these particles encounter the magnetosphere of the Earth, it is similar to water molecules in a river encountering the pier of a bridge. A bow shock wave is formed, and behind that turbulence occurs in the transitional area. In these areas the behavior of the solar wind is similar to air or water currents. Because of the electrons that accompany the ions, however, there are enormous electrical currents in the plasma stream, and these interact further with the Earth's field, producing side effects as spectacular as the Auroras and as problematic as vast "radio storms" that interfere with radio communications over entire hemispheres. The bow shock always faces the Sun. Opposite is a tail that extends at least a million miles.</p><p>The fluid nature of the bowshock, magnetopause, and tail result in perturbations of the entire system when particularly active streams of particles from the sun arrive. The forces that generate the Earth's dipole m a g netic field are fairly stable from the scale of a human lifetime. m e interaction with the Sun's charged particles creates a vast, sensitive, electrically active caul around the planet that has significant impact on many people's daily activities.</p><p>Watrhiw the svstem.</p><p>These behaviors are too complex to be completely predicted by mathematical models. An optical facility in Boulder Colorado keeps track of disturbances of the Sun's surface that will result, sev-eral days later, in perturbations of the Earths magnetosphere. These are reported to military and corporate clients whose activities depend on clear radio transmissions. Since the magnete sphere is not visible to the naked eye, its shape must actually be calculated from data about ion density, temperature and direction. Most of the interplanetary medium data is collected by satellites, either earth or solar orbiting. The quality and nature of the data from the satellite is affected by its orbit. An earth orbiting satellite is always in an elliptical orbit, with a near and far point that keep their alignment relative to the celestial sphere, but change their alignment relative to the earth-sun line as the earth moves in its orbit. Every six months the major axis will be wholly within the magnetotail. When it is in the magnetotail, it is not collecting accurate data about the solar wind. This leaves significant gaps in the data record, and lesser gaps of a daily scale as the satellite moves behind the earth in every orbit.</p><p>NASA' s Goddard Space Flight Center has collected the interplanetary medium and magnetic activity data over the last twenty years and packaged it for general scientific uses on the NODIS system as the OMNl data set. This set consists of some 35 parameters which can be downloaded by the investigator in ascii format. I chose the following thirteen for this exercise:</p><p>1. Field magnitude average: this is the average strength of the magnetic field, ignoring any shifts in vector orientation. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Flow Longitude: An indication</head><p>of solar wind direction.</p><p>9. Flow Latitude: An indication of solar wind direction.</p><p>10. Kp* 10: a measure of Earth's magnetic field strength and motion from the ground 1 1 .C9: An index of activity in the 10 cm radio bandwidth.</p><p>12. r (sunspot) 13. year/day/hour The parameters of the solar wind are taken from sensors outside the magnetopause. This ensemble was chose to depict, in broad strokes, concurrent states and levels of activity in the three main domains of the system: solar wind, magnetosphere, and ground level effects. m e and softvrare;</p><p>The software system is a proto type developed by the author to demonstrate the glyph approach to depicting higherdimensional data sets. It accepts data from the clipboard of a Macintosh personal computer with minimum format constraints, and automatically scales the display for physical size of glyph, location of glyph, and color mapping based on the mean and standard deviation of columns. If you copy a 625 row and 25 column table from the clipboard, the system will present the data as a major matrix of 20x25 cells and a minor matrix within each cell of 5x5 elements. It will calculate the mean and standard deviation for each column in the Once the default display is constructed, the investigator has control over several of the mappings from data to graphic that take place:</p><p>1 . Shape of display matrix 2. Number of standard deviations above and below the mean to establish color thresholds 3. Shape of elements 4. Non-standardized scaling of elements to emphasize certain variables, bringing them into the perceptual foreground, as it were.</p><p>5. Visibility and color coding of elements.</p><p>6. Alternate support geometry consisting of an Wimensional Euclidian distance measure/scaling facility that allows the selection of any subset of variables to be grouped and computed as the y axis and any other subset of variables to be grouped and computed as the x axis of a scatter diagram. In this technique the entire glyph is presented instead of a single point, with or without labels. 7. Limited animation facility for moving the color threshold down from the top and up from the bottom of the range partition in regular steps, allowing the perception of the "knottedness" of variables in higher dimensional space, as well as the general distribution of values within the entire data set.</p><p>The key features are: "tomated translation of data format</p><p>This increases the likelihood of using the program, and of submitting interesting or important data to it.</p><p>for an initial display:</p><p>1. Size and position of glyph and its internal elements 2. Subranges within value ranges for color coding 3. Color assignment This also increases the attractiveness of the program, and greatly improves the researcher's orientation to the data.</p><p>Interactive control over color map, shape'assignment and differential scaling of elements.</p><p>Once the general layout of the data has been assessed, many The experiment was to depict all parameters simultaneously, and see if any global or local patterns emerged. Several difficulties attended the use of this data which should be noted. The occlusion of the sensor bearing satellites by the earths magnetotail results in dropouts in the data set, with several parameters missing for days at a time. In <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> the missing data has been coded as solid black elements. (The last sample screen on the video.) The scale of the set, at approximately 6000 data points, was appropriate for the visual coding strategy of depicting each hour as a sub matrix of solid squares within the display matrix. The Display.</p><p>(Please refer to figures)</p><p>The display matrix presented one entire day's data on one row, with twentyane rows. This arrangement leaves space at the bottom of the screen for the detail alphanumeric data, which is polled by the cursor. By allowing polling of alphanumeric detail in real time, the investigator is free to look for and interrogate any number of POtential visual patterns without the ir, terruptions of continual requests to display and discard display of alphanumeric identities or values. The Figures. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. This is a laserwriter snapshot of a color screen which maps the value set as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1. Missing values -&gt; White 2. Low values -&gt; Grey 3. Mid Values -&gt; White 4. High Values -&gt; Black</formula><p>In the third and fourth rows from the top and bottom (the sy"e try is coincidental) there is a dense clustering of high and low values which show both identifiable shape and shape development over time as a function of the topology of the higher dimensional space. succeeds in indicating to the irivestigator some areas to follow up. One example starts to take shape in row three, column four, is established in column 7 and breaks up in column 12. The "z" shape that occurs consists of high readings in the field magnitude, average vector, ion density, kp, c9 and sunspot indices. A slight sub pattern of low value in flow latitude starts to a p pear. When the middle of the "z" drops out in column 12, the element to the left of center goes high, along with the ele As an exploratory device this ment on the right edge of the center row, forming a broken donut.</p><p>An even stronger sequence starts in row 3, column 18 and contim ues through row 4, column 12, or further, depending upon the investigators sense of threshold for shape groups. An interesting set of diagonal triplets starts to take shape at the end of row 14. is quite coherent through the first eight hours of row 15, struggles to r e shape itself through the remainder of row 15 before giving up at the end of the row. Finally, at the end of row 17 there is an echo of the morphology of row 3 and 4. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. This maps the values as; This allows the operator to perceive grouping of high and low values within individual cells, while discriminating between the high and low. scaling assignments have been changed. One variable of interest has been assigned a outline circle shape, and its scaling has been increased to five times normal in order to exaggerate its variation while preserving information about activity among the other variables. A related variable has been assigned a filled circle shape, while r e taining its normal scaling. This is a technique that establishes and exploits a "figure-ground" relationship among variables that is determined interactively, according to the operator's priority. It is difficult to explain interactive visualization methods in print, but an analogy might be made with the stops on an organ, that affect timbre, voicing, etc. across the entire range of tones. In this respect, it can be understood that nonlinear quantitative operations can serve the interest of qualitative perception, which pays off in distinctions that are ultimately quantitative, but not predictable from the initial conditions or appearance.</p><p>maps are the same as in <ref type="figure">Fig. c3</ref>, but the value subrange thresholds are changed consistently among all variables as follows:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure c3</head><p>In this figure the shape and High values, &gt;+30</p><p>This serves two main purposes: as a decluttering strategy it simplifies the visual field. As a quantitative strategy it identifies distribution of extreme values within the data set.</p><p>Visual browsing of higher dimensional displays is a supplement to the numerical and statistical analysis of patterns, trends, and exceptions within the data. There are several methods for extracting some shape sense from higher dimensional data sets, such as principle component analysis, multidimensional scaling, cluster analysis, and variants on these techniques. Most of these techniques are forced to make assumptions about the distribution of values within the data set. The visual inspection of the data patterns does not require that any assumptions be made.</p><p>. .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>jmpltcations of the research and furthe r directions,</head><p>This experiment proves that much more complex data can be pre sented for visual pattern extraction than standard methods allow. This has significant implications for traditional database management problems, where "similarity recognition" is more important than set-t heoretic filtering and extraction.</p><p>Other methods of shape coding might involve more sophisticated visual techniques that exploit visual edge d e tection, negative space perception, and complementary value enhancement . A display feature that treated each glyph as one frame in an animated sequence would combine motion and shape coding for enhanced feature extraction.</p><p>More time needs to be spent in lab conditions comparing subject r e sponse to the display to computed r e sponse. Other methods of interactively changing display characteristics in real time need to be developed on more powerful microcomputers. Studies need to be made of the crossover threshold where the "gestalts" of each glyph become mere texture compo nents of a large field display.</p><p>Interactive methods of marking groups to submit for further analysis are necessary. Neural network methods could be used to characterize and recognize distinctions among data sets, and qualitative infrastructures within the data set.</p><p>More research needs to be done in which traditional knowledge of competent graphic artists is combined with "transparent" interface strategies to facilitate browsing and rapid remap ping of display parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>knowledaements; -</head><p>The author would especially like to acknowledge Lloyd Treinish, then of Goddard, now of IBM, and H. Kent Hills, of Goddard, for their patient assistance in acquiring and interpreting the data set used in this paper.  In this figure the shape and scaling assignments have been changed. One variable of interest has been assigned a outline circle shape, and its scaling has been increased to fwe times normal in order to exaggerate its variation. A related variable has been assigned a filled circle shape, while retaining its normal scaling. This is a technique that extablishes and exploits a "figure ground" relationship among variables that is determined interactively, according to the operatots priorities. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure C 4 (Color Plate 712, page 478)</head><p>In this figure the shape and color maps arr the same as in <ref type="figure">Fig. c3</ref>, but the value subrange thresholds are changed consistently among all variables as folows: Low values, &lt;-30 Middle values, between -30 and +30 High values, &gt;+30 This serves two main purposes: as a decluttering strategy it simplifies the visual fkld. As a quantitative strategy it identifies distribution of extreme values within the data set.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>variations can be tried by the operator in establishing an optimum figurelground relationship between high and low-priority variables or parame ters</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure c 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>In this figure the shape and color Low values, c-30 Middle values, between -30 and +30</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Any mistakes in interpretation are entirely my O M .FO I IOW-U D "The Blackboard", a newsletter on this and related topics, is currently published by the author of this paper.This maps the values as;1. Missing values --&gt; Black 2. Low values --&gt; Blue3. Mid Values --&gt; Red 4. High Values --&gt; GreenThe entire data set is displayed as it would appear to the operator on initial conditions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure ~3 (</head><label>~3</label><figDesc>Co/or Plate 111, page 478)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This maps the values as;1. Missing values --&gt; White 2. Low values --&gt; Cyan 3. Mid Values --&gt; White 4. High Values --&gt; Red This allows the operator to perceive grouping of high and low values within individual cells, while discriminating between the high and low.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>table, and assign colors to each of three subranges and zero or missing data values within the column value range. The default sub</figDesc><table><row><cell>ranges are:</cell></row><row><cell>Low values, c-1 o</cell></row><row><cell>Middle values, between -1 o and +1 o</cell></row><row><cell>High values, &gt;+ 1 o</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
