<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PERSONAL VISUALIZATION SYSTEM: APPLICATIONS IN RESEARCH AND ENGINEERING</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dolecek</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory Laurel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20707</postCode>
									<settlement>Maryland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moorjani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory Laurel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20707</postCode>
									<settlement>Maryland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory Laurel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20707</postCode>
									<settlement>Maryland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tilley</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory Laurel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20707</postCode>
									<settlement>Maryland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Denney</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory Laurel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>20707</postCode>
									<settlement>Maryland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PERSONAL VISUALIZATION SYSTEM: APPLICATIONS IN RESEARCH AND ENGINEERING</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper describes an innovative personal visualization system and its application to several research and engineering problems. The system bridges both hardware and sofiware components to permit a user to graphically describe a visualization problem to the computer; thereby reducing program development time to a few hours. Low-cost visualization is achieved using PC-based sofiware that can either be executed on the PC or drive graphic workstations for high resolution displays. In either case, supercomputer computation rates are made available to the visualization process. On Pc&apos;s this is done with one or more Pip plug in cards, each of which is capable of 100 million floating point operations per second. On workstations this is done with the QUENTM (trademark of Interstate Electronics Corporation, Anaheim, California) array processor. Problem Visualization Ivan E. Sutherland, a pioneer in the programming of computers to create and manipulate images, once remarked: &quot;I think of a computer display as a window on Alice&apos;s Wonderland in which a programmer can depict either objects that obey well-known laws or purely imaginary objects that follow laws he has written into his program. Through computer displays I have landed an airplane on the deck of a moving carrier, observed a nuclear particle hit a potential well, flown in a rocket at nearly the speed of light and watched a computer reveal it&apos;s innermost workings.&quot; This is the process of visualization. Until recently Sutherland&apos;s experience of visualizing an event or problem through the seemingly magical powers of interactive computer graphics could be shared only by a handful of people: mainly scientists and engineers engaged in computer-aided design and mathematical modeling. Even here, visualization was limited by computational speed and the requirement to write complex code for each application. Although many of the elements for problem visualization exists today, effective visualization lies beyond the reach of most. What is needed is an open-ended system that brings high speed computation and graphic displays together for user applications without requiring extensive coding.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Personal Visualization System (PVS) is such a system. This software bridges existing software packages and hardware systems for visualization.</p><p>It aims to empower nonprogramming end users to solve their own visualization problems. This is done by allowing a user to rapidly compose a new application or integrate an existing application with graphic displays and high speed computation while insulating the user from low level hardware details and the coding of graphic displays. It is operational on personal computers and VAX workstations.</p><p>PVS has three basic components: (1) a user interface that is easily understood, easily used, and graphic in nature, <ref type="formula">2</ref>an open-ended Blackbox structure that accepts existing routines and integrates them into the entire visualization process, and (3) integrated system elements and calls that provide supercomputer computation rates using the QUE"</p><p>[I] processor. The result is an unprecedented level of integration for simulation, analysis, and visualization. A person familiar with flowcharting and Microsoft Windows or the Macintosh type icon menu will be able to rapidly learn to use PVS. Then problem visualization will be limited only by the user's imagination and perception of a problem.</p><p>In order to use PVS, you must fist come to grips with some key concepts including objects, variables, cards, elements, and Blackboxes. An object is anything on the screen that you select to make something happen (like a screen button or icon).</p><p>A variable is an object (whether it is displayed on the screen or not) that contains changeable information. A card is an object that contains other objects such as screen buttons, text, and images. This is similar to a card in Hypercard. An element is an object in the flowchart that performs a specific action such as displaying a variable or computing a numerical transform. A Blackbox is an element that contains an external function or routine. implemented. All PVS programs are built in the form of flowcharts. They define the computations and actions of a program by invoking intemal elements and using extemal routines through Blackboxes. You typically start the program creation process by drawing a rough flowchart outline of your process. You continue refining and extending the rough flowchart by adding elements, Blackboxes, images, and control menus built on cards. The Card Tool in Mamx Layout is used to design and modify cards as they are needed. Any required extemal routines, not already in PVS, are entered by generating Blackboxes using the Blackbox Manager. Blackboxes may be written in any language that results in executable code blocks or results in object code blocks compatible with BASIC, C, or PASCAL. PVS then generates C code to execute the flowchart and interact with any Blackboxes used. The generated C code is then compiled and run on the target system. Thus, the user enters an application via a flowchart, but has the option of using high level languages and assembly code as components of the flowchart.</p><p>Graphic displays are done with Hoops [3] and PV-Wave [41.</p><p>Hoops is an object oriented display system that implements interactive two-and three-dimensional displays on a 80386 PC or VAX Workstation. Although Hoops can handle raster scan (pixel) type displays, raster displays must be rectangular and are limited in rotation, view, and transformation capabilities. PV-Wave provides high level computation functions and full raster scan display capabilities.</p><p>Ultrahigh speed computation is provided by a memory linked wavefront m y processor. This is implemented with a QUE" processor on VAX computers and with pip (Parallel Information Processor) on personal computers. When plugged into the PC-AT or an 80386 personal computer, P P provides  to go to infinity, where C = X + jY, and X and Y are the coordinates of an image pixel. Of course one does not wait for the numbers actually to go to infinity, but to some escape value T. If Z escapes within some number of iterations N, the X,Y pixel is assigned a color representing the number of iterations required for escape. If not, it is assigned the color black.</p><p>The top level flowchart for this computation is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure  2</ref>. The first block in the figure opens PVS for a program. The second block opens a window on the display screen to enter control parameters and show computation results. A continuous loop is then entered that reads input parameters and plots the resultant image until the STOP screen button on the display is selected. The user enters computation parameters in the fifth block by filling out the card image shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. Block 6 calls a procedure, written by the same graphic flowchart method, to perform the interactive computation. This procedure called a Blackbox to do the actual computation on a 16-element QUE" processor. The final action in the loop is to display the results using the PVS Display Analysis command.</p><p>The result of a typical computation is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>. This 400 x 400 pixel image was computed and displayed on a VAX 3500 Workstation, using the QUEN processor, in less than 2 seconds. It required over 500 million floating point operations to compute. The same image could be generated on a 80386 PC. This would require many hours on the PC alone, or less Because computer graphics are a way of making thoughts and ideas visible, Sutherland's magic window is becoming the universal language of our time. PVS brings the privilege of exploring real and imaginary worlds through the looking glass of the computer to a broad range of applications. This is illustrated in the following applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ocean Wave Imagine Application</head><p>This application required complex computations on massive data sets. The problem addressed by PVS was the transfer of existing code to a VAX computer using a QUE" array processor to achieve "real time" displays. The application also required the development of code to produce image displays. A synthetic aperture radar (SAR) specialist, with no supercomputer experience, was able to easily move the application to the PVS system and display an image. This resulted in the computation time for a typical image reducing from about 3 hours to less then a minute. The first PVS image display resulted in several ideas for more informative images that are now being explored.</p><p>The Labrador Sea Extreme Waves Experiment (LEWEX) was an international effort to assess methods of modeling and measuring the directional aspects of wind generated ocean waves. Two dimensional fields of cross section data were collected by a C-band synthetic aperture. radar mounted on a Convair-580 aircraft operated by the Canada Centre for Remote Sensing. An on-board processor recorded 8-bit integer data as a seven look summation of the backscattered intensity after Doppler frequency compression of the pulsed radar signal. On 18 March 1987, the aircraft SAR system observed a northerly wind wave generated system recording picture elements (pixels) in slant range perspective with 4.OOm and 3.89m resolution across and along the radar track. The SAR image was radiometrically corrected and geometrically rectified to a ground range projection on a square 12.5m grid at the Applied Physics Laboratory of the Johns Hopkins University.</p><p>A 512x512 pixel segment (6.4 kilometers square) of the ocean scene has been Fourier filtered to reduce the speckle noise inherent in the coherent SAR measurement of pixel cross section and to restore wave height significance. Prior to Fourier transformation, the image was preprocessed to subtract and divide by the mean scene intensity. After application of the Fourier transform, the Fourier power statistics were computed from the 64-bit complex valued wave spectrum. These power spectrum statistics were used to define a power threshold below which both the real and imaginary Fourier amplitudes were reduced by a factor of lbo. This reduced the Fourier power over approximately 97% of the wavenumber domain without changing the Fourier phase. Wave height significance was restored to the principal Fourier descriptors by applying a spectral modulation model based on theories of surface tilting and velocity bunching acting independently in the across track and along track coordinates, respectively. Fourier power was then redistributed according to these modulation theories [5] by reducing the real and imaginary Fourier aplitudes by a common factor at any given point in the Fourier domain. An inverse Fourier transform was then applied to the complex spectrum; resulting in an 8-bit surface elevation database in phase with the original cross section database.</p><p>200x150 pixel segments of the databases were selected for visual assessment of spatial correlations between surface elevation and texture. The Fourier filtered database, representing Ocean wave height variance, was used to define a threedimensional surface. That surface was then shaded with the original SAR database, representing sea surface texture. The result is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref>. The appearance of short scale features windward of the long wave crests suggests a wave sheltering modulation of roughening at the radar resonant wavelength. The apparent spilling of capillary breakers down the forward faces of the Ocean waves also suggests that SAR image speckle may be useful in researching non-homogeneous surface hydrodynamics. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Characterizing Superconductors Application</head><p>This application addressed the ease of using PVS and the requirement for high computational speed on a low cost system. The application was easily coded in less then a day using PVS on a 386SX personal computer. The resulting program and main computation loop is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref>  A novel method for characterizing superconductors has recently been developed [6] which assesses not only intrinsic properties of superconductors, but also the morphology or granularity of a sample <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">[7,8]</ref>. In. this method, magnetically modulated resistance (MMR) vs. temperature is recorded. An example of typical results is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7</ref> for a high temperature ceramic superconductor, EuBa+2u,07., (EBCO). The shapes of these curves is seen to be influenced by the magnetic field. A similar type of dependence occurs for the current in the sample.</p><p>This behavior of the MMR response curves with magnetic field and current depends upon the morphology of the sample. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref> shows a micrograph of this particular sample which shows the granular morphology. The grain size distribution in the sample ultimately determines the behavior of the MMR response curves.</p><p>A model for simulating the experimental MMR response in superconductors has been developed [8]. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 9</ref> shows the results of a simulation of the experimental results in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7</ref> using a random distribution of effective grain sizes. The predicted behavior of the curves with respect to current and field is in good agreement with the experimental curves, indicating that the assumed distribution is valid. This distribution was inferred by mal and error, and is in qualitative agreement with micrographs obtained with a scanning electron microscope.</p><p>These results form the basis for a functional measure of the granularity of superconductors using MMR. The MMR vs. temperature is recorded for a number of different values of magnetic field or current. This information can then be displayed as a three dimensional surface. Corresponding surface displays can be computed using the model for simulating MMR with various grain size distribution. The computed surfaces are compared visually with the experimentally generated surface. The surface which most closely agrees with the experimental surface provides the best estimate for the grain size distribution.</p><p>Reduction of the model computation time from days to minutes not only permits practical applications of the method, but also is critical to further research. The ease of using PVS will also permit the development of enhanced models.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Solar Sail Visualization</head><p>This application used PVS to animate simulations of a complicated mechanical process.</p><p>The results were dramatic. Designers were able to insert their model simulation software into PVS in a few hours. The first animated run yielded insights on the process that were not even suspected prior to visualization. Now PVS visualization is an integral part of the design process.</p><p>The JHU-APL Solar Sail Consortium is designing a solar sail spacecraft to compete in the Columbus 500 Space Sail Cup race to Mars. The spacecraft is powered by a 208 meter diameter circular sail held flat by a large hoop as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>.</p><p>The sail is composed of 480 triangular pieces arranged like the petals of a flower. On Earth, the alumized mylar petals are    individually rolled onto long, thin spools which form the hoop when the sail is unfurled. These spools are connected end-toend by flexible springs and bunched together so the entire spacecraft can be packed into the nose of a Pegasus rocket. Once the Pegasus is in orbit, the solar sail spacecraft is released, and the springs cause the sail to unfurl. If the sail does not unfurl properly, the race is lost. Since it is not feasible to build a prototype of a sail this size on Earth, a mathematical model of the sail is used to simulate the unfurling process. Each of the 480 petals requires 12 state variables to describe its motion. Consequently, 5760 numbers are generated for each time step. This large amount of data is virtually impossible to analyze without the aid of visualization.</p><p>of bridging levels of abstraction between "system" users and advanced superprocessing. By providing a graphic method for describing problems to the computer and bridging software packages, PVS permits rapid development of complex visualization problems. Cost is reduced by an order of magnitude using the PC-based parallel processor card Pip. In summary, PVS is an innovative and affordable solution to problem visualization.</p><p>PVS was used to visualize this unfurling process by using the state variables at each time step to display an animated three dimensional drawing of the hoop similar to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>. With this method, problems such as oscillations or tangling are spotted easily and parameters such as spring constants, damping, or sail thickness can be changed to correct them. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>Visualization can actually simulate creativity. The power of superprocessing makes visualization possible, but often difficult and costly. Lengthy software development time can be required for producing even simple images. The Personal Visualization System reduces these problem and the difficulty QUEN Processor User's Guide, Interstate Electronics</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>shows a component block diagram of PVS. Developing an application involves using the tools in Matrix Layout [2] to make a flow-chart of the process to beFigure 1. Components of the Personal Visualization System.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Top level flowchart in PVS for the computation and display of Manelbrot Fractals.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Control menu for Fractal program generated using the Card Tool in Matrix Layout. from 80 to 640 million floating point operations per second depending on the model used. Computations are invoked by Blackboxes in the flowchart of a process. Use of PVS is illustrated with the computation of a Mandelbrot fractal in Figures 2 and 3. The fractal is a representation of the number of iterations required for the complex function z = z z + c</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>A typical 400x400 Fractal display done using PVS with direct calls to the VAX display system.(Color Plate 186, page 490)then 7 seconds using the slowest Pip processor plugged into the PC.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>texture done with PV-Wave under PVS.(Color Plate 187, page 491)Visual synthesis of Ocean surface elevation and</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. This program requires over 17 hours of computation on a 20Mhz 386 personal computer. Replacing the 386 computer Blackbox calls shown in the figure with Pip Blackbox calls reduces computation time to a few minutes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Personal Visualization System program for computation of superconductor model. Blackboxes shown in the main computation loop can be done either on a PC or the PiP PCcard.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>......................................... ...... :... .... t . . . . . . . Magnetic field dependence of the MMR response (dotted) and dc resistance (xl-solid, xl0-dashed) of EuBa&amp;O,., using a current of 5mA.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Micrograph of ceramic superconductor EBCO showing the granular morphology which determines the behavior of the MMR response curves.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Results of a simulation of the experimental results inFigure 7using a random distribution of effective grain sizes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 11 .</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Solar sail visualization using a model driven wireframe display with HOOPS. (Color Plete 189, page 407) References Figure 10. Solar sail spacecraft. ( m o r Phto 1-p g o 491)</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How To Turn Your Ideas Into Reality</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Matrix Software Technology Corporation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Anaheim, CA; Boston, MA; Ithaca Software, Alameda, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Corporation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Pv-Wave Desktop Reference</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Precision Visuals, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Tilley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">John Hopkins APL Technical Digest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Johns Hopkins University, Applied Physics Laboratory</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moorjani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bohandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Adrian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Shull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Swartzendruber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4036</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Adrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moorjani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2029</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bohandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Adrian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moojani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">904</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">929</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>U.S</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Johns Hopkins University, Applied Physics Laboratory</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bohandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Adrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moorjani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
