<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">VISUALIZATION FOR THE INFORMATION AGE</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Laurin</forename><surname>Herr</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Pacific Interface New York</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10023</postCode>
									<region>New York</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">VISUALIZATION FOR THE INFORMATION AGE</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HDTV and the Digital Video TelecomDuter</head><p>HDTV is much more than big TV. HDTV raises the prospect that all visual media --TV, film, photography, and printing -will share a "master" digital image format. HDTV stimulates the fusion of computers, communications, and television. It pushes the envelope of performance, expands applications, and raises the stakes of the information age.</p><p>This case study explains the basic parameters of current TV, traces the origins of HDTV, and prepares the viewer for a discussion of the c m n t debate over HDTV standards. It also explains the various "flavors" of new TV being proposed in Japan, America and Europe.</p><p>This presentation reports on available HDTV hardware, new applications that this hardware enables, and the economics involved. It looks at how HDTV fits into the film and television industries from the perspectives of production, distribution and creativity. Another part of this presentation explores HDTV's demands upon telecommunications and explains why data compression plays a critical role. In addition, it spotlights the resonances between HDTV and computer graphics, animation, and image processing.</p><p>Discussions include the expected schedule for HDTV introduction and examination of the economics and leadership issues in light of the digital technologies that may carry HDTV beyond 1125160. Ahead: the digital video telecomputer of the information age.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Workstations and the Ouest for Virtual Realite</head><p>We have entered the information age. The ability to integrate high speed digital computation and communication creates the need for new types of tools. These tools will build upon rapid hardware advances and exploit increasingly intuitive user interfaces. What will evolve is a "desktop digital video telecomputer," the ubiquitous general purpose multimedia work platform of the 21st century.</p><p>The presentation traces the evolution of the present workstation from many analytical perspectives, leading up to the most recent product introductions of all the major vendors. Also, it views the developments in accelerator boards and interactive graphics peripherals.</p><p>Another highlight is the focus on the evolution of the madmachine interface. In the 2D domain, this leads to the paradigms of the interactive desktop, the "dashboard to the network," and multimediamypermedia. In the 3D domain, the quest has been to create a Virtual Reality that can transcend the barrier of the screen by making the interface intuitively transparent.</p><p>The conclusion takes a brief look at the not so futuristic promise of virtual reality and telepresence, the applications and business opportunities that will emerge, and the hardware and software technologies that will make it a practical tool.</p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="429">r</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
