<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Extracting Geometric Models Through Constraint Minimization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Design Research Center Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute Troy</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Breen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Design Research Center Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute Troy</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wozny</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Rensselaer Design Research Center Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute Troy</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Extracting Geometric Models Through Constraint Minimization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Geometric models that represent the features in a greyscale image allow for alternative visualizations of the features. These alternatives can lead to a greater understanding of the extents and interrelationships of the features in the image. We present a technique that extracts the geometric nature of a feature by constraining a known geometric model to conform to the characteristics of the feature. The constraints embody local properties of simple polygons and the nature of the relationship between noise and the features in the image. By minimizing these constraints we are able to deform ow initial model to fit the feature.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The extraction of geometric models that represent the features of interest in an image is one of the techniques of image analysis and understanding. By visualizing the geometric models of the features; one can gain a better understanding of the spatial extents, locations and separations of the features without the clutter of noise and irrelevant features. The difficulty in extracting geometry from images arises from the nature of the image data. Image data represents an estimate of a scene, since the imaging process may introduce artifacts that distort the scene. Simple closed objects may be mapped into features with holes or leaks (finite regions where the feature is indistinguishable from the background). Extracting just the edges of such a feature will result in an object with little resemblance to the original.</p><p>The goal in extracting geometry from images is to generate a topologically accurate representation of the initial object. Unfortunately, current methods either do not guarantee a topologically connected model, or they require techniques which may be more complicated than necessary. Traditional methods identify edges either through digital gradients <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref> or through a minimization of edge type components 121 and then stitch the edges together to form a connected model (a difficult task at best). We propose a methodology that will extract a topologically closed geometric model from a 2D image. This is accomplished by starting with a simple model that is already topologically closed, and deforming the model based on aset of constraints, so that the model grows (shrinks) to fit the feature within the image while maintaining its closed and locally simple nature. The initial model is a non-selfintersecting polygon that is either embedded in the feature or surrounds the feature. There is a cost function associated with every vertex that quantifies its deformation, the properties of simple polygons, and the relationship between noise and feature. By minimizing these constraints an effect similar to a balloon inflating within a container or a piece of shrink wrap compressing around an object can be achieved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods and Analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Problem Space</head><p>The problem space that we are addressing consists of a feature that can be described by a single topologically simple polygon. This does imply that the feature itself is closed, but merely that the approximation (model) of the feature is closed. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> illustrates several features that could have been distorted by the imaging process and the geometric models that may represent them. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> (a) contains concavities which may be ignored. In this case, a polygon would "shrink wrap" around the feature. <ref type="figure">Figure  1</ref> (b) contains concavities in the opposite nature as in 1 (a). The model in 1 (b) could be generated by expanding a model from within the feature (like a balloon). Figm 1 (c) is riddled with noise and leaks, but a model can still be generated by expanding a model from within the feature. <ref type="figure">Figure 1 (d)</ref> consists of a feature whose boundary is hardly defined, however, we can still generate a model of the feature by expanding the initial model from within the feature. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definitions</head><p>To insure a proper frame of reference, we will provide our definitions of the various components of an image.  Each of these constraints can be characterized by one of the following four classes.</p><p>Class I -Interacting with a Feature This class of constraint is used to stop the deformation of the model in a point's current direction. Basically this constraint simply informs the vertex that it may be in contact with a feature pixel. This constraint need not be able to distinguish noise and feature, but must be able to identify the case, a frame of reference can be any configuration of image or model parameters. The frame of reference may be a point inside the feature to be modeled, or it may be the set of vertex points in their previous configuration. A vertex point will move in the direction of the lowest local potential (in the absence of the other constraint classes). This function must be monotonically decreasing (or increasing) from the frame of reference. For instance, the deformation potential could repel (attract) all the vertex points from the original centroid of the model or it could repel (attract) the current vertex point from every other vertex point in the system. In order to "shrink wrap" a feature, the vertex points must be attracted to something;</p><p>while in order to expand a model, the vertex points must be repelled. A variety of functions fit this description e.g.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>l/r2 (or r').</head><p>Due to the relative magnitudes of the remaining class constraints, we use the following function to expand a model to fill a feature (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">figure 3)</ref> where:</p><p>(20, 90) is the location of the focal point (frame of reference),</p><p>g is a weight that allows for the priority of this function to be altered, M is the maximum distance the point can travel (typically the diagonal of the image).</p><p>L Distance from focal point Class III -NoidFeatwe Relationship The third class of constraint quantifies the signal to noise relationship while it also maintains the distribution of vertex points around the perimeter of the model. The deformation POtential will not affect all the vertex points equally if the frame of reference is a poorly chosen point within the feature. The effect will be that portions of the model will deform at a rate far greater than other portions of the model. While this is desirable to a certain extent, it is undesirable for a few points to leak out the holes in the feature and continue on their paths toward infinity. This constraint must control the distances between neighboring vertex points so that there is very little local variation in the distance between neighboring vertex points; but still allow a global variation in the distance between neighboring vertex points. The constraint is modeled through a piecewise continuous function. If the inter-point distance is within an acceptable region, there is no cost added to the system. When the inter-point distance exceeds the bounds of this acceptable region, a monotically increasing function is returned (i.e. the further the bounds are exceeded, the larger the cost).</p><p>The parameter we developed to allow small local variations and possibly large global variations in the inter-point distance is called the local or neighbor mean. Here, each point w i l l calculate the mean distance between neighbors for a subset of the points in the model. Specifically, each point w i l l calculate the average distance between neighbors for typically one to six neighbors to each si&amp; (see dmin is typically 20% below the local average distance @) while d,,, is typically 20% above the local average distance @). The cost function then uses the parameters dmin and d,,, along with the current distances to each of the immediate neighbors <ref type="figure">( d l e j t , dright)</ref> to generate a piecewise continuous function. If the current distance to a neighbor is between <ref type="figure">[d,;,, d,,,]</ref>, the function contributes nothing to the total cost to the system. However, if the distance to a neighbor is less than dmin <ref type="figure">or greater than d,,,,</ref> the cost function contributes a linear term which is the amount the distance exceeds the limits. This portion of the cost function con- This constraint quantifies the signal to noise relationship by classifying any portion of the image that can squeeze between adjacent model points to be interpreted as noise.</p><p>A feature would be a collection of pixels that is far too large to fit between neighboring model points. This constraint effectively provides an adaptive sampling of the feature. Note that if more model points are used, then the interpoint distance will decrease and smaller collections of pixels will be interpreted as features.</p><p>Class local minimum in either of these two cases by contributing a monotonically increasing cost that is a function of how much the local configuration is violating the spatial bandwidth. By controlling the local spatial bandwidth, you can insure that the topology of the model will remain intact during the minimization process. Without this constraint, the polygon may not remain simple due to noise confrontation and hence violate the topology constraint</p><p>To implement this constraint we monitor the angle formed by connecting a model point to its neighbors (a) ( <ref type="figure">figure   5</ref>). If a large number of points are used and the initial model is a circle, then a initially is 1800. We limit the amount that a can vary by bounding it by f15%. If a stays within these bounds then no cost is added to the system, otherwise a cost proportional to the amount that a exceeds the bounds is added to the system. This can be expressed by a set of piecewise continuous linear functions (figure 6)</p><p>current p i n t right neighbor  <ref type="figure">between [a,,,;,,</ref> , amall. Otherwise a linear cost proportional to the error is contributed to the cost of the system. <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> illustrates "shrink wrapping" a CT scan of a turbine blade. The original image is 512x512~16 bits. The model consists of 200 vertex points distributed about an ellipse. The vertex points are attracted to a point within the turbine blade through a deformation potential of r2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>There is a gain on @(a) of 10, a is allowed to fluctuate 15% from its original value, one neighbor to each side of the current model point is used to determine the local mean, and the inter-point distance is maintained within 20% of the local mean. Using a DECStation 3100, we are able to extract the models described in roughly 50 seconds. The ability to expand a model in real time will allow for the development of an interactive system where the user can pick the cavity and initial location of a model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>An image can be visualized as an elevation map where the grey level indicates a measure of altitude. The boundaries of features will appear as peaks or rolling ridges of large area, whereas noise will appear as high peaks covering very little area. The image term we use simply reduces the height of all peaks (noise or boundary of feature) and sets the remainder of the image (region below the threshold) to some constant plateau (zero). The model then travels along the plateau until it hits a ridge on the elevation map. If the point tries to travel up the ridge it will slide back down to a position of lower potential. If a point encounters an element of noise it will move around the peak instead of trying to move over the peak. If the inter-point distance is smaller than the noise, the points encountering that noise will have to travel up the sides of the noise peak in order to satisfy the distance constraint. This will cause an increase in cost and may hinder that portion of the model from straddling the noise.</p><p>The form of edge determination used here (simple threshold) works well with scanned images, but if standard camera images are used then a more sophisticated edge detection algorithm should be employed. This will be necessary since the background illumination will vary through the image. Digital gradients <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref>, the Canny operator <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, or rolling ball algorithms [8, 91 should be used to define an edge or reduce the amount of background illumination.</p><p>The deformation functions we use provide a very fast method for expanding or contracting a model, but for best results requires that (zo, yo) be somewhat near the center of the feature. The dependence on the location of the focal point has been minimized by the local mean (neighbor mean) parameter. For the features that we have modeled, we place a circle with a radius of one pixel inside the feature and repel the points from its center or we use a circumscribing ellipse as the initial model and attract the vertex points to a p i n t within the feature. The circle is the best choice for the initial model if nothing is known about the basic shape of the feature. But if the feature was known to be long and skinny; then an ellipse could be used as the initial model, and the points in the model could be repelled (attracted) from the line connecting the foci of the ellipse.</p><p>By using the local mean for maintaining the distribution of points along the model; each point will behave in a fashion similar to its neighbors, rather than behaving like the average case in the model or like independent entities. This allows for points to reach the boundary of the feature without limiting the movement of the points still expanding. It also allows for points to keep expanding without effecting the points that have reached the boundary. Note that if only one neighbor to each side is used to calculate parameter p , the current point is kept equidistant from both its neighbors (within the percentage of p used to cal- culate dmin and dmaz). In fact the best results have been obtained from the features tested when only one neighbor to each side is used to calculate the local mean.</p><p>Since the distances between neighbors is allowed to fluctuate throughout the model, the points will dishibute themselves to accommodate the variations in the boundary as well as minimize the adverse effect of deforming the model relative to some non-central focal point. Portions of the model are allowed to reach the boundary of the feature far in advance of the remainder of the model, allowing distant gulleys to be reached. Since the distances between neighbors is allowed to fluctuate slightly without an additional cost added to the system, the model will stretch in order to pull its points off of noise and to conform to the variations in the boundary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Characteristics of Constraint Based Model Extraction</head><p>Constraint based model extraction attempts to give the computer the same subjective contour extending abilities that are commonplace with the human eye. Our eye naturally extends broken contours across small voids to generate a virtually closed cavity so that we can better understand the extent and shape of the cavity. We actually say that we can see a fully connected boundary, or at least where the boundary would have been if it were there. However, getting a computer to perfm subjective contour extentions is not so simple. The methodology that Although the mechanism for expanding the model is constant throughout the deformation, different components of the cost function dominate during various phases of the deformation. Initially the deformation potential will dominate the cost function resulting in rapid changes in the dimensions of the model. When an element of "noise" is encountered, the portions of the cost function that maintain the distribution of points and the basic shape of the model tend to dominate. The deformation will decelerate in the region containing the noise until the model has worked its way around the "noise". at which time the expansion will accelerate back to its initial velocity. When the majority of the points in the model have reached the boundary of the feature, the model will fluctuate slightly. This is caused by the algorithm constantly fine tuning the model in an attempt to find the maximum fit. One term in the cost function will dominate the expansion until another term decides that it is doing more harm than good. When this happens, another term will dominate temporarily in order to compensate for damages rendered.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minimization Technique</head><p>The software used to implement the minimization of the cost function was extracted from the cost-unulysis object <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> that was developed for The Clockworks <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, an animation and visualization system. The minimization technique uses an adaptive algorithm to move a point in the model in the direction of steepest descent along the cost surface. This direction is the gradient of the cost function Ci, and is estimated by numerically approximating the differentials % and 2. The amount that a point moves is adjusted based upon the past history of movements. The stepsize can be reduced if movement by the current stepsize results in an increase in the cost function; or the stepsize can be increased if the point takes numerous steps where the cost function decreases at every step. For the purposes of deforming a geometric model within an image, the stepsizes are maintained between [1/4, 21 pixels. This allows for rapid changes in the dimensions of the model when it is in a void as well as fine adjustments in the model when it encounters an element of noise or the boundary of the cavity. This is not a problem because we have set up the cost functions to introduce local minima whenever a critical point is found. A critical point occurs whenever a maintenance constraint (@(a), A(d)) is violated or when a possible feature pixel is encountered. The cost function is actually a summation of functions that calculate parameters from the current status of the model. The terms that maintain the shape and distribution of the model are zero until they determine that the current trend is violating the maintenance constraints. When this occurs, these portions of the cost function contribute a term that is linear with respect to the amount that the constraint is violated. This produces a local minima and a slope that will return the model to a state that is acceptable. Note that a maintenance constraint may be ignored if another term in the cost function is decreasing with a rate greater than the maintenance term is increasing. This allows for a priority to be assigned to the various constraints.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Future Work</head><p>This research will be extended to extract three-dimensional solids from slice or volume data. The principle will remain constant. A discrete model will be deformed to fit a feature through the minimization of a set of cost functions.</p><p>The initial model will most likely be some approximation to a sphere, similar to the circle used for 2D. The geometric model will be expanded in three dimensions allowing the model to wrap itself around any concavity in the feature. A simpler approach would be to extract a series of two-dimensional models from slice data and stitch the individual models together. The problem with this approach is that with the current two-dimensional algorithm, it will not allow for concavities in the direction normal to the slices. An example of such a cavity would be the inside of a wine bottle. If the bottle is standing, with slices taken perpendicular to the axis of symmetry; then the only way to get the model to wrap around the concavity in the bottom of the bottle is to expand it in 3D.</p><p>The parameters used to generate internal potentials, and hence control the shape and distribution of the model will have to be changed. If a straight transition is taken from 2D to 3D, the number of parameters that need to be controlled greatly increases. Despite having to develop new parameters for the three-dimensional case, the algorithm and methodology should extend without alterations. This should provide a fairly fast method for extracting a closed geometric model of an approximately closed threedimensional feature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary and Conclusions</head><p>We have presented a method of extracting the geometric nature of approximately closed features through the minimization of a constraint based system. Each vertex in a discrete model has a constraint equation to minimize.</p><p>The basic principle is that a point in the model should behave in a fashion similar to its neighbors. The constraints model the local properties of deformation, images, and simple polygons. The deformation can be an expansion or contraction, various boundary event detectors can be inserted, and alternative models for simple polygons can be used. Once a geometric model of a feature is generated, it can be used for visualization or analysis. The concept of constraint based geometry extraction also extends very easily to three-dimensions. Our future research will focus on extracting solid models of features within volume data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Lorensen and Cline have developed marching cubes [31 12180-3590 to extract three-dimensional polygonal surfaces from volume density data, but no information about connectivity is derived. Kass, Witkin and Terzopoulus have developed "Snakes" [4] which model the contours of an image by minimizing the energy associated with a spline. Tenopoulus, Witkin, and Kass extended the concept of snakes into symmetry-seeking models [SI, that derive three-dimensional shape from a two-dimensional image by modeling an mi-symetric elastic skin spread over a flexible spine. Bajcy and Kovacic used a multiresolution approach to elastically deform a known brain atlas to match a scanned brain[61.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>4 Figure 1</head><label>41</label><figDesc>Example features and the possibly useful geometric models. These illustrate the "shrink wrap" and "balloon expansion" characteristics of this method. Notice that in dl cases the features are not intact, but the models may be more accurate representations of the objects.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>pixels that is associated with an object.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The image term is a shifted threshold of the farm ( X -M)'. No cost is added if the intensity is below the threshold. Linear cost is applied if the intensity is above the threshold. transitions from a region of an image that could be a feature to regions of an image that is definitely not a feature. The important aspect of this constraint equation is that it introduces a local minima at b o u n m events. Operations that identify boundary events include digital gradients [I], the Canny operator [7], and morphological operations [8]. For our purposes, however, we have found it sufficient to use a simple threshold operation. Pixels above the threshold are possibly feature pixels, while pixels below the threshold are considered background. Our image term is actually a shifted threshold of the form (X-M)+ (figure 2), or more exactly Class 11 -Deformation Potential The deformation potential defines a scalar field where each position in space is assigned a value based on a frame of reference. In this</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Graph illustrating how the driving function presents a slope for the minimization technique to follow.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>figure 4 )Figure 4</head><label>44</label><figDesc>. The point is then maintained within a certain percentage of the local mean. The lacal mean is a weighted sum of inter-point distances(4) 1 P = ; Ipi+l(+, Y)pi(z, y)I i = k -n k + n where: n is the number of neighbors to each side of the current model point used to calculate p, pi (2, y) is the position of a neighboring model point (the ith model point; which could be the immediate neighbor, or the immediate neighbor's neighbor, etc.) within n neighbor links from the current point (the kth model point). r b Illusmation of the distances used to calculate the local mean. Here, two neighbors to each side of the current point are used in the calculation.The parameter p (local mean) is used to derive two other parameters @,in and d,,,).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>d m i n I dright 5 dmaz ( 6 )</head><label>6</label><figDesc>drightdmaz dright &gt; d m a z .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>IV -Spatial Frequency and Topological Moderator The fourth class of constraint controls the local spatial bandwidth of the perimeter of the model. As an important side effect, this constraint also maintains the model as a locally topologically simple polygon. The two shortcomings of digital images that constraint based modeling addresses, sampling artifacts and noise, are handled by the spatial frequency and topological moderator. The feature of interest may have a partially defined boundary or be riddled with noise (as in figure l b and c). Under these conditions, the deformation of the model vertex may need to stop before it finds the boundary of the feature (in fact it may never reach a boundary if it is directed towards a hole). If a point's neighbors have reached feature pixels and the current model point has not, then this may indicate that the current model point is in a hole. If a point has reached a feature pixel and its neighbors have not, then this may indicate that the current model point is on an element of noise. This constraint will introduce a</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 5 /Figure 6</head><label>56</label><figDesc>The parameter a is defined as the angle between the two vectors that connect the current model point to its immediate neighbors. Graph of the cost of violating the angle constraint. A constant cost (typically zero) is contributed to the system if (Y is</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 7 (Figure 70 )Figure 7 (Figure 7</head><label>77077</label><figDesc>a) (Color Plate 29, page 464) (Color Pbte 30, page 464) c) (Color Piate 31, page 465) Figure 7(d) (Color Plate 32, p e p 465) The deformation of an ellipse to "shrink wrap" a C I ' scan of a turbine blade.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>we have developed essentially extends contours by fitting connected segments across the breaks in the contours. This is done without ever determining explicitly what portions of the image are contour and what portions are breaks. By contracting a large model around a feature, the points on the model will approach the boundary of the feature. The points are connected by lines which may bridge small breaks in the contour. Note that in figure 7, the upper right boundary of the turbine blade has a concavity that the exnacted model bridges. The approach is based upon Witkin et al.'s work on energy constraints [lo] and Breen's work in generating goal-oriented motion [ll]. Here, the high-level motion of actors in a computer animation is produced by the definition and minimization of a cost function. The same idea is applied to constraint based model extraction by providing each point in the polygon with its own cost function to minimize. The cost function contains terms that reflect global conditions within the model as well as local conditions between various neighboring vertex points. These terms may be thought of as opposing potentials that either push the model towards the boundary or maintain various local constraints. The local nature of the constraints allows each vertex point to behave in a fashion similar to its neighbors while still allowing global variations in the model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This technique will find local minima. No global minimization techniques such as simulated annealing [2, 141 are performed; so global minima are not always found.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>a region where the boundary of a feature is missing. This may also be referred to as leak since if aflood fill is performed on the region, the fill would "leak" out the hole and spread through the image.</figDesc><table><row><cell>a collection of pixels that is small in</cell></row><row><cell>stature and is not associated with an</cell></row><row><cell>object. Noise may alter the boundary</cell></row><row><cell>of a feature, ur obstruct the constraint</cell></row><row><cell>minimization. It is very important that</cell></row><row><cell>the size of a feature be far greater than</cell></row><row><cell>the size of any noise element.</cell></row><row><cell>Constraint Classes</cell></row><row><cell>A constraint equation that is to be minimized is associated</cell></row><row><cell>with each vertex. The constraints reflect local properties</cell></row><row><cell>of simple polygons; the relationship between leaks, noise,</cell></row><row><cell>and features; and the interaction between the model and</cell></row><row><cell>the image data. By minimizing all the constraint equations</cell></row><row><cell>in parallel, the model is incrementally deformed until it fits</cell></row><row><cell>the feature. Each consnaint can be represented by a single</cell></row><row><cell>cost function. The cost associated with the current location</cell></row><row><cell>of the model vertex will be the sum of the individual</cell></row><row><cell>constraint functions,</cell></row><row><cell>Ci(z, Y, d , @ ) = I ( z , Y) + D ( z , Y) + A(d) + @(a) (1)</cell></row><row><cell>where:</cell></row><row><cell>Cj(z, y, d , cy) is the cost associated with this position</cell></row><row><cell>of the current model point.</cell></row><row><cell>Z(z, y) is the image term that identifies feature</cell></row><row><cell>events,</cell></row><row><cell>D ( z , y) is a potential field that drives the model</cell></row><row><cell>points towards the boundary,</cell></row><row><cell>A(d) maintains the distribution of points along the</cell></row><row><cell>model (d is a distance),</cell></row><row><cell>0 ( a ) maintains the shape of the model, a topologi-</cell></row><row><cell>cally simple polygon (a is an angle).</cell></row><row><cell>The collection</cell></row><row><cell>must be of reasonable stature and must</cell></row><row><cell>have an explicit or implicit boundary</cell></row><row><cell>associated with it. In instances where</cell></row><row><cell>we generate a model by expanding a</cell></row><row><cell>model within a feature, we sometimes</cell></row><row><cell>refer to the feature as a cavity.</cell></row></table><note>hole noise~</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The problem of extracting geometric models of features within images was presented to us by Bill Lorensen of GE Corporate R&amp;D. We would like to thank Bob O'Bara and Phil Getto for sharing their comments and ideas with us.</p><p>Special thanks must go to Dr. Donald House for providing us with helpful suggestions conceming the organization of the article. This work was partially funded by GE Corporate R&amp;D through the RDRC Industrial Associates Program.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wintz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Digital Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A cost minimization approach to edge detection using simulated annealing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gelfand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Delp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>West Lafayette, Indiana</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Purdue University, Computer Vision and Image Processing Laboratory, School of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching cubes: A high resolution 3d surface construction algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics &apos;87 Conference Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Snakes: Active contour models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Witken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Terzopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Computer Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Symmetryseeking models and 3d object reconstruction. Int&apos;l</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Terzopoulus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Witkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kass</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Computer Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Multiresolution elastic matching. Computer Vision, Graphics and Image Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bajcsy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kovacic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="21" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Finding edges and lines in images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Canny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983-06" />
			<pubPlace>Cambridge, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Masters thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Grayscale morphology. Computer Vision, Graphics, and Image Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Stemberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="355" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of morphological transformations to the analysis of two-dimensional electrophoretic gels of biological material</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Skolnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Graphics, and Image Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="332" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy constraints on parameteri7-4 models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Witkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fleischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Barr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ml-M2</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Choreographing goal-oriented motion using cost functions. State-of-theArt in Computer Animation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">]</forename><forename type="middle">D E</forename><surname>Breen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Animation &apos;89 Conference Proceedings)</title>
		<editor>N. Magnenat-Thalmann and D. Thalmann</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tokyo</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="151" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The cost analysis object in the clockworks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Breen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TR-88048</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>RPI</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Rensselaer Design Research Center Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An object-oriented architecture for a computer animation system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Getto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Breen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization by simulated annealing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gelatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Vecchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">220</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4598</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
