<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Volume Microscopy of Biological Specimens Based on Non-Confocal Imaging Techniques</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Senft</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Experimental Neurology and Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Saint Louis</settlement>
									<region>Missouri</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Volume Microscopy of Biological Specimens Based on Non-Confocal Imaging Techniques</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The newly available confocallight microscopes produce series of aligned images that implicitly constitute volumes. This would directly provide scientists with the capability for volumetric study of the biological world at high spatial resolutionexcept that methods to effectively visualize volume data have been insufficiently rapid and flexible. We have developed software research tools to fill that need. In the process, we have found that excellent reconstructions could be made from serial sections acquired using a charge-coupled device and a conventional light microscope (modified after Inoul [ l ]). Brightfield images of high-contrast subjects (such as golgi-impregnated or horseradish peroxidase labeled cells) were reconstructed crisply, as were some fluorescently labeled cells. Volume microscopy now should be within reach of, and of use to, a wider range of scientists.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Standard imaging methods in light microscopy collapse</head><p>an exmded optical depth of field into two dimensions. In some cases this can be advantageous, however the great majority of biologically interesting microscopic samples a~ intrinsically three-dimensional. Binocular (stereo) imaging can broaden the viewpoint a bit, but stereo explores only a limited range of angles near the optical axis. Until recently. fully arbihiuily oriented three-dimensional representations of microscopic specimens were unachievable except by fecourse to extremely laborious methods.</p><p>The confocal microscope has dramatically altered this situation. Confocal optics reduce the depth of field that conaibutes to each image of a series, by geometrically rejecting out-of-focus information (via spinning disks [2] or laser scanning techniques [3,4,51). This gene" serial sections, each containing information derived h m very narrow levels of focuswhich improves resolution both laterally and axially. Unfortunately, however, each single section is usually less interpretable than a conventional microscopic image, because it contains less of the overall structure being studied. In addition, many more sections are required in order to account for an adequately sampled total volume. These stringent limitations and demands require powerful data visualization techniques to compensate for them. Fortunately, one approach based on concurrent advances in computer graphics workstations and rendering algorithms (in particular, a technique known as volume rendering) is proving to be an intuitively straightforward and visually effective approach for accurate reconstruction of volumetric microscopy data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Volume Rendering</head><p>Volume rendering is a method for directly visualizing the distribution of some property in three-dimensional space, by projecting and compositing an array of volumetric samples (voxels) into a planar image on the computer screen <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr">7]</ref>. In contrast to surface extraction methods, which do not display the full data, volume rendering methods preserve the original resolution and avoid interpretation artifacts that result when surface methods are applied to complex or noisy data [81.</p><p>However, because such rendering algorithms must exhaustively traverse the entire volume of data (comprising many millions of voxels), volume rendering taxes even the most powerN (and expensive) of computer workstations. Hence, this approach has been neither practical nor affordable for most microscopists.</p><p>To remove these obstacles, we created software (Voxel-Viewm, Vital Images) optimized to run efficiently on moderately-priced, general-purpose graphics workstations (IRIS 4 D series, Silicon Graphics Computer Systems). Rendering speeds of up to 4 million voxels/second have been achieved, making it possible to render typical microscope data sets in a few seconds. In addition, the user interface has been designed to promote interactivity and easy access to the necessary rendering techniques.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Confocal reconstructions</head><p>We were interested in determining whether these relative ly straightforward and effective additions for three dimensional data acquisition could be made use of more widely, or whether Dr. InoutYs results required the special optical design and skill of their originator. Therefore we attempted to partially replicate his system, using readily available components.</p><p>An example of data acquired from a confocal microscope and reconstructed using our volume rendering software is given in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. Among the techniques used to produce this image were (a) thresholding based on voxel-value, (b) assignment of an opacity function for "alpha blending". and (c) application of a lighting model.</p><p>We started with a Zeiss AxioPlan microscope fitted for bright field, differential interference contrast @IC) and epifluorescence with 4Ox (1.0 N.A.) and 63x <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(1.4 N.A.)</ref> infinity-comted PlanApo lenses. We attached an Ellistype (Technical Video) fiber-optic light pipe <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>   Non-confocal reconstructions Until recently, the optical sections obtainable with confocal microscopes were considered to be thinner than those attainable using more conventional microscopes; and the resulting reconstructions were considered preferable.</p><p>However, Inout! [l] has shown that optical sections of comparableor even superiorthinness can be obtained through inexpensive additions to the conventional transmitted light microscope. These include a fine-focus stepping-motor, fiber-optic "light scrambler", and, for highest resolution, polarizers and compensators. Volume rendering of transmitted light data (obtained using a specially designed system having these features and kindly provided by Dr. S. Inou6) is shown, in stereo, in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>. processor, DEC 3200 and 3520 workstations and Ethernet!). Total time for data collection, and circuitous transfer ranged from 10-30 minutes; reconstuctions using Vital Images' rendering software ranged fiom less than a second to one and a half minutes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effects of differing light sources</head><p>As is well known, the characteristics of the microscope's light source can dramatically impact the quality of the images obtained. Most transmitted light microscopes have uneven transmitted illumination, caused by spatial inhomogeneity in the heated filament. This variation in light intensity across the image usually is reduced by means of a ground-glass diffuser, but inevitably persists to a significant extent. In practice this prevents one from using the full numerical aperture of the system, and this translates directly into loss of spatial resolution in all dimensions (most notably along the optical axis). However, by interposing an ess-shaped single-strand quartz fiber optic light pipe between the light source and the microscope, one can dramatidy improve the uniformity of the lightand thereby make use of more of the system's numerical aperture <ref type="bibr">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">10]</ref>. We illustrate in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> the effect that a diffuser or light pipe has on composited transmitted-light images. B e cause of the improvement in image quality with the light pipe, data were subsequently taken with it in place. Simple p o k r s also appeared to improve the images some what <ref type="figure">(Figure 3d)</ref>, and therefore were used for the stem views of HRP-labeled mouse thalamocortical mons in  ' Ihe applications of volume imaging in microscopy clearly extend well beyond the realm of the confocal microscape. With nonconfocal volumetric imaging one presently s8Qifices dynamic range for signal-to-noise. For station.</p><p>many types of studies this is already an acceptable tradeoff. In the not too distant future, faster hardware for data colkctia~ and &amp;blurring routines (i.e. on the order of a few seconds) are likely to make realizable and affordable metric mde?ing speeds and with extended dynamic range ptrhaps even in m e color.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Vincent J .</head><label>.</label><figDesc>Argiro and William L. VanZandt Department of Physiological and Biological Sciences, Maharishi International University, and Vital Images, Inc., Fairfield, Iowa, USA</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Hippocampal CA3 pyramidal cell, 10 day old rat, Lud e r Yellow fiu; BioRad MRC umfocal microscope, uhr (0.8 NA) lens. Data courtesy of Lh. J. Turner 191.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Golgi-impregnation, 9 days old mouse thalamus, I OX 0.9 NA (stereo pair). Data courtesy of Dr. S. InouB.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>3e,f (which additionally uses techniques described next forFigure 4).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We thank Dr. Thomas Woolsey of Washington University for use of the computer-microscope facility, and Mr. Rich McFall of Silicon Graphics for use of the Iris workmicroscope me^ that operate at SUb-Wond VOlU-</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Whither video Microscopy? Towards 4-D Imaging at the highest resolution of the light mi</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Incd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Drebin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hawahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="74" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Westover</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chapel Hill Workshop on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">Visualization</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Chapel Hill</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Electron Microscopy Techniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>National Institutes of Health)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Egger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Petran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1967" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>pp 305</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Aslund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="235" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>et all987 Scanning 9</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Amos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fordham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bralenhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Blom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barends</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cell Bwl. 105 pp 4148</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="232" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
