<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.1" ident="GROBID" when="2016-09-09T14:57+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Artificial Defocus for Displaying Markers in Microscopy Z-Stacks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Alessandro</forename>
								<surname>Giusti</surname>
								<roleName>Member, Ieee</roleName>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Pierluigi</forename>
								<surname>Taddei</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Cristina</forename>
								<surname>Magli</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Giorgio</forename>
								<surname>Corani</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Luca</forename>
								<surname>Gambardella</surname>
								<roleName>Member, Ieee</roleName>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Luca</forename>
								<surname>Gianaroli</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Artificial Defocus for Displaying Markers in Microscopy Z-Stacks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Index Terms—Depth of field</term>
					<term>Microscopy</term>
					<term>Focus stacks</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>(a) slice 6 (b) slice 8 (c) slice 11 (d) slice 12 Fig. 1. Few slices from a Z-stack of a flea chest: different structures are visible in good focus in different slices, depending on their depth. Colored visual markers, which defocus just like other entities, are drawn to mark some of the structures, and provide an intuitive visualization which accounts for their depths. Original stack courtesy Daniel Stoupin [1]. Abstract—As microscopes have a very shallow depth of field, Z-stacks (i.e. sets of images shot at different focal planes) are often acquired to fully capture a thick sample. Such stacks are viewed by users by navigating them through the mouse wheel. We propose a new technique of visualizing 3D point, line or area markers in such focus stacks, by displaying them with a depth-dependent defocus, simulating the microscope&apos;s optics; this leverages on the microscopists&apos; ability to continuously twiddle focus, while implicitly performing a shape-from-focus reconstruction of the 3D structure of the sample. User studies confirm that the approach is effective, and can complement more traditional techniques such as color-based cues. We provide two implementations, one of which computes defocus in real time on the GPU, and examples of their application.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p> Due to optical reasons, microscope objectives with large magnifications have a very shallow depth of field, i.e. they can only focus on a thin slice of space. When the sample to be observed is thick, it may be impossible to get a single image where the whole sample appears sharp enough. Instead, structures at different depths appear sharp at different focal planes, and progressively defocus as the focal plane moves farther away. In manual microscopy observations, microscopists continuously manipulate the focus knob, and quickly realize the global appearance of the sample, possibly gaining an insight of its 3D structure by means of an implicit and subconscious depth-from-focus reconstruction. Observation is therefore a dynamic process, which is closely linked to live focus manipulation. In most automated microscopy applications dealing with thick samples , this problem is dealt with by shooting Z-Stacks, also known as focus stacks or multilevel images: instead of a single image, a set of images is acquired at different – usually equally-spaced – focal planes. Users navigate such images on a computer by continuously tweaking the focus (usually with the mouse wheel) just like they would do on a microscope. In this context, we deal with the problem of displaying and interacting with visual markers overlayed to image data, in a precise but practical and usable way. Displaying markers on Z-stacks is mainly useful in two scenarios: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>@BULLET </head><p> @BULLET visualizing manual annotations, for interpersonal communication or for subsequent automated measurements; @BULLET visualizing the results of image processing algorithms – e.g. for segmentation or detection tasks – which often need to be validated by domain experts. </p><p>In both cases, conveying both the 2D position and the depth of the markers is often an important requirement. Several naive approaches to the problem can be envisioned: for example , the 3D space covered by the images can be represented from different viewpoints in order to explicitly show the z dimension. While this very effectively conveys the features' relative positions and spatial relations, it also deforms the image display and makes it hard to correlate the markers to the actual image data, which is particularly problematic in most situations, especially when validating image processing results. Therefore, we stick to the familiar 2D display, which maximizes the perceived image quality, while leveraging on the microscopists' second nature of continuously tweaking the focus. Then, one may show the visual marker only when the image at the corresponding focal plane is displayed. While this precisely localizes the marker and its depth, the result is not very usable as the marker appears and disappears unnaturally when moving across its depth; moreover, the user does not have a global view of the markers at different depths. The situation is slightly improved by always displaying the markers' projections on the image, but in a subdued way. The resulting visualization is however still unnatural, mainly because hints of the distance from the correct focal plane are needed for each marker. Encoding such hints by decreasing marker size, color saturation or opacity as the depth difference can be effective, although such approaches are usually not self-explanatory and need some effort for adaptation. Our main contribution is a novel technique to represent markers at different focal planes, by increasingly defocusing them as the depth distance from the current focal plane increases (Section 3), thus simulating the microscope's limited depth of field. The result is a natural behavior which is immediately understood by users familiar with microscopy . The approach can be applied for marking points and naturally conveying their depth, but it also trivially extends to line markers, possibly representing 3D curves, and area markers, representing 3D surfaces. As the defocusing effect is gradual, the correct direction for bringing a marker (or a part of a marker) into focus is easily determined by any experienced microscopist by observing how its appearance changes after small focus tweaks – just like with any normal image feature. On the other hand, the graduality of the effect may also be a disadvantage as determining the precise depth of a feature may not be immediately obvious when using standard markers. In scenarios where precision in depth determination is important, we propose in Section 3.1 to use markers with some high spatial frequency details (that are naturally lost as soon as a slight defocus is applied), which therefore gain a readily-recognizable, distinctive appearance when in exact focus. Because the markers defocus naturally, they may be confused with the image data when out of focus. This might be a limitation in most scenarios: we discuss the issue and propose solutions in Section 3.2. As the defocusing effect is symmetrical (i.e. features at a given distance from the current focal plane have a similar appearance regardless of whether they lie above or below), a single still image can not properly convey the 3D positions of the markers: we propose in Section 3.3 a simple extension in order to overcome this, but as its effectiveness is not clear in all settings, our representation should be mainly considered for dynamic, interactive use. In Section 4 we discuss the software implementation of the technique 1 , which takes advantage of GLSL shaders for interactive visualization . Computing the marker appearances in realtime also enables us to implement interactive markers, which are discussed in Section 4.3. Application examples on actual microscopy tasks in the context of In Vitro Fertilization are discussed in Section 5. Section 6 presents a user study on two user groups, namely microscopists and users unfamiliar with microscopes, which measures the effectiveness of the proposed technique. Section 7 concludes the paper and presents future research directions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORKS</head><p>Visualizing image data from microscopes is the subject of a large amount of research, which covers many different fields and applications , and is well summarized in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,145.07,587.16,13.74,8.02" target="#b31">[34]</ref>. In particular, the works most relevant to the topic of the present paper are those related with the visualization of image stacks. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Visualization and Processing of Image Stacks</head><p>Image stacks are frequently used in microscopy; in particular, our work deals with Z-stacks, where each slice of the stack is acquired at a different focal plane. Acquisition and display of such stacks is a feature of many microscopy packages. For example, <ref type="bibr" coords="2,212.79,670.19,10.45,8.02" target="#b4">[7] </ref> offers visualization of Z-stacks, where a scrollbar determines the displayed focal plane; similar features are offered by several commercial microscopy packages <ref type="bibr" coords="2,58.94,700.08,9.71,8.02" target="#b2">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="2,72.23,700.08,6.47,8.02"> 6]</ref> , some of which also offer easier navigation of image stacks through the mouse wheel. Handling of Z-stacks is also a core feature of generic systems such as ImageJ <ref type="bibr" coords="2,455.64,53.38,10.45,8.02" target="#b1">[3] </ref>and its distribution aimed at 3D microscopy <ref type="bibr" coords="2,375.18,63.35,9.52,8.02">[2]</ref>. Annotations in Z-stacks are a useful feature, which is available in the majority of systems. However, no particular attention is typically given to the visualization of the annotations' depth. For example, in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,294.20,103.59,13.74,8.02" target="#b26">[29]</ref>, which is designed for collaborative annotation of large images over the web, annotations at a given depth are visualized only when the current focal plane is displayed, whereas they simply disappear when the focal plane changes; the same behavior occurs in the IMOD <ref type="bibr" coords="2,520.56,133.48,14.94,8.02" target="#b16">[19] </ref>system, which makes heavy use of point and line markers in order to build 3D representations of image data. In other systems, such as <ref type="bibr" coords="2,522.80,153.40,9.52,8.02" target="#b4">[7]</ref>, annotations do not even carry information about their depth in the image stack, and are displayed unchanged regardless on the current focal plane. The present work fits in the crowded scene of microscopy packages by providing a simple but effective tool for visualizing the depth of markers or annotations in Z-stacks. This represents a feature which well complements the advanced functionality that existing microscopy systems offer. One deeply-studied problem, with applications both in microscopy and macro photography, is extended focus or extended depth of field, i.e. obtaining a single image visualizing all the details available in the full Z-stack. Such result can be obtained for example by sampling the sharpest parts from each image of the stack <ref type="bibr" coords="2,449.38,283.70,9.71,8.02" target="#b5">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="2,462.19,283.70,11.21,8.02" target="#b7"> 10,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="2,476.49,283.70,10.65,8.02" target="#b33"> 36]</ref> . When successful , one may visualize the sample 3D structure as a height map, with a texture which is sharp everywhere and represents the extended focus image. While such techniques are very frequently used in macro photography, they do not apply to many problems in biological microscope imaging, where the samples are optically transparent, and their structure is more complex, with multiple substructures overlapping at different focal planes. A different approach to visualizing focus stacks is often adopted with images from confocal laser scanning microscopes. In confocal images, structures not on the focal plane, instead of appearing defocused , are simply invisible. Therefore, the images can be interpreted as optical sections – like slices of CT or MR data – and Zstacks are easily visualized with standard volume visualization tech- niques <ref type="bibr" coords="2,311.32,423.57,14.19,8.02" target="#b13">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="2,328.29,423.57,11.21,8.02" target="#b27"> 30,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="2,342.29,423.57,11.21,8.02" target="#b28"> 31,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="2,356.29,423.57,11.21,8.02" target="#b29"> 32,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="2,370.28,423.57,10.65,8.02" target="#b32"> 35]</ref>. In some cases, volume visualization can be successful with Z-stacks obtained with a conventional fluorescent microscope, after deconvolution techniques remove the defocused images of structures at different depths <ref type="bibr" coords="2,419.07,453.46,13.74,8.02" target="#b22">[25]</ref>. In principle – but rarely in practice – deconvolution may also allow one to obtain optical sections of simple stained specimens using transmitted light imaging <ref type="bibr" coords="2,502.81,473.39,13.74,8.02" target="#b11">[14]</ref>. Such techniques allow one to build a rich representation of the sample , which is naturally visualized in 3D, and in many cases would not require observing the original Z-stack. This is exploited for efficient annotation and segmentation of such volume images in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,489.47,513.63,13.74,8.02" target="#b20">[23]</ref> . Unfortunately , in many biomedical microscopy tasks, especially those not dealing with fluorescent samples, observing the original data in the Zstack is the only feasible option, as richer representations of such data can not be obtained both robustly and automatically. Still, feature detection and segmentation approaches working on Zstacks can explicitly reconstruct at least part of the 3D structure of the sample. Other than the application shown in Section 5, other examples are given in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,357.36,593.72,13.74,8.02" target="#b23">[26]</ref>, where cellular and subcellular structures are segmented from data acquired in different microscopy imaging modalities ; and in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,332.32,613.65,13.74,8.02" target="#b12">[15]</ref>, which deals with visualization of dendritic spines segmented from light microscopy data. In general, results of such detection and segmentation techniques need to be manually validated, both during algorithm development, and possibly during actual usage, depending on accuracy and robustness requirements. This calls for a visualization technique for markers in image stack which is both usable and accurate; as a result, the output of image analysis algorithms can be easily verified and correlated to actual image data. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Rendering Depth of Field</head><p>Advances in automated microscopy also prompted the development of advanced techniques for visualizing very large resolution images or image stacks, which are quite common in histology <ref type="bibr" coords="2,490.80,736.42,13.74,8.02" target="#b30">[33]</ref> . In the present implementation, we concentrate instead on the common situation where Z-stacks are acquired of single samples, and disregard issues related to very large images obtained by mosaicing. Realtime rendering of depth-of-field is a challenging and wellstudied problem in computer graphics <ref type="bibr" coords="3,173.48,93.29,13.74,8.02" target="#b17">[20]</ref>. As in this paper we are interested in defocusing simple objects such as visual markers, implementation is not as challenging, but is still not straightforward especially if realtime operation is required (Section 4). Other than for photorealism, depth-of-field is useful for attracting the viewer attention to part of the scene – a purpose often exploited by photographers; however, in photography depth perception is not much related to focusing and defocusing of different objects. The case of microscopy is radically different, mainly because microscope operators have the ability (and need) of continuously adjusting focus, and because focus is usually the only depth-related cue available. Depth-of-focus effects in microscopes are influenced by a number of different interacting optical phenomena, whose realistic simulation is considered in <ref type="bibr" coords="3,89.70,222.91,14.19,8.02" target="#b14">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="3,106.03,222.91,10.65,8.02" target="#b25"> 28]</ref>. In this work we are not interested in realistic simulation; on the contrary, we only aim at conveying a general idea of defocus, possibly designing an ad-hoc defocus model which may be physically-implausible (Section 3.3). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Augmented Reality</head><p>During user testing, one microscopist observed that our markers look like fluorescent structures physically lying in the samples. This prompts an interpretation of our approach as a peculiar augmented reality system, where virtual objects (markers) are composited over the sample during its navigation, and realistically blurred depending on their depth. This resembles the work in <ref type="bibr" coords="3,192.87,333.39,13.74,8.02" target="#b15">[18]</ref>, where videos from low-cost cameras are augmented with virtual objects, whose image is degraded with various artifacts – including blur – for increased realism . In <ref type="bibr" coords="3,60.08,363.27,13.74,8.02" target="#b24">[27]</ref>, a similar approach is followed, specifically dealing with defocus and motion blur. Note that, in contrast to such works, in our approach we do not want the user to confuse the marker with the actual image (see Section 3.3). In human depth perception, depth cues are also conveyed by the accommodation process of the eye, i.e. its ability to focus on objects at different distances; by means of specific hardware <ref type="bibr" coords="3,222.11,423.10,13.74,8.02" target="#b18">[21]</ref>, researchers have been able to take advantage of this for improving the realism of augmented reality systems. In microscopes, even when directly observing the sample using oculars, flat images are generated, and the eye accommodation does not play any role in depth perception. On the contrary, eye accommodation is surrogated by the continuous adjustment of microscope focus by the user, which plays a similar role for depth perception, and further explains why rendering defocused markers provides an intuitive experience. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">VISUALIZING MARKERS IN Z-STACKS</head><p>We operate on an input Z-stack, i.e. a set of N images I 1 , I 2 , ..., I N taken at different focal planes z = z 1 , z 2 , ..., z N . Such focal planes can be considered horizontal slices at different depths of a 3D space whose Cartesian axes are (x, y, z). Although the underlying imaging model might be quite complex (e.g. for phase contrast optics), a few intuitive principles hold <ref type="bibr" coords="3,253.56,584.25,13.74,8.02" target="#b19">[22]</ref>, on which we base our approach: @BULLET structures which lie on or near the current focal plane z i appear sharp (i.e. they exhibit strong localized gradients) in the image intensity I i ; @BULLET as the focal plane depth moves farther from the structure's depth, the structure image becomes blurred; @BULLET structures often appear transparent, i.e. multiple overlapping structures may show in the same image area. </p><p>The defocus affecting structures not lying on the current focal plane is described by a 3D point spread function (PSF) h(x, y, z); the double cone shape visible in <ref type="figure" coords="3,109.98,726.46,30.46,8.02">Figure 2</ref>shows how, while the depth difference increases, the resulting defocus kernel (a horizontal slice of the 3D PSF) gets larger. Although rather precise knowledge of the actual 3D PSF is required in most deconvolution applications, such as <ref type="bibr" coords="3,508.62,63.35,9.52,8.02" target="#b5">[8]</ref>, in our scenario it is only used for defocusing markers, and does not need to closely match that of the imaging system. Therefore we build a simple PSF roughly matching the expected defocus given the stack acquisition parameters, but also allow for different, physically implausible shapes (see Section 3.2). Let us consider a point marker centered at coordinates (x m , y m , z m ). The appearance of the marker over image I i is given by the sharp marker image convolved with the 2D PSF h (x, y, (z m − z i )). Note that the defocused marker's edges should appear semitransparent and blend with the background: therefore, we operate on the marker's transparency (alpha) channel as well as its actual image. Let M be a stack of marker images which is transparent everywhere, except at (x m , y m , z m ), where a sharp picture of the marker appears. The stack V 1 ,V 2 , ...V N of the overlay images pertaining to such marker is readily determined as V = M * h. Such procedure trivially extends to markers which may span multiple focus planes, such as line or area markers. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Enhancing the Marker Under Exact Focus</head><p> When using a simple marker shape, such as a circle, it may not be obvious whether the marker appears in exact focus or slightly defocused. In applications where such an effect is undesirable, one can modify markers in order to include high spatial frequency content – such as a thin line around the main marker – which is lost even after slight defocusing. The marker therefore gains a distinctive appearance in its sharp state, without losing naturality in behavior. For this to work, the PSF should be such that h (x, y, 0) maps to a single pixel. A similar approach can be applied to line markers (e.g. drawing a double line instead of a single thicker one), and to area markers. In the latter case, in particular, we propose to use a simple repeated pattern of thin lines, which both provide the necessary high frequency components, and allow the user to see through. This allows one to represent planar or nonplanar surfaces spanning multiple focal planes. A different option, which can complement the previous, is to use color for highlighting the focused marker (see Section 6). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Handcrafted Point Spread Functions</head><p>Markers are mainly intended as visual annotations to image data, and these two entities should never be confused. This is normally not a problem as markers have a distinctive appearance; however highly defocused markers might be misinterpreted as defocused image data. Some possible solutions to the problem follow: @BULLET when the image is grayscale or has a limited palette of colors, then color alone (which is not affected by defocus) can represent a very powerful discriminator; @BULLET markers can be made blinking or fading; @BULLET an handcrafted PSF can be used, which makes heavily-defocused points look distinctive, while still conveying an idea of defocus. An example is shown in <ref type="figure" coords="3,405.83,614.93,29.66,8.02">Figure 2</ref> , where a PSF with a doublepyramid shape makes a point marker appear as a diamond. The appearance of a heavily-defocused point of light is named bokeh in photography, and is often exploited (by using different lenses and apertures) for aesthetic effects. The PSF still makes the point defocus gradually and naturally, because it has a steadily increasing support area for larger |z|. As convolution is commutative (i.e. V = M * h = h * M) the appearance of a defocused marker can also be interpreted as the appearance of the relevant slice of the 3D PSF convolved with the sharp marker image. If the sharp marker image has a small support area, this results in slight defocusing of said slice of the PSF; this allows one to design ad-hoc PSFs which make a point marker look like any desired shape. <ref type="figure" coords="4,37.99,203.08,3.32,7.37">2</ref>. Appearance of defocused markers when using different PSF shapes and energy profiles f (z). The stack is composed by 5 rows of 40 point markers each, which are placed at increasing z; the displayed slice is the middle of the stack. Note confocal-like PSF (d) in first row, realistic PSF (e) in second row, and physically-implausible PSFs with amplifying energy profile in rows 3, 4 and 5; row 5 uses PSF (c), which is not symmetrical w.r.t. the z = 0 plane, and provides different bokeh above and below the current focal plane. Also note the discernible appearance of the focused marker, due to its high-frequency content. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Differentiating Markers Above and Below the Current Focus Plane</head><p>The same approach can be adopted for differentiating markers which lie above and below the current focal plane. At least at first approximation , realistic PSFs are symmetric w.r.t. the z = 0 plane. However, nothing prevents us from designing a PSF which does not exhibit such symmetry: in figure 2, we show how a PSF which is not symmetrical with respect to the z = 0 plane results in different bokeh depending on the direction of defocus. The effect of the PSF on a graduallydefocusing point marker still appears natural and intuitive. Another approach for conveying the direction of markers is using color; this is explored in further detail in Section 6. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Enhancing the Visibility of Defocused Markers</head><p> Realistic PSFs in traditional microscopes have equal energy independently on z; i.e., f (z) = xy h(x, y, z) dx dy = 1. Instead, confocal microscopes are designed in such a way that, as a structure gets farther from the focal plane, it disappears; i.e., f (z) drops to 0 when |z| increases . Using such a PSF for defocusing markers would make them invisible as soon as they are not in close vicinity of the current focal plane, which is not desirable in most situations. In practice, we observe a similar problem with realistic PSFs: a defocused marker, as it blurs to a larger area, becomes more and more transparent (i.e., its opacity decreases with the square of the radius of the relevant PSF slice), and is easily lost in the background. Although this matches the expectations of microscopists 2 , this is generally undesirable for visual markers; therefore, we use physically-implausible PSFs which amplify the energy of defocused markers (see <ref type="figure" coords="4,233.17,561.99,28.89,8.02">Figure 2</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p> Two alternative approaches can be followed for implementing the system: precomputing the defocused marker stack V by convolution of the sharp marker stack M with PSF h, and then compositing the relevant slice V i over the corresponding image I i ; or rendering defocused markers in realtime over the visualized frame of the stack. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Precomputation of Defocused Markers</head><p>The former approach is conceptually simpler, as it represents the direct implementation of the model described previously. Unfortunately, 3D convolution is expensive, as its computational complexity, per pixel of I, is O(h x · h y · h z ), where h x , h y , h z represent the x, y, z sizes of h, in pixels. In practice, prohibitive precomputation times amounting to several hours are required even for a small 800×600×24 image stack, when using a 75×75×24 PSF. In most cases, one can dramatically optimize the results by considering the very definition of discrete convolution in the spatial domain , and exploit the sparse nature of M, which is zero everywhere except at voxels constituting the images of sharp markers and lines. V can be therefore computed by accumulation of the 3D PSF centered on each nonzero voxel of M. The resulting precomputation time linearly depends on the amount of such nonzero voxels and on the size of the PSF. In the current pure-matlab, unoptimized implementation, this corresponds to few milliseconds per nonzero voxel in M, which, for realistic scenes such as those displayed in <ref type="figure" coords="4,453.29,392.20,29.49,8.02">Figure 1</ref>, sums up to a total of few seconds of precomputation time. Once V is computed, it can be either permanently composited over I, or kept as a separate stack, and composited in realtime. The latter option allows one to easily manipulate the visibility, color or transparency of markers, possibly keeping different precomputed stacks for different markers or groups of markers. When interactively browsing the stack, a simple alpha compositing operation of V i over I i is required at each change of focus, which is extremely fast and easily implemented in most frameworks. We provide a prototype MATLAB implementation following this approach in the supplementary materials. Implementation is clear and concise, amounts to a few hundreds of lines of code, and, by construction , supports arbitrary PSFs. Visualization code allows navigating image stacks with blurred markers, but is not optimized and does not allow one to manipulate markers in realtime (except for adding new markers, after which few seconds are needed for precomputation of the defocused stack of new markers), which is instead possible in the Java/OpenGL implementation described in the next section. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Realtime Rendering of Defocused Markers</head><p> In order to allow the user to interactively manipulate markers, defocused markers must be rendered in realtime over the currently visualized slice of the stack. We provide a Java/OpenGL implementation following this approach in the supplementary materials, where defocus is implemented by an approximated 2D convolution computed in the GPU using GLSL shaders. The implementation is based on an optimized approach for rendering an appropriately-defocused projection of 3D polylines. More complex , possibly animated objects, such as boxes, rulers, protractors and text, are represented as a combination of one or more polylines. A vertex shader implementing a billboarding technique is used for representing each line segment as a line band facing the camera: in particular, we provide the graphic pipeline with the vertices of the polyline. For each vertex, the tangent vector is computed as the sum of <ref type="figure" coords="5,31.50,413.80,19.17,7.37">Fig. 3</ref>. First row: Use of interactive tools for measuring the length of a 3D curve, and a 3D angle, from a Z-stack acquired in an industrial environment representing an hole. One can notice that only a small part of the scene appears in-focus in the displayed slice, whereas other structures appear defocused; note how the curve on the left and protractor on the right are defocused accordingly. Second row: point and line markers on a stack representing a fly eye. Two different slices are represented in the two images. Bottom: partially overlapping filaments of Ulothrix alga, with 3D centerlines visualized as blue line markers (original image courtesy Arturo Agostino <ref type="bibr" coords="5,121.62,498.98,8.24,7.37" target="#b3">[5]</ref>). the directions of the two connected segments. The width of the band at each vertex v i depends on the depth difference d i between the vertex and the current focal plane, being minimal when the vertex is in perfect focus. For each pixel of the line band, we exploit the linear interpolation provided by the graphic pipeline to compute two values: a distance function m from the median line of the band – which corresponds to the in-focus projection of the line; and a depth difference d, computed by marking each vertex v i with its actual depth difference d i with respect to the current focal plane. In the fragment shader, these two interpolated values are used to compute the alpha value α of each pixel. In particular, such value is computed by evaluating a gaussian function whose variance depends on d, and whose mean depends on m: </p><formula>α = exp − m 2 2d 2 . </formula><p> Experimentally, the resulting blur is convincing despite being approximated ; this relatively simple approach handles hundreds of line and point markers at 30fps on most modern systems, including laptops with integrated graphics. For example, using an Intel 4-series integrated graphics controller, framerate drops below 30fps when more than 5200 line segments are visible; in most realistic applications, this is hardly a limitation. It is worth noting that, as defocus does not depend on line direction , the approach approximates a point spread function with circular symmetry; moreover, the effect of the PSF is only simulated in the direction orthogonal to the line, and does not apply to line extremities. Both these limitations prevent this approach to faithfully model more complex point spread functions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Basic Interaction Techniques</head><p> In the Java prototype, hovering over a marker (even if defocused) highlights it by changing its color; a single click smoothly brings it into focus, and a second click selects it – which changes its appearance. Point and line markers can be interactively added. When adding polylines , the last vertex of the line follows the mouse pointer, as in most user interfaces. When the focal plane is changed through the mouse wheel, the line extends in 3D and is realistically blurred. We provide two interactive tools: a 3D ruler and a 3D protractor. </p><p> Both are interactively manipulated while realistically blurred, and allow to measure accurate distances and angles between features on Zstacks (see <ref type="figure" coords="5,334.95,536.20,28.89,8.02">Figure 3</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">APPLICATION EXAMPLES</head><p>The proposed technique is rather general and can be applied in many different microscopy scenarios, as exemplified in <ref type="figure" coords="5,472.09,577.02,32.50,8.02">Figures 1</ref>, 3 and 4. One of such scenarios is represented by In Vitro Fertilization (IVF) lab procedures, which is a practical field where observation of Z-stacks plays an important role; in fact human zygotes and embryos are observed by means of a microscope equipped with Hoffann Modulation Contrast, in order to determine their viability and evaluate their implantation chances <ref type="bibr" coords="5,363.74,636.80,9.71,8.02" target="#b6">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="5,376.14,636.80,11.21,8.02" target="#b8"> 11,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="5,390.03,636.80,10.65,8.02" target="#b21"> 24]</ref>. As the samples are thick with respect to the microscope's depth of field, Z-stacks can be acquired, where different structures appear sharp at different focal planes, depending on their depth. As in several other biological applications, these Z-stacks are not handled by extended focus algorithms, are not good candidates for deconvolution, and do not provide a useful representation when visualized as volumes; moreover, embryologists seek for subtle structures and textures which can be best observed in the original image stacks. In this context, the proposed visualization technique can be an important building block for user-assisted measurement of zygotes: users (a) slice 13 </p><p>(b) slice 18 can visualize the automated segmentation of relevant structures, and confirm the validity of both the segmentation and the recovered depth, as shown in <ref type="figure" coords="6,66.86,336.57,30.14,8.02" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>for pronuclei detection <ref type="bibr" coords="6,183.15,336.57,13.74,8.02" target="#b9">[12]</ref>. A similar evaluation can be performed on embryos, which are composed by a number of blastomeres; the sizes and morphological relations among blastomeres are considered important features for evaluating the embryo viability. However, automated segmentation of blastomeres from Z-stacks is hindered by their complex appearance, and the fact that defocused and focused images of different blastomeres overlap. State-of-the-art automated techniques manage to segment the correct blastomeres in approximately 70% of the images, when 4 blastomeres are present <ref type="bibr" coords="6,96.97,427.07,13.94,8.02" target="#b10">[13]</ref> ; intuitive visualization of the detected contours as line markers allows users to confirm the correct segmentations and their depth, interactively selecting the correct candidates by verifying their fit to the image data. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">USER STUDY</head><p>In order to quantify the utility of our approach, we designed a user test which is implemented as an alternative controller for the Java/OpenGL prototype. Readers can find the user test in the supplementary material and execute it. The user test is designed to quantify the ability of an operator to bring a single marker into focus, when using different alternate representations of the marker depth with respect to the current focal plane. When the marker is in focus, the user has a clear feedback as its edge doubles. As a baseline, we consider a representation of depth through color, which does not involve defocus. Namely, the marker appears red if significantly below the current focal plane; gradually fades to green when nearby; and then gradually fades to blue when above the current focal plane. We informally experimented with different variations of the approach , but found the gradient described above, which has a rather small green area around the current focus, to provide the most informative representation. We could not find any other technique, not involving defocus, providing better performance for the task described below. Such a representation will be referred to as color gradient (CG) in the following. <ref type="figure" coords="6,86.32,695.73,34.47,8.02">Figure 7a</ref> also compares data obtained using different depth-color mappings, which we had already found to be not as performing. The CG representation is compared during the test with two alternative approaches: defocus, where markers appear violet (in order not to create confusion with the previous approach), and defocus according to their distance from the current image plane, with a Gaussian PSF. </p><p>CG+defocus, where markers appear defocused as before, but colored according to the CG representation. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Experiment Setup</head><p>The experiments are performed by users, which do not usually require any assistance. The experiment begins with a short interactive tutorial, which lets the user familiarize with the following points: @BULLET the focus stack and its navigation by means of the mouse wheel; @BULLET the markers and their highlighted appearance when visualized in the current frame of the stack; </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>@BULLET the CG representation; </head><p>@BULLET the defocused representation; @BULLET the combined CG+defocus representation. </p><p>Finally, users are instructed on how to make a marker disappear, by highlighting it (i.e. moving to its focal plane) and waiting a short time without moving the focus. When highlighted, the marker displays an animated clock around it, which completes in 1 second; then the marker disappears. During the tutorial, attention is given to not privilege any of the three visualization methods, and to give equal opportunity to the user to familiarize with each. After the tutorial completes, a new marker appears at a random position and depth (but farther than 3 focus slices from the currently visualized one), using one of the three presented visualizations at random. As soon as the user makes the marker disappear, the process is iterated: a new marker appears at a random position and depth, with a random depth representation. In total, the user must complete 80 iterations. The whole process is logged, and statistics can be later computed. The test is administered on a recent laptop with integrated graphics, which however runs the Java prototype without glitches. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Subjects</head><p> The test has been administered to 9 subjects familiar with optical microscopy , and 13 subjects not familiar with optical microscopy; all subject were reasonably familiar with computers. No subject needed any assistance or interference during the test. In total, we collected 1760 focusing operations, divided in 580 using Defocus only, 595 using CG only, and 585 using CG+defocus. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Results</head><p> Focusing times are computed from the moment that the marker is presented , to the moment that the marker is brought and kept into focus. The 1s waiting time before the marker disappears (which is necessary to avoid accepting a marker when the user " overshoots " ) is already subtracted. As a baseline for performance, one may consider the represented 1.18s, which we informally measured as the average time for a quick user to solve a mechanically-identical task, when using a readily obvious visualization of depth difference. In particular, we created a separate test where users could move a square (representing the current focal plane) along a vertical path (representing the available slices in the stack) using the mouse scrollwheel. The square had to be moved to a position indicated by an arrow (the depth of the target). The test was governed by the same mechanism and timings. For each user, we consider the focusing times, grouped by each of the three representations. This results in about 27 samples for each representation for each user 3 . As some outliers are apparent in such distributions (evenly occurring in all three representations), we consider the median as a more robust statistic. This gives three values for each user. <ref type="figure" coords="7,72.97,155.22,34.95,8.02">Figure 7a</ref>shows the average of such median values over all 22 users for each representation type. <ref type="figure" coords="7,187.26,165.18,35.49,8.02">Figure 7b</ref> depicts the distribution of the 22 values, for each of the three representations. The distributions are very spread and exhibit a large variance, which is most probably due to variations in user competitivity, hand-eye coordination , and familiarity with computers and videogames. From such distributions alone, no statistically significant effect of different representations can be concluded. However, more powerful significance tests can be applied as our samples are paired, i.e. we can relate the measure for a user when using a given representation, to the measure of the same user when using a different representation. This allows us to draw the scatter plots in <ref type="figure" coords="7,60.00,274.86,32.94,8.02">Figure 7d</ref>, 7e and 7f. In particular, in <ref type="figure" coords="7,193.56,274.86,34.42,8.02">Figure 7d</ref>the superiority of CG+defocus over " CG only " is apparent, as only for three of the users the latter representation is better than the former. In particular, such observation is formalized by means of the non-parametric Friedman's test, which outputs that the superiority of CG+defocus over CG is statistically significant (p-value &lt; 0.01). Similarly, CG+defocus performs better than defocus (p-value &lt; 0.05, <ref type="figure" coords="7,200.00,334.64,32.23,8.02">Figure 7f</ref>), whereas no statistically-significant difference can be concluded between defocus and CG (<ref type="figure" coords="7,66.78,354.56,33.31,8.02">Figure 7e</ref>) when considering all users. Interestingly, when selecting only users familiar with microscopy, our data suggest that defocus outperforms CG (p-value &lt; 0.05). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4">Discussion</head><p>The user study confirms that defocus cues are useful for conveying marker depths, and that the focusing task is solved faster when defocus cues are used. On the other hand, the accurately-chosen CG representation also demonstrates to be a powerful cue for the simple task implemented in our test. In comparison, other naive representations perform much worse. When using defocus alone, without color cues, as soon as a new marker is displayed users are forced to determine the correct focusing direction by randomly adjusting focus and observing the appearance variation of the defocused marker. While this is very natural for microscopists , it results in a large time delay for the present task. Instead, color cues allow the competitive, concentrated user to immediately move in the correct direction (as soon as the meaning of the different colors has been memorized). The difference is clearly visible in <ref type="figure" coords="7,31.50,545.09,33.60,8.02">Figure 7b</ref> . Once the marker is near to the current focal plane, defocus provides a significant advantage over CG – despite CG has been optimized to provide strong cues even near the current focal plane – mostly due to the very visible and intuitive appearance variations of the marker when subject to slight defocus. As confirmed in informal observations by microscopists, defocused markers convey a significantly more natural and intuitive representation of depth in the images, which is learned without any effort. However , the advantages of such properties over the CG representation are only marginally highlighted in the simple task proposed in this user test. In particular, almost all users quickly learned the utility of color cues in this context. <ref type="figure" coords="8,22.50,374.69,21.91,7.37">Fig. 7.</ref>(a) Focusing time using different representations, averaged over all users. The figure also reports (gray) the focusing times measured during preliminary tests (on a subset of all users) using inferior representations. (b) distribution of median focusing times for each user, grouped by the three different representations (from top to bottom: defocus only, CG only, CG+defocus). (c) Average distance profiles between current focus plane and target focus plane, normalized for initial distance. (d,e,f) scatter plots comparing pairs of representations (see main text). Each data point is a single user. Circles indicate users familiar with microscopy; Crosses indicate users not familiar with microscopy. Source data in supplementary material. </p><formula>(a) (b) (c) (d) (e) (f) </formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0" coords="4,22.50,203.08,513.00,7.37;4,22.50,212.54,513.00,7.37;4,22.50,222.01,513.00,7.37;4,22.50,231.47,513.00,7.40;4,22.50,240.94,146.63,7.37"><head>Fig. </head><figDesc>Fig. 2. Appearance of defocused markers when using different PSF shapes and energy profiles f (z). The stack is composed by 5 rows of 40 point markers each, which are placed at increasing z; the displayed slice is the middle of the stack. Note confocal-like PSF (d) in first row, realistic PSF (e) in second row, and physically-implausible PSFs with amplifying energy profile in rows 3, 4 and 5; row 5 uses PSF (c), which is not symmetrical w.r.t. the z = 0 plane, and provides different bokeh above and below the current focal plane. Also note the discernible appearance of the focused marker, due to its high-frequency content. </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2" coords="5,294.12,448.07,250.38,7.37;5,294.12,457.54,250.38,7.37;5,294.12,467.00,250.38,7.37;5,294.12,476.47,250.38,7.37;5,294.12,485.93,168.51,7.37"><head>Fig. 4. </head><figDesc>Fig. 4. (a): 3D measurements of diatom lengths [7]; diatoms at different depths appear in focus at different slices of the stack, and so do the respective ruler markers. (b,c): point markers and manual 3D angle measurements displayed on two slices of a Z-stack representing stack Peyer plaques from the intestine of a mouse [8]. </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3" coords="6,22.50,274.24,250.38,7.37;6,22.50,283.70,245.01,7.37"><head>Fig. 5. </head><figDesc>Fig. 5. Markers visualizing detected pronuclei in two slices of a focus stack representing a human embryo, acquired during IVF procedures. </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5" coords="7,31.50,114.50,513.00,7.37;7,31.50,123.96,121.56,7.37"><head>Fig. 6. </head><figDesc>Fig. 6. Appearance of a set of markers at different depths, when using the representations under test. Note that the correct depth is artificially highlighted by doubling the border. </figDesc></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> Implementations, source code, and example stacks are available as supplementary material at http://www.idsia.ch/ ˜ giusti/stack</note>

			<note place="foot" n="2"> structures which are very defocused (such as dirt or scratches on the other face of the microscope slide) are invisible in practice</note>

			<note place="foot" n="3"> The exact number varies as each new target is shown using a random representation , and the test stops when a total of 80 targets have been focused</note>

			<note place="foot" n="7"> CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORKS We have proposed a simple technique for intuitive visualization of visual markers in image stacks, by applying a depth-dependent defocus which mimics the behavior of the microscope optics. Building handcrafted point spread functions also allows one to force a desired appearance for defocused point markers, while keeping the natural effect of defocus. This allows the user to easily see markers even when they are far from the current focal plane, and prevents such defocused markers to be confused with image data. We also discussed how carefullydesigned markers can achieve a distinctive appearance when in perfect focus, and how color cues can complement defocus in conveying marker depth. User tests confirm that the approach is valid and well received by users with prior experience with microscopes: it provides measurable advantages in the simple task of bringing a single marker into focus as fast as possible, despite specifically-optimized color-based depth representations also provide immediate (although not as natural) cues for this task. We are setting up more complex and realistic test cases, involving the selection of correctly-segmented blastomeres in embryo image stacks, where different techniques for visualizing marker depths could be further evaluated. In general, the integration of defocus depth cues for visual markers allows intuitive user interfaces to be designed, especially for users already familiar with optical microscopy.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </head><p> This work was partially supported by CTI (Swiss confederations innovation promotion agency) grant n. 9707.1 PFSL-LS. </p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,396.37,58.31,7.13;7,400.04,396.80,144.46,6.15;7,312.38,406.26,64.16,6.15;7,298.11,415.30,27.34,7.13;7,347.94,415.73,196.56,6.15;7,312.38,425.19,45.03,6.15"  xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">notes-from-dreamworlds. blogspot.com/. [2] Fiji</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
				<surname>Stoupin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,434.23,148.54,7.13"  xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Imagej</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,443.70,188.38,7.13"  xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<surname>Imagesurfer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,453.16,199.76,7.13"  xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Microscope</forename>
				<surname>Italy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,481.56,214.68,7.13"  xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The virtual microscope</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,491.02,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,500.48,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,509.95,44.27,7.13"  xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Joint texture and topography estimation for extended depth of field in brightfield microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Aguet</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Van De Ville</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Unser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ISBI</title>
		<meeting>. of ISBI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,519.41,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,528.88,198.65,7.13"  xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods of embryo scoring in in vitro fertilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Baczkowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kurzawa</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">W</forename>
				<surname>Głabowski</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reprod Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,538.34,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,547.81,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,557.27,143.72,7.13"  xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual microscopy with extended depth of field</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Bradley</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Wildermoth</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Mills</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Lovell</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Maeder</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital Image Computing: Techniques and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,566.74,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,576.20,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,585.66,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,595.13,17.93,7.13"  xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oocyte euploidy, pronuclear zygote morphology and embryo chromosomal complement</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Gianaroli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Magli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Ferraretti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Lappi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Borghi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Ermini</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Reproduction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,604.59,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,614.06,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,623.52,157.03,7.13"  xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3D localization of pronuclei of human zygotes using texture features from multiple focal planes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Giusti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Corani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Gambardella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Magli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Gianaroli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of MICCAI</title>
		<meeting>. of MICCAI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,632.99,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,642.45,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,651.92,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,661.38,17.93,7.13"  xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blastomere segmentation and 3D morphology measurements of early embryos from hoffman modulation contrast image stacks</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Giusti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Corani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Gambardella</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Magli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Gianaroli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ISBI</title>
		<meeting>. of ISBI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,670.85,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,680.31,229.22,7.13"  xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blind deconvolution of 3D transmitted light brightfield micrographs</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Holmes</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<forename type="middle">O</forename>
				<surname>Connor</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Microscopy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">200</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,689.77,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,699.24,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,708.70,229.63,7.13"  xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification and uncertainty visualization of dendritic spines from optical microscopy imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Janoos</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Nouansengsy</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Xu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Machiraju</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Wong</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="886" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="7,312.38,718.17,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,727.63,232.12,7.13;7,312.38,737.10,98.52,7.13"  xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume visualization in cell biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Kaufman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Yagel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Bakalash</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Spector</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 1st conference on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>. of the 1st conference on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,452.30,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,461.77,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,471.23,102.82,7.13"  xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A framework for holographic scene representation and image synthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Kaufmann</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,480.70,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,490.16,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,499.63,102.82,7.13"  xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simulating low-cost cameras for augmented reality compositing</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Klein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Murray</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="380" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,509.09,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,518.55,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,528.02,65.31,7.13"  xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer visualization of three-dimensional image data using IMOD</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Kremer</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Mastronarde</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Mcintosh</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of structural biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,537.48,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,546.95,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,556.41,187.62,7.13"  xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time depth-of-field rendering using anisotropically filtered mipmap interpolation</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Lee</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Choi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="453" to="464" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,565.88,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,575.34,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,584.81,213.16,7.13"  xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel prototype for an optical seethrough head-mounted display with addressable focus cues</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Hua</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Cheng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">381</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,594.27,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,603.73,67.85,7.13"  xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">V</forename>
				<surname>Locquin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Langeron</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Handbook of Microscopy. Butterworths Company Ltd</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,613.20,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,622.66,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,632.13,65.31,7.13"  xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A 3D digital atlas of c. elegans and its application to single-cell analyses</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Long</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">H</forename>
				<surname>Peng</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">X</forename>
				<surname>Liu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Kim</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Myers</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="667" to="672" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,641.59,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,651.06,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,660.52,215.68,7.13"  xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Embryo morphology and development are dependent on the chromosomal complement</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>Magli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Gianaroli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<forename type="middle">P</forename>
				<surname>Ferraretti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Lappi</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Ruberti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Farfalli</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fertility Sterility</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="534" to="541" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,669.99,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,679.45,227.38,7.13"  xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional imaging by deconvolution microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Mcnally</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Karpova</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Cooper</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Conchello</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,688.92,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,698.38,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,707.84,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,717.31,102.82,7.13"  xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstruction of cellular biological structures from optical microscopy data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Mosaliganti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">L</forename>
				<surname>Cooper</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Sharp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Machiraju</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Leone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Saltz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="863" to="876" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,40.76,726.77,232.12,7.13;8,40.76,736.24,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,452.30,72.25,7.13"  xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Augmented reality based on estimation of defocusing and motion blurring from captured images</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">B</forename>
				<surname>Okumura</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Kanbara</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Yokoya</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ISMAR</title>
		<meeting>. of ISMAR</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,461.77,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,471.23,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,480.70,142.21,7.13"  xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fluorosim: A visual problem-solving environment for fluorescence microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">W</forename>
				<surname>Quammen</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biomedicine</title>
		<meeting>. of Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biomedicine</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,490.16,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,499.63,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,509.09,112.69,7.13"  xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CATMAID: Collaborative annotation toolkit for massive amounts of image data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Saalfeld</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Cardona</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Hartenstein</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Tomancak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,518.55,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,528.02,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,537.48,98.52,7.13"  xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of laser confocal microscopy datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Sakas</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Vicker</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Plath</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 7th conference on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>. of the 7th conference on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,546.95,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,556.41,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,565.88,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,575.34,133.04,7.13"  xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume rendering phenotype differences in mouse placenta microscopy data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Sharp</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Ridgway</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Mosaliganti</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Wenzel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Pan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>De Bruin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Machiraju</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Huang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Leone</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Saltz</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computing in science &amp; engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,584.81,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,594.27,108.68,7.13"  xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Light microscopy techniques for live cell imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Stephens</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">V</forename>
				<surname>Allan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5616</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">82</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,603.73,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,613.20,206.90,7.13"  xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visualization of multiresolution image stacks in 3D</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Trotts</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Mikula</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Jones</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1038" to="1043" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,622.66,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,632.13,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,641.59,228.64,7.13"  xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of image data from cells to organisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">T</forename>
				<surname>Walter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Shattuck</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Baldock</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Bastin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Carpenter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Duce</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Ellenberg</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Fraser</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Hamilton</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Pieper</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,651.06,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,660.52,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,669.99,204.01,7.13"  xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gpu-based visualization techniques for 3D microscopic imaging data</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Wang</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Y</forename>
				<surname>Sun</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Robinson</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="8,303.38,679.45,232.12,7.13;8,303.38,688.92,179.27,7.13"  xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Microscope Image Processing, chapter Three-Dimensional Microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">Q</forename>
				<surname>Wu</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">F</forename>
				<surname>Merchant</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">K</forename>
				<surname>Castleman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
