<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Case Study Using the Virtual Environment for Reconstructive Surgery</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Montgomery</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">National Biocomputation Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Stephanides</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">National Biocomputation Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephen</forename><surname>Schendel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">National Biocomputation Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Muriel</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">NASA Ames Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94035-1000</postCode>
									<settlement>Moffett Field</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Case Study Using the Virtual Environment for Reconstructive Surgery</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>computer applications</term>
					<term>life and medical sciences</term>
					<term>surgical planning</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper details the use of a Virtual Environment for Reconstructive Surgery (VERS) in the case of a 17 year-old boy with a severe facial defect arising from the removal of a softtissue tumor. Computed tomography (CT) scans were taken of the patient, the data were segmented, a mesh was generated, and this patient-specific mesh was used in a virtual environment b y the surgeons for preoperative visualization of the defect, planning of the surgery, and production of a custom surgical template to aid in repairing the defect. This paper details the case of this patient, provides a background on the virtual environment technology used, discusses the difficulties encountered, and describes the lessons learned.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>The Virtual Environment for Reconstructive Surgery (VERS) project was started three years ago between the NASA Ames Biocomputation Center and the Stanford University Department of Reconstructive Surgery. Its initial aims were to use the 3 D reconstruction and visualization technologies that were developed for space-related research toward providing surgeons with visualization capabilities to aid in preoperative planning. Since then, the scope of the work, and our organizations, have expanded substantially.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NASA and Stanford have recently founded a National</head><p>Biocomputation Center to expand this work to adapt and deploy many of NASA's technologies in the broader area of medicine. The new Center ties together many different groups throughout NASA, with many groups within Stanford (plastic surgery, neurosurgery, education, radiology, computer science, engineering) and external organizations to push the state of the art in computation and visualization to revolutionize medicine.</p><p>The VERS project is only one of several research areas currently under development and it has since expanded its scope to allow full visualization and interaction between the surgeon and the reconstructed data of their patient. The result is a complete surgical planning station that allows the surgeon to visualize their patient's data, extract quantitative information (such as distances and angles) directly from the dataset, to actually simulate the surgical procedure for training purposes, and t o even generate patient-specific custom templates that can be used in the surgery itself. This paper will briefly discuss the technologies behind this project, detail a case study for which this system proved invaluable, and explore the lessons learned in the production and use of a virtual environment for reconstructive surgery.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CASE BACKGROUND</head><p>This case involves a 17 year-old hispanic boy. At age 9 he had a fast-growing soft tissue tumor removed from under his left eye. Because this was an advanced and very aggressive tumor, the surgeon removed all bones and much of the soft tissue on the left side of the boy's face (including the eye) in order to be certain t o fully remove the tumor (see <ref type="figure">figure 1a-</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reconstruction</head><p>First, a computed tomography (CT) scan of the boy was performed. This data was then transferred from the Radiology Department to our SGI Onyx InfiniteReality server. Once there, the data are translated (if necessary) from their vendor-specific format into the standard DICOM format.</p><p>Next, in-house 3D reconstruction software reads the successive DICOM slice images, allows viewing of the raw data, performs segmentation using morphological techniques and connected components analysis, generates a mesh using a Marching Cubes algorithm, allows for automated and semiautomated artifact removal, and permits mesh reduction through a number of techniques. The resulting high resolution meshes are then used for preoperative visualization, where great detail is required (see figures 1a-d).</p><p>There were 2.5 million polygons in the skull model and 1.5 million polygons comprising the face. For preoperative visualization, we typically view these images in stereo, so we require a minimum of 8 million polygons per frame. With currently available technology, this much information could clearly not be rendered in real-time.</p><p>Therefore, the meshes are reduced for interactive visualization purposes in the VERS environment. In the case of this dataset, both the skull and face were reduced to roughly 500K polygons for interactive visualization. Our mesh reduction techniques preserve as much detail as possible, while reducing the number of triangles required to represent the surface. However, this was the minimum size that was judged by the surgeons that still provided sufficient detail. The WorldToolKit application reads in the given mesh files and allows the user to visualize, measure, interact, and manipulate the data of their patient. A number of "virtual tools" are implemented:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Virtual Environment for Reconstructive Surgery</head><p>• Selection/moving tool-allows the user to grab and move/rotate an object • Marker tool-allows the used to lay down markers on the surface of an object • Lighting tool-a "spotlight" that allows more precise localization of lighting A number of operations are also available. There are operations for performance characterization and scene graph display, manipulating object attributes (color, transparency), turning on/off display of objects, setting standard viewpoints, rendering modes (wireframe, solid), saving the scenegraph in VRML, dumping a screen image, deleting all markers, and on-line help. In addition, a number of operations use the locations of the markers: the measure operation measures and displays the distances (linear and surface) and angles between each of the markers; the cut operation subdivides the mesh between to the markers; the reflect operation allows the user to make a duplicate, but reversed object, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Difficulties and Solutions</head><p>The major difficulties identified in producing such an environment lie in the desire to maintain a high fidelity of the dataset, but to provide a reasonable frame rate for the interactive virtual environment. Note that this is a very different paradigm than occurs in most virtual environment applications. In many application areas (such as architectural walkthrough), many objects may be culled because they are currently out of view of the user. In these cases, a scene graph model is of great benefit t o decrease rendering to only those polygons that may be visible in the scene. Also, a bounding box test can be used for aiding i n visibility or selection testing and each object is relatively small (under a thousand polygons). In addition, maintaining multiple levels of detail of an object can further decrease rendering requirements. These techniques can allow the elimination of the consideration of many objects in the scene and further increase display and selection speed.</p><p>In a surgical virtual environment application <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[14]</ref>, there i s typically one, very high resolution object to be viewed. All of the object is in view, all of the time. Even at 500K polygons and with a high-end graphics supercomputer providing a theoretical peak of 10M polygons/second, we have a theoretical maximum framerate of 20 fps. Our observed performance of 4 fps (without display-list objects) or 8 fps (with display-list objects) was considerably less.</p><p>A number of techniques were employed to ameliorate this situation. First, the original meshes of millions of polygons need to be reduced dramatically. Curvature-based (chord height) methods (which reduce the number of polygons in areas of low curvature) initially appeared straightforward, but these techniques, when applied liberally, produced large faceted (flat) areas, particularly on the forehead. By not constraining the size of the conjoined regions, such areas of low curvature were over decimated. Employing polygon size metrics (to eliminate small polygons because they contribute little to the overall visualization) worked well and solved the above shortcomings. However, these techniques, when applied liberally, would tend to erode away sharp edges of the model (such as near the sutures of the skull), since small polygons are often present along such sharp edges. Finally, a technique that allowed user control of the weighting of these two functions allowed us to decrease polygon count, but preserve sufficient fidelity. This is clearly an area that warrants more research. Second, once the original meshes have been decreased in size as much as the surgeons deemed clinically accurate, the issue of how to render these meshes efficiently becomes important. In our case, the large geometry was split up into smaller "slabs". In this way, the slab comprising the rear of the skull could be viewed i n lower resolution using a level-of-detail mechanism. Note that a rear slab can not be completely culled from the scene because there may exist holes in the slabs closer to the user (through the eyes, for instance).</p><p>In addition, this slab-based approach also dramatically improved prebuild time (time to optimize the geometry for rendering and create display list objects-an O(n^2) operation) from 20 minutes to 2 minutes. When preprocessing required 2 0 minutes, the system was very difficult to use and to test due t o this time delay. After the reduction in time, preprocessing, and hence its great rendering advantages, could be realized.</p><p>Moreover, this approach allowed for an optimized selection mechanism. When laying down markers, the marker tool casts a ray toward the geometry and displays a surface-hugging cursor at the location that it is hitting. By subdividing the geometry into these slabs, a quick bounding box test could be used t o determine which slab the ray was hitting, before the more expensive determination of which polygon was being hit was attempted.</p><p>A related difficulty arose in the implementation of certain of the operations listed above. When geometries are small (a thousand polygons), a frame rate can be high enough to allow for interactive, simple polygon deletion for cutting (subdividing) a mesh. While this technique provides a less than optimal cut (very ragged cut lines based on the geometry), it is often used and is trivial to implement. A further refinement is to actually calculate the real location of the cut and to subdivide cut polygons on the fly. Again, this technique works well for small geometries, but does not scale well and does not lend itself t o use with lower frame rates.</p><p>For these reasons, we developed the marker-based cutting method outlined above. By interactively laying down markers, the user can specify the locations of the endpoints of the cut and the more computationally complex cutting algorithm can be invoked after all cut endpoints are specified. This algorithm can take as much as a few seconds with no impact to the user. Moreover, the surgeons found that this mode of interaction fit their paradigm of cutting from point to point well also and they were more amenable to display lag when positioning a marker than they were during interactive mesh subdivision. This method of deferring the computationally intense tasks until after all interactive parameters are provided and the user is willing t o wait is a technique that worked well and we intend to pursue further.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CASE STUDY APPLICATION</head><p>For this case, the surgeons first visualized the high-resolution data of the patient and produced color prints from various views. Next, the VERS system was used to interact with the data. The surgeon could use the system to quickly interact with the meshes representing the skull and the soft tissue (face). When concentrating on the skull, the face object can be left unrendered. The skull could be moved closer into a clipping plane to allow viewing inside the skull for interior structural anomalies. Markers can be laid down on the surface of the skull to measure distances and angles in order to compare the intact side of the face with the affected side. They also could use the cut operator to cut the bone on the intact side of the face, use the reflect operation to produce a mirror duplicate, and examine the fit of this new piece of bone into the area of the defect. If correct, the resulting surgical template could be written out as a VRML file for later use.</p><p>In the case of this patient, the intact side of the face was reflected over the affected side and a template to fix the defect was produced (figure 1e). While this did make the assumption that lateral symmetry could be used as a basis for reconstruction, this was deemed clinically acceptable. This template was then subdivided into more planar subpieces. Then a CT model of the boy's hip was generated and, within the environment, the pieces of the template could be moved within the model of the hip t o find the location of the best curvature match. Then a paper template was produced and taken into the operating room t o allow the surgeon to harvest the bone directly from the hip. Since they had planned it out ahead of time, they could be able to harvest the bone, wire it together as planned, and repair the defect in significantly less time than would otherwise be required. Also, the goal was to repair the defect correctly the first time, without requiring the usual successive procedures for refinement. Both of these benefits also decrease the risk to the patient due to long-term exposure to anesthesia and risk of infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUMMARY</head><p>We have created a system which integrates 3D reconstruction, visualization, quantification, and manipulation of multimodal patient data for the purpose of surgical planning. This system was found to be instrumental in the preparation and correction of a severe craniofacial defect and was well received by the surgical community. While more research is warranted i n segmentation, mesh reduction, high-performance visualization, user interfaces, and other areas, this tool is a first step and will continue to be used clinically and enhanced to provide the surgeon with all the capabilities required to ensure a superior outcome.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>This work was partially supported by the NASA Ames Research Center, under grants to Muriel Ross. The authors would like t o acknowledge and thank her for her support of the National Biocomputation Center and continued support of this work.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three Dimensional Computer Graphics for Craniofacial surgical planning and Evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vannier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Warren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH 83 Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive surgical planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brewster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Trivedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tuy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Udupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="1984-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Display of medical objects and their interactive manipulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jayaram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dewey</forename><surname>Udupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Odhner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Graphics Interface</title>
		<meeting>Graphics Interface</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989-06" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive graphics for plastic surgery: task-level analysis and implementation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Steven</forename><surname>Pieper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Zeltzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Symposium on Interactive 3D Graphics), v(25)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-03" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="134" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Von Buren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fankhauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Parish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Simulating Facial Surgery Using Finite Element Methods, SIGGRAPH 96 Conference Proceedings, ACM SIGGRAPH</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="421" to="428" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vikas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jeffrey</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Vannier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lun-Jou</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Assessing Craniofacial Surgical Simulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="54" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VERS: a virtual environment for reconstructive surgery planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Montgomery</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE<address><addrLine>Scott S. Fisher</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3012</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Stereoscopic Displays and Virtual Reality Systems IV</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Merritt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Robb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bernard</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jon</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Camp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Surgical planning for radical prostatectomies using three-dimensional visualization and a virtual reality display system Proc. SPIE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-04" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2431</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Yongmin Kim</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ken-Ichi</forename><surname>Kameyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Koichi</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Ohtomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ohhashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>Akinami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Iseki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>Hiroshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Naotoshi</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kintomo</forename><surname>Takakura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Virtual surgical operation system using volume scanning display Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Yongmin Kim</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2164</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Medical Imaging 1994: Image Capture, Formatting, and Display</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ed</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="154" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual Data Exploration and Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Sader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Zeilhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">;</forename><surname>Hans-Florian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Horch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Hans-Henning Computer simulation of orthognathic surgery with video imaging Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Robert J. Moorhead</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2178</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Deborah</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Derek</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Crossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hawkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Glynn</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Strong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gleeson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Visualization of multimodal images for the planning of skull base surgery Proc. SPIE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1808</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ron</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Harvey</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Altobelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visualization and manipulation of 3-D reconstructions for the planning of surgical</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Halle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Jolesz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ferenc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization i n Biomedical Computing &apos;92</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Richard A. Robb</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-09" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1808</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="559" to="563" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>procedures Proc. SPIE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alfred</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Linney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Moss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Richards, Robin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mosse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Grindrod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anne</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Coombes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Use of a 3-D visualization system in the planning and evaluation of facial surgery Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Robin E. Herron</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991-04" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1380</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="199" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computer-Integrated Surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lavallee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Burdea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Moesges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-09" />
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
