<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.8 [Computer Graphics Applications]</term>
					<term>I.6 [Simulation and Modeling]</term>
					<term>H.5 [Information Interfaces and Presentation]</term>
					<term>J.2 [Earth and Atmospheric Sciences] visualization</term>
					<term>perception</term>
					<term>user tasks</term>
					<term>graphics design</term>
					<term>meteorology</term>
					<term>operational weather forecasting</term>
					<term>computational tracking</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Efforts to create highly generic visualizations, both content and interface, often fail when applied to non-research-oriented or operational activities composed of several goals. Although these goals may appear to be related, they are often composed of distinct tasks. Generic solutions, even if domain-specific, may lack sufficient focus to be effective for such purposes. The design of different visualization tools matched to a set of tasks but built on top of a common framework with a similar approach to content is a promising alternative. This hypothesis is tested in detail by application to a demanding problem-operational weather forecasting.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Many sources of data can be utilized for different visualizations matched to distinct tasks. Visualization has matured sufficiently that the mechanism of its application to specific problems and the requirements of varying users can be addressed. This can be as important as the underlying numerical methods for realization or the process of rendering in enabling effectiveness. Recent attempts to build very generalized systems to address these tasks have been useful for research activities as well as applications development. However, they have often failed in direct application to more focused, operational environments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Background --Other Approaches</head><p>Given the potential need for more specialized visualizations, efforts to define the prerequisite tasks have ranged from modelling of user needs to creating a taxonomy for design <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. Of course, appropriate content in the visualization is required. Hence, matching of design to task, both interface and composition has been considered recently for the study of geographic data as well as business data <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">9]</ref>. These earlier efforts achieved their decomposition after significant iteration with the consumers of the visualization. Another approach is by automating the design process. For example, Zhou and Feiner discuss an expert system-based implementation focused on design elements, which also uses a taxonomy of data characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>. This approach is only viable because of the relatively limited nature of the visualization techniques, and the application and data domain. For broader problems, the user (intelligence) that defines the tasks must be part of the visualization process to utilize that expertise and the human capacity for pattern recognition. Alternatively, can a set of visualization tasks coupled with appropriate designs be developed a priori, and then refined through iteration? Further, can generalized approaches to these design elements be employed to more efficiently develop appropriately focused visualizations?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">TASK-BASED VISUALIZATION</head><p>To begin, consider three steps to defining visualization tasks: i. Identification of user needs ii. Composition of design elements and interface actions iii. Establishing different techniques for various users Then decompose the tasks hierarchically by recognizing that the user's task are not the same as the visualization tasks. Hence, a given user may require one or more visualization tasks, and a specific visualization technique may support more than one user task. Then consider goals for the user in visualizing (i.e., exploration, insight, presentation), and that there is a likely desire for specific results, such as: To test these ideas, they are applied to a significant set of distinct problems, namely visualization of meteorological data for operational weather forecasting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">OPERATIONAL WEATHER FORECASTING</head><p>Although the concepts for task decomposition in visualization design are independent of application, operational weather forecasting provides an excellent framework for its consideration. This work is an extension of the project that enabled rapid generation and analysis of mesoscale weather simulations by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) National Weather Service (NWS) at the 1996 Centennial Olympic Games <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>. It is a collaborative effort with NOAA Forecast System Laboratory (FSL). It provided a unique initial testbed for new visualization techniques, focused on meeting specific forecasting goals, yet affected by real, operational constraints.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Related Visualization Work</head><p>Visualization in meteorology has a rich tradition and history. The majority of visualization systems today for meteorology are designed from the perspective of "one size fits all". While there is variation among them, they individually provide one interface and one style of visualization independent of the task because they have been designed from the perspective of supporting a single class of users. While such systems clearly can be successful, further efficiency in utilization is possible by recognizing that a single class of users is likely to have more than one goal in visualizing a data set that maps to a specific set of tasks. In mission-critical tasks like operational weather forecasting, improvements in speed and effectiveness have significant impacts. That is why weather agencies have invested in developing highly focused visualization tools. One major example is the Advanced Weather Interactive Processing Sys-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Task-Specific Visualization Design: A Case Study in Operational Weather Forecasting</head><p>Lloyd A. Treinish</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center</head><p>Yorktown Heights, NY lloydt@us.ibm.com tem (AWIPS) deployed by the NWS provides two-dimensional visualizations <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref>. Conceptually similar tools are available from a plethora of other organizations worldwide. Current sources of acquired and computed data imply the generation of large, three-dimensional volumes, for which improved facilities for analysis are required for timely assessment and utilization in forecasts. However, two-dimensional techniques dominate in operational settings, even though their use can be burdensome with large data volumes. There are a few exceptions to this situation. Chief among them is Vis-5D developed at the University of Wisconsin. It has a fixed user interface with specific visualization tools typically tied to graphics hardware on Unix workstations, with support for a single class of data. The implementation focuses on manipulation of regularly gridded data, preferably compressed to byte precision to increase the speed of operation. As a result, the package is highly interactive, easy-to-use and maps well to many meteorological data sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref>. However, for forecasting tasks such as model assessment and dissemination, it is too generic and does not have the ideal interface or content, because its primary focus has been on analysis. Fraunhofer Institut für Graphische Datenverarbeitung (FIGD) has taken a different approach. They have implemented independent systems that are highly focused for specific tasks yet designed to be operated by meteorologists. Their development has been in conjunction with the Deutscher Wetterdientst (DWD). The first was Triton, oriented toward generating two-dimensional visualizations for the non-meteorologist <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>. The second, TriVis, is based upon a related goal --providing two-and three-dimensional visualizations for television broadcasts <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>. The third system, RASSIN, is designed to provide analysis facilities directly on the native grids of the meteorological data <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>. The latter two systems are in use by DWD. The FIGD systems only share an underlying renderer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">COMPOSITIONAL GUIDELINES</head><p>These methods have been developed within a natural coordinate system to provide a context for three-dimensional display and interaction. They provide representations of the atmosphere consistent with the data source that are registered with terrain and political boundary maps. This approach is one of correlative visualization, where each data set to be examined is processed independently and merging takes places at render time <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>. Both the design of the content and the choice of coordinate system has been dictated by the particular task to support both conceptual and physical realizations.</p><p>Since color is a critical aspect of design, knowledge of human perception is applied via a rule-based advisory tool that is sensitive to the spatial frequency of data and the visualization task <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>. For example, relatively noisy data such as wind speed are primarily mapped into luminance, while relatively smoothly varying data such as temperature are primarily mapped into opposing saturation pairs to impart an isomorphic or continuous representation. For moisture-related data (e.g., humidity and precipitation), two colormaps are combined such that dry regions are mapped to brown ranging through yellow to green for modest values. At high levels, the data are mapped into blue, with decreasing luminance. When contouring is used to map the data onto a set of bands, a segmented colormap with perceived ordinality is applied. For discrete three-dimensional representations (e.g., cloud surfaces), uniform but complementary colors are chosen to minimize the effects of color mixing. For direct volume rendering of these data, the same hue is employed, but coupled with simultaneous mapping into luminance and opacity.</p><p>Several techniques are implemented for surface wind velocity, which are pseudo-colored by wind speed draped over the topographic surface: vector arrows of fixed size, which point in the wind direction, streamlines with directional arrows, which show continuous flow, or waving flags. Keeping the vector arrows of fixed size eliminates misleading motion cues during animation and is useful to show gross atmospheric movement. In contrast, this form of streamlines, although visually more complex, is superior at capturing fronts, convergence zones, vortices etc. The flags point in the direction of the wind, which can be either rigid or furled (i.e., straight at maximum speed and draped against a flag pole in the absence of wind). The use of flags has been effective to illustrate wind motion to the non-meteorologist.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">RESULTS</head><p>Independent of the sources of data, four classes of visualization are derived from the aforementioned tasks: I. Traditional two-dimensional vector graphics II. Two-and 2-1/2-dimensional analysis III. Three-dimensional browsing IV. Three-dimensional analysis The first class as discussed earlier is not adequate for current data volumes. It consists of conventional representations of selected meteorological fields. It has evolved to support primarily analysis tasks by forecasters with minimal direct (graphical) interaction at a specific "layer", either the ground or at a constant atmospheric pressure (isobaric level). Given a flat canvas for visualization design consistent with the display of a single layer, these tools can only show a few parameters simultaneously (e.g., overlaying wind as barbs or arrows, a scalar variable as line contours). Simplified versions of these representations have also been developed to support presentation to non-meteorologists, particularly for the media (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> is an example of a typical visualization produced by class I tools. They may also provide simple film-loop-like animation. The latter three visualization classes are the focus of the work discussed herein. In each case, the user has a set of tools to design a visualization and interact with selected data. The available techniques are limited to focus on specific tasks, which are then supported by relatively simple interfaces. Class II can be viewed as a superset of class I by including enhancements into three dimensions and the ability to leverage modern workstation hardware. Its focus is for analysis by forecasters, particularly to support data comparison. Because the appearance of the visualizations may be complex, direct manipulation is provided. As a result, up to five parameters may be visualized simultaneously. These twodimensional variables may be any combination of surface or upper air layers from the same or different source. They may be illustrated redundantly by applying multiple techniques (e.g., color and height). The variables and techniques can be independently selected interactively. An example is shown in figure 2. Class III enables forecasters to create qualitative three-dimensional representations for both interactive investigation and production of animation via browsing. The consumers may or may not be specialists but the interactive user is likely to be a meteorologist. Thus, the results may be suitable for media and public dissemination to support the explanation of specific forecasts. The visualizations have a simplified appearance to utilize pattern recognition for general understanding as well as feature identification. It requires highresolution data (temporally and spatially) to enable a coherent presentation. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref> shows a result from such a browsing application, which enables interaction in geographic-altitude coordinates. The ability to create both time-based and key-frame (flyover) animations is available. The browser enables tracking of simulations during execution. Although direct interprocessor communication between the visualization and simulation could have been used to balance the output with bandwidth, a custom file format was designed instead associated with a set of specialized readers. To further minimize the volume of data to be accessed, several parameters (humidity, dew point and heat index) were computed within the visualization application from more basic variables. Thus, limited variables generated at 10-minute intervals of simulated time optimized for network access resulted in little observable latency in interactive application.</p><p>Class IV provides analysis, viewing, interrogation and interaction tools with standard products designed for AWIPS. This class is similar to the visualization tasks addressed by the aforementioned Vis-5D and RASSIN packages, but with greater emphasis on direct manipulation and the introduction of new realization methods. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> shows a result from such a viewing/analysis application, which enables interrogation in a geographic-pressure coordinate system annotated with an axes box and base maps. One may probe the volume for specific values at selected locations within the data set.</p><p>After each model or analysis execution, all of the results are collected and reorganized into a form that can be used by standard meteorological tools. These post-processed data are made available for interactive visualization and analysis. This includes all of computed variables, but at hourly resolution unlike the browser application that works with a subset of variables at six times the temporal resolution. The upper air three-dimensional wind velocity is visualized via interactive marking of geographic locations for virtual soundings within the model atmosphere. At each location, a vertical profile is extruded through the atmosphere, which is realized as a tube. The wind velocity along the profile is shown by a set of vector arrows that point in the direction of the wind. Horizontal speed at these points is indicated by the color and length of the arrows. Optionally, the locations on each virtual wind profiler can be used for seed particles for particle advection, which is realized as streamlines. These lines, which are also pseudo-colored by horizontal speed, indicate the instantaneous direction of the modelled wind from these locations. These profiles are also shown via a conventional pressure-profile plot in a separate window.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>A suite of tools invoked through c-shell scripts on a UNIX workstation or shortcut icons on a WIntel workstation provides the facilities for visualization classes II, III and IV. They present a user interface based upon XWindow/Motif for indirect interaction and OpenGL for direct three-dimensional interaction in cartographic coordinates. They have been implemented with IBM Visualization Data Explorer (DX) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. DX is a portable, general-purpose software package for visualization and analysis. It employs a client-server architecture with an extended data-flow execution model. A generic toolkit was used to avoid having to implement a graphics and computational infrastructure. Unlike traditional meteorological graphics, DX enables the use of modern workstation hardware equipped with three-dimensional graphics accelerators and is parallelized for symmetric multi-processors. DX is built upon an unified data model that enables these applications to operate directly on the native grids without transformation or compression, which preserves the fidelity during visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>. Further, such a toolkit is extensible to allow development to be focused on meteorological data and tasks, and reuse of tools between applications with similar user interface components. This simplifies training of users to employ the applications with different content matched to separate tasks. It also reduces the cost of development and maintenance, and enables more rapid iterative refinement with or adaptation to new users. These tools are part of integrated system that provides operational mesoscale numerical weather prediction in a wide variety of environments. It evolved from the aforementioned experiments to support forecasting at the 1996 Olympic Games <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>. Additional information about the system as well as numerous visualization examples are available on the World-Wide-Web (http://www.research.ibm.com/ weather).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">UTILIZATION</head><p>The browse application (class III) is used to evaluate model results and create various products. Typically, an animation with 10-minute resolution over the full model run (24 hours long on a 3-hour duty/refresh cycle) is created after the forecaster selects the variables, techniques and geographic view. One or more animations are generated for local playback at workstation resolution to support media briefings. They are MPEG-encoded and associated with a higher-resolution image for distribution on the World-Wide-Web. The contents of such a snapshot image can also be disseminated as a VRML geometry, key-frame flythrough animation or a panoramic scene (i.e., via IBM PanoramIX). As with VRML support, PanoramIX is a web-browser plug-in to enable navigation through the three-dimensional representation of the weather data, but uses image-based rendering. In addition, the ability to track the model during execution provides quality control and comparison with results from previously completed runs. Analysis with the view application (class IV) must wait until the post-processing phase was completed at the end of a run.</p><p>As a result, such interaction generally took place well after the next run was begun, which limited the ability to simultaneously compare output.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Specialized interfaces and tools matched to user goals and underlying visualization tasks to support them is a promising approach to providing new visualization facilities to operational activities, especially in weather forecasting. Such successful facilities can be characterized as being easy to master via simple interfaces, even if the underlying capabilities may be quite complex. Although highly generalized systems can be employed to provide similar functionality, the lack of focus in the interface increases learning time beyond what would be considerable acceptable in time-critical activities. This is in contrast to what is often preferred in many research environments. An effective compromise has been developed herein, where the generic tools are used for both prototyping new applications and efficient implementation of complete systems, particularly by promoting high-level reuse of underlying tools and design elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1">Application-specific</head><p>Class III visualizations proved to be more effective than initially expected. For example, one could easily infer vertical motion based on a three-dimensional display of clouds forming. Although the model may not have indicated precipitation occurring in a specific location, the existence of clouds gives forewarning that precipitation may be possible in that vicinity. The single, most useful aspect of class III is that it virtually eliminates the need to laboriously evaluate numerous class I images by presenting all the relevant information in an easy-to-interpret, four-dimensional display. Concep-tual models that would normally require inference from a significant amount of two-dimensional data (e.g., the horizontal extent of cloud dissipation in the lee of the Appalachian mountains) are obvious in three-dimensional animations. Originally intended for media displays, the browse application quickly gained favor by forecasters as a valuable operational forecasting tool. The subsequent introduction of class IV into operations complements class III. However, it uncovered some problems inherent in utilizing the data for AWIPS. Although the user can easily select a data set of interest, the organization of the data is not ideal for the type of required access. Often the post-processed results (all variables and time steps) are collected into a single, large file. While convenient from the perspective of the data generator, access to specific arrays forces unnecessarily long seeks across a local-area network. This limits performance until requested data are loaded into memory. One could introduce an additional post-processing step to reorganize the data, but that would further delay access to generated data, and increase the need for disk storage. In addition, not all of the variables defined in this format are consistently populated, and the metadata describing the variables are incomplete. This can lead either to user error or increasing the complexity of the application and interface to compensate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">FUTURE WORK</head><p>This approach to visualization in operational weather forecasting was of immediate value at the 1996 Olympic Games, enabling the NWS to provide information for athletes, spectators and officials to plan around adverse weather conditions. These technologies could be applied in other areas where precision forecasting shows promise like tourism, aviation, agriculture, broadcast, energy, insurance, pollution monitoring, and fire control and management. For effective utilization outside of general forecasting, a refinement of the task decomposition will be necessary based upon the specific application. Initially, that would imply customized interfaces, products and packaging, most likely for class III. For aviation, that might include, for example, support for route planning, dispatch, etc. for both safety and efficiency, where predictions of prevailing winds, icing surfaces and clear-air turbulence are shown along a flight path.</p><p>Since there is prepondence of potential data sources that could be utilized with these tools, extensions to support them will be driven by the ability to leverage "standard" products (e.g., data formatted for AWIPS). Part of that effort will be to more tightly couple the interaction between class III and the simulation to enable more efficient tracking/steering. Another aspect is to improve the organization of the model output, particularly for the post-processing (analysis) products.</p><p>Web-oriented visualizations can be generated by the current set of applications but an intermediate step of migrating the products to a web server is currently required. This has the advantage in an operational environment, where the forecaster has control over the content of the visualizations that may be disseminated to a variety of consumers. However, the task decomposition can be further refined by considering direct generation of visualizations within a web browser. Similar tasks could still apply, but the user interface and the content must be simplified to be effective. Thus, the current indirect interaction would be replaced with Java-based applets in the browser as a client that communicates with a DX server processing the data and generating the requested visualization. All of the aforementioned methods, MPEG animations, and image, VRML and PanoramIX snapshots are relevant. However, the generation time for the animation of a suitable length and the download time for VRML are current barriers. The notion of task-driven customization of visualization content and interface has shown to be successful in weather forecasting. Although the results are discipline-specific, the concept is not. Many problem areas do imply different visualization tasks with various mappings to user tasks. The current literature on task definition, user modelling and content design generally employs examples from disciplines other than weather forecasting. Therefore, applying the approach discussed herein to other domains is desirable. Likely candidates include results from medical scanners, the output of data mining algorithms applied to relational data bases, and utilization of results from terascale physics simulations.    </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>• Feature or event identification • Comparison or fusion of data from disparate sources • Decision support • Communication of the results Independent of the user goals and potential results, is the definition of visualization tasks. These consist of various graphical or interface actions such as select, interact, animate, interrogate, etc. The actions are used for specific composition like browse, analyze or present.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Class I Visualization. Traditional meteorological visualization showing a precipitation forecast for August 4, 1996 at 8 pm EDT.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Class II Visualization. Four scalar fields are visualized in the stereographic coordinates of the model for December 5, 1995 at 11:00 pm EST. The primary features are precipitable water as the height of a shaded, deformed surface, pseudo-colored by temperature, and marked with the mean sea level pressure at discrete locations. Color-coded relative humidity contours at 10% intervals are overlaid along with streamlines of wind. The wind direction is indicated by arrows and the speed by color. The surface is also draped with local coastline (black), state boundaries (magenta) and river (blue) maps. A correlation is visible between moderate levels of precipitable water and humidity with high temperature in south-central Georgia, and lower levels of precipitable water, wind and temperature along the coast. In northern Georgia and southwestern North Carolina, there is a direct correlation between lower precipitable water and temperature with higher humidity.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Class III Visualization. A three-dimensional representation of predicted cloud structure is shown as translucent, white isosurfaces of cloud water density at 10 -5 kg/kg for August 4, 1996 at 9:00 pm EDT. The cloud surfaces are registered with a terrain map overlaid with coastline (black) and state (white) boundary maps in a terrain-following, stereographic grid, where the cities of Atlanta and Savannah are marked. This familiar representation can effectively show gross atmospheric motion and potential distribution of moisture. The terrain is pseudo-colored by total precipitation to indicate where and how much rainfall is predicted (heavy rainfall as blue puddles). Translucent, cyan isosurfaces in the interior of the clouds are forecast radar reflectivities at a threshold of 25 dBz, approximating rain shafts. The correspondence between the rain shaft and the region of relatively heavy precipitation is quite clear. The surface is also overlaid with vector arrows of surface wind velocity, color-coded by speed. The results were computed at 8 km horizontal resolution and are shown for the time during the Closing Ceremonies of the 1996 Summer Olympic Games. The model, as illustrated through three-dimensional visualization, correctly predicted thunderstorm activity in the vicinity of Atlanta, but NOT over the city itself. Thus, forecasters were able to give Olympic officials an "all clear" despite thunderstorms in the area.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Class IV Visualization. Observations for April 27, 1998 at 8 am CDT are shown. A surface variable (visibility) has been selected for display as pseudo-color, which is overlaid on a topographic map. Rivers (blue) and coastlines (black) are draped on the surface. An upper air variable (relative humidity) is represented via surface extraction at 85% in translucent tan corresponding to a cloud boundary. Another field (temperature) has been selected to show as a vertical slice, which is pseudo-color contoured. Any of the three-dimensional fields available can be visualized with either of these methods. The upper air wind data can be seen along three vertical profiles, which are specified interactively. The direction of the wind field along these virtual soundings are shown via vector arrows pseudo-colored by horizontal wind speed. The length of the arrows also corresponds to the horizontal speed. In addition, winds are shown via streamribbons, using the arrow origins as seed points. Each profile is realized as a pseudo-colored tube, which is contoured by the variable selected for isosurface realization (i.e., humidity).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Extended Data-Flow Architecture for Data Analysis and Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Abram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE Visualization 1995 Conference</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE Visualization 1995 Conference<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-11-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="270" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Structure of the Information Design Space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE Information Visualization 1997 Conference</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE Information Visualization 1997 Conference<address><addrLine>Phoenix, AZ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="99" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">User Modeling for Adaptive Visualization Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Domik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gutkauf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Conference</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="223" />
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Visualization of Earth and Space Science Computations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hibbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Santek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Battaiola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Voidrot-Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A System for Guiding and Training Users in the Visualization of Geographic Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1st Conference of GeoComputation. School of Geography</title>
		<meeting>the 1st Conference of GeoComputation. School of Geography<address><addrLine>Leeds, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="470" to="482" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Visualization System for Operational Meteorological Use</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fruhauf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixth International Conference in Central Europe on Computer Graphics and Visualization (WSCG&apos;98)</title>
		<meeting>the Sixth International Conference in Central Europe on Computer Graphics and Visualization (WSCG&apos;98)<address><addrLine>Plzen, Czech Republic</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="534" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://www.nws.noaa.gov/msm/awips/awipsmsm.htm" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">National Weather Service. AWIPS Program Information</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Not to Lie with Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rogowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="274" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Visualization Customer Segmentations Produced by Self Organizing Maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rushmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lawrence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Almasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE Visualization 1997 Conference</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE Visualization 1997 Conference<address><addrLine>Phoenix, AZ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Meteorological Data for a Lay Audience</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schroder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">September 1993</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="14" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">TriVis --Professional Television Weather Presentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schroder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.igd.fhg.de/www/igd-a4/projects/docs/trivis/trivis_e.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local-Domain Mesoscale Analysis and Forecast Model Support for the</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Snook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stamus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Christidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcginley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Centennial Olympic Games. Weather and Forecasting</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of Disparate Data in the Earth Sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="671" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-Dimensional Visualization for Support of Operational Forecasting at the 1996 Centennial Olympic Games</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rothfusz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thirteenth International Conference on Interactive Information and Processing Systems for Meteorology, Oceanography and Hydrology</title>
		<meeting>the Thirteenth International Conference on Interactive Information and Processing Systems for Meteorology, Oceanography and Hydrology<address><addrLine>Long Beach, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Meteorology Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data Characterization for Automatically Visualizing Heterogeneous Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE Information Visualization 1996 Conference</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE Information Visualization 1996 Conference<address><addrLine>San Francisco, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
