<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>This case study describes the design and development of VISOR (Visual Integration of Simulated and Observed Results), a tool which supports the visualization and analysis of a wide variety of data relevant to aerospace engineering design. Integrating data from such disparate sources is challenging; overcoming the obstacles results in a powerful tool. The process has also been valuable in exposing requirements for the libraries of reusable software tools for visualization and data analysis being developed at NASA Ames.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">INTRODUCTION VISOR (Visual Integration of Simulated and Observed Results)</head><p>is a program that has been developed at NASA Ames Research Center to support analysis and visualization of aeronautical data from a variety of experimental and computational sources. This software provides the ability to display and analyze data from these heterogeneous sources in a single three dimensional environment. VISOR is both a working prototype with a small collection of users and a testbed for developing visualization and analysis ideas.</p><p>The exploitation of data from many sources for a single purpose is a trend that is growing rapidly in science and engineering. Reduced costs and increasing benefits both contribute to this growth. As computers become cheaper and more powerful, more data acquisition systems become digital, making observations and experiment results available for analysis. The same trends result in increasing use of simulations as computational experiments. Networks linking large numbers of widely distributed computers improve the ability of analysts to bring related data together. Data from different sources can be used to check consistency, test models, provide context, and generally improve understanding of a subject.</p><p>Using data from multiple sources is difficult in a variety of ways. The heterogeneity of data is the key difficulty, and it may be expressed in many ways, including differences in geometric coordinates, precision, sampling densities, units of measurement, and the circumstances of capture or creation. Software can be used to shield users from many of the common difficulties.</p><p>Aeronautics researchers and engineers at NASA Ames and our industrial partners have a wide variety of tools which are used to analyze various types of data for their distinct purposes. However, these tools are generally customized for particular uses and particular categories of data. New data acquisition technologies have driven a conversion of wind tunnel methods from analog to digital, and also created an opportunity for collaboration between experimental aeroscientists and computational aeroscientists. By broadening this collaboration to include all groups involved in design of an aircraft, industry can continue to move from sequential engineering design steps to concurrent engineering, resulting in both better designs and shorter design time.</p><p>The current project at NASA Ames supports collaboration of experimental and computational fluid dynamicists, who concurrently access two dimensional and three dimensional computational fluid dynamics (CFD) results, data from new wind tunnel acquisition technologies such as Pressure Sensitive Paint (PSP) data <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, Doppler Global Velocimetry (DGV) data <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, data acquired via Phased Microphone Array Technology (PMAT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, Video Model Deformation (VMD) data, and more traditional, sparsely sampled data, like pressure measured by pressure taps on the wind tunnel model. The visualization aspect of this project is a continuation of the effort which produced exVis <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</p><p>VISOR is designed to be used as a testbed for ideas in comparative visualization, supporting image level comparisons, data level comparisons and feature level comparisons. It has already contributed to the development of the collection of reusable code libraries collectively called "horizontal products" at NASA Ames. The current version of VISOR uses the second version of the Field Encapsulation Library (FEL2) and several features in FEL2 are present as a direct result of the needs demonstrated by VISOR. The program has also served as a pathfinding development for other object oriented visualization tools.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">REQUIREMENTS</head><p>One purpose of VISOR is to provide a venue for the discovery of software issues concerning multi-source visualization. With this in mind, the primary requirements for VISOR arise from the goal to provide a visualization tool for the NASA DARWIN <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> project. DARWIN is an integrated system of hardware and software designed to facilitate the flow of information from wind tunnels in the aircraft design cycle. Data from the various wind tunnel experiments mentioned above is stored on the DARWIN server where it may be retrieved later for analysis. DARWIN is being extended to coordinate the work of computational fluid dynamicists involved in design revisions of the wind tunnel models. Data from four different CFD codes add to the heterogeneity of the data to be considered.</p><p>In addition to the heterogeneous mix of data sets of varying dimensionality, format, and numeric type DARWIN provides VISOR, there is also metadata with each data set, in differing amount, format and content. This heterogeneity creates a need for a general data model which both user and software developer find useful. A user should be required to know as little as possible to use analysis tools, but the tools should be sufficiently powerful and flexible to meet the needs of the most knowledgeable users. Metadata allows software to determine reasonable defaults for accessing data and appropriate methods for manipulating it. Tools should include methods to access this information without requiring users to understand it and these methods should be defined in the data model.</p><p>In some cases, a visualization technique will require two or more data sets of differing physical contexts such as dimensionality or location. This difference might be resolved by projecting one data Experimental data often contains missing values and outliers. In many cases, experimentalists will want to probe a scene for these and other actual data values. Results from simulation, although generally less noisy, can be very large, especially if they are time variant. These issues must also be addressed by a multi-source visualization application.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Development of a Multi-Source Visualization Prototype</head><p>In order to serve users at all NASA centers and those from corporate partners, the DARWIN server is accessible over the Internet. This convenience introduces network issues including latency and security which complicate the implementation of an application. VISOR must handle authentication, resolve URLs to file names, and handle file transfer without blocking the user from making other requests.</p><p>The DARWIN project provides the VISOR team with a set of users and a user environment for which to design. The users are also heterogeneous, with distinct backgrounds, specializations and missions within the DARWIN project. Presently, these users examine different data with separate tools; the tools may be specific to the data or to the user and the task. An integrated system will allow users to access data new to them. A user may be an expert in one field and a novice in another, which presents some interesting user interface challenges. There are also several issues involved in combining data from different sources into a single effective visualization.</p><p>New experimental technologies are constantly being developed, and new data formats created. Adding a new data source usually means creating one or more new visualization techniques. As a testbed for comparative techniques and integration of support libraries such as FEL2, VISOR must have a flexible and scalable architecture. These characteristics facilitate the addition and modification of new techniques and data sources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">DESIGN</head><p>The VISOR design was strongly influenced by our previous experience collaborating with users in developing exVis. We continue to learn about the applications and data complexities, and the design evolves in response. Several libraries under development at NAS will be useful for VISOR; some pre-release portions have been used in the current version.</p><p>The object-oriented design of the VISOR architecture is intended to promote flexibility and scalability. This design includes a collection of objects which manage data and information about the data, apply visualization techniques, display geometry and data mapped to visible attributes, and support user interaction of various kinds. Many of these objects are designed to be reused in other applications. The most important object classes are described here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">DataSet</head><p>The data model was designed to handle the heterogeneous nature of the data that VISOR is required to display. A few observations regarding the movement of data through a visualization system led to the construction of the following model.</p><p>A scientist tends to work with one or more groups of data values which can be called a "data set". In an analysis, operations are expected to be performed on the entire data set or some subset thereof. Therefore the basic unit of the VISOR data model is the DataSet class. This class represents a group of data values which are all of the same numeric type (e.g. int, float), dimensionality (e.g. 1D, 2D), and rank (e.g. scalar, vector). The same DataSet object (an instantiation of the DataSet class) can be identified by the user at any point along the analysis path from when it is in a file to when displayed by a visualization technique.</p><p>Scalar and vector operations are substantially different, so the DataSet class is subclassed into the ScalarDataSet and VectorDataSet classes. These derived classes offer interfaces specific to their rank. The subclass CompoundDataSet supports grouping of DataSet objects.</p><p>DataSet objects contain a description of their data including its class, organization, origin, numeric type, dimension, rank, and any other metadata associated with it. Any of this information may be retrieved from the DataSet through public methods. The DataSet object can be stored in a file containing the data description, metadata, and a description of the file that contains the data values. Some DataSet description files are automatically generated for VISOR by DARWIN.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">FileLoader</head><p>Given a DataSet, a FileLoader object will load its data values. Subclasses are derived from the FileLoader class for each scientific data format used in DARWIN. Those currently implemented include Plot3D for 3D geometry and CFD data, and FITS for 2D image data. At NASA Ames, many experimental data sets also use the Plot3D format to allow the use of existing visualization tools.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Technique</head><p>Each Technique subclass implements a visualization technique with input from one or more DataSets. A Technique may also create DataSet objects. Subclasses include ImageAnalyzer, ImageResection, SurfaceAnalyzer, and Grapher. Each of these objects processes its DataSets, accessing any metadata it needs, and creates one or more WorldObjects which are then placed in a viewing window. The ImageAnalyzer class displays 2D data sets as color-mapped images. The ImageResection class, performs an image resection of views from several cameras, and produces a VectorDataSet of texture coordinates. The SurfaceAnalyzer class displays color-mapped data from one or more images on a surface and provides a cutting plane tool for extracting and graphing specific data values. The Grapher technique graphs the DataSets produced by the cutting plane tool.</p><p>The primary example used in this case study is a photogrammetry technique described by McLachlan &amp; Bell <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, modified to use texture mapping. This technique was chosen for the following reasons: data appropriate for this technique is available from DARWIN, it merges data of different types and dimensions, and there are corresponding CFD results available for comparative visualization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">WorldObject</head><p>The images, surfaces, and cutting plane tools created by Technique objects are called WorldObjects. An object of this class represents an item or group of items (e.g. a surface, set of images, etc.) which acts as a unit and exists in the world displayed in a viewing window. It is the graphical interface for the technique and can draw or move itself and can be controlled by the user. Subclasses of the WorldObject are based on functionality (e.g. Surface, Image, etc.).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Dialog</head><p>The Dialog class encapsulates the user interface for a Technique. It allows the user to create a new technique or edit an existing one. Subclasses include one for each technique class.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">IMPLEMENTATION</head><p>The VISOR prototype is implemented in C++, OpenGL, and Motif on Silicon Graphics platforms. Two other libraries were also considered: Silicon Graphics' OpenInventor, and the Visualization ToolKit. However, neither provided enough additional value to justify their use at the time development started. And since the software is intended to be distributed to users on other machines and at other locations, the fewer libraries required, the easier the distribution process. OpenInventor was used in the previous tool, exVis, but ruled out for VISOR partly for reasons of performance on small machines and partly with the ease of porting to other platforms in mind. A VISOR framework was created to manage and service the objects described above.</p><p>For the example technique, the prototype uses data sources PSP, DGV, and PMAT. For each source, the model grid is a curvilinear surface grid in Plot3D format. Providing one value for every model grid node, the DGV and PMAT data is ready for the SurfaceAnalyzer to render, as the texture map coordinates correspond to grid node indices. The PSP data, on the other hand, consists of several images from cameras at different viewpoints and requires an image resection to be performed before rendering. The ImageResection object uses a direct linear transform computed from landmark points on the model and in the images to produce a new DataSet. This DataSet contains a 2D image coordinate for each model grid node as it would be projected on the image. These values are used as texture map coordinates by the SurfaceAnalyzer class to render the image onto the surface.</p><p>For further analysis, the SurfaceAnalyzer employs a PlaneTool object, which implements a cutting plane to extract actual data values along a crossection of the surface. FEL2 is used with an isosurface method to compute the intersection of the cutting plane and the surface and for interpolation between model grid nodes. Both the isosurface method and the FEL2 are part of the NASA Ames reusable code libraries.</p><p>The WorldObjects are implemented in two parts: a subject and an observer. The subject contains data which the observer uses for drawing graphics in the viewing window. Only one copy of the data is maintained, which reduces memory usage. This configuration also provides the persistent object for the implementation of probing for actual data values. There may be many observers in different windows displaying one subject.</p><p>Metadata is stored in a DataSet object as strings consisting of key/ value pairs. This allows the DataSet to store the metadata values without needing to know their numeric type. Techniques are the only objects that actually know what the type is. Overloaded access methods on the DataSet provide the Technique with the means to retrieve the metadata values according to numeric type.</p><p>Colormaps are created and modified with the ColormapEditor tool. This tool is also part of the reusable code libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">RESULTS</head><p>The design provides a simple, flexible architecture. To add a visualization technique, a new Technique subclass and its Dialog subclass are created. The Technique subclass may use existing WorldObject subclasses or add others to VISOR as necessary. The interface between the new Technique subclass and its associated classes may be as complicated or simple as the developer wishes. To add a new file format only a FileLoader must be added.</p><p>VISOR provides real-time interaction with a 200,049 node aircraft geometry, texture mapped with 4 PSP images and a PMAT and a DGV surface in one scene on an SGI Indigo2. This scene is depicted in figures 5a and 5b.</p><p>The partial integration and use of two of the NASA Ames reusable code libraries into VISOR proved useful in testing those products. Several issues were identified which affected their implementation.</p><p>During development, preparing multi-source data for input to VISOR was a challenge. It became evident that there is a need for a greater use of self-describing file formats. Also, more metadata is needed; many bits of information stored in the mind of the originator of a data set or hard-coded in some custom software, needs to be available on-line for other users.</p><p>In <ref type="figure">figure 5</ref>, three surfaces created from three different data sources are displayed. Each data source uses a different colormap. It is difficult to create three distinguishable colormaps; alternate visualizations are needed.</p><p>Due to the ever changing nature of a prototype, the graphical user interface for VISOR was kept extremely simple and lacking suitable defaults and help facilities. Thus the dialog panels are somewhat cumbersome to use. Also, with so many data sources, knowing how they can be combined and visualized is somewhat overwhelming. The user interface is being improved as users provide additional feedback. The first row shows steps in the image resection process required to map two dimensional data acquired via an imaging system back into three dimensions. The set of four small images in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> are PSP data sets acquired at the same time by different cameras viewing the same model during a test, and stored as FITS files. The four cameras are arranged with two above the model, one upstream and one downstream, and two below, also upstream and downstream. The data stored are coefficient of pressure (Cp) values, which are displayed using color mapping. The differences among the data from the images are most visible on the flaps along the trailing edge of the wing and the slat along the leading edge.</p><p>The <ref type="figure">Figure 2a</ref> shows the lower upstream camera's image of the underside of the wind tunnel model mapped onto a geometric model of the surface. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2b</ref> shows the upper upstream camera's image of the upper surface mapped to the same geometric model. The small blue dots are the locations of "control points" used as landmarks for the process of registering the image to the geometric model. Cameras with an oblique view of a surface show the surface with a foreshortened area. When the data set is mapped to the model, foreshortened areas are spread, resulting in lower data resolution.</p><p>The data from these four views is combined into a single data set using heuristics to select the best source of data for portions covered by more than one data set. This unified data set is used in all the remaining figures. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figures 3a, 3b and 4</ref>, a cutting plane is displayed along with the model and the data on it. This tool is used to select data to be graphed.</p><p>A linear slice through all wing elements (wing, flaps and slats) selecting data from both upper and lower surfaces was a central requirement of the experimental aeroscientists. Graphs of data from such slices along a chord of a wing (as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figures 3a, 3b and  4)</ref> or along a span (from fuselage to wing tip) have been constructed from sparse wind tunnel experiment data for many years. Not only are the users comfortable with the form, with years of experience in what to expect, but it also provides an easy way to compare data acquired via the PSP system to data from more traditional methods like rows of pressure taps. The graph in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref> clearly shows the two distinct levels of Cp value characteristic of the upper and lower surfaces of a wing. Discontinuities at the spaces between model elements are also visible.</p><p>Figures 5a and 5b show two views of a scene containing data acquired from three different instrumentation systems with a computational wing model. The Cp values on the wing surface, acquired via the PSP system, have been given a more restricted color map than the one used above, to avoid conflicts with colors used for the other data. The small blue-green rectangle behind the wing tip shows one component of velocity vectors acquired using a DGV system. The large red, magenta and purple surface below the model is displaying acoustic amplitude of a single wavelength on this surface, as reconstructed using PMAT. Being able to display different kinds of data in the same three dimensional scene provides a great deal of information about the relative size, location and orientation of the various items. For example, even those who are familiar with the data are startled when first examining this scene by how small the region of DGV data is compared to the others.</p><p>The system is capable of displaying computational data in the same scene as well. Initial feedback is very positive for viewing multiple data sets in proper 3D relationship and the ability to control the view. The control and behavior of the slice tool also receives strong approval. Getting the tool to this stage makes it possible to begin addressing the issues raised by using the current version. Current issues include better coordinating the display of diverse data and a better user interface for selecting data to be shown. The image to model matching and mapping process is also being examined both for more automated support in the process and to broaden the applicability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">STATUS &amp; PLANS</head><p>The initial release of VISOR is in August 1998 to a small group of scientists collaborating on a project involving the use of supercomputers and a wind tunnel at NASA Ames for roughly three months. Feedback from this group will help prioritize the list of features, modifications and developments. As additional horizontal products become available, VISOR will integrate appropriate portions, resulting in additional visualization techniques and an improved user interface, among other things. Some multi-source data is of the same or similar kinds, for example pressure computed by a CFD simulation and Cp measured via PSP system. Data of similar kinds from different sources provide an ideal opportunity to explore comparative visualization ideas. The VISOR team is involved in the work of Shen, Pang and Uselton <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and will be more active in this area in the future.     Views of multi-source visualization showing PSP, DGV, and PMAT data texture mapped onto models.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>VISOR is still under development, and being used as an exploration vehicle finding new requirements both for users and for reusable software development. The figures give an idea of the current capabilities. Numerical values, legends and color bars are missing to protect the proprietary nature of our users' data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2a Figure 2b PSP</head><label>2b</label><figDesc>images from 4 cameras. Single images mapped onto aircraft model. Blue dots indicate control points.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 3a Figure 3b Figure 4</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 3a Figure 3b Figure 4</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5a Figure 5b</head><label>5b</label><figDesc>Top and bottom views of fully composited model with PlaneTool.Graph of Cp values along intersection of plane.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>Glenn Deardorff, Ravi Samtaney, Ling-Jen Chiang, Yinsyi Hung, Arsi Vaziri, Sandy Johan, David Kao and Dan Machak have contributed substantially to the VISOR development effort, and most of the NAS Data Analysis Group has commented or contributed at some point. The people outside our group who were most crucial to the collaboration were James Bell, David Korsmeyer, and Joan Walton, although there were several times that many who have given feedback or wind tunnel experiment orientations when needed. This work was supported under NASA contract NAS2-14303.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FEL: The Field Encapsulation Library</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stephen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Kenwright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Gerald-Yamasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization `96. IEEE</title>
		<editor>Roni Yagel and Gregory M. Nielson</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="247" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">exVis:A Visual Analysis Tool for Wind Tunnel Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Glenn</forename><surname>Deardorff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Leslie</forename><surname>Keely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sam</forename><surname>Uselton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visual Data Exploration and Analysis</title>
		<editor>Robert F. Erbacher and Alex Pang</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-01" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3298</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>SPIE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DARWIN -Remote Access and Data Visualization Elements</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Korsmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Walton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gilbaugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AIAA 19th Advanced Measurement and Ground Testing Technology Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New Orleans, LA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>AIAA Paper No. 96-2250</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement Capabilities of Planar Doppler Velocimetry Using Pulsed Lasers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mckenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Optics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-02-20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pressure-Sensitive Paint in Aerodynamic Testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mclachlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Experimental Thermal and Fluid Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="470" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Data Level Comparison of Wind Tunnel and Computational Fluid Dynamics Data. to appear IEEE Visualization `98</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Qin</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alex</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sam</forename><surname>Uselton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-10" />
			<pubPlace>Chapel Hill, NC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">exVis: Developing A Wind Tunnel Data Visualization Tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Samuel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Uselton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization `97. IEEE</title>
		<editor>Roni Yagel and Hans Hagen</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Phoenix, AZ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microphone Array Phased Processing System (MAPPS)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Watts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mosher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2nd AIAA/CAES Aeroacoustic Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>AIAA Paper No. 96-1714</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
