<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">TOPIC ISLANDS TM -A Wavelet-Based Text Visualization System</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nancy</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
							<email>nancy.miller@pnl.gov</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>Pak</roleName><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mary</forename><surname>Brewster</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Harlan</forename><surname>Foote</surname></persName>
							<email>harlan.foote@pnl.gov</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 999</postBox>
									<postCode>99352</postCode>
									<settlement>Richland</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">The Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">TOPIC ISLANDS TM -A Wavelet-Based Text Visualization System</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>text visualization</term>
					<term>information visualization</term>
					<term>wavelet transform</term>
					<term>and information retrieval</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present a novel approach to visualize and explore unstructured text. The underlying technology, called TOPIC-O-GRAPHY TM , applies wavelet transforms to a custom digital signal constructed from words within a document. The resultant multiresolution wavelet energy is used to analyze the characteristics of the narrative flow in the frequency domain, such as theme changes, which is then related to the overall thematic content of the text document using statistical methods. The thematic characteristics of a document can be analyzed at varying degrees of detail, ranging from section-sized text partitions to partitions consisting of a few words. Using this technology, we are developing a visualization system prototype known as TOPIC ISLANDS TM to browse a document, generate fuzzy document outlines, summarize text by levels of detail and according to user interests, define meaningful subdocuments, query text content, and provide summaries of topic evolution.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Consider the large and ever growing number of electronic documents we have to read everyday. We often judge the importance of a document simply by looking at its title and then decide whether to proceed. As we go further into the information age, we are simultaneously tantalized and overwhelmed by the glut of textual information that requires our attention. Several visualization systems, such as DEPICT <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and SPIRE <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> have attempted to help information consumers sift though massive quantities of text. Such technologies are primarily concerned with the general characterization of a corpus, enabling the user to rapidly focus on a subset of potentially interesting documents. Ultimately, however, the user must endure the often tedious effort of reading the identified documents. This can be especially cumbersome for lengthy documents. Quick ways that adapt to the amount of detail the user is willing to accept are needed.</p><p>We are creating an interactive software prototype, TOPIC ISLANDS TM , to characterize the content and flow of a text document using only the words within the document and to do so at varying levels of detail. The varying levels of detail are directly available from the multiresolution levels (MRLs) that result from the application of wavelet transforms to a mathematical signal built from the text narrative.</p><p>Our primary goal is to enable the user to rapidly assess the relevance of documents to his specific interests by providing a tool that connects the text narrative to embedded themes. These methods may also provide multiple ways for the user to interact with the documents at the corpus level.</p><p>TOPIC-O-GRAPHY may improve the efficiency of our natural text-scanning practices. For documents written in English or other Latin-based languages, we tend to read only a portion of a word (e.g., "real" instead of "really") before jumping irregularly to the next position, and repeating the process <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. We tend to move our eyes from the upper left to the lower right corners of each text column. TOPIC-O-GRAPHY is designed to enhance this natural reading behavior by providing the rich thematic information of a document in such a way that the scanning has already been done. The reader thus has a more balanced viewing window (i.e., without stretching to the right or the bottom of the page) and spends more time in the important parts of the text.</p><p>Our initial results using TOPIC ISLANDS appear promising. Additional work is in progress. Usability studies are required to quantify the true impact of our technology on reading practices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">PREVIOUS WORK</head><p>Although we believe our approach is novel, much inspiration for our approach is found in the work of others. Here we discuss important prior work on text visualization, text theme characterization, and wavelet processing in visualization in general.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Text Visualization</head><p>Text visualization is challenging! It is much more difficult to apply scale measures to textual documents than it is to quantitative data sets. Recently, many visualization scientists have developed techniques to browse different kinds of textual data.</p><p>Eick and Steffen <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> visualize the execution status of a large software program in SeeSoft. In this system, program modules are shown as blocks, and color is used to indicate the frequency count of a line of code being called. SPIRE graphically displays the similarities among documents of a corpus based on word similarities and automatically discovers key topics in the text. The Galaxies view is based on a dimensionality reduction technique called multidimensional scaling (MDS) with closely related documents clustering together in a 2D projection. The Themescape view produces a terrain map of themes found in the corpus. DEPICT uses Kohonen's <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> Self-Organizing Map (SOM) to visualize the information content of document corpora. The neural-network-based design reduces the highdimensional context vectors of a corpus into a low-dimensional data space for visualization.</p><p>Card, et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> have developed WebBook to browse and organize Internet web pages. Users can riffle through pages, rip pages from a book, and tack a page to a desk or wall in the 3D room in which the book is located. WebBook is among the latest additions of the Xsoft project, which includes text visualization techniques such as Perspective Wall <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and Document Lens <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Cat-a-Cone <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> integrates the designs of Cone Tree <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and WebBook into a powerful visualization tool to search and browse very large category hierarchies with their associated text documents.</p><p>Closest in intent to our work is Hearst's TileBars <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, which allows the user to define specific topics of interest and then produces a linear color block map to show where chunks of the documents are likely to contain these topics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Thematic Partitioning</head><p>Several methods have been used to locate and visualize theme breaks found in electronically formatted text. Salton's tour <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> is a graph with links and nodes. His "tour" or summary of a docu-ment is produced by ordering merged paragraphs in chronological (or narrative) order and producing a summary for each of the merged sets.</p><p>Hearst <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> describes an algorithm for finding subtopic structure in expository text that uses a moving window approach. Adjacent blocks are compared using cosine similarity measured on the full set of words within each block. Boundaries for topic changes are found by identifying the points of greatest change in the smoothed cosine-gap sequence from the moving windows after applying a set of rules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Wavelets in Visualization</head><p>Wavelet transforms are based on translation (W(t) → W(t-1)) and dilation (W(t) → W(2t)). Without loss of generality, wavelets can be considered as signal filters that accept data streams of n items and generate (n/2) items of approximations and (n/2) items of details. The approximation is a coarse summary of the original data, and the details contain the data lost during the decomposition. A hierarchy of coarse approximations is generated when this process is applied iteratively to the approximations to obtain increasingly coarse data.</p><p>The fact that wavelet signals are highly localized in both space and frequency domains makes them a better and more reliable choice over the prevailing signal analysis tools, such as the discrete cosine transform (DCT) and even the fast Fourier transform (FFT). Ever since Mallat <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> presented the groundbreaking fast multiresolution implementation of wavelet transforms in 1989, scientists and engineers have found new opportunities in many disciplines and applications. In the last few years, we have successfully used wavelets to visualize the authenticity of multiresolution scientific data sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, multidimensional volume data sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, and multivariate relational data sets <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>. In the same community, wavelets have also been used to visualize and analyze a variety of structured <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> and unstructured <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref> data sets. What differentiates this work from our previous work and all other uses of wavelet analysis is the application to seemingly nonrefinable free text and the new, innovative wavelet implementation, which achieves the highest possible grains of wavelet details. This is the first attempt to analyze the context of a document or corpus in wavelet space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DESCRIPTION OF WAVELET ENERGY</head><p>A custom digital signal of a document is constructed from the words, the word associations, and the chronological or narrative order of the words within the document. In this process, several of Bookstein's <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> ideas regarding identification of content-bearing words, which we refer to as topics or channels in our analysis, are used to extract information from a document. Wavelet transforms are then applied to this custom signal to calculate three types of wavelet energy: channel, composite, and query. The strength of wavelets is that the output signal, which is a function of narrative index (word order), is defined for a suite of MRLs. In this section, we describe the types of wavelet energy used in our visualizations and their interpretation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Channel Energy</head><p>The most basic wavelet calculation is the channel energy. Each channel or topic signal is processed and stored independently. Mathematically, our implementation of the piecewise constant Haar wavelets is defined as <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> where y is a vector of associations, m is the channel or topic, k is the MRL, and j corresponds approximately to the narrative index at which the filter is centered. The numbers of resolution k in our analysis are a function of the length of the document. The output signal for each channel at each MRL has the same length as the text narrative.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Composite Energy</head><p>The composite wavelet energy is calculated by generalizing the calculation of the channel energy to include all information across all channels (index m) for a fixed location (index j) and fixed MRL (index k). The multiresolution composite energy is used to identify breaks of the narrative flow in frequency domain, in which the information is related to the overall thematic content of the document using statistical methods. The conceptual flow can be analyzed at varying degrees of detail, ranging from sectionsized text partitions down to partitions consisting of a few words.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Query Energy</head><p>For a more flexible and broad-spectrum query procedure, the composite energy calculation is modified to include information from a specified usage pattern that has been determined to be relevant to the query. The result is the query energy that shows the local relevance between the narrative and the query. A base resolution level, which is determined by the length of the query, is selected. The second summation in Equation <ref type="formula">1</ref>is then replaced by a static representation derived from the query. The results shown in this paper use this approach, which generates a singleresolution output signal <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p><p>It is in the implementation of queries that the importance of the word associations becomes clear. If the zero-order statistics such as word frequency are used, as in many other prevailing systems, there will be no recognition of the synonymous use of different words. Note that in either approach described below, the query words may or may not actually appear in the article; however, similarity in usage pattern may still be noticeable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Wavelet Energy Interpretation</head><p>The edge-detecting property defined by the wavelet calculation is useful for a variety of analyses. The composite energy is used to detect the point where the narrative topic changes. When the energy is high, we have strong evidence of a change in topical flow in the text. In our visualization, we typically show the upside-down view of the normalized energy for each MRL whereby dips or valleys in the curve correspond to evidence of theme changes. Because we have a suite of MRLs and can examine the evidence from consecutive MRLs simultaneously, we do not need to worry about the optimal size of pseudo-sentences as do many other techniques.</p><p>The query energy reaches the lowest when a good match to the query is found. We have done a small amount of work to date with the channel energy. The channel energy is most useful for automatic assignment of keywords to text partitions that have been found using the composite energy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">TOPIC ISLANDS VISUALIZATIONS</head><p>In this section, we present a set of interrelated visualizations, collectively referred to as TOPIC ISLANDS, based on the wavelet energies of two lengthy documents. The composite energy calculations are first shown for the full suite of MRLs. The user selects a subset of the MRLs for further detailed examination. This detailed subset of energies defines a 3D structure that we visualize as a wave. The MRL subset is also used to partition the text into MRL document subchunks; these subchunks are then used to form volumes whose thematic content is used to create a 3D island visualization. The island visualization has a simple geometrical view. The tree visualization lets the user navigate between the text narrative and the island thematic view. We have created a document viewer in which the wavelet energies have been directly superimposed upon the text to render a color-annotated document view that draws the eye to changes in themes and fertile locations to read for text summarization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Our Goals</head><p>The primary goal of TOPIC ISLANDS is to reduce the amount of time the user needs to spend reading long articles to understand the various topics discussed and thus to assess whether this is a document to which he should devote in-depth attention. TOPIC ISLANDS is not an automatic text summarizer per se, but it does draw the attention of the user quickly to the thematic structure of the document and the parts to read for a quick summary. A strong emphasis is placed on interactions, such as brushing and linking, among various visualizations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Analysis Data Set</head><p>The documents analyzed in this section and Section 5 are part of a collection of Time magazine articles published in 1963. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> This corpus is attractive because it contains some very long articles that are of general interest rather than scientific. (Scientific articles are more thematically cohesive and tend to be easier to analyze.) This data set is somewhat tedious as there are no paragraph breaks in the electronic text, and the character set is all uppercase. A technical editor read each document and identified where paragraph breaks would likely occur and identified theme transitions for our analysis. We make heavy use of the author-inserted subheadings for the articles in the discussion found in Section 5. Within this corpus, there are multiple authors with very different writing styles. The two articles we present here are referred to as the "Buddhist article" and the "Ireland article" in the captions and in the discussions to follow in Section 5. The Buddhist article discusses the violent crackdown of South Vietnam's Diem regime on the Buddhists. The Ireland article discusses Ireland's challenges to modernization under the leadership of Sean Lemass.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">TOPIC ISLANDS™ Visualizations</head><p>We are developing a highly interactive text visualization prototype using C++, Motif, and OpenGL. The design, which contains a variety of user-friendly visualizations and navigation tools, lets a user to browse and query the content of a single document in a multiresolution fashion. Our definition of multiresolution is somewhat different from the traditional levels-of-detail designation, in the sense that a particular resolution reflects the ranges of the theme breaks being examined instead of the size of the data. In the following discussion, we describe the functionality of individual visualization tools and describe the role of each tool in the overall design. We also show an integrated example and describe how a user can benefit from our approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">Overview MRL Strip Chart</head><p>Our discussion starts with a set of MRL strip charts showing various degrees of thematic changes in the narrative flow for a document. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>  tion of the line plots to designate this portion of the text for further analysis (see section 4.3.2). All other visualizations are keyed from this selected subset of multiresolution energies and the corresponding text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Detail MRL Strip Chart</head><p>A detail MRL strip chart is the zoomed view of the highlighted portion of the overall MRL strip chart. In the detail MRL strip chart, a user selects a narrative-based section from the multiresolution plots and then accesses the corresponding portion of the text through a pop-up browsing window. The MRL-specific theme breaks, which can be automatically generated, are presented to the user in the detail MRL strip chart.</p><p>The detail strip chart and the pop-up text browsing window together allow a user to inspect the system-suggested theme breaks visually and to possibly override the system-generated break points with precision up to the individual word. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>, five break points are tagged from MRL 8, ten are tagged in MRL 7, and nineteen are tagged from MRL 6. The user selects or deletes break points with mouse clicks. MRL 5 is viewed as evidence but is not used to generate any breaks. The breaks determine a subdividing strategy for the documents using three consecutive MRLs. Once the subdividing is accepted, the result is available for creation of the island view.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.3">Island View</head><p>From the detail MRL view, a collection of break points have been selected based on energy changes within the narrative flow, and these break points, in turn, define document subchunks for each   MRL. In the island view, the subchunks are displayed in a 3D visualization where the x-y location is determined from an MDS projection of the document vectors created from the subdividing process. The z-axis represents the MRL in descending order.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>, each document subchunk is depicted as a geometric object whose centroid coordinates are provided by the MDS calculation and whose base radius is determined by a measure of variability across the cylinders. One variability candidate could be the length of each document subchunk.</p><p>The green cylinders, yellow ellipsoids, and orange cones represent subchunks from MRL 8, 7, and 6 respectively. We plan a terrain version that smoothes the volumes of the previous island view to create a 3D manifold. The island visual depiction quickly builds a non-verbal mental model of the thematic interplay in the Buddhist article using the break points tagged in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.4">Tree Navigation Tool</head><p>The tree tool, shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>, allows the user to navigate between the theme-based island visualization and the text narrative. The crosshairs in the tree correspond to the theme breaks (tick marks from the detail strip chart), which are used to create the island visualization. The tree canopy color indicates the MRL.</p><p>With this tool, the user can interrogate the visualizations either at the narrative or the theme level. There are two modes of operation: global or local. In the global mode, the position of the slider widget causes all subchunks corresponding to this part of the narrative to light up. In the local mode, only a single MRL is active at a time. In the latter case, the user also has the option of picking islands and observing the part of the narrative to which the slider moves. As in the detail MRL view, a text browser window follows the action of the tree tool so that the user can relate actual text to narrative index or island location.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.5">Wave</head><p>The set of MRL energies presented in the detail overview is also used to create a wave, a 3D-colored surface plot, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>. This image is formed by taking the x-axis as the narrative order of terms, taking the y-axis as the discrete MRLs, and using color shade (or gray-scale) along the z-axis to indicate energy level. Also, we smooth the surface. Of critical importance for visualization is to animate by rotating the viewing angle. This dynamic surface shows at a glance the entire thematic complexity of the article at the MRLs, including major sections of topics and subsections.</p><p>We call this surface a wave both because as we animate it through various orientation angles, it really looks like waves and because of the connection to wavelets. A wave is the visual equivalent of an outline. Further, the surface representation is more flexible than a standard hierarchical outline such as a tree because instead of requiring each subsection to be strictly contained in one and only one higher-level section, subsections may be fuzzily contained in a section or more than one section. This flexibility is very useful in extending other hierarchical structures such as categorization of subjects for encyclopedias or libraries to more accurately represent interdisciplinary topics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.6">Color and Stereo Fly-in Document Viewers</head><p>In addition to the text browser window previously described, we have created another type of document viewer that directly superimposes the wavelet composite energies onto the text itself. In <ref type="figure">Figure 6a</ref>, the highest energies that correspond to theme changes are shown in pinkish purple; the lowest energies are shown in red.</p><p>Through comparison of the color patterns, strong evidence for thematic transitions at various levels emerges. In 6b, the energy calculations from MRL 8 shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref> have been normalized to a common break-point value to emphasize the user's breakpoint perspective and smoothed across all words. In this view, the user can quickly see all theme transitions that he has elected to emphasize. We have elected the rainbow color map in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>, as opposed to the heat temperature color map used in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>, to visualize a broader distribution of energy values.  In our design, the user "flies in" to read a color-coded section; he can switch to stereo, where the degree to which words stand out from the page, using anaglyph glasses, is determined by the original energy levels within the given MRL. This is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 7</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION</head><p>So how well does this technology work? To fully address this question, formal usability studies must be conducted. To investigate performance, we must understand the Buddhist and Ireland articles in some detail. In this section, we describe the two articles. We also compare the theme transition points indicated by our wavelet analysis to paragraph and theme breaks, and interpret the island visualizations. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 8</ref> shows the wavelet energy of the Buddhist article in MRLs 6, 7, and 8 with vertical dashed lines drawn and numbered at each location where the editor-imputed paragraph breaks occur. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 9</ref> contains the same information for the Ireland article. In addition to the numbered paragraphs, capital letters are inserted at the top to indicate the locations of the articles' subheadings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Description of the Articles</head><p>Tables 1 and 2 make the correspondence among the paragraph numbering scheme, letter abbreviations, and the full title of the subheadings.      As shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, the Ireland article contains three photo captions or sidebar stories inserted toward the beginning of the article, interrupting the narrative flow and introducing unrelated topics to the current discourse. The writing styles for the two articles are very different. In the Buddhist article, the author uses transition paragraphs and takes the reader on an orderly transit across the topics. In the Ireland article, the author jumps from topic to topic, challenging the reader to keep the numerous topics straight through the tangled narrative.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Comparison of Break Points</head><p>The MRL wavelet composite energy for the Ireland article, shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 10</ref>, does a very good job of tracking the paragraph breaks with spikes downward in the signal for at least one MRL -6, 7, or 8. These three signals collectively catch at least twothirds of the editor-imputed paragraph break points and all but one author subheading (the "All the Details" subheading at paragraph 24). Amazingly tiny dips in energy occur even at the mention of a name, such as John Kennedy, with no other supporting discussion. The paragraph breaks in the Buddhist article are not so easily identified. However, six out of the seven subheadings are identified with dips in the MRL signals shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 9</ref>. The different writing styles of the two authors are evident here.</p><p>In both the Ireland and the Buddhist articles, the wavelet decomposition identifies additional dips within paragraphs that catch fine theme shifts. A good example is the dip in paragraph 2 for the Buddhist article at MRL 6. The paragraph begins by talking about specific acts of violence directed against the Buddhists, and then switches to a discussion of acts of bravery by the Buddhists as they tried to save ashes of a famous martyr housed in the pagoda where the attack occurred. The wave visualization is a useful device for visual integration of themes captured when using higher frequency filters but missed with lower frequency filters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Comparison of Theme Maps</head><p>The MDS-based island visualization that results from a specific subchunking strategy presents a useful thematic organization of the text. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures 11 and 12</ref>, a top view of the islands is augmented with manually generated theme labels and divisions. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 12</ref> results from the subchunking shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>. An MDS projection using the author's subheadings as theme breaks produces theme maps very similar to ours. The narrative order is indicated on the top view island maps using solid black arrows in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures 13 and 14</ref> for the Ireland and Buddhist articles, respectively. Several author subheadings are also indicated for MRL 8 (in green) using white arrows. Again, the very different writing styles of the authors are obvious as the Buddhist narrative flows easily across the theme map, while the Ireland article's narrative flow is scattered.   We investigate the strengths and weaknesses of TOPIC ISLANDS TM and compare them to other prevailing text browsing systems including TileBar and Xsoft. The discussion is based on the example presented in Section 5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Innovative Design</head><p>In many ways we believe that TOPIC ISLANDS TM is a successful attempt to visualize textual data. Its innovative design represents many revolutionary breakthroughs in visualization and analysis of text documents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.1">Multiresolution Analysis</head><p>Our wavelet-based topic-discrimination engine is capable of analyzing textual data with varying degrees of context locally, in the highest possible grains of detail. Different wavelets can be used to analyze different writing styles or to bring out various characteristics of a single article. The fact that our algorithm successfully identifies nearly all the story inserts as well as the major theme changes in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures 12 and 13</ref> reflects the strength of our design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Stereoscopic Text Visualization</head><p>We share a fundamental design concept with Xsoft that a document browser should always include the "text" during data navigation and exploration. A real challenge for us is to present the discrete multiresolution wavelet energy effectively alongside the text. Our novel stereoscopic image solution in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 8</ref> represents a one-of-a-kind text visualization technique to display text attributes (e.g., energy wave) without expensive contouring, textual mapping, and data occlusion of a 3D rendering manifold. Our solution has fewer side effects than mapping the energy to color or font size, which are the obvious choices for many visualization systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.3">High-Dimensional Display</head><p>The visualization in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> shows the multiresolution clustering of related topics of a document using a multidimensional scaling (MDS) based display. The scatterplot technique, using the similarities among topics, is a more robust context-sensitive option (over the color-coding scheme in TileBar) as the overall topic distribution of a document is portrayed. Highlighting the islands that contain user queries further strengthens the performance of the system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Shortcomings</head><p>Our preliminary results also expose the shortcomings of some of our current approaches. The syntactically complex writing styles of many articles can create unpredictable and noisy input signals to the wavelet analysis. The crude nature of the piecewise constant Haar wavelets may not be the optimal basis function for the decomposition. Additionally, our prototype so far has not been able to predict the optimal MRLs from a wavelet hierarchy without human intervention.</p><p>Many other processes, such as creating the digital signal for the wavelet engine, may require a particular set of run-time parameters to achieve optimal results. We have not yet performed an exhaustive sensitivity analysis to fully automate the selection of these parameters. By far the most important discovery of our initial investigation is that the global extremum (maximum or minimum point) of the wavelet signal is not nearly as important as the local extremum (the highest or lowest in the finite neighborhood). Visualization is the most successful part of our project; we are using TOPIC ISLANDS TM to visualize the performance of our wavelet engine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">FUTURE WORK</head><p>New and improved features are in the pipeline for our prototype and include</p><p>• an extension of this work to cross-document analysis • an extension of text query analysis to channel energy data • a rule-based wavelet engine to handle a variety of documents • a statistic-based power words and power sentences generator for individual island characterization at each MRL • a query energy visualization using topological morphing.</p><p>Some of these enhancements extend the theoretical foundations of our wavelet engine, while the others improve the exploration power of the visualization front-end. In the long run, we wish to include ontological extensions to strengthen the query capability, a database management system to handle the corpus metadata, a smart wavelet engine to incorporate the latest digital library technology, and a client-server model to support network environment operations.    </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>depicts a set of nine strip charts, each showing a different multiresolution wavelet energy plotted against the narrative of the same document. The window serves as both a visualization and a navigation tool. A user can highlight any por-1 These articles may be viewed at http://multimedia.pnl.gov:2080/topicography .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Overview MRL strip chart for 9 MRLs for Buddhist article. MRLs 5-8 have been selected for detailed probing.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Detail strip chart for Buddhist article. Final break points are shown as white ticks.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The tree tool facilitates navigation between text narrative and the thematic island view.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Island view for Buddhist article created from docu-ment sub-chunking shown inFigure 2. See also Color Plate 1 (CP1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>"Wave" for Buddhist article using MRLs 6 -8. See also CP2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>10 A</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Composite energy from Buddhist article with dotted lines at editor-imputed paragraph breaks.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Composite energy from Ireland article with dotted lines at editor-imputed paragraph breaks. 6a 6b Figure 6a &amp; 6b: The text of the Buddhist article with wavelet energies superimposed using two strategies. See also CP3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Stereoscopic view of part of the Buddhist article. See also CP4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 10 :Figure 11 :</head><label>1011</label><figDesc>Composite energy from Ireland article with dotted lines at editor-imputed paragraph breaks. The top island view for the Ireland article showing major themes. See also CP5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>The top island view for the Buddhist article showing major themes. See also CP6.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc>The top view of the islands for the Ireland article show the interplay of theme map and the narrative. See CP7.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 14 :</head><label>14</label><figDesc>The top view of the islands for the Buddhist Article shows the interplay of theme map. See also CP 8.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Buddhist Article -2,673 words &amp; 17 paragraphs</figDesc><table><row><cell>Paragraph</cell><cell>Subheading</cell></row><row><cell>Number</cell><cell>Phrase</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>B -Boola, Boola</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>R -Rope Trick</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Ireland Article -4,859 words, 31 paragraphs</figDesc><table><row><cell>Paragraph</cell><cell>Subheading</cell></row><row><cell>Number</cell><cell>Phrase</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>H -Holy Ireland</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>P -Porther and Shamrock</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>S1 -Sidebar -Industrial Boom</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>S2 -Sidebar -Sporting Events</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>B -Bloody Baluba</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>T -Two-Way Bridge</cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell>F -Four R's</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>P -Poor Risk</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>S -Spanglish &amp; Spells</cell></row><row><cell>18</cell><cell>H -Heat with Peat</cell></row><row><cell>21</cell><cell>T -Trim Sails</cell></row><row><cell>23</cell><cell>TE -Total Effort</cell></row><row><cell>24</cell><cell>A -All the Details</cell></row><row><cell>27</cell><cell>R -Rebels &amp; Monarchs</cell></row><row><cell>30</cell><cell>RG -Radiant Goals</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>Research in the TOPIC-O-GRAPHY TM technology and development of the TOPIC ISLANDS TM prototype is sponsored by the P1000 Project of the Office of Research and Development. Enhancements to this technology are also being funded by the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA). We also wish to thank Scott Decker, Vern Crow, Grant Nakamura, David McKinnon, Frank Ryan, Sharon Eaton, Irene Schwarting, Jim Thomas, and Renie McVeety who provided assistance of many forms throughout this research. In 1997, we applied for a U.S. patent for the TOPIC-O-GRAPHY technology.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clumping Properties or Content-Bearing Words</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bookstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Raita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The WebBook and the WebForager: An Information Workspace for the World Wide Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stuart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>York</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of CHI 96, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Software</title>
		<meeting>CHI 96, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Software</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="117" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Code Profiling Line Oriented Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Stephen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Eick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;92<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="217" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cognitive Psychology: A Student&apos;s Handbook</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eyesenck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Keane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<publisher>Hillside</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New Jersey</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet-Based Volume Morphing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Taosong</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sidney</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arie</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;94<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="92" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-Paragraph Segmentation of Expository Text</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marti</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hearst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 32 nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<meeting>32 nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics<address><addrLine>Las Cruces, NM</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TileBars: Visualization of Term Distribution Information in Full Text Information Access</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marti</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hearst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)<address><addrLine>Denver, CO</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cat-a-Cone: An Interactive Interface or Specifying Searches and Viewing Retrieval Results Using a Large Category Hierarchy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chandu</forename><surname>Hearst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Karadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 20th Annual International ACM SIGIR Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 20th Annual International ACM SIGIR Conference<address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Self-Organizing Maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Teuvo</forename><surname>Kohonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlay</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perspective Wall: Detail and Context Smoothly Integrated</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jock</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Roberston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stuart</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of CHI 91</title>
		<meeting>CHI 91</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="179" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Theory for Multiresolution Signal Decomposition: The Wavelet Representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephane</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mallat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="674" to="693" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A New Paradigm of Wavelet-Based Text Data Retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nancy</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>PNNL-SA-29980</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haar Wavelets Over Triangular Domains with Applications to Multiresolution Models for Flow Over a Sphere</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;97</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cone Trees: Animated 3D Visualizations of Hierarchical Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">George</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Roberston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stuart</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jock</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of CHI 91</title>
		<meeting>CHI 91</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="188" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Document Lens</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jock</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Roberston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of UIST &apos;93</title>
		<meeting>UIST &apos;93</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="107" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DEPICT: Documents Evaluated as Pictures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marc</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rushall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ilgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Information Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Information Visualization &apos;96<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="107" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Automatic Text Theme Generation and the Analysis of Text Structure</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Salton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Amit</forename><surname>Singhal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>TR 94-1438</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-07" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer Science, Cornell University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progressive Transmission of Scientific Data Using Bi-orthogonal Wavelet Transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hai</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;94<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="99" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing the Non-visual: Spatial Analysis and Interaction with Information from Text Documents</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kelly</forename><surname>Pennock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Lantrip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Marc</forename><surname>Pottier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anne</forename><surname>Schur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Vern</forename><surname>Crow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Information Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Information Visualization &apos;95<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authenticity Analysis of Wavelet Approximations in Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R. Daniel</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bergeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;95<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="191" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brushing Techniques for Exploring Scientific Volume Datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R. Daniel</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bergeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;97</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dual Multiresolution HyperSlice for Multivariate Data Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R. Daniel</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bergeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Information Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Information Visualization &apos;96<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiresolution Multidimensional Wavelet Brushing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R. Daniel</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bergeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;96<address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="148" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Waveletbased Multiresolutional Representation of Computational Field Simulation Datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Machiraju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;97</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
