<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Feature Comparisons Of Vector Fields Using Earth Mover&apos;s Distance</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yingmei</forename><surname>Lavin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Stanford University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Stanford University Stanford</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305, 94305-4035</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA, CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rajesh</forename><surname>Batra</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics Department of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Stanford University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Stanford University Stanford</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305, 94305-4035</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA, CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lambertus</forename><surname>Hesselink</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Electrical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University Stanford</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94305-4035</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Feature Comparisons Of Vector Fields Using Earth Mover&apos;s Distance</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>In this paper, a novel approach is introduced to define a quantitative measure of closeness between vector fields. The usefulness of this measurement can be seen when comparing computational and experimental flow fields under the same conditions. Furthermore, its applicability can be extended to more cumbersome tasks such as navigating through a large database searching for similar topology. This new measure relies on the use of critical points, which are a key feature in vector field topology. In order to characterize critical points, and parameters are introduced. They are used to form a closed set of eight unique patterns for simple critical points. These patterns are also basic building blocks for higher order nonlinear vector fields. In order to study and compare a given set of vector fields, a measure of distance between different patterns of critical points is introduced. The basic patterns of critical points are mapped onto a unit circle in-space. The concept of Earth Mover&apos;s Distance [1] [2] is used to compute the closeness between various pairs of vector fields, and a nearest-neighbor query is thus produced to illustrate the relationship between the given set of vector fields. This approach quantitatively measures the similarity and dissimilarity between vector fields. It is ideal for data compression of a large flow field, since only the number and types of critical points along with their corresponding and parameters are necessary to reconstruct the whole field. It can also be used to better quantify the changes in time varying data sets.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Introduction</head><p>Vector fields have numerous applications in physical science. The force fields arising from gravitation and electromagnetism; the velocity vectors of a fluid motion, found for example over an airfoil; and gradients, such as the pressure gradient appearing on a weather map are all elements of vector fields. The concept of critical points in vector fields has been well studied and has proven to play a key role in vector field topology. However, there hasn't been any study on quantitative measurement of similarities and differences between vector fields using topology. In fluid dynamics, simplifications are a necessary evil in the numerical simulation process in order to compute analytical solutions of flows over complex bodies in a reasonable amount of time. Researchers formulate various models with the hope of capturing the essential features of real flows. For example, Reynolds stress and velocity fields in turbulent flows are almost impossible to solve analytically. Many turbulence models, both linear and nonlinear, have been suggested to better capture real flows. However, the models for a large part have been quite arbitrary. In order to test the validity of a certain model, a comparison between the computational and experimental results are necessary. However, a metric for the closeness between the computational and experimental results remains unsolved. Traditionally, a series of charts for each component of Reynolds stress and velocity vector has been drawn. It is perceptually not intuitive as well as difficult to show the intrinsic structural differences between the two fields. Past study in our group has focused on the geometric structure of vector and tensor fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> [4] <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. However, a topological property of a vector field is a property possessed by this vector field and all its topological equivalents. The dissimilarity of their appearances sometimes can fool human eyes. For example, vector fields 15 and 16 in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>, are two swirling flows that have the same topological structure yet appear quite different to a human observer. Therefore, a quantitative measurement for comparison of vector fields is essential.</p><p>Earth Mover's Distance(EMD), first introduced by Yossi Rubner et al. for fast retrieval of similar images in a large data base <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, computes the minimal amount of work that must be performed to transform one distribution into the other by moving "distribution mass" around. In our vector fields analysis, the feature distribution is defined as the set of critical points and their corresponding , parameters of a vector field. After extracting the feature distribution, a set of EMDs are computed. Multidimensional Scaling (MDS) was originally used for seeking the configuration of points given the Euclidean distances between them <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. Here, with the help MDS, we can display the similarities and differences between selected vector fields.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Critical point theory 3.1 Critical points Definition 1 (Critical Points) A critical point is a point in a vector field where all three vector components are zero and the streamline slope is indeterminate.</head><p>Critical points are the only points in a vector field where tangent curves may cross each other. In the case of a steady state velocity field, tangent curves represent streamlines. Critical points are characterized according to the behavior of nearby tangent curves. A particular set of tangent curves which end on critical points are of special interest because they define the skeleton which characterizes the global behavior of all other tangent curves in the vector field. The number and nature of critical points in a vector field remain unchanged under a continuous transformation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Classification of critical points</head><p>A first order critical point can be classified according to the eigenvalues of its Jacobian matrix. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> A positive or negative real part of an eigenvalue indicates a repelling or attracting nature, respectively . The imaginary part denotes circulation about the point. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, Helman has listed 6 different patterns for simple critical points. After careful study, we added two more types which are attracting and repelling stars corresponding to points with zero imaginary parts and equal real parts. The complete list of the first order critical points are listed above in figure 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Vector field representation in Clifford space 4.1 Clifford algebra</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> [9], Sheuermann et al. introduced Clifford algebra for vector field visualization. Clifford algebra provides a nice way to describe the relation between real and complex numbers in 2D space. The vector fields are defined over a The usual vectors x; y 2 R 2 are identified with</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Center α = 0 β &lt; 0 Saddle Point α = 0 β &gt; 0 Repelling Star α &gt; 0 β = 0 Attracting Star α &lt;0 β = 0 Attracting Focus α &lt; 0 β &lt; 0 Repelling Focus α &gt; 0 β &lt; 0 Repelling Node α &gt; 0 β &gt; 0 Attracting Node α &lt; 0 β &gt; 0</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">xe 1 + ye 2 2 E 2 G 2<label>(7)</label></formula><p>and the complex numbers</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">a + bi 2 C with a1 + bi 2 G 2 (8)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Vector fields in Clifford space</head><p>A Clifford vector field is just a multivector field with val-</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">ues in R 2 G 2 v : R 2 ! R 2 G 2<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Let z = x + iy, z = x , iy be complex numbers in the Clifford algebra. This means</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">x = 1 2 z + z (10) y = 1 2i z , z<label>(11)</label></formula><p>We get</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">v r = v 1 x; ye 1 + v 2 x; ye 2 = v 1 1 2 z + z ; 1 2i z , z e 1 ,iv 2 1 2 z + z ; 1 2i z , z e 1 = E z ; z e 1<label>(12)</label></formula><p>Generally, a linear vector field can easily be shown as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">vr = Ez; ze 1 = az + b z + ce 1 (13)</formula><p>where a; b; c C.</p><p>Let E : C 2 ! C be the polynomial so thatṽ = Ez; ze 1 . Let F k : C 2 ! C;k = 1; : : : ; n be the ir-</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">reducible components of E, so that Ez; z = Q n k=1 F k ,</formula><p>then an arbitrary polynomial vector field with isolated critical points can be expressed as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">vr = Ez; ze 1 = n Y k=1 a k z + b k z + c k e 1<label>(14)</label></formula><p>where z k is the unique zero of a k z + b k z + c k . where C stands for center, RN for node, AN for attracting node, RF for repelling focus, AF for attracting focus, AS for attracting star, RS for repelling star and Sa for Saddle, see <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">-space analysis</head><p>A new space , is introduced where these basic patterns are points located at ; . Vectors in this space obey all the rules defined for a regular 2D Euclidean space.</p><p>We normalize the points in this , space, namely,</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">0 = p 2 + 2 (15) 0 = p 2 + 2<label>(16)</label></formula><p>The values of and themselves do not determine a certain pattern of a critical point, the only thing that matters is the ratio . Therefore a normalization procedure for and doesn't change the pattern of a vector field and all the points in -space can be mapped onto a unit circle <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref>  After careful study, we found that the EMD concept can be used to compute the differences between vector fields. Here, the feature distribution is redefined as the characteristics of a vector field. </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">Energy = v u u t n X i=1 2 i + 2 i ;</formula><p>where n is the total number of critical points in this field.</p><p>This energy here is a quantity that characterizes the critical points of a vector field. It is different from the physical energy. The concept "work" is used to measure the energy differences between two vector fields or the amount of energy used to transform one vector field into the other. </p><formula xml:id="formula_11">i=1 i , 0 i 2 + i , 0 i 2 .</formula><p>Intuitively, given two feature distributions, one distribution can be seen as a set of discrete point-objects with a certain amount of mass of earth spread in space, the other as a collection of holes in the same space. The work measures the least amount of energy needed to fill the holes with earth and is called the Earth Mover's Distance (EMD).</p><p>Computing the EMD is based on a solution to the old transportation problem from linear optimization <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. This is a bipartite network flow problem which can be formalized as the following linear programming problem: Let I be a set of suppliers, J a set of consumers, c ij the cost to ship a unit of supply from i 2 I to j 2 J c ij = q i , j 2 + i , j <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> and it is the same as the Euclidean distance d ij = kṽ i ,ṽ j k in -space. A critical point either exists as a whole or does not exist, it can not be split. In this case, the transportation problem has the property that the optimal flow f ij can only be 0 or 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. We want to seek a set of f ij that minimizes the overall cost:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">E MD x; y = min X i2I X j2J c ij f ij (17)</formula><p>subject to the following constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">f ij 0 i 2 I, j 2 J (18) X i2I f ij = y i ; j 2 J (19) X j2J f ij = x i ; i 2 I (20) X j2J y j = X i2I x i (21)</formula><p>Where x i is the total supply of supplier i and y j is the total capacity of consumer j. Constraint (18) allows shipping of supplies from a supplier to a consumer and not vice versa. Constraint (19) forces the consumers to fill up all of their capacities and constraint (20) limits the supply that a supplier can send as a total amount. Constraint ( 21) is a feasibility condition that ensures that the total demand equals the total supply, in other words, the distributions have the same overall mass and the EMD is a true metric <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>It is likely that a set of vector fields will not have the same number of distributions. In order to satisfy constraint (21), we can create regular points to make the supply equal the demand without changing the vector fields. For example, if the supplier field contains 3 critical points and the vector field remains unchanged. However, now we have two more regular points corresponding to 1 with = 0 and = 0 , and both the supplier and the consumer have 5 points in their feature distributions. All the conditions are satisfied, and we are ready to compute the EMD for these two fields and find out the dissimilarity between them. In order to evaluate the meaningfulness of our new metric, we use Multidimensional Scaling(MDS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> [14] to embed the vector fields in a two-dimensional Euclidean space so that distances in the embedding are as close as possible to the true EMDs between vector fields. The MDS is introduced in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Display of EMDs for a Large Set of Vector Fields</head><p>The above discussions are for comparison of a pair of vector fields. If there exist a large set of vector fields and we want to compare their topologies, it is necessary to display them in a more meaningful way than a 1D list sorted by their EMDs. Yossi Rubner et al. have used Multidimensional Scaling Method (MDS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref> to display a set of images on a 2D map. Given n objects in a high dimension, the MDS method computes a configuration in a lower dimension space such that the distance between every pair of objects in this low dimension space best matches the real distance in the high dimension. Inspired by their work, we compute the EMDs between every pair of vector fields and position the vector fields on a 2D map such that the distances between the vector fields match their EMD values as close as possible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Applications</head><p>Using MDS can assist navigation in the space of vector fields and provides a better way to display the query results of selected vector fields. Instead of the one-dimensional list of vector fields sorted by their distances, we can display a two or three dimensional map of vector fields, where each vector field is positioned according to the MDS result.</p><p>As a simple example, 16 analytically created vector fields are shown in figure 4. These vector fields can be sorted by their similar feature distributions. The first 4 vector fields contain saddle points in various configurations, therefore it is expected that the EMD will cluster these topologies together. Vector fields 5,6,7,and 8 contain various topological elements such as repelling and attracting foci and nodes.</p><p>Vector fields 9 and 10 both have a pair of foci and one center, but slightly different and values, and their distance between them should be very small. Vector fields 11, 12 and 13 all have one center and two nodes, therefore they are expected to group together. Vector fields 14, 15 and 16 all have two foci but different and values, particularly for vector field 15, the value here is so close to zero that two foci appear like two centers. Results are shown in <ref type="figure">figure 6</ref>, and as can be seen agree well with our expectation: the , <ref type="bibr">16 2</ref> EMDs were computed and MDS correctly grouped the similar vector fields together and separated apart the dissimilar ones according to the distances between them. (The vector fields in figure 6 have been slightly moved for viewing purposes, because the distances between some vector fields are so small that they lay on top of each other.)</p><p>As another example of locating intrinsic pattern within a vector field, we turn to a computational solution of a flow past a circular cylinder. Rogers and Kwak simulated a timeaccurate flow over a cylinder at Reynolds number of 200 using an upwind scheme on the incompressible Navier-Stokes Equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Thirty frames were computed capturing a complete cycle of vortex shedding which is composed of alternating clockwise and counter-clockwise vortices. For a Reynolds number within this regime, we expect to see regular, alternating patterns of vortices being shed downstream. The vortices form due to viscous effects. The viscosity increase the boundary layer forming a flow reversal in the latter half of the cylinder where an adverse pressure gradient exists. Due to the relatively high Reynolds number, standing vortices become unstable and are shed downstream in a pattern called a Karmen vortex street. The frequency of the shedding, first measured by Blenk et. al., has been represented via the Strouhal number <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. We can use the quantitative measure developed above to depict the regularity within this flow field.</p><p>Since the flow is incompressible, from the continuity equation we have r V = 0 which makes the trace of the Jacobian matrix zero. Solving for and under this constraint, it can easily be shown that = 0 and 6 = 0 , hence the flow field can consist only of center and saddle points. Once the topologies have been extracted from each frame, the EMD matrix is computed and visualized in figure 5. We immediately see that the matrix is symmetric and that the lowest values of the EMD is when the frame is compared to itself (center diagonal blue line). Interestingly, secondary blue lines exist starting at 16; 1 and 1; 16. On closer examination, we see that the topologies of the flow separated by 15 frames are in fact nearly identical. The flow is merely shedding the alternate vortex. This can be seen in figure 7 which depicts frames 3 and 18. The vortex is being shed from above in frame 3 and below in frame 18, however, the topology is identical. It can be argued that even though the topology is the same, the pictures are not visually identical. This method does not distinguish a picture's orientation. However, once the fields have been identified, additional metrics can be included to distinguish position and strength information. To see the regularity further, frame 3's EMD is plotted against all of the other frames in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">figure 3</ref>. Clearly, the periodicity of the flow can be recognized.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Conclusions and future work</head><p>Visualizing vector field topology is a very important subject in vector field visualization and has received a lot of attention. However, to our knowledge, almost no work has been done on quantitative measurements for vector field comparisons. In this paper, comparisons are based on feature distributions of vector fields. Critical points are key features of vector fields. The basic patterns of simple critical points can be classified into eight categories. The number and patterns of critical points in a nonlinear field can be derived from a set of linear fields based on Clifford algebra. Feature distributions are comprised of their critical points and their corresponding and parameters.</p><p>The Earth Mover's Distance was introduced by Yossi Rubner et al. for image retrieval for large image data bases. It computes the least amount of work needed to transform from one distribution to another. In our research, critical points are characterized by their and parameters. We define an -space so that all the basic patterns are points in this space. The distances between different features are defined in this -space, and are normal Euclidean distances. In the computation of EMD, the same number of suppliers and consumers are ensured in Clifford space, therefore, it is true metric.</p><p>Multidimensional Scaling has been used in psychophysics for perceptual and spatial frequency discrimination. We used this technique to sort through a list of vector fields and generate a two dimensional map to demonstrate the relationship (distances) between pairs of vector fields.</p><p>In this paper we have applied EMD and MDS to two dimensional vector fields. An interesting research topic will be applying this technique to the three dimensional vector fields and possibly can also be extend to tensor field studies.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 : 2 ( 1 )</head><label>121</label><figDesc>basic patterns for simple critical points complex field in this algebra and the nonlinear vector fields are represented as multiplications of linear fields. For the Euclidean plane we get a 4-dimensional Ralgebra G 2 with the basis 1; e 1 ; e 2 ; i = e 1 e 2 as a real vector space. Multiplication is defined as associative, bilinear and by the equations 1e j = e j ; j = 1 ;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>For a linear vectorFigure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>fieldṽ = az + b z + ce 1 , let a = a 1 + a 2 i and b = b 1 + b 2 i. Eigenvalues of the Jacobian around its critical point z 0 are 1 = b 1 Basic patterns for critical points in -space;C for center, RN for node, AN for attracting node, RF for repelling focus, AF for attracting focus, St for star, Sa for Saddle and R for regular point</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Definition 2 (</head><label>2</label><figDesc>feature distribution) A feature distribution for a vector field is the set of and values associated with the vector field's critical points: f 1 ; 1 ; 2 ; 2 ; : : : ; n ; n g: Definition 3 (Energy) The energy for a vector field is:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>b 0 i z + c 0 i e 1 (23)The supplier side has two fewer points in the , space.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Frame 3 EMD compared against all other frames. Frame 3 and 18 have highly similar topologies</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 4: sixteen different vector fields</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :Figure 6 :Figure 7 :</head><label>567</label><figDesc>Earth Mover's Distance Values via topological metric on 30 frames of the flow around a circular cylinder sixteen different vector fields sorted by MDS Topologically similar frames 3 and 18 of a timeaccurate incompressible Navier-Stokes solution of a flow about a circular cylinder.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. For the rest of the paper, all the 's and 's have been normalized. Now, a simple critical with a certain and in physical space has a corresponding point on the unit circle in the ,space. A regular vector field with no critical point expressed asṽ = const e 1 has = 0 and = 0 and is at the origin in , space, see figure 2.The Earth Mover's Distance is first introduced in [1]<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> for content-based image retrieval in a large data base. It is used to compute the minimal amount of work that must be performed to transform one feature distribution into the other. Feature distribution in<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> are the color and texture signatures of an image.</figDesc><table><row><cell>point at , 2 p 7 ; , space.</cell><cell>p 3 p 7 and another point at 2 p 7 ;</cell><cell>p 3 p 7 in ,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">6 Earth Mover's Distance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">6.1 EMD analysis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>A multiple point with a set of 's and 's corresponds to a set of points in the , space. For example,ṽ = z 2 e 1 is a dipole which has two 1; 0 point in , space; and v = z , 2 + 2i z + c 1 z + 2 + 2 i z + c 2 e 1 has one</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1 details of the derivation see [10]</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</head><p>The authors are most indebted to Yossi Rubner for providing EMD and MDS codes. The authors are supported by NASA under contract NAG 2-911 which includes support from the NASA Ames Numerical Aerodynamics Simulation Program and the NASA Ames Fluid Dynamics Division, and also by NSF under grant ECS-9215145.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A metric for distributions with applications to image databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rubner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tomasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Guibas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Internations Conferences on Computer Vision</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Internations Conferences on Computer Vision</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The earth mover&apos;s distance, multi-dimensional scaling, and color-based image retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rubner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Guibas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tomasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ARPA Image Understanding Workshop</title>
		<meeting>the ARPA Image Understanding Workshop</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation and display of vector field topology in fluid flow data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Helman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hesselink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer</title>
		<editor>M. Nielson &amp; B. Shriver</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-08" />
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Also appears in Visualization in Scientific Computing</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Visualization of Second-Order Tensor Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Delmarcelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stanford University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Singularities in nonuniform tensor fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hesselink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization &apos;97 Conference Proceeding</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Snowmass, Colorado</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>AIAA</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidimensional scaling: I. theory and method</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Torgerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="1952" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discussion of a set of points in terms of their mutual distances</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Householder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="1938" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of higher order singularities in vector fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Menzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Visualization &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;97<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>CS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="74" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing non-linear vector field topology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kruger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Menzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rockwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics and Its Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Special Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Topology based visualization for vector and tensor fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stanford University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Application of the simplex method to a transportation problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dantzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1951" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="359" to="373" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Activity Analysis of Production and Allocation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear programming</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dantzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Springer series in operations research</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-dimensional scaling by optimizing goodness-of-fit to a nonmetric hypothesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="1964" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The analysis of proximities: Multidimensional scaling with an unknown distance function, i and ii</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shepard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychometrika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="1962" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An upwind differencing scheme for the time-accurate incompressible navier-stokes equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kwak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AIAA 6th Applied Aerodynamics Conference</title>
		<meeting>the AIAA 6th Applied Aerodynamics Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="502" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Über die messung von wirbelfrequenzen</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Blenk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liebers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Luftfahrtforschung 12</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1935" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
