<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Acoustic Imaging and Visualization of Plumes Discharging from Black Smoker Vents on the Deep Seafloor</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rona</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bemis</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kenchammana-Hosekote</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Acoustic Imaging and Visualization of Plumes Discharging from Black Smoker Vents on the Deep Seafloor</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Visualization and quantification methods are being developed to analyze our acoustic images of thermal plumes containing metallic mineral particles that discharge from hot springs on the deep seafloor. The acoustic images record intensity of backscattering from the particulate matter suspended in the plumes. The visualization methods extract, classify, visualize, measure and track reconstructions of the plumes, depicted by isointensity surfaces as 3D volume objects and 2D slices. The parameters measured, including plume volume, cross sectional area, centerline location (trajectory), surface area and isosurfaces at percentages of maximum backscatter intensity, are being used to derive elements of plume behavior including expansion with height, dilution, and mechanisms of entrainment of surrounding seawater. Our aim is to compare the observational data with predictions of plume theory to test and advance models of the behavior of hydrothermal plumes through the use of multiple representations.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>We are developing innovative new acoustic and visualization methods to image and analyze thermal plumes containing metallic mineral particles with the appearance of black smoke that discharge from hot springs on the deep seafloor <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. Our objective is to advance understanding of the dynamics of the black smoker plumes as major agents of dispersal into the ocean of heat and chemicals derived from the Earth's interior. The plumes consist of a stem and a cap. The stem is formed of particles suspended in thermally expanded fluids which mix with surrounding seawater. The fluids buoyantly rise up several hundred meters to a level of neutral buoyancy where they spread laterally to form the cap. Plume studies prior to our development of the plume imaging sonar have used a combination of other techniques including: video and photo imagery which illuminates only small volumes within meters of a vent (owing to rapid attenuation of light in seawater); construction of 2D cross sections of plumes from asynchronous individual profiles of temperature, conductivity (salinity) and optical light attenuation or scattering properties versus depth (Conductivity-Temperature-Depth profiling method); records made with standard sonar instruments; and laboratory tank simulations. Of these various approaches, acoustic methods are particularly well suited to synoptically image 3D hydrothermal plumes since they are large (linear dimensions m) and contain suspended particulate matter.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>). Our initial calculations indicated that this type suspended particulate matter could be detected at ranges of up to hundreds of meters using acoustic frequencies of hundreds of kHz <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. We modified an existing sonar system to calculate specifications (frequency 330 kHz; pulse duration 100 microseconds; transmit power level of 220 dB). The sonar device was mounted in a forward-looking configuration on a submersible, and it imaged plumes discharging from black smoker-type vents at a depth of 2300m at a known field of hot springs at latitude on a submerged volcanic mountain range, the East Pacific Rise just south of the Gulf of California <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. A photograph of the plume is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. The imaging was done with a fixed geometry by setting the submersible on the seafloor with the sonar transducer about 10m from two black smoker vents several meters apart. The sonar transducer mechanically scanned the two plumes emanating from the vents in azimuth ( azimuthal steps) at successively higher elevations ( elevation steps). About 30 minutes was required to record a "frame" of data consisting of the set of scans in azimuth and elevation angles that define a plume volume by stacking of individual scans <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. old level pertains to the intensity of acoustic backscatter. A voxel in a volume object is a global maximum if it has the highest acoustic backscatter intensity within the object. A voxel is a local maximum if it has a higher intensity than that of any of its neighbors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Acoustic Imaging</head><p>The plumes were then isolated and quantified <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. A 3D region growing algorithms was used <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. The region growing algorithm starts with a seed node (local extrema value) and searches all the neighbors, until a neighboring voxel whose value is less than a userdefined threshold is reached. Optimal threshold values for the quantification of plume objects can be chosen interactively. The intensity of acoustic backscatter is directly proportional to the amount of particulate matter suspended in the plume <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, so isointensity surfaces are proxies for isosurfaces of dilution. The plume objects in the dataset were then independently processed. Isosurfaces were used to compute the bounding surface of each plume object <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. The software was implemented within the Advanced Visualization System (AVS, Inc) package. Methods which incorporate metrics for quantification of scalar and vector fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref> were applied to visualize and analyze the gridded dataset.</p><p>Once the plumes are segmented from the background, quantifications can be computed over each object. Quantifications are very important, since the visualization alone does not give us any insight into the exact structure of the plumes. Our aim is to compare the sensed data with predictions of plume theory to test and advance models of the behavior of hydrothermal plumes using multiple representations. For each plume object the following parameters were computed over a global domain comprising the whole plume, as well as over localized domains within the plume: volume; mass; first and second mass moments; centroid of mass; position and intensity of each local maximum and of the global maximum, centerline bending and merging <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Figure 3)</ref>, and best-fitting ellipsoid <ref type="figure">(Figure 4)</ref>.</p><p>The volume, mass, first and second moments, centroid, and local extrema values are computed during the segmentation phase. The centerline of each plume was computed by searching each slice for a central value and then connecting the values slice by slice. The method is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and is similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, however, because the direction of the centerline is known (in the upwards Y direction) from the way the data is collected, a vector field is not necessary to specify the direction of search. The central value can either be a local maxima or local minima of the scalar variable under investigation, the center of mass of each slice, or the area center of each slice. The searching can be restricted to a small neighborhood or performed over the segmented area on the slice. A seed centerline is calculated by starting at the bottom of the plume and working up, searching in a restricted local neighborhood. Another interesting quantity is the global centerline, which takes the global maxima of a slice and then connects the points. This is interesting because it shows how the relative strengths of the two plumes compare. The centerline is a very important quantity and needed for accurate analysis and understanding of the plume structure.</p><p>The centerlines are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures 2-4</ref> (see also color images). The dataset is and contains backscattering intensity. The plumes were observed in 1990, and 1996. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows an underwater photograph of the actual plume. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>, the isosurfaces of the two plumes (at a threshold of 10% of the maximum) is displayed with a graded-tone slice and a center-of-mass centerline. The slice is taken above the two vents (which are several meters apart) showing progressive decrease in acoustic backscatter intensity outward from high-intensity cores in a seafloor hydrothermal field. The dataset is from the 1990 collection. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>, three centerlines are shown. Note how the adjacent plume isosurfaces expand and how the centerlines abruptly merge 16-18m above the vents. This is of interest to establish whether the adjacent plume cores actually merge, and how they become intertwined.</p><p>Another important quantification is eccentricity of the plume shape. This is used to compare plume theory with the observation data. Eccentricity is calculated by fitting an ellipsoid to the extracted plume object <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The ellipsoid can also be used as a measure of surface roughness of the plume, i.e. the ratio of the surface area of the computed isosurface to the surface area of the fitted ellipsoid. Even though noise in the dataset causes bumpiness in the isosurface, we have found this measure to be useful. An example is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. Another useful quantification is the fitted ellipsoid subtracted from the plume object. This can be done by voxelizing the ellipsoid and performing a set subtraction. This is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. Some of the resulting (subtracted) volume objects are "eddy-like" regions entrained within the plume. We are currently investigating these objects and plan to compare them to 3D tracked simulations of plumes where these regions are visible and followed throughout the simulation. (A simulation with tracking results can be seen on our web site <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.) The quantitative measurements from the acoustic images are of scalar properties related to time averaged parameters of plume theory owing to acquisition of the acoustic images by stacking successive scans to reconstruct a plume over a period which is long (minutes) relative to evolution of turbulent vortices (seconds), but short relative to rise time of the plume (hour). The scalar properties measured pertain to the behavior of plumes in entraining surrounding seawater and in dispersing heat, chemicals (dissolved and particulate), and biological materials in the plume.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>The development of visualization and analysis methods is enabling us to make quantitative measurements from acoustic images of buoyant hydrothermal plumes, and to quantitatively compare the behavior of plumes at different locations as well as time series of the same plume <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Visualization alone is not sufficient, since quantifications are crucial for proper analysis. The scalar properties measured pertain to the behavior of plumes in entraining surrounding seawater and in dispersing heat, chemicals (dissolved and particulate), and biological materials in the plume. The acoustic imaging technique employed in combination with the methods described can be applied to a broad range of fluid flow regimes that incorporate suspended particulate matter in oceans, rivers and lakes including the study of sediment transport processes, material suspended by dredging and dumping operations, offshore sewage outfalls, water mass intrusion, assemblages of fish either dead in anoxic zones or alive in schools, and harmful blooms of algae.  (c) local maxima centerline: also called seed centerline because it is grown upwards from a seed point. Centerlines grown from seed points at the two adjacent vents eventually merge, suggesting that the plume cores merge 16-18m above the vents. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>: Best-fit ellipsoids: they resemble the iso-dilution surface predicted by plume theory. Comparison of surface areas of the ellipsoid and the isosurface gives a quantifiable measure of the hydrodynamic mechanisms contributing to the entrainment of surrounding seawater by the buoyant plumes. <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>: A useful quantization is the fitted ellipsoid subtracted from the plume object; Some of the resulting volume objects are "eddylike" regions entrained within the plume. These objects can be compared to results from 3D volume tracked simulations that are based on plume theory.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Photograph of one of the deep sea plumes that was imaged.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The plumes are reconstructed from the acoustic imaging data. A graded tone slice is shown demonstrating progressive decrease in acoustic backscatter intensity outward from high-intensity cores in a seafloor hydrothermal field. The isosurface (10% of maxima) is superimposed on the slice with a center-of-mass centerline. The sonar sweep shows up as the light region in the horizontal slice.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Three different centerline algorithms: (a) center-of-mass centerline: it is well centered and used in quantification of radial plume properties. (b) global maxima centerline: it provides valuable insight on the relative strengths of the two adjacent plumes.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3">Visualization MethodsOur goal is to compare the observed data to plume parameters that are defined in plume theory<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and that elucidate plume behavior. In order to apply these methods, the acoustic data was resampled onto an evenly spaced 3D rectangular grid with 0.25m spacing. Each grid point is considered to be the center of a cubical volume element, or voxel of uniform density, whose edge is equal to the grid spacing. The set of voxels collectively forms a volume object if the voxels are connected and lie above a threshold level. In this case, the thresh-</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Acknowledgments</head><p>The imaging work was supported by the US Navy Submarine Development Group ONE, NOAA Undersea Research Program and the National West Coast and Polar National Undersea Research Program. The visualization work was performed in the Laboratory for Visiometrics and Modeling, CAIP Center and received funding from the Institute of Marine and Coastal Sciences (IMCS) at Rutgers.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acoustic imaging of seafloor hydrothermal flow regimes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bemis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Dworski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kenchammana-Hosekote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Amer. Geophys. Un</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">685</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of black smoker hydrothermal plumes at monolith vent, juan de fuca ridge and epr 21 degrees north</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bemis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trans. Amer. Geophys. Un</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">841</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The acoustics of &quot;black smoker&quot; hydrothermal plumes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mottl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Acoust. Socc, Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acoustic imaging of hydrothermal plumes, east pacific rise, 21on, 109ow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Czarnecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophys. Res. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Turbulent gravitational convection from maintained and instantaneous sources</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Morton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc., R. Soc. London, Ser. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">234</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1956" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying Visualizations for Reduced Modeling in Nonlinear Science: Extracting Structures from Data Sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zabusky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Visual Communication and Image Representation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iconic Techniques for Feature Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Van Walsum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;95<address><addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="295" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Object-Oriented Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching Cubes: A High Resolution 3D Surface Construction Algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Siggraph Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Predictor-Corrector Technique for Visualizing Unsteady Flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ellipsoidal Quantification of Evolving Phenomena</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zabusky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Samtaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization of Physical Phenomena. Proceedings of Computer Graphics International &apos;91 Symposium</title>
		<editor>N. M. Patrikalakis</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="588" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Laboratory for Visiometrics and Rutgers University Modeling. Feature tracking</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.caip.rutgers.edu/vizlab.html" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>under Research</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
