<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Polycrystalline Orientation Microstructures with Spherical Color Maps</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Boris</forename><surname>Yamrom</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">GE Corporate Research and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">tGE Aircraft Engine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 River Road, One Neumann Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>12345, 45215</postCode>
									<settlement>Schenectady, Cincinnati</settlement>
									<region>New York, Ohio</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sutliff</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">GE Corporate Research and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">tGE Aircraft Engine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 River Road, One Neumann Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>12345, 45215</postCode>
									<settlement>Schenectady, Cincinnati</settlement>
									<region>New York, Ohio</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Woodfieldt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">GE Corporate Research and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">tGE Aircraft Engine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1 River Road, One Neumann Way</addrLine>
									<postCode>12345, 45215</postCode>
									<settlement>Schenectady, Cincinnati</settlement>
									<region>New York, Ohio</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Polycrystalline Orientation Microstructures with Spherical Color Maps</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Spherical color maps can be an effective tool in the microstructure visualization of polycrystals. Electron backscatter diffraction pattern analysis provides large arrays of the orientation data that can be visualized easily using the technique described in this paper. A combination of this technique with the traditional black and white scanning electron microscopy imaging will enable scientists to better understand the correlation between material properties and their polycrystalline structure.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. Introduction</head><p>Material scientists possess a large arsenal of tools for the exploration of physical and chemical properties of materials. Many of these tools directly address human abilities to process visual information. Others generate data sets that can be analyzed employing special-purpose computer programs designed to extract meaningful and useful information. Metallurgists and geologists often study polycrystalline materials, that is materials composed of many small grains of crystals. Physical properties of these materials (strength, elasticity, etc.) may be strongly influenced by the orientation of these grains, also called crystallographic textures. These textures are the subject of numerous investigations <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>.</p><p>Typical scanning electron microscope images can show boundaries between crystal grains and can reveal compositional differences between grains of different components called phases. In most cases, however, they will not show particular orientation of individual grains and, therefore, will not tell if several grains define a domain of similar orientation.</p><p>To address the problem of imaging orientation-based features in microstructures, a relatively new method of electron backscatter diffraction pattern analysis(EBSP) is used <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>. The diffraction pattern analysis by itself is not new, but special enhancements (automation) in the diffraction pattern collection combined with the computeraided processing enables generation of up to 1800 sample orientations per hour [10](in 1988 it was possible to obtain only 120 measurements per hour, <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>).</p><p>Orientation of the crystals in the sample is usually defined with Euler angles a, p, and y, that represent three consecutive rotations of the coordinate system associated with the crystal to align it with the sample coordinate system <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>. The first rotation is about the crystal's z' axis (we denote the sample coordinate system axes with x, y, z, and the crystal coordinate axes with X I , y' , and z' ), the second rotation is about the crystal's x' axis, and the third rotation is again about the z' axis. All rotations are made counterclockwise. Euler angles a, p, and y satisfy the following constraints:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">0 I a &lt; 27c, 0 I p &lt; n, 0 I y &lt; 27c.</formula><p>There are variations in the Euler angles definition: some authors use the y' axis instead of the x' axis for the second rotation, angles boundaries may be shifted too, but these are of no concern to us here. The data collected is represented by the file of records aBYxY9 where a, p, and y are Euler angles, and x, y represent two Cartesian coordinates of a measured point relative to some sample reference point. In the case of materials containing multiple components the above record can be expanded to contain the type of phase at a particular sample location. Sample points coordinates x, y may belong to a regular grid or be random.</p><p>A few visualization techniques exist for orientation data. The most popular technique is the pole figure. A particular direction is selected in a crystal coordinate system (z' axis, for example) and for all points ( x , y ) in a sample, the selected direction is mapped to a unit sphere (where a ray of this direction from the origin intersects the sphere) and then projected onto the xy plane with one of the two widely used projection techniques: stereographic or equal-area projection <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>. Thus orientation distribution of a sample is represented as a set of points in the disk. We get more information about the material if we plot pole figures for all crystal major axes x', y' , and z' . Another way to visualize orientation distribution is to display a set of points representing Euler angle triplets in the Euler angle volume of 3D space.</p><p>Though both techniques are widely used, their limitations are well recognized. One of the limitations relates to the fact that these are statistical visualizations, that is we plot points in the function value domain (a, p, y) and lose all information about spatial distribution of orientations (in x, y domain). Other limitation relates to distortion introduced by the curved character of Euler angle space.</p><p>Recently some authors addressed the limitation of Euler space mapping <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref>. Other researchers recognize that orientation, being multivariate, can be represented by color or black and white texture <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref>. However, all attempts so far were not satisfactory. Either these mappings require stereo displays [6], or the mappings were non-consistent and not easy to use. General dissatisfaction with the existing color maps for visualizing orientations is expressed in the following quotation taken from [lo]: "However, there are two problems which can arise from color visualizations of microstructure. First, inherent to any color representation is the danger of physiological responses to particular colors, biasing the interpretation. Second, for most parametrizations of orientation space, it is difficult to find a color mapping which insures that grains of similar orientation are assigned similar colors."</p><p>We try to address both of these concerns in our paper. The first concern is addressed by using multiple color maps instead of one, thus avoiding bias caused by specific physiological responses to a particular color or group of colors. The second concern is the major stimulus to our investigation. We present a set of maps that is free of these problems and that can be successfully used for producing orientation images of polycrystalline microstructures. As was indicated in <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref> no single color map of orientation space can be fully satisfactory, but their combination may be. We limit the scope of this investigation by an issue of color coding leaving out the geometry coding and other deciphering and interpreting techniques [8]. Our experiments show that those techniques may be very useful for small arrays of data, but are substantially outperformed by color coding in a case of very large data sets.</p><p>First, we observe that in many practical situations the scientist is interested in the x'y' plane orientation of the crystal only and is not interested in the rotation of the crystal about the axis normal to its x'y' plane. This is typical when we are interested in the strength of material and we know that a crystal can be more easily split along the x'y'plane than along any other plane. Other planes of interest can be analyzed similarly simply by changing the initial frame of reference. Orientation of the plane is uniquely specified by the direction of its noma1 vector, i.e., z' axis for the x'y' plane. To simplify the exposition, we assume here that the crystal axes are orthogonal, but final results still hold for arbitrary crystals.</p><p>The direction of the normal vector along the z' axis can be uniquely represented by a point on a unit sphere. Moreover, we should identify as equal the opposite points on a sphere, since they correspond to the same orientation of the x'y' plane relative to the sample coordinate system. Therefore, the limited orientation space we are dealing with is represented by a unit sphere in 3D space with opposite points being identical. This is a so called two dimensional projective plane. The arbitrary orientation, however would require a unit sphere in 4D space (with the same property of identity of the opposite points), or projective space of three dimensions.</p><p>Now we can formulate the problem to be solved in exact terms. We would like to create coloring of a sphere that satisfies the following conditions:</p><p>(a) every point on a sphere is assigned a color; (b) opposite points get the same color; (c) different points get different colors; (d) similar (close) points get similar colors.</p><p>Since we can represent color in RGB system with three parameters <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>, color gamut is a 3D topological region. If we treat conditions (a)-(d) literally, we would need an imbedding of projective plane (topologically equivalent to the Klein bottle) into 3D space that we know is impossible <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref>. Luckily, we do not treat conditions (a)-(d) to the letter. In reality, even if we could create a map satisfying (a)-(d), it would not be very useful. If we allow for every point on a sphere to have a unique color and use this color map to color the orientation corresponding to each sample point x, y , we get a picture that will contain too much information to comprehend. The segmentation of the image that is easily done with pre-attentive vision in the case of limited number of colors becomes more difficult or impossible to do when the amount of colors grows dramatically. Therefore, we change the condition (a) to be (a' ) the sphere is subdivided into a finite number of regions, possibly of similar area, each region is assigned a color;</p><p>and we require that (b)-(d) is applied to these regions instead of points. We call these new conditions (a' )-( d' ).</p><p>In the next section we construct maps that satisfy these conditions. Then we discuss how the mapping of orientation data into color space is implemented. At the end we summarize and point out new directions of research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Spherical Color Maps</head><p>Since the ideal subdivision of a sphere into subregions should possess many symmetries, it is natural that we tum our attention to the subdivision induced by regular polytopes inscribed into a sphere. Among all regular polytopes the icosahedron has the maximum number of faces -20. Each face of an icosahedron is a regular triangle and all points opposite to ones in a face represent one of the other faces of the icosahedron. We have the same property satisfied by cube, octahedron, and dodecahedron. Thus all regular polytopes except tetrahedron can be used for orientation color maps (compare with <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>). We present here a detailed description of the design of color maps based on icosahedron and on octahedron geometries.</p><p>Coloring a cube satisfying (a' )-( d' ) is easy, one just has to assign primary colors red, green, and blue to pairs of opposite faces. With the icosahedron it is not so easy and the existence of appropriate coloring may be viewed as some kind of magic. Indeed, let us consider one triangle face of the icosahedron and look at its adjacent faces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Three adjacent faces of an icosahedron</head><p>Let the central triangle in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> be colored in red, then we choose adjacent faces colors to contain equal red components but mixed with other primaries. One face will become yellow and another will get magenta. Since there is no fourth primary color, we mix red with white to color the third adjacent triangle. If we assign two other primary colors to other faces and repeat this construction, then, with the realization that each face color will be repeated twice in the icosahedron, we get two of each colors on the surface of icosahedron: red, green, blue, yellow, magenta, cyan, light red, light green, and light blue. All together there are 18 faces. Just add two whites and we color all the faces of the icosahedron. Question: can this be done in a consistent way that is exemplified in <ref type="figure">Figure l</ref> ? Yes, this is indeed possible and demonstrated in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, where an icosahedron is shown from two opposite points of view so all its faces can be observed unobstructed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. Two opposite views of an icosahedron</head><p>This coloring is characterized by other symmetries: every combined color, yellow for example, is surrounded by two primary colors it is combined with, red and green, and also by a light blue. White color is surrounded by three light primaries. All colors specifications can vary slightly to accommodate for different display devices or color printer devices.</p><p>The created color map satisfies (a' )-( d' ) conditions and contains ten colors. This color map is just an example and a proof of existence by the demonstration. Other coloring schemes can be designed for an icosahedron that may be even more natural than this one.</p><p>If we want finer resolution of orientation in color space, we need to subdivide the sphere into more regions. We can build such subdivision by splitting each triangle face of an icosahedron into four equal triangles, projecting three new vertices (edge centers) onto the sphere, and connecting them in a triangle mesh.</p><p>Instead, we start with an octahedron and by a similar face subdivision we create color maps with 4, 16, 64 and 256 colors. To demonstrate a different approach to color map design we use the HSV color system [5] and assign to each triangle facet of the polyhedron the color corresponding to its geometric center point. To find this color we first check the sign of z components of the point coordinate and, if it is negative, we negate all components of the point. The resulting point in the northem hemisphere we project onto the xy plane using stereographic or equalarea projection <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>. Then we take the polar coordinate of the projection point r, cp, (0 I r I l,-n I cp &lt; 7c) and calculate h, s, and v by the formulas (C language notation is used here) </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">s = r, v -(cp &gt; O)? 1 : 0.7,</formula><p>where h is hue, s is saturation, and v is value. The first expression makes standard hue of the color wheel to be repeated twice in one full turn around the origin. This is done to assign equal hue to all points on a meridian. The second formula makes color different for different points on a sphere based on their latitude coordinate. Points closer to the equator get more saturated colors and points closer to the north pole get color close to white. The last formula makes a distinction in coloring two symmetric points, the points with projected coordinates (r, cp) and (r, cp + IF). These points will have the same hue and saturation but can be distinguished by the value v (as previously, variations in formulas are possible). The image of 64 colors map equal-area projection of northern hemisphere is presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>. One unavoidable artifact of this color map is the contrast boundary (more pronounced in the printed image than on the color monitor) between the light and dark quarters of the sphere (discontinuity in value along the equator and zero meridian). The more colors we get in the color map, the more difficult would be to avoid discontinuity in mapping a projective plane to the color space. With this comment in mind it immediately follows from our construction that the designed color map satisfies conditions (a' )-( d' ). In cases when the sample orientation data is limited in its range a simple color map of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> can be used. In this color map opposite points on the boundary do not coincide and may have a different color. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Implementation and Examples</head><p>Figure 5 presents algorithm of processing orientation data.</p><p>1. Select one of the color maps and the associated polyhedron described in the previous section. Make the face indices of polyhedron faces be equal to the color indices in the color lookup table.</p><p>Create a rectangle subdivided into squares according to all x,y sample points. (We assume that a regular grid is used for simplicity). 3. For each sample point do the following: 3.1 Calculate a 3 x 3 orientation matrix based on the Euler angles of the sample. 3.2 Apply the transformation matrix from the previous step to the direction vector (0,0,1) (crystal's z' axes).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Find the intersection (polyhedron face index)</head><p>between the ray from the origin along the transformed z' axes and the polyhedron centered at the origin.</p><p>3.4 Use the face index of the intersection point to color the corresponding square in the rectangle of step 2.</p><p>2. Color can be used also to represent the misorientation between the adjacent regions (grains) of homogeneous orientations. This may be done semiautomatically by selecting pairs of adjacent regions and by displaying the misorientation data and color, but also can be automated to display the grains adjacency graph with the links colored according to a selected color map. Misorientation between the two grains is measured by the smallest rotation angle required to align one grain orientation with another. The detailed description of the adjacency graph and its coloring goes beyond the scope of this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Summary and Conclusions</head><p>We have created a technique for visualizing the orientation microstructure of polycrystalline materials. The technique is based on a few key ideas. First, the general orientation of the crystal grain is reduced to the orientation of a fixed plane associated with the crystal coordinate system. Second, the orientation of the plane in 3D space is mapped to the projective plane realized in 3D space as a unit sphere with identified opposite points. Third, the unit sphere is triangulated in a way compatible with the topology of projective plane (icosahedron, octahedron and their subtriangulations suite well). Fourth, each triangle of the triangulation is assigned a unique color with conditions (a')-(d'). Thus each orientation of the crystal plane gets its color code.</p><p>The color map based on the sphere subdivision induced by the inscribed icosahedron contains 10 different colors. For color maps with 64 and 256 colors solid angles subtended by each region become much smaller. This leads to less variations in color transition from region to region. To satisfy the conditions of color separation and color similarity, we used all three dimensions of the color gamut. More research is required to find psychologically the best uniform subdivision of the color space satisfying conditions (a' )-( d' ).</p><p>The small discontinuity in the HSV value parameter along the zero meridian and the equator psychologically is more visible than the changes in saturation and hue. One way to preserve the separation of colors is to use colored texture in two quarters of the sphere instead of reducing the value in the HSV model. In cases when all orientations vary in some solid angle less than d 2 in diameter the discontinuity in the value parameter can be moved away by changing the reference point in the northern hemisphere. By default it is the north pole, but any other point can be used.</p><p>We tried to create isotropic maps and for this reason avoided a simplistic mapping of longitude and latitude coordinates on a sphere into hue and saturation. In our approach the proportion of a color in the image is defined by the proportion of the corresponding orientation in the raw data and is not distorted by the nonuniformity of color representation that would be caused by the longitude/latitude mapping. On the other hand, simple longitudeflatitude mapping could be much more efficient from the (See color plates, page  computational point of view. For some applications anisotropic maps may suite even better than the ones we have created. Spherical color maps may be viewed as visual filters and the search for particular features in the data may pose specific requirements for the design of these filters. <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>, each square is oriented according to the Z' direction</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure9. The same data as in</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure8. 32 x 32 detail of orientation data in Figure6 colored with the 64 colors map of Figure 4</head><p>Even without optimizations to find out ray-polyhedron intersection, the processing time of the 10,000 sample points on a SPARCstation 1+ was a matter of a few minutes, which is negligibly small compared to the time required to collect the data. Nevertheless, the application of multiple color maps, the selection of subregions, and the reprocessing of those regions interactively would require some optimizations.</p><p>We only briefly mentioned the misorientation imaging and presented some of the possible techniques but there is much more to be said about it and we hope to do so in a forthcoming publication. Finally, the comparison of orientation patterns with the SEM images of the same sample, we believe, will provide many new insights into the structure of polycrystalline materials.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>See color plates, page CP-5.) h = (cp &gt; O)? cp / x : (cp + IF) / IF,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The equal-area projection of 64 colors map of the northern hemisphere</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>A color map with 64 colors</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The conceptual scheme of the color mapping orientation dataFigures 6-7 represent a sample of data taken with the step size 1 micron on a 100 x 100 grid. A detail of the image inFigure 6is reproduced inFigures 8-9using the color map ofFigure 4.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">(See color plates, page CP-5.)</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Orientation Maps: Techniques for Visualizing Rotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Alpem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grayson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pelkie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On-line microstructure determination using backscatter Kikuchi diffraction in a scanning electron microscope, ICOTOM 8, The Metallurgy Society</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dingley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Encyclopaedia of Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">275</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rendering and managing spherical data with Sphere Quadtrees</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization 90</title>
		<meeting>Visualization 90<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer Graphics, Addison-Wesley, 1990. Frank, F.C., Orientation Mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metallurgical Transactions A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microtexture Determination and its Applications, The Institute of Materials, 1992. Visualization of Multiparameter Images, Panel Session</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Randle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization 90</title>
		<editor>Wenk, H.-R.</editor>
		<meeting>Visualization 90<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Preferred Orientation in Deformed Metals and Rocks: An Introduction to Modem Texture Analysis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of new automatic lattice orientation measurement technique to polycrystalline aluminum</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kunze</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Material Science and Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
