<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Integrating Spatial Data Display with Virtual Reconstruction</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Philip</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Archaeology School of Computing Science School of Computing Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V5A 1S6</postCode>
									<settlement>Burnaby</settlement>
									<region>B.C</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brian</forename><surname>Hayden</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Archaeology School of Computing Science School of Computing Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V5A 1S6</postCode>
									<settlement>Burnaby</settlement>
									<region>B.C</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>David Fracchia</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Archaeology School of Computing Science School of Computing Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Simon Fraser University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>V5A 1S6</postCode>
									<settlement>Burnaby</settlement>
									<region>B.C</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Integrating Spatial Data Display with Virtual Reconstruction</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>In the process of archaeological excavation, a vast amount of data, much of it three-dimensional in nature, is recorded. In recent years, computer graphics techniques have been applied to the task of visualizing such data. In particular, data visualization has been used to accomplish the virtual reconstruction of site architecture and to enable the display of spatial data distributions using threedimensional models of site terrain. In the case we present here, these two approaches are integrated in the modeling of a prehistoric pithouse. In order to better visualize artifact distributions in the context of site architecture, surface data is displayed as a layer in a virtual reconstruction viewable at interactive rates. This integration of data display with the architectural model has proven valuable in identifying correlations between distributions of different artifact categories and their spatial proximity to significant architectural features.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>In studying the remains of prehistoric architecture, it is generally of interest to identify how different areas of a structure were utilized. The answer to this question can be seen as an important step in the development of a theory of the social organization of the site's former inhabitants.</p><p>Under the assumption that certain artifacts have a strong association with a specific activity, by examining the spatial distribution within the site architecture of different artifact types, it is possible to formulate a hypothesis which identifies areas according to usage. However, in order to form a more complete understanding of dwelling organization, one must question why one area is associated with a particular usage pattern and not another.</p><p>In the case presented here, we describe how, using computer graphics techniques, it is possible to incorporate the display of artifactual data distributions into the structural and environmental context of site architecture (in this case, a prehistoric pithouse). We have found that visualizing excavation data in this manner can, in addition to being a valuable aid in the identification of correlations between the spatial distribution of artifacts and significant site features, be a useful tool in identifying the implications of architectural constraints on usage areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Visualization in archaeology</head><p>Computer graphics techniques are increasingly being used to visualize complex data in archaeological investigation. In recent years, several projects involving the creation of detailed virtual reconstructions of archaeological sites have been undertaken. In these applications, a three-dimensional computer graphics model of the site is constructed and viewed using standard modeling, rendering, and animation techniques.</p><p>Some of the most well-known examples of virtual reconstruction have involved the application of solid modeling techniques (CSG) in the recreation of historical architecture. Initially applied to the modeling of the temple precinct of Roman Bath, CSG techniques were later refined and applied to the more ambitious modeling of the Saxon Minster of Winchester using the WINSOM solid modeller [13]. A later project, the modeling of the Furness Abbey <ref type="bibr">[ 5 ]</ref> , expanded on the techniques pioneered in the earlier efforts and offered interactive viewing capabilities, although at a fairly low degree of realism.</p><p>Recent efforts in virtual reconstruction have produced increasingly photorealistic results. A detailed model of the Dresden Frauenkirche, destroyed during the second world war, has been used to create a high resolution computer generated film <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>. Unlike most archaeological sites where the only source of data is the site itself, original plans and photographs of the architecture existed on which to base the model. One of the outstanding features of this reconstruction is the attention paid to the recreation of interior lighting and surface detail, evoking in the viewer a sense of the architectural space. Attention to detail and accurate surface characteristics are also evident in the virtual reconstruction of the Visir tomb in Egypt <ref type="bibr">[ 111.</ref> In both of these cases, the visualization is not the ultimate goal, but is being used as part of the process leading to the eventual physical reconstruction of the site.</p><p>Computer graphics techniques have also been applied to the analysis of archaeological sites. From site survey data, a three-dimensional model of terrain can be constructed <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref>. Digital terrain models (DTM) can then be used as a context in which tsdisplay spatial data such as artifact distributions <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>. This approach is fundamental to geographic information systems (GIs), and their applicability to archaeology has also become evident, particularly when considering data at the site or intra-site level <ref type="bibr">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr">10]</ref>. A related approach considers the problem of visualizing spatial data throughout several noncontemporaneous layers <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref>. In this early system, a data layer can be displayed in a plan view, or a cross-sectional view can be used to slice through multiple layers.</p><p>The ability to visually relate the distribution of data to surface characteristics has proven useful in the identification of spatial correlations. This technique can be extended to include less tangible features such as viewsheds and solar paths, While less physical than surface characteristics, these environmental factors are nonetheless, sufficiently important. Analyses of these features have been applied in architecture <ref type="bibr">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr">12]</ref>, and have potential application in archaeology <ref type="bibr">[8]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Visualization</head><p>The Keatley Creek site in British Columbia consists of over 100 cultural depressions, several of which have been fully excavated since 1986. The majority of these depressions are the remains of residential dwellings that were occupied over 2000 years ago. The case we present here describes the virtual reconstruction of one of the largest of these dwellings. The type of dwellings associated with these cultural depressions are referred to as p i t h o u s e s . Pithouse construction consists of an approximately circular subterranean floor with a raised earthen rim and a roughly conical roof structure. The roof is constructed of log beams pinned to the rim and sloping inward towards the center of the pit. The inward sloping beams, supported by upright log posts are interlaced with joists and covered with wood thatching and dirt. At the apex of this roof structure is a central smoke-hole, which, in addition to serving as the source of light and ventilation, also serves as the pithouse entrance. Ingress and egress from the smoke-hole is accomplished using a log ladder. The major structural components are illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Virtual reconstruction</head><p>In constructing the model, the focus was on creating a visual representation that conveyed the major structures, yet was simple enough to navigate at interactive rates on available hardware. Moreover, structural features that were not necessary to convey the basic architectural shape were intentionally left out.</p><p>The floor was reconstructed from survey data by fitting a non-uniform b-spline surface that interpolated known surface points. Beams and posts were modeled using cylindrical primitives, and the roof covering was constructed from simple polygonal patches (Plates 1 and 2). A simple shading model with minimal texture mapping is used.</p><p>In addition to the major structural components of the pithouse, simple representations of significant interior features are also included. The locations of hearths are indicated by the position of red spheres on the pithouse floor. Similarly, the positions of storage pits are denoted by black disks (Plate 3)</p><p>The user can move in, out and around the model, in real time, by steering a virtual camera using a mouse or SpaceBall. The standard display is in the first-person, and the interaction method used does not require the user to change focus away from the model. In addition, an orthographic overview of the floor can be displayed simultaneously. In this view, an arrow glyph is used to indicate position and orientation in the main view (Plate 5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Spatial data display</head><p>The spatial distributions of a variety of artifacts can be displayed within the model. Distribution plots are layered on top of the pithouse floor using a model in which the greater the artifact density, the more the surface colour is modified (Plate 4). Multiple plots can be layered at once, using different colors, transparency or vertical displacements if desired.</p><p>Most artifact data at this site was recorded as discrete counts within square regions. Therefore, spatial data is plotted at this resolution, and no colour interpolation is used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Light availability</head><p>A characteristic feature of pithouse architecture is the central smoke-hole. This opening at the apex of the roof structure is the only source of natural light in the dwelling. Because of the limited availability of light, it is hypothesized that the usage of different areas of the house floor was subject, at least partially, to the availability of working light.</p><p>In order to approximate the directly lit areas of the house interior, a light source approximating the emission area of the smoke-hole is modeled. This light source illuminates the floor model so that areas of direct light can be easily seen. The solar path of the sun is calculated for the site, and can be specified to correspond to a given date. The user can then interactively manipulate the light source through its apparent daily motion to see its relation to data distributions layered onto the floor surface (Plate 6). This method, while not a correct model of the actual sunlight distribution, is a useful approximation for the purpose of data exploration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Results</head><p>In the case presented here, we have used threedimensional computer graphics techniques to integrate the display of spatial data into a model of a prehistoric pithouse. This has provided us with some valuable insight into the implications that the architectural structure of a pithouse can have on usage areas within the dwelling. By viewing artifact data in an approximation to its original context, we were able to more readily identify potential relationships between data distributions and the pithouse structure.</p><p>Artifact data from the Keatley Creek excavation is probably the most detailed and comprehensive ever collected from a similar site <ref type="bibr">[ 141.</ref> Various hypotheses exist relating the spatial distribution of certain artifact types to areas of the pithouse floor. In order to visualize how particular data distributions relate to the site, distributions were layered onto the surface model of the floor (Plate 4).</p><p>Distribution plots of this type are commonly displayed on two-dimensional site maps. Placing the data in the three-dimensional model has the advantage of making obvious any relation to surface slope. As can be seen in Plate 4, it is readily apparent when a high density of artifacts, in this case, debitage, are on a wall slope (possibly indicating a storage area).</p><p>While the analysis of spatial relationships between data and floor position has proved useful, we have found the most insightful information from this visualization comes as a result of considering that the structure imposes constraints on usage areas.</p><p>In the orthographic projection shown in Plate 5 , two different artifact distributions are displayed. One of the data sets is clearly more concentrated in the periphery than the other. The data set that is more central is likely related to its proximity to the hearths as it is commonly thought to be associated with food preparation. The outer data set, however, is associated with personal possessions. One possible reason for this peripheral distribution might be that sleeping areas were on the edge of the structure. While not identifiable in the two-dimensional plot, it is readily seen in Plates 3 and 6 that the ceiling height at the edge is quite low, and therefore, the edge could not have been useful for much else other than sleeping or storage.</p><p>Another form of architectural constraint inherent in the pithouse structure is the availability of working light. Since the only source of natural light is the smoke-hole, we have approximated how much of the interior would be lit at a given time of day. In Plate 5, the distribution of the data set shown in blue (heavily-retouched scrapers), is more concentrated towards one end of the floor. By examining the same plot in Plate 6, it is readily apparent that this artifact is more dominant in the area lit by the midday sun. This would indicate that this artifact type is associated with work requiring some visual acuity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Future work</head><p>While the use of computer graphics as a visualization technique in archaeology is becoming more common, there are still many possibilities for further research. In particular, the case presented here can be expanded on in several ways. Our research up to this point has concentrated on creating a model of major structural features only. We have taken this approach for two reasons: First, it was necessary to minimize the complexity of the model in order to maintain interactivity on available hardware. Second, the structural factors that we were most interested in testing the implications of (direct light availability and ceiling height), did not require significant structural complexity. With access to faster hardware, more detailed features could be incorporated without sacrificing display speed, and as a result interactivity.</p><p>While the simple lighting model implemented thus far has proven useful, the development of a more accurate model that accounts for light from hearths, in addition to <ref type="figure">(See color plates, page CP-40.)</ref> natural light, would provide a better basis for work area theories.</p><p>A further enhancement to the model would b e to implement it in a virtual reaEity (VR) environment. In addition to providing the user with a sense o f t h e architectural space, V R techniques have potential for integrating the display of data in the context of a <ref type="figure">model [3]</ref>.</p><p>Finally, it would be o f interest t o integrate the visualization model with the underlying data such that it is no longer a passive display device only, but can be used to query data and perform statistical functions.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Pithouse architecture.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1070">-2385/94 $04.00 0 1994 IEEE</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">(See color plates, page CP-40.)</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>This work was supported in part by a Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council (NSERC) post-graduate scholarship. Equipment, resources, and encouragement were provided by the faculty, statff, and students of the Graphics and MultiMedia Research Lab at Simon Fraser University.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interaction with a color computer graphics system for archaeological sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Virginia</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Badler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Badler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (Proceedings of SIGGRAPH &apos;78)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1978-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="221" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Expanding the role of computer graphics in the analysis of survey data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Boismier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>C. L.</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ruggles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P Q</forename><surname>Rahtz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="225" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>BAR Intemational Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The virtual windtunnel: An environment for the exploration of three-dimensional unsteady flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Steve</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Creon</forename><surname>Levit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;91</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;91<address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From ruins to reality-the Dresden Frauenkirche</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Brian</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Furness abbey survey project-the application of computer graphics and data visualisation to reconstruction modelling of an historic monument</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ken</forename><surname>Delooze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jason</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology</title>
		<editor>Kris Lockyear and Sebastian Rahtz</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="148" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>BAR Intemational Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing n-dimensional implications of two-dimensional design decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stephen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ervin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;92<address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Digital terrain modelling and three-dimensional surface graphics for landscape and site analysis in archaeology and regional planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology</title>
		<editor>C . L. N. Ruggles and S . P. Q. Rahtz</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="172" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>BAR Intemational Series</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data exploration in archaeology: New possibilities and challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Kokonya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Communication in Archaeology: a global view of the impact of information technology</title>
		<editor>Paul Reilly and Sebastian Rahtz</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">One</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="64" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Data Visualisation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geographic information systems and archaeology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kenneth</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kvamme</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology</title>
		<editor>Gary Lock and Jonathan Moffett</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>BAR International Series S577</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing spatial data: the importance of geographic information systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gary</forename><surname>Lock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Trevor</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Archaeology and the Information Age: a global perspective</title>
		<editor>Paul Reilly and Sebastian Rahtz</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Routledge</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="96" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The virtual restoration of the Visir tomb</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Palamidese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Betro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Muccioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;93</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;93<address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="423" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An interactive environment for architectural energy simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jon</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pittman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Donald</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (Proceedings of SIGGRAPH &apos;82)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boston, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="242" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data visualization in archaeology</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IBM Systems Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="569" to="579" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Artifact distributions on housepit floors and social organization in housepits at Keatley Creek. Master&apos;s thesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Spafford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Simon Fraser University, Department of Archaeology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
