<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Volume Rendering of Pool Fire Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rushmeier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mech. Engr. Univ. of Illinois at Chicago Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60607-7022</postCode>
									<region>IL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Hamins</forename><surname>Caml</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mech. Engr. Univ. of Illinois at Chicago Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60607-7022</postCode>
									<region>IL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>MD</roleName><surname>Gaithersburg</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mech. Engr. Univ. of Illinois at Chicago Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60607-7022</postCode>
									<region>IL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M.-Y</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Mech. Engr. Univ. of Illinois at Chicago Chicago</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>60607-7022</postCode>
									<region>IL</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Volume Rendering of Pool Fire Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We describe how techniques from computer graphicsare used to visualize pooljre data and compute radiative effects from pooljires. The basic toolsare ray casting and accurate line integration using the RADCAL program. Example images in the visible and infrared band are shown which give qualitative insights about the fire data. Examples are given of irradiation calculations and novel methods to visualize the results of irradiation calculations.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Overview</head><p>In a pool fire, a puddle or pool of liquid fuel is ignited and bums in the atmosphere. Understanding pool fires is important to devising methods to control the impact of hazardous situations resulting from spilled fuels. In this paper we consider techniques for visualizing the data measured in pool fires, and for computing the radiative transfer from pool fires. Combustion is a challenging example for development of visualization techniques. Fires are turbulent, non-steady, and multi-wavelength in emission. Fire data is an example of a class of visualization problems for which it is important to consider the radiative simulation used to generate visualizations.</p><p>We see objects as a result of the visible light they emit, transmit or reflect. All rendering methods in some way simulate the radiative transfer of light <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. When visualizing abstract representations of objectssuch as molecular modelssimple, heuristic rendering methods are useful. This is particularly Vue in volume visualization, in which a complete physical simulation of light propagation can be extremely computationally demanding <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. However, in some volumetric problems, radiative transfer is a critical part of the phenomenon being visualized. For these problems, using radiometrically accurate techniques to generate images of the data can provide useful insights.</p><p>In the case of fire data, radiative transfer plays two important roles. First, data is obtained from fires by detecting radiation. Data is collected with probes inserted in the fire to measure radiative transfer over short distances. Qualitative information about the fire is obtained by simply observing the luminosity of the flame. Second, a major quantity of interest is the radiation from the fire that reaches surrounding surfaces. For example, the flame can ignite adjacent pools of fuel by radiative heat transfer.  accurately image fire data, efficient calculations can also be made about the impact of the fire on its surroundings.</p><p>In the particular experiments we consider in this paper, data were taken for a 10 cm diameter heptane pool fire, using a pair of opposed, water-cooled, nitrogen-purged, intrusive probes separated by 12 mm, which defined the optical path. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref> diagrams the fire and typical measurement locations. Because the time averaged flame is cylindrically symmetric, data were taken only for varying radii r from the center of the pool and for height z above the pool. Local instantaneous temperature, soot volume fraction and CO2 concentrations were determined from radiation measurement in three wavelength regions (900, 1000 and 4350 nm.) These data were used to estimate the concentrations of H2O and CO. Typical data locations are shown in two-dimensional plots in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>. Details of the experimental procedure are given in <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref>. These data were taken to examine various features of radiative transfer from the fire.</p><p>In this paper we consider how visualization and graphical techniques can be used along with this data to answer the following questions:</p><p>How well do the measurements represent the actual data? The two-dimensional plots shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref> are difficult to relate to one another, and to the luminous flame observed in the laboratory. 0 What is the importance of the radiation from the gases relative to the radiation from the soot? Usually in the past only soot has been considered.</p><p>0 What is the radiative feedback to the fuel surface? How much heat does the flame contribute to the pool surface for vaporization?</p><p>What is the irradiation at points in the space around the fire? At what distance from the fire would other materials be ignited?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Visualization</head><p>The basic tool for imaging and computing radiative transfer is ray casting. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref> diagrams casting a ray through the volume of data. Because data were only taken at varying r and t , the volume of data is a stack of cylindrical rings. Rays are simply followed from the observer (or in the case of irradiation calculations from the collector position) through the cylinder. For each ring encountered, the next pierce point is found. If the wall of the ring is pierced, the r index is incremented (or decremented) to find the next ring encountered, else the z index is incremented or decremented.</p><p>Once the complete traversal of the ray is found, a list is constructed of the ring segments that the ray passes through. For each segment distance, temperature, soot volume fraction and gas partial pressure are collected. These data are passed to the routine RADCAL <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> for performing the line integration which gives intensity i(1) (energy per unit projected area, time and solid angle, referred to as radiance in the lighting and graphics literature) at the end of the ray path 1. RADCAL accurately calculates the radiation taking into account the detailed spectral properties of COz, HzO, CH4, CO, N2,Oz and soot. In  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">r i x = i ' a x ( l * ) d l * i x ( 1 ) = ix,we-nx(')</formula><p>In the above equations X is wavelength, and XI and A2 are the limits of the wavelength band of interest for the calculation. The band can be the entire infrared spectrum for irradiation calculations, or narrow bands for the purpose of examining radiation in the visible, or other bands of interest. 'ix is the optical thickness of the medium, which by definition is a function of the absorption coefficient aA along the path. i~,~ is the spectral intensityat the beginning of the ray path. For the pool fire problem, this is taken to be the black body intensity at normal room temperature (about 300 K). i b ,~( I * ) is the blackbody intensity along the path.</p><p>RADCAL considers only absorption and emission along the pathnot scattering, since the effect of scattering is negligible for the problem of radiation in combustion products. RADCAL assumes local thermodynamic equilibrium ( L E ) , which is an accurate assumption for the radiative transfer of interest in thermal problems. It should be noted that non-LTE radiation, luminescence which occurs by excitation other than thermal agitation, is responsible for a significant amount of visible radiation in some types of flames. However visibleradiation in most fires, such as the heptane pool fire considered in this paper, are dominated by LTE radiation from soot particles. One way to evaluate the measurements is to use a camera model which is sensitive to wavelengths throughout the infrared. Another way is to view the measured data in the same manner as the fire is physically observed. The luminous flame is imaged by computing radiances in the visible band and performing appropriate perceptual transformations to produce a true color image. This would be done most accurately by using RADCAL to calculate spectral intensities in the range of 400 nm to 700 nm, convolving these intensities with the CIE X(A), Y ( A ) and Z(X) functions for the human visual system, and converting from X Y 2 coordinates to RG B using measured monitor characteristics (e.g. see <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>). Because the radiated spectrum from the soot is relatively smooth, to generate images rapidly, we sampled the spectrum at the peaks of the X , Y, Z curves only to estimate the ratios X : Y : Z. The sample spectral intensities are in units of watts per meter squared-steradian. These intensities must be scaled to CRT display values in the range 0-255. Again, to generate images rapidly, the results were displayed by simply scaling the average luminance value to 128 in the final image. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref> shows time-averaged images of a pool fire. For purposes of comparison, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4a</ref> is the average of 30 images grabbed from video tape of the actual pool fire. An uncalibrated video camera was used, and the flame colors in the video are quite desaturated compared to the colors observed directly in the laboratory. Figure4b shows a synthetic image generated from measured data. Two thousand measurements were taken at each spatial location. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4b</ref> was generated using the average of all 2000 values at each location. As expected, the synthetic image shows that the spacing of the measurements doesn't represent the geometric detail of the flame. However, the measurements are adequate to capture the necking in of the flame near the fuel surface, and broadening further above the surface. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures 4c and d</ref> illustrate the difference between radiation from time averaged measurements, and time averaged images from a time series of measurements. The image in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4c</ref> as generated using the average of 30 measurements at each location. The image in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4d</ref> was generated by averaging 30 images, each generated by using just one of the 30 measurements at each location. Because intensity values must be clipped for each image, the image in 4d is desaturated in a similar manner as the averaged video image in 4a. A comparison of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figs. 4c and d</ref> shows that there is a substantial difference between the radiation from averaged data and the average radiation. This indicates that just as spatially detailed data is needed, rather than data averaged over the volume, temporally detailed rather than time-averaged data is needed to accurately estimate radiation transfer from the flame.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Discussion</head><p>Note that in all of the synthetic images in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 4</ref> no numerical legend is shown. This is because these are visual simulations, not pseudo-colored displays. Insight into the relative importance of soot versus gas radiation can be gained by imaging the fire using a synthetic camera which includes wavelengths through the entire infrared range. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref> shows the resulting image when temperatures, soot volume fraction. and gas partial pressure data are given to RADCAL (on the right), versus the image which results when temperatures and soot volume fraction data only are used. A comparison of the figures shows that the gases are responsible for a significant amount of radiation. A numerical legend is shown on these images, since the gray shades are assigned based on the total intensity visible at each pixel, not on perceptual principles.</p><p>The same ray casting and line integration techniques used to generate images can be used to compute irradiance on surfaces around the fire. For example, the radiative feedback per unit area, q l / (~) to a point on the pool surface at radius r is given by:</p><p>The angles B and 4 are respectively the polar and azimuthal angles of a coordinate system based on the pool surface. The intensity i ( 0 , 4) is the incident intensity from direction 0 , 4 . i ( 0 , 4 ) is found by casting in a ray in the direction i i 8 , 4 and computing i(l) for that direction, as in Eq. 1. The integral can be evaluated using a Monte Carlo method, summing up the results of casting rays in a large number of randomly chosen directions. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> shows typical results for the fire data given in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 2</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref> also shows small, wide angle images (136 degree field of view) generated from each of the points for which q / / ( r ) was calculated. These images demonstrate that the fall off in irradiation is primarily due to the decreasing solid angle subtended by the hot products of combustion. (Note, these results are only shown as examples of the calculations. Details of numerical results for total radiative feed back to the pool fire can be found in [ 11).</p><p>The incident flux qll at other surfaces around the fire is also of interest, to study the potential for ignition of other To estimate the flux in the space around the fire, Eq. 2 was evaluated for a grid of points in the space around the fire, with a surface normal vector oriented towards the center of the fire to estimate the maximum flux. Because the fire data is rotationally symmetric, the results can be diagrammed in two dimensions as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 7</ref>. However, this does not give a good sense of the meaning of the data to a casual observerit doesn't communicate that the irradiation is spread through space and that it applies to surfaces oriented towards the fire. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 8</ref>, a volumetric rendition of the irradiation data is shown. A collection of spheres are colored according to the maximum incident flux at that location. A simple lighting heuristic is used to highlight the sphere in the direction of the fire, to emphasize the role of orientation in the flux calculation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Summary and Future Work</head><p>We have shown how techniques from computer graphics can be used to gain insight into data from pool fires. Visible images generated using measured data demonstrated how well the measurements represented the fire. Images generated over the entire infrared spectrum demonstrated the relative importance of gas versus soot emission. The same ray casting that was used to generate images was used to calculate irradiation from the fire. Graphical techniques were further used to illustrate the results of the irradiation calculations.</p><p>The data in the examples given in this paper were obtained using an immersive probe. Such a probe has the disadvantage that the entire temperature and emissivity distributioncannot be obtained simultaneously. An alternative approach for obtaining fire data is imaging, and applying techniques from tomography. A potential future role for synthetic images of fire data may be in the design of such imaging systems.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Typical locations for taking pool fire data,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Typical temperature, CO2 partial pressure, and soot volume fraction data for a pool fire. The data are shown in two-dimensional, gray-scaled plots.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>[21, RADCAL is presented as an independent FORTRAN program (code is included in the publication), however it can readily be adapted to a callable subroutine. RADCAL evaluates the following equations to obtain i(1): r .,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Using the measured data, the fire is numerically modelled as a stack of cylindrical rings, with uniform properties in each ring. To generate images or calculate incident irradiation, rays are cast through the numerical model and the points where the ray pierces each cylindrical ring are found. ) i b , A ( l * ) e z P [ ( o ( l ) -m(l* ))ldKA(l*)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>See color plate at end.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Infrared images of radiation from soot and gas, versus soot alone.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>(Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>See color plates, page CP-45.) Irradiation of the pool surface by the hot combustion products. The small images show a wide angle view image of the view of the combustion products at the various radial positions looking upward from the pool surface. materials. The incident flux is a function of position in the volume around the fire, and orientation relative to the fire.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Two-dimensional plot of contours of constant irradiation for points around the pool fire.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>See color plate at end</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous optical measurement of soot volume fraction, temperature and CO1 in heptane pool fire</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hamins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rushmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kashiwagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Proceedings of the 2 S h Symposium</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>To appear in. Int&apos;l) on Combustion</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">RADCAL: A narrow-band model for radiation calculations in a combustion environment. NIST Technical Note 1402</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Grosshandler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-04" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Institute of Standards and Technology</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Illumination and Color in Computer Generated Imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The rendering equation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kajiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH &apos;86 Proceedings)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGGRAPH</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="150" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The zonal method for calculating light intensities in the presence of a participating medium</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rushmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Torrance</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (SIG-GRAPII&apos;87 Proceedings)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>See color plates</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
