<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Visualization of Mesoscale Flow Features in Ocean Basins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Johannsen</surname></persName>
							<email>andreas@erc.msstate.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Mississippi State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Mississippi State</addrLine>
									<postCode>39762</postCode>
									<region>MS</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Moor</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Mississippi State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Mississippi State</addrLine>
									<postCode>39762</postCode>
									<region>MS</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Box</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Mississippi State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Mississippi State</addrLine>
									<postCode>39762</postCode>
									<region>MS</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Visualization of Mesoscale Flow Features in Ocean Basins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Environmental issues such as global warming are an active area of international research and concern today. This case study describes various visualization paradigms that have been developed and applied in an attempt to elucidate the information provided by environmental models and observations. The ultimategoal is to accuratelymeasure the existence of any long term climatological change. The global ocean is the starting point, since it is a major source and sink of heat within our global environment.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The NSF Engineering Research Center ( E R 0 for Computational Field Simulation at Mississippi State University was established in 1990 with the mission of mounting a concerted research program to provide U.S. industry with the capability for the computational simulation of large-scale, geometrically-complex physical field prob lems. For the Scientific Visualization Thrust of the ERC, oceanographic visualization has been a major area of research and development. An interactive acoustic visualization tool has been developed for the Naval Oceanographic office 14.61, which allows an analyst to visualize 3D ocean sound speed fields volumetrically to determine the location of subsurface oceanographic features. An eddy detection. extraction, tracking, and animation capability has been developed with the MSU Center for Air-Sea Technology <ref type="bibr">[5,10,111.</ref> The present visualization focus on ocean data is part of the Acoustic Monitoring of Global Ocean Climate (AM-GOC) Program, which involves many of the major ocean* graphic researchers and centers in the United States, as well as many abroad, in an effort to measure ocean temperature using acoustic thermometry to provide direct evidence of the rate of global climate change. The 30-month pilot project is primarily focused in the Pacifc Ocean.</p><p>Since oceans cover about three-quarters d the earth and are vast reservoirs of heat and carbon dioxide build-up from our industrialized world. an murate measure of ocean temperature on a global scale can provide direct evidence of the rate of global climate change caused. In fact, the global ocean has been called the climatological flywheel.</p><p>Within the AMGOC program, global climate models are being studied and refmed. Data from these models aid inthepredictionofglobalwarmingtrends and the prediction of acoustic travel time trends, which are tested against measurements. Both long-range acoustic propagation and ocean climate models provide a better understanding of the effects of seasonal and other natural variability of ocean temperatures. Sound speed in the ocean is a function of temperature. pressure, and salinity. Global ocean warming of as little as 3-5 millidegnxs Celsius produces a sound speed increase of 0.02 m/s. Over global paths (16,000 km) this results in a travel time reductionof 0.1-0.2 seconds. Thuseven aminiscule global warming signal canbe detected by the decreased propagation time. However, this decmse in travel time must be detected against a background of travel time fluctuations caused by oceanographic variability arising from sources other than warming. Such fluctuations are largely due to mesoscale, seasonal, and longer term variability. It is these oceanographic "noise" sources that the work described in this case study attempts to visualize effectively.</p><p>As the AMGOC program evolves, the visualization system will allow the visualization of fluid flow and acoustic propagation within the same scene. This comprehensive visualization system will allow detection of computational and experimental problems, discovery of unexpected physical phenomena and confirmation of the expected, and will provide an effective means of visual communication among project participants and to the scientific and lay communities in general.</p><p>The visualization system will include representations of ocean temperature fields, ocean current fields, ocean surface height, sound speed data, acoustic source and receiver 1070-2385/94 $04.00 0 1994 IEEE locations and structure, and acoustic propagation paths showing propagation losses, boundary interactions, and acoustic arrival pattems. Effective representationof mesoscale eddies, internal waves, and other relevant ocean characteristics will be developed. This data visualization capability will include both experimental and computational model data. Effective comparison of forward predictive modeling with resulting assimilated data will be included. The visualization system will be interactive, providing a global view and high resolution sectional views under user control of both location and viewpoint. It will be possible to move about the targeted section for alternate views or to move around geometrical features.</p><p>The key elements of the visualization system have been the GUI, the datamanagement, and the flow visualizationalgorithms. The value of the work is determined by the degree to which it allows the users to explore their data and extract information. The ability to see contextual information -bathymetry, coastlines, location of acoustic sources and receivers, physical extent labelling (latitude, longitude, and depth) --is crucial.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dataset</head><p>The primary data set that has been visualized is the result of an ongoing simulation of the Pacific Ocean [21, the so-called NRL model. It covers the area from 109.125'E to282"Eandfrom2O0S to62'Nwithafixedlatitude/longitude sampling of 0.125" x 0.17578125". whichresults in a resolution of 989 x 657. The model has 6 isopycnal (constant density) horizontal layers. Although the intemal timestep of the model is 20minutes, data is saved only every 3.05 model days, which yields 120 samples per model year.</p><p>The outputs ofthe simulation are layer thickness deviations, h, and the horizontal current, [u,vIT. This produces 3 GB of data per model year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visualization System Issues</head><p>For the design and implementation of the ocean model visualization software, an object-oriented approach has been adopted. Advantages of object-oriented programming are well-documented, e.g., [31; in particular it facilitates stable extensions to large software systems. Extensibility is a major concem for the ocean model visualization software.</p><p>as it is used by a wide variety of institutions within the AM-GOC program. Furthermore, the visualization paradigms found useful within the context of ocean modeling should be applicable to other fields. For example, the techniques developed for oceanographic flow visualization should also be useful for hydrodynamic, meteorological, and aerodynamic flow visualization, necessitating extensions tocomputational grids other than the ones used for the AMGOC ocean models.</p><p>The inherent size of ocean models makes data handling an important part of the visualization system. For an initial implementation, data handling has been restricted to structured, four-dimensional grids. This provides enough flexibility for the model, while allowing efficient data access. Access to raw model data is supplied by an IOStructu-redGrid4D object. This object administers all data files, it chooses appropriate readers for specifk file formats and. in compliance with main memory size, makes an attempt to buffer data.</p><p>Results from one ocean model experiment are typically mhived in several files to keep file sizes manageable. For example, thedataforthePacificOceanfromtheNRLmode1</p><p>is split into files which contain all the output data for a quarter year. However, this partitioning should not be visible during the analysis of the data. Therefore. the visualization system provides the means to describe a Logical Grid; the current implementation uses an ASCII file, since this is permanent, data-relatedinformation. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows part of the Logical Grid File for the Pacific Ocean data set. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Extract from a Logical Grid File</head><p>The Wimension commandprovides adescription of index ranges for the entire logical grid. The data itself is described by \variable commands, each specifying the name of a data variable. its data type and its meaning (as a comment string). With this information available, each \filename command specifies the index subrange and the data variables stored in one particular file. Any continuous index subrange and any combination of variables is allowed; the example given in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows only subranges in i and for all files variables h, U, and v. The bathname command is provided for convenience, all following filenames are ap-pended to the current pathname. The actual access to data files is determined by their \filetype, which the IOStructu-redGrid4D uses to choose specXic readers.</p><p>The IOStructuredGrid4D object provides data access through its method Getvertex (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2)</ref>. In each of the four dimensions, an arbitrary index subrange (or the special SymbolfullRange) canbespecifiedfor any variable, allowing flexible random access of any zero-to four-dimensional data subset. This includes obvious choices like "one layer of h at a particular time" and less obvious. but potentially useful ones like "one vertical line of h for all timesteps." Providing an easy-to-use but very general data interface like Getvertex encourages localized data access, leading to improved system performance through a reduced number of actual disk file accesses. The size of oceanmodel datasets usually prohibits local storage on avisualization computer. Data is stored on a file server and accessed through a network, which typically presents a serious performance bottleneck. In order to address this problem, one filetypeheader combination in the visualization system uses a wavelet compression method r8.91. Data files are compressed off-line, transmitted when accessed, and decompressed on the fly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flow Visualization</head><p>For visualization purposes, graphical representations with suitable visual attributes have to be derived from the ocean model data. The structure of layered ocean models suggests layer interfaces for graphical representation. At any fixed time, each of the layer interfaces is defined by a height field, with height values (or depthvalues, rather) provided for each of the model's latitudeflongitude pairs.</p><p>The geometrical shape of a layer interface can bevisualized by an appropriate surface (interpolated or approxi-mated), withvisualclues provided by a lighting model. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows the layer interfaces for the six-layer NRL model. To avoid aliasing artifacts along the shoreline and for increased drawing performance, the land data has been masked for all but the lowest layer interface.</p><p>At any fixed time, the horizontal current in one layer is characterized by vectors [u,vIT on a latitudeflongitude rectilinear grid. Visualizations of steady (instantaneous) and unsteady (time dependent) flow traditionally use tufts or arrows to indicate flow directions at fixed and/or moving points, e.g., [71. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> shows a 10x10 degree subsection of the uppermost two layers in the Pacific Ocean dataset, with an arrow anchored at each grid point. This is a useful technique and it has been used extensively. but for larger datasets, i.e., larger regions and/or finer grids, pictures tend to be overcrowded with arrows, making flow features practically undetectable.</p><p>For the visualization of horizontal flow within the layers of a layered ocean model, a technique termed colorwheel has been developed. The basic idea is to abandon any auxiliary graphical objects like arrows, which might overcrowd or clutter the picture, and instead use color for representing flow direction. A circular color lookup table provides an individual color for all directions; given a vector [u,vlT, it is straightforward to compute its direction in terms of an angle a, which is used to access the corresponding color in the table. <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> shows the colorwheel technique applied to the uppermost layer in the Pacific Ocean model. In order to relate colors and directions, the colorwheel itqelf is reproduced on a planar surface with a fixed position relative to the layer; it follows all transformations (e.g., rotations) of the layer in 3-space. For ease of computation and understanding, the colorwheel has been designed using the HSV color model, with the flow direction corresponding to Hue. In <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>, the other two channels, S and V, are set to a fixed value of 1.0, i.e., full saturation and value (lightness).</p><p>For the detectionof flow features, it is desirable tovisualize not only vector directions. but alsovector lengths. Given avector [u,vlT, this can be achieved by letting its direction determine the color and "scaling" that color according to the vector's length. In the HSV color model, for example, the vector's length can scale the saturation (S) and/or lightness (V) channels. <ref type="figure">Figures 6 and 7</ref> illustrate logarithmic scaling of S and V. Prominent flow features include the equatorial (east-to-west) and equatorial counter (west-toeast) currents, the Kuroshio Current off Japan, and eddies, which, as circular flow, appear as a rotation of the colorwheel codiguration. Clockwise and counter-clockwise eddies can be easily distinguished. A rotated view, <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> canbe probed by pointing with the mause and reporting the flow vector &lt;II the colorwheel legad.</p><p>These initial experiments with the colorwheel technique have shown its usefulness in visualizing ocean model flow data However, there is ample room for improvements and extensions. The HSV color model has been chosen for convenience of computation; other color models are being investigated. To facilitate the qualitative interpretation d visualizations. changes of perceived colm on the wheel should currespond directly to (angular) changes of vectcc seem to be useful. for example, concentrating the color gamut in a wedge of the colorwheel to increase the resolution of direction. In additim various configurations on the wheel particularflow directions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary</head><p>A large part of the task has been and Continues to be gaininganundmtandingoftheoceanographers' andacousticians' knowledge, nomenclatwe, questions, and interests.</p><p>The basic task of visualizing ocean models and acoustic paths is not likely to change over the next few years. The focus will be on developing and integrating more tools (other vectorflow visualization techniques, tensor visualization for 8coustic propagation, etc.) and extending the flexibility of the system (e.g.. handljng data on other grids structures.</p><p>etc.). For example, coastal modelers with whom we also collaborate are interested in applying the colorwheel technique to visualize flow in their problem domain, e.g.. flow in tributaries and bays 111</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Basic data access methodThe current implementation of IOStructuredGrid4D buffers rectangular subsets of layers, so-called tiles. The number of tile buffers can be tailored to the available main memory by using the method SetNoOfBuff em. Individual tiles are loaded with filetype-specific readers, which receive a filename, file-relative indices, and a variable name. This establishes a compact and clean interface and makes readers for new filetypes easy to add.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, clearly shows the rising of the uppermost layer interface between the equatorial and counter-equatorial currents. For a detailed analysis of flow features, the visual representation (See color plates, page CP-39.)</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The work described herein is part of a larger project involving many people. Kelly Parmley Gaither developed the vector visualization routines whichproducedFigure4, Scott Nations wrote much of the data management routines and GUI code, and Bernd H a m m provided much information on surface reconstruction and vector visualization paradigms. Their contributions are gratefully acknowledged.</p><p>This work has been supported in part by AFWA and the Strategic Environmental Research and Development Program (SEXDP).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lee</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-03-29" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Coastal Engineering Research Center, US Army Corps of Engineers</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>private communications</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling of the Global and Pacific Oceans: On the Path to Eddy-Resolving Ocean Prediction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hurlburt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alan</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wallcraft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E. Joseph</forename><surname>Sirkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Metzger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Oceanogra</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Object Oriented Sofrware Construction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OVIRT -Oceanographic Viualization Interactive Research Tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J B</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lever</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Navy Scientific Visualization and Virtual Reality Seminar, Bethesda. MD</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feature Extraction for Oceanographic Data Using A 3D Edge Operator</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization &apos;93</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oceanographic Vkdization Interactive ResearchTool (OVIRT)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Everitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcallister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SPIEProc. 2178,SPIEIIS&amp;TElec-tronic Imaging</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fluid Flow Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Frits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>The0 Van Walsum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Focus on Scientific Visualization</title>
		<editor>H. Hagen. H. Muller, and G.M. Nielson</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lossless Progressive Transmission of Scientific Data Using Biorthogonal Wavelet Transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hai</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Austin, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progressive Transmission of Scientific Data Using Biorthogonal Wavelet Transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hai</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, D.C.</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Feature Extraction and Tracking in Oceanographic Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Anand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Raju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SPIE Proc. 2178, SPIEIIS&amp;T Electronic Imaging</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Jose, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Feature Detection Techniques for Time-Varying Volumetric Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Workshop on Visualization MdMachine Vision</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Seattle, WA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
