<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Flow with Quat ernion Frames</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indiana University Bloomington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47405</postCode>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hui</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Indiana University Bloomington</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>47405</postCode>
									<region>IN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Flow with Quat ernion Frames</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Flow fields, geodesics, and deformed volumes are natural sources of families of space curves that can be characterized by intrinsic geometric properties such as curvature, torsion, and Frenet frames. By expressing a curve&apos;s moving Frenet coordinate frame as an equivalent unit quaternion, we reduce the number of components that must be displayed from nine with six constraints to four with one constraint. W e can then assign a color to each curve point by dotting its quaternion frame with a 4 0 light vector, or we can plot the frame values separately as a curve in the threesphere. As examples, we examine twisted volumes used in topology to construct knots and tangles, a spherical volume deformation known as the Dirac string trick, and streamlines of 3 0 vector flow fields.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>We propose new tools for the visualization of a class of volume data that includes streamlines derived from 3D vector field data as well as deformed volumes. The common feature of such data that we exploit is the existence of a family of static or time-varying space curves that do not intersect, but which may exhibit extremely complex geometry; typically, portions of neighboring curves are similar in some regions of the volume, but become inhomogeneous when interesting phenomena are taking place. Our approach is based on the observation that families of curves in threespace possess several intrinsic but locally computable geometric properties: these include the curvature, the torsion, and a local coordinate frame, the Frenet frame (also called the Frenet-Serret frame), defined by the tangent, normal and binormal at each point of each curve.</p><p>While it is awkward to represent the Frenet frame itself visually in high-density data because it consists of three 3D vectors, or nine components, it has only three independent degrees of freedom; it is well known that these three degrees of freedom can conveniently be represented by an equivalent unit quaternion that corresponds, in turn, to a point in the three-sphere (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>). We exploit the quaternion representation of rotations to reexpress the Frenet frame of a 3D space curve as an elegant unit four-vector field over the curve; the resulting quaternion Frenet frame can be represented as a curve by itself, or can be used to assign a color to each curve point using an interactive 4D lighting model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Frenet Frames</head><p>The Frenet frame is uniquely defined for (almost) every point on a 3D space curve (see, e.g., <ref type="bibr">[5, 61, and also [I, 81)</ref>. If G(s) is any smooth space curve, its tangent, binormal, and normal vectors at a point on the curve are given by</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">G ( s ) = ii(s) x Q S ) .</formula><p>The Frenet frame obeys the following differential equation in the parameter s:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">0 -T ( S ) (2)</formula><p>where v ( s ) = //G'(s)ll is the scalar magnitude of the curve derivative, ~( s ) is the curvature, and ~( s ) is the torsion. All these quantities can in principle be calculated in terms of the parameterized or numerical local values of G(S) and its first three derivatives as follows:</p><p>(3)</p><p>If we are given a non-vanishing curvature and a torsion as smooth functions of s, we can theoretically integrate the system of equations to find the unique numerical values of the corresponding space curve (up to a rigid motion).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Theory of Quaternion Frames</head><p>A quaternion frame is a unit-length four-vector q = (qo,ql,qzlq3) = (q0,d that corresponds to exactly one 3D coordinate frame and is characterized by the following properties: 0 Unit Norm. The components of a unit quaternion obey the constraint,</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">( 4 O l 2 + (d2 + + ( q 3 y = 1 (4)</formula><p>and therefore lie on S3, the three-sphere.</p><p>0 Multiplication rule. The quaternion product of two quaternions q and p , which we write as q p , takes the form</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">qOP2 + POqZ + q3P1 -qlP3 qOP3 + PO43 + qlP2 -q2Pl * 1 QOPO -4lPl -QZP2 -q3p3 qOP1 + PO41 + qZP3 -q3PZ [4 * PI3</formula><p>This rule is isomorphic to multiplication in the group SU(2), the double covering of the ordinary 3D rotation group SO(3).</p><p>0 Mapping to 3D rotations. Every possible 3D rotation R (a 3 x 3 orthogonal matrix) can be constructed from either of two related quaternions, using the quadratic relationship:  <ref type="formula">6</ref>, to get the needed information; Equation (6), having only four components and automatically enforcing the constraint Eq. (4), is much simpler for numerical analysis than Eq. (2).</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">q = ( 4 0 , 41, q z ! 43) Or -4 = (-40, -413 -qzr -q3)i D'(123) Q ( -+ -) D-(231) , D-(312) P ( 2 3 1 ) Q ( --+)<label>(5)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Frames 4 Assigning Smooth Quaternion</head><p>The Frenet frame equations are pathological, for example, when the curve is perfectly straight for some distance or when the curvature vanishes momentarily. Thus, real numerical data for space curves will frequently exhibit behaviors that make the assignment of a smooth Frenet frame difficult or impossible. In addition, since any given 3 x 3 orthogonal matrix corresponds to two quaternions that differ in sign, methods of deriving a quaternion from a Frenet frame are intrinsically ambiguous. Therefore, we prescribe the following procedure for assigning smooth quaternion Frenet frames to points on a space curve: 0 Assign an initial orientation to the beginning of each curve. Appropriate choices may depend on context.</p><p>0 Given a sequence of points for a sampled space curve, compute the numerical derivatives a t a given point and use those to compute the Frenet frame according to Eq. (2). If any critical quantities vanish, keep the frame of the previous point.</p><p>0 &lt;heck the dot product of the previous binormal B(s) with the current value; if it is much less than one, choose a correction procedure t o handle this singular point. Among the correction procedures we have considered are (1) simply jump discontinuously to the next frame to indicate the presence of a point with very small curvature;</p><p>(2) create an interpolating set of points and perform a geodesic interpolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>; or (3) deform the curve slightly before and after the singular point to "ease in" with a gradual rotation of the frame. Creating a jump in the frame assignment is the easiest, and is an intuitively reasonable choice, since the geometry is changing dramatically at such points.</p><p>Apply a suitable algorithm such as that of Shoemake <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref> to compute a candidate for the quaternion corresponding to the Frenet frame.</p><p>If the 3 x 3 Frenet frame is smoothly changing, make one last check on the 4D dot product of the quaternion frame with its own previous value: if there is a sign change, choose the opposite sign to keep the quaternion smoothly changing (this will have no effect on the corresponding 3 x 3 Frenet frame). If this dot product is near zero instead of f l , you have detected a radical change in the Frenet frame which should have been noticed in the previous tests.</p><p>If the space curves of the data are too coarsely sampled to give the desired smoothness in the quaternion frames, but are still close enough to give consistent qualitative behavior, one may choose to smooth out the intervening frames using the desired level of recursive slerping <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref> to get smoothly splined intermediate quaternion frames.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, we plot an example of a torus knot, a smooth space curve with everywhere nonzero curvature, together with its associated Frenet frames, its quaternion frame values, and the path of its quaternion frame field projected from four-space. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> plots the same information, but this time for a curve with a discontinuous frame that flips too quickly at a zero-curvature point. This space curve has two planar parts drawn as though on separate pages of a partlyopen book and meeting smoothly on the "crack" between pages. We see the obvious jump in the Frenet and quaternion frame graphs at the meeting point; if the two curves are joined by a long straight line, the Frenet frame is ambiguous and may optionally be declared undefined in this segment.</p><p>Alternative Frames. We have chosen to deal directly with the more familiar properties and anomalies of the standard Frenet frame in the treatment pre-sented here; however, it is worth noting that alternative methods such as the parallel transport frame formulation proposed by Bishop 111 can be used to avoid frame discontinuities. The quaternion frame method extends also to parallel transport frames [8].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Visualization Methods</head><p>Once we have calculated the quaternion Frenet frame, the curvature, and the torsion for a point on the curve, we have a family of tensor and scalar quantities that we may exploit to expose the intrinsic properties of a single curve. Furthermore, and probably of greater interest, we also have the ability to make visual comparisons of the similarity and differences among families of neighboring space curves.</p><p>The Frenet frame field of a set of streamlines is potentially a rich source of detailed information about the data. However, the Frenet frame is unsuitable for direct superposition on dense data due to the high clutter resulting when its three orthogonal 3vectors are displayed; direct use of the frame is only practical at very sparse intervals, which prevents the viewer from grasping important structural details and changes at a glance. The 4-vector quaternion frame is potentially a more straightforward and flexible basis for frame visualizations; below, we discuss several alternative approaches to the exploitation of quaternion frames for data consisting of families of smooth curves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Direct Three-Sphere Plot of Quaternion Frame Fields</head><p>We now make a crucial observation: F o r each 30 space curve, t h e quaternion f r a m e defines a completely n e w 4 0 space curve lying on t h e unit three-sphere e mbedded in 4 0 Euclidean space.</p><p>These curves can have entirely different geometry from the original space curve, since distinct points on the curve correspond to distinct orientations. Families of space curves with exactly the same shape will map to the s a m e quaternion curve, while curves that fall away from their neighbors will stand out distinctly in the three-sphere plot. Regions of vanishing curvature will show up as discontinuous gaps in the otherwise continuous quaternion frame field curves. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures Id and 2d</ref> present elementary examples of the three-sphere plot. More complex examples are introduced in Section 7 and shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 3b, 4b</ref>, and 5b. The quaternion frame curves displayed in these plots are 2D projections of two overlaid 3D solid balls corresponding to the "front" and "back" hemispheres of S3. The 3-sphere is projected from 4D to 3D along the 0-th axis, so the "front" ball has points with 0 5 Q O 5 t l , and the "back" ball has points objective is achieved, we can interactively employ a moving 4D light and a generalization of the standard illumination equations to produce images that selectively expose new structural details.</p><p>Once we have generated our (possibly piecewise) smooth quaternion frames for each curve, we see that the quaternion frame q ( s ) is pecisely what is required to apply 4D lighting and thus instantly identify those sections of the curves with similar orientation properties by their matching reflectances. The lighting equ* tion we adopt is simply</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Probing Quaternion Frames with 4D Light</head><p>As an alternative display method, we now adapt techniques we have explored in other contexts for dealing directly with 4D objects (see <ref type="bibr">[11]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[12]</ref>, and <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>). In our previous work on 4D geometry and lighting, the critical element has always been the observation that _ -4D light can be used as a probe of geometric struccurves or surfaces until they become true 3-manifolds) to define a unique 4D normal vector that has a welldefined scalar product with the 4D light; when that ture provided we can find a way (such as thickening I(s) = <ref type="figure">Ia + I d ( &amp; . q ( s )</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">) I (7)</formula><p>where L is a 4D unit vector representing a 4D light direction, and we have included both an ambient and a diffuse term. The 4D dot product may be treated in several ways when it becomes negative: if the particular application actually has a reason to distinguish two equivalent quaternion frames because of their POsition in a time sequence, one may distinguish positive and negative dot products by assigning different color ranges (this method is used in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 3-5)</ref> or by setting the diffuse value to zero when the dot product is negative; if this distinction is not significant, the absolute value may be used. We have found it useful to use a variety of color maps in place of a strict gray scale of intensities. A moment's reflection reveals that this amounts to assigning shells of color to the threesphere and tagging the quaternion vector field lines in the three-sphere plot with the values of the color shells through which they pass; rotating the light is equiv-alent to rotating the 4D orientation of the color map distributed across the three-sphere. Yet another variation would assign each point of the three-sphere to a unique color in the 3D hue-saturation-intensity space, making 4D rotation of the "light" irrelevant except for permuting the emphasized orientations. It is also possible to add a heuristic specular term to Eq. (7), e.g., .by considering the projection direction of the threesphere plot to be a 4D "view vector."</p><p>Figures 3a, 4a, and 5a show streamline data sets rendered by computing a pseudocolor index at each point from the 4D lighting formula Eq. (7).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Additional Geometric Cues</head><p>Gray [6, 31 has advocated the use of curvature and torsion-based color mapping to emphasize the geometric properties of single curves such as the torus knot.</p><p>Since this information is trivial to obtain simultaneously with the Frenet frame, we also offer the alternative of encoding the curvature and torsion as scalar fields on a volumetric space populated either sparsely or densely with streamlines; examples are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 3c,d, 4c,d and 5c,d</ref>.</p><p>Another extension one might adopt is based on the idea that, from Eq. (4), the curvature ~( s )</p><p>is proportional to the norm of a 3-vector: we can thus construct the four-component object and then use the normalized "four-vector" K(s) = c(s)/llc(s)ll as the quantity to be probed with 4D light. Since we normally start the interactive system with the light shining directly in the direction of the component assigned to ~( s ) in Eq. (8), we can begin with an image coded strictly by the strength of the curvature, and move the 4D light out into the other dimensions to reveal the components of the vector whose magnitude is the curvature.</p><p>Finally, we remark that stream surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[14]</ref> can in principle also be mapped to the three-sphere, e.g., by choosing an interpolation of the quaternion frames of the streamline curves from which the stream surface is derived.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Interactive Interfaces</head><p>4D Light Orientation Control. Direct manipulation of 3D orientation using a 2D mouse is typically handled using a rolling ball <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref> or virtual sphere [2] method to give the user a feeling of physical control. Here we briefly outline the extension of this philosophy to 4D orientation control (see <ref type="bibr">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr">91)</ref> To control a single 3D lighting vector using a 2D mouse, we note that the unit vector in 3D has only two degrees of freedom, so that picking a point within a unit circle determines the direction uniquely up to the sign of its view-direction component. By choosing some convention for distinguishing vectors with positive or negative view-direction components (e.g., solid or dashed line display), we can make the direction unique. To control the light vector using the rolling ball, begin with the vector pointing straight out of the screen, and move the mouse diagonally in the desired direction to tilt the vector to its new orientation; rotating past 90 degrees moves the vector so its view component is into the screen. The analogous control system for 4D lighting is based on a similar observation: since the 4D normal vector has only 3 independent degrees of freedom, choosing an interior point in a solid sphere determines the vector uniquely up to the sign of its component in the unseen 4th dimension (the U4D view-direction component"). The rest of the control proceeds analogously.</p><p>Three-sphere projection control. A natural characteristic of the mapping of the quaternion frames to the three-sphere is that a particular projection must be chosen from 4D to 3D when actually displaying the quaternion data. In order to expose all possible relevant structures, the user interface must allow the viewer to freely manipulate the 4D projection parameters. This control is easily and inexpensively provided using the interface just described for controlling the 4D light orientation. Our "MeshView" 4D viewing utility supports real-time interaction with such structures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Examples</head><p>We present three different examples of streamline or flow data. Each data set is rendered four ways: (1) as a Euclidean space picture, pseudocolored by 4D light;</p><p>(2) as a four-vector quaternion frame field plotted in the three-sphere; (3) in Euclidean space color-coded by curvature, (4) in Euclidean space color-coded by torsion. In principle, any of the images for which we have shown only streamline curves can also be displayed with stream surfaces or interpolated solid volume rendering; we have a module for solid rendering that displays data such as that in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref> as slices of the solid object.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Conclusion</head><p>In this paper, we introduced a visualization method for distinguishing critical features of streamline-like volume data by assigning to each streamline a quaternion frame field derived from its moving Frenet frame; curvature and torsion fields may be incorporated as well. The quaternion frame is a four-vector field that is a piecewise smoothly varying map from each original space curve to a new curve in the three-sphere embedded in four-dimensional Euclidean space. Furthermore, this four-vector can be interpreted as a fourdimensional normal direction a t each curve point, thus allowing us to build on our previous work exploiting 4D illumination; by assigning a shade to each curve point that depends on the scalar product of the quaternion frame with a 4D light, we can explore a wide variety of local data features by interactively varying the light direction.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>(a) Projected image of a 3D (3,5) torus knot. (b) Selected Frenet frame components displayed along the knot. (c) The corresponding smooth quaternion frame components. (d) The path of the quaternion frame components in the three-sphere projected from four-space. Gray scales indicate the 0-th component of the curve's four-vector frame (upper left graph in (c)). with -1 5 qo &lt; 0. The qo values of the frame at each point are displayed as shades of gray in the curves of Figures 1 and 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>(a) Projected image of a pathological curve segment. (b) Selected Frenet frame components, showing a sudden change of the normal. (c) The quaternion frame components. (d) The discontinuous path of the quaternion frame components in the three-sphere. Gray scales indicate the 0-th component of the curve's four-vector frame (upper left graph in (c)).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>0Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>An AVS-generated streamline data set; the flow is obstructed somewhere in the center, causing sudden jumps of the streamlines in certain regions.0 Figure 4. The "Dirac string trick" deformation [13] of a spherical solid consisting of concentric spheres in Euclidean space. 0 Figure 5. A complicated set of streamlines derived from twisting a solid elastic Euclidean space as part of the process of tying a topological knot.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Vector field streamlines. (a) With 4D light. (b) Quaternion field path. (c) Curvature. (d) Torsion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Dirac Strings. (a) With 4D light. (b) Quaternion field path. (c) Curvature. (d) Torsion.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Knot volume deformation. (a) With 4D light. (b) Quaternion field path. (c) Curvature. (d) Torsion.(See color plates, page CP-11.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>q~~q~k q~j Z q~ and D*(ijk) = 2qiPj 2 q O q k . 0 Quaternion Frenet Frame. All 3Dqo -qi qz -43 q1 qo 43 Q2 q2 43 40</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>As a check, we verify that the matrices</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>40 A = [ 43 qz q i 40 ] 41 -qz -43 -42 93 -qo 41 -43 4 2 Q1 -20 B = [ qo -q1 -42 43 1 c = [ -q1 -40 43 : : I</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>give rise directly to the usual quantities: IAl.1q'1 = .i.' = ZI-IClq IBI * = fi' = -VK? + ZIrfi, IC1 *</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>JdqJ = 6' = -Z I T $ , where we have applied Eq. (6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>to get the final terms.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Just as the Frenet equations may be integrated ex-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>plicitly to generate a unique moving frame with its</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>space curve for non-vanishing -IC(.) [6], we could in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>principle integrate the quaternion equations, Eq.</cell></row><row><cell>R = [</cell><cell>Q(+ --)</cell><cell>D-(123)</cell><cell>Ot(312)</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">where Q(*jZ*) = coordinate</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">frames can be expressed in the form of quater-</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">nions using Eq. (5); if we assume the columns</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">of Eq. (5) are the vectors (?, fi, g), respectively,</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">one can show (see [8]) that Iq'(s)I takes the form</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1070">-2385/94 $04.00 0 1994 IEEE</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was supported in part by NSF grant IRI-91-06389. We thank Brian Kaplan for his assistance with the vector field data set, and John Hart, George Francis, and Lou Kauffman for the Dirac string trick data description. Bruce Solomon brought reference [l] to our attention.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotations for n-dimensional Tech</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">406</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Indiana University graphics. Computer Science Department</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visualization methods for four dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;93</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;93</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="203" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing the fourth dimension using geometry and light</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;91</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;91</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="328" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illuminating Computer Graphics and the fourth dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Heng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="62" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visualizing quaternion rotation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kauffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constructing stream surfaces in steady 3d vector fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hultquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;92</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="246" to="251" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to frame a curve.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mountford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Sellen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study in interactive 3-d rotation using 2-d control devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (1988)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="130" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings of SIGGRAPH</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Description of Alfred Gray&apos;s knots colored to represent variation in curvature and torsion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cipra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">259</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="894" to="895" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Mathematicians gather to play the numbers game</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual reality performance for virtual geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>these Proceedings</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Treatise on the Differential Geometry of Curves and Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Eisenhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1960" />
			<publisher>Dover</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">1909</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Modern Differential Geometry of Curves and Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<publisher>CRC Press, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boca Raton, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The rolling ball</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Graphics Gems</title>
		<editor>D. Kirk</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quaternion frenet frames: Making optimal tubes and ribbons from curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Indiana University Computer Science Department</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep. 407</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Math. Monthly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Animating rotation with quaternion curves</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shoemake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="254" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Computer Graphics</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
