<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Severe Rainfall Events in Northwestern Peru (Visualization of Scattered Meteorological Data)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lloyd</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
							<email>lloydt@watson.ibm.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yorktown Heights</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Severe Rainfall Events in Northwestern Peru (Visualization of Scattered Meteorological Data)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The ordinarily arid climate of coastal Peru is disturbed every few years by a phenomenon called El Niiio, characterized by a warming in the Pacific Ocean. Severe rainstorms are one of the consequences of El Niiio, which cause great damage. An examination of daily data from 66 rainfall stations in the Chiura-Piura region of northwestem Peru from late 1982 through mid-1983 (associated with an El Niiio episode) yields information on the mesoscale structure of these storms. These observational data are typical of a class that are scattered at irregular locations in two dimensions. The use of continuous realization techniques for qualitative visualization (e.g., surface deformation or contouring) requires an intermediate step to define a topological relationship between the locations of data to form a mesh structure. Several common methods are considered, and the results of their application to the study of the rainfall events are analyzed.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>The climate of coastal Peru and southwestem Ecuador is mainly controlled by the Humboldt current, a cold ocean current which travels northward along the coastline of Chile and Peru before dispersing near the equator. The current helps cause dry conditions to persist continuously along the Peruvian littoral, making the land strip between the Andes and the Pacific Ocean one of the most arid deserts in the world. Every few years this condition is disturbed by a phenomenon called El Niiio, characterized by an ocean warming which appears off the coastlines of northwestem Peru and southwestem Ecuador. This warming modifies the Humboldt current destroying the persistent high pressure zone normally induced by the Humboldt on the west side of the Andes, which in turn generates major changes in the local meteorology and climate <ref type="bibr">[ 131.</ref> Excessive and severe rainstorms are the most disastrous consequences of El Niiio, and such storms can cause great damage to human life, property, crops, and animal life. The rainfall from such episodes causes the flooding of existing rivers, huaycos (mudslides), and the sudden creation of new rivers and lakes.</p><p>The 1982-1983 El Niiio has received wide attention for its severity <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>. In Peru alone, it was responsible for much loss of life, damage affecting over 80% of the highway system, railroad washouts, and material loss estimated in the billions of dollars. The heating of the ocean off the Peruvian coast during El Niiio periods has also caused the loss of much marine life. For example, the El Niiio of 1972 virtually destroyed the Peruvian anchovy fishing industry, which at that time represented a significant percentage of the world's protein supply with a catch of about 12 million tons per year <ref type="bibr">[l 11</ref>. Such destruction emphasizes the need to better understand the meteorological forces unleashed by this powerful ocean-air interaction.</p><p>Goldberg et a1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6]</ref> have investigated the mesoscale structure of severe rainfall events during the 1982-1983 period by examining daily data from 66 rainfall stations in the Chiura-Piura region of northwestem Peru. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows the location of this region, which was selected because it was most severely affected by the 1982-1983 El Niiio and because the data were highly reliable and com- These data support the study of rainfall characteristics over this localized region during El Niiio and non-El Nifio periods, as a function of elevation, geographic location, and time of year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatment of scattered data</head><p>The data from the rainfall stations are typical of observational data that are scattered at irregular locations in two or three dimensions (i.e., data with no notion of connectivity or topology).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>200</head><p>Although such techniques preserve the fidelity of the data, they fail to impart qualitative information about the spatial characteristics of the measurements or the phenomena of which they represent discrete samples. Thus, the application of continuous realization techniques (e.g., surface deformation or contouring for two-dimensional data, volume rendering or surface extraction for three-dimensional data) is necessary. An intermediate step of defining a topological relationship between the locations of data to form a mesh structure is required. Conventional continuous realization techniques can then be applied to such a mesh. There is a long history of mathematical methods to create such meshes. Each method does change the data and their artifacts must be understood because they will carry through to the actual visualization. This discussion is only meant as a very brief introduction to the topic. <ref type="bibr">Nielson [8]</ref>   The simplest and quickest approach is to create a regular grid from the point data by nearest neighbor meshing -find the nearest point to each cell in the resultant grid and assign that cell the point's value as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>. Such a technique is valuable because it preserves the original data values and distribution of a grid after a coordinate transformation may have taken place on a collection of points. Although computationally inexpensive, the results may not be very suitable for qualitative display because of the preservation of the discrete spatial structure. An alternate approach that preserves the original data values involves imposing an unstructured grid dependent on the distribution of the scattered points. In two dimensions, this would be a method for triangulating a set of scattered points in a plane <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[2]</ref>. This technique first requires the Voronoi tesselation of the plane with a polygonal tile surrounding each of the scattered points. These tiles are such that the locus of all points within a particular tile are closer to the scattered point associated with that tile than they are to any other points in the set. A triangulation can then be constructed which is the dual of the Voronoi tesselation (i.e., connecting a line between every pair of points whose tiles share edges). This is known as Delauney triangulation and is illustrated in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> as applied to the rainfall stations. For a relatively random distribution of a small number of points such as these rainfall data, the application of continuous realization techniques to the triangulated mesh does not yield useful qualitative results. Consider <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 6</ref> , in which the mesh from <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> is pseudo-colored by amount of rainfall. The rendering process applies bilinear interpolation to the value at each node to determine the color of each pixel in the image. Although the original data are preserved, the sparseness of the points results in a pseudo-colored distribution that is difficult to interpret.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gridded</head><p>A potentially more appropriate method, and certainly one that is more accurate than nearest neighbor meshing, uses weighted averaging as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7</ref>. For any given cell in a grid, the weighted average of the n nearest values in the original data distribution spatially nearest to that cell is chosen. A weighting factor, wi = f(di), where di is the distance between the cell and the ith (i = 1 , ..., m) point in the original distribution, is applied to each of the n values.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implementation</head><p>The techniques described herein have been developed with the IBM Visualization Data Explorer (DX), a generalpurpose software package for scientific data visualization and analysis. It employs a data-flow-driven client-server execution model and is currently available on Unix workstations from Sun, Silicon Graphics, Hewlett-Packard, IBM, DEC and Data General <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref>. DX provides tools for operating on both scattered and gridded data. The DX Connect module performs the Delauney triangulation used in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figures 5 and 6</ref> while the Regrid module performs the weighted average interpolation used in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figures 8 , 9</ref> and 10.</p><p>The Regrid module provides independent control of the exponent of the weighting factor, the size of n and the radius of influence from each node of the grid within which to consider data points. In this case a radius of 0.36 degree (of latitude and longitude) was used. It should be noted that for each day of data, not all stations have rainfall measurements. This is NOT the same as a station reporting no rain. DX supports a notion of data invalidity. Hence, for any given day, only those stations having measurement are considered by both the Connect and Regrid modules in creating gridded versions of the data. The choice of modules that support continuous realization is independent of the use of Connect or Regrid even though they result in different mesh structures because these DX operations are polymorphic. These tools were used to create a DX application that supports the study of the rainfall data, which is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The detailed results of these analyses are presented by Goldberg et a1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6]</ref>. The data have shown that enhanced rainfall during El Niiio can be divided into two categories; first, a general increase in background levels over non-El Niiio periods and second, sporadic bursts of intense rainfall superimposed over the enhanced background levels (cf., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 3</ref>). It is these sporadic bursts which were most responsible for the great damage during the 1982-1983 El Nifio episode.</p><p>The data further show that the severe storms (or bursts) often originate near the Andean foothills and may be induced by the interaction of rainbands moving inland from the coast with mountain downslope winds. This is best shown with a time sequence during such an event. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures  12 and 13</ref> illustrate the distribution of rainfall for January 24-27, and May 19-22, 1983, respectively, when a severe series of storms took place. The gridding process described earlier is used to create a pseudo-colored mesh independently for each day. The mesh is deformed by the altitude at each node, which is determined from the same gridding process applied to the altitude of each station. This deformed surface gives a reasonable approximation of the topography in northwestern Peru, especially given the paucity of high-resolution elevation data for this region.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions and future work</head><p>The characteristic topography near regions such as Chulucanas (roughly in the center, cf., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 3, 11, 12  and 13</ref>), where such storms were observed to occur on a frequent basis, is ideal for the aforementioned interaction between the rainbands and the Andean foothills. The origin of the east-west rainbands near the north Peruvian coast is less clear but may be caused by low altitude wind surges, which are driven northward along the coast of Peru by a large and quasi-permanent high in the southeastern Pacific.</p><p>Investigation of the applicability of other methods of gridding scattered data will be considered for these and similar, but larger sets of meteorological data <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref>      </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>location of Peruvian Rainfall Stations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>is representative of a straightforward discrete realization of such data as a scatter plot to show the spatial distibution.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 3illustrates the temporal distribution for a single station.Rainpall (mm) i n Northwestern Pen. January 28</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>summarizes many of the methods in use today 1 [Day 3051, 1982 to June 30 [Day 1811. 1983: [January 1 = Doy 621)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Time History Plot of Rainfall Measurements at Chulucanas, Peru with January 26, 1983 Highlighted.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Nearest Neighbor Gridding.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>RalnfaU 0 Figure 5 .</head><label>05</label><figDesc>(mm) in Northwestmn Peru. January 28.1983 Longitude Ckgreea E.) k Delauney Triangulation of Rainfall Stations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>illustrates the case where n = 3. A common weight is w = d-2. These are variants of Shepards method [15]. For example, Renka [14] modified this approach with local adaptive surface fitting. Collectively, these methods are typically O[nlog(n)] in cost.Intermediate in quality and computational expense would be using linear instead of weighted averaging.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 .Longitude</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Weighted Average Gridding All methods in the aforementioned class do introduce aliasing or smoothing of the data to achieve a gridded structure. The form of the interpolation may also impart artifacts on the results depending on the relative spatial variability of the original data vs. how close the interpolant function may be able to model that structure. Given a goal of qualitative visualization, such artifacts may be acceptable.Figure 8shows a regular mesh with spacing of 0.04 degree (of latitude and longitude), onto which the rainfall data for January 26, 1983 has been gridded using d-2 weighting for n = 5. The mesh and the data locations have been similarly pseudo-colored. There is good, but NOT perfect correspondence between the original data values and that of the interpolated grid, sufficient for qualitative realization. From this grid isocontour lines of constant rainfall every 25 mm and a pseudo-colored image are created as shown inFigures 9 and 10, respectively. RBinfall (mm) In Nathwestern Peru January 28 1883</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, [31, 141, [51, P I , W I , U61 and H71.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Pseudo-Colored Rainfall Distribution from Delauney Triangulation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Averaging and Rainfall Stations. Pseudo-Colored Mesh from Weighted Figure 10. Pseudo-Colored Rainfall from Weighted Average Gridding of Stations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 1 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>User Interface of a DX-based Application for Studying Peruvian Rainfall Data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Rainfall Distribution in Northwestern Peru on January 24-27, 1983.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Rainfall Distribution in Northwestern Peru on May 19-22, 1983.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, Maryland.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smooth surface reconstruction from scattered data points</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Alfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mathematical Methods in Computer Aided Geometric Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="39" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Scattered Data Interpolation in Three or More Variables</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Method of Bivariate Interpolation and Smooth Surface Fitting for Irregularly Distributed Data Points</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Akima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Mathematical Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="148" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="1978-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiquadric Equations of Topography and Other Irregular Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1905" to="1915" />
			<date type="published" when="1971-03-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smooth Interpolation to scattered data by bivariate piecewise polynomials of odd degree</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H J</forename><surname>Gmelig-Meyling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pfluger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Aided Geometric Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characteristics of Extreme Rainfall Events in Northwestern Peru during the 1982-1983 El Niiio Period</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tisnado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Scofield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14225" to="14241" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Architecture for a Scientific Visualization System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Abram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Epstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gresh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcauliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;92</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scattered Data Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An interpolation method for estuarine and oceanographic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M E</forename><surname>Perillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Piccolo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers and Geosciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="813" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomalous El Niiio of 1982-1983</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Philander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<editor>Quinn, W. H., D. 0. Zopf, K. S. Short and R. T. W.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">305</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Two-dimensional interpolation function for irregularly-spaced data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kuo-Yang ; Ramstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shepard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Historical Trends and Statistics of the Southern Oscillation, El Niiio, and Indonesian Droughts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1968" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="517" to="524" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings 23rd National ACM Conference</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gridding with continuous curvature splines in tension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wessel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bivariate Polynomial Natural Spline Interpolation to Scattered Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yue-Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lii-Tai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Migdal</forename><surname>Agishtein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rasmusson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Renka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
