<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">An Annotation System for 3D Fluid Flow Visualization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Maria</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Loughlin</surname></persName>
							<email>loughlin@crl.dec.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Cambridge Research Lab Digital Equipment Corporation One Kendall Sq</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02139</postCode>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Brown University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>1910, 02812</postCode>
									<settlement>Box, Providence</settlement>
									<region>RI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">An Annotation System for 3D Fluid Flow Visualization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Annotation is a key activity of data analysis. However, current data analysis systems focus almost exclusively on visualization. We propose a system which integrates annotations into a visualization system. Annotations are embedded in 30 data space, using the Post-it&apos; metaphor. This embedding allows contextualbased information storage and retrieval, and facilitates information sharing in collaborative envimnments. We provide a traditional database filter and a Magic Lens2 filter to create specialized views of the data. The system is customized for fluid flow applications, with features which allow users to store parameters of visualization tools and sketch 3 0 volumes. Post-it is a registered trademark of 3M. &apos;Magic Lens is a trademark of Xerox Corporation.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In a study to characterize the data analysis process, Springmeyer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref> observed scientists analyzing scientific data. They found that recording results and histories of analysis sessions is a key activity of data analysis. Two types of annotating were observed: 0 recording, or preserving contextual information throughout an investigation 0 describing, or capturing conclusions of the analysis sessions.</p><p>Despite the importance of annotation, current systems for data analysis emphasize visualization and provide little or no annotation support. In this paper, we describe a system that supports annotation as an integrated part of a fluid flow visualization system. Unlike typical annotations on static 2D images, our system embeds annotations in 3D data space. This immersion makes it easy to associate user comments with the features they describe. To avoid clutter and data hiding, annotations are represented by graphical annotation markers that have associated information. Therefore, graphical attributes of the markers, such as size and color, can differentiate annotations with different functions, authors, etc.</p><p>Annotations can easily be added, edited and deleted. Also, many sets of annotations can simultaneously be loaded into a visualization. This allows scientists, collaborating on a data set, to use annotations as a form of communication, as well as a history of data analysis sessions. Annotation markers also aid scientists in navigating through the data space by providing landmarks at interesting positions. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1(a)</ref>-(c) show the visualization environment, annotation markers, and the annotation content panel. <ref type="bibr">Figure l(d)</ref> shows a Magic Lens filter which hides the annotation markers and widget handles. The implementation has been applied to three-dimensional Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) applications. However, the techniques can be used in visualization systems of many disciplines. The design can also be extended to 3D stereo and virtual-reality environments.</p><p>This paper is organized in six sections. Section 2 reviews previous approaches to annotation. Section 3 describes design guidelines for annotation systems. Section 4 details our implementation of annotation within a visualization system. In the last two sections, we discuss possible future work and conclusions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Background</head><p>Scientific visualization systems provide little, if any, support for annotation. For example, the Application Visualization System (AVS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref> and the Flow Analysis Software Toolkit (FAST) <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref>, two software environments for visualizing scientific data, facilitate attachment of labels to static 2D images. These systems also allow a user to record and playback a sequence of interactions with the visualization. This support is useful for generating presentations from the data, but does not facilitate the recording and describing operations observed by Springmeyer et al.</p><p>Outside the scientific visualization domain, annotations have been integrated in different applications.</p><p>MacDraw, a 2D paint program, introduced a notes feature, which allows static 2D annotations using the Post-it metaphor. Media View <ref type="bibr">[ll]</ref>, a multi-media publication system, allows annotations in all media components including text, line art, images, sound, video, and computer animations. The format of annotations has been expanded, but their use is still limited to presentation of information in a static environment. Document annotation is used as a means of communication in the Wang Laboratories multi-media communication system, Freestyle <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref>. Freestyle's multimedia messages are based on images, including screen snapshots and hand-drawn sketches. Freestyle advances the concept of annotations as communicators, but does not address the issues of clutter and management of annotations in the environment.</p><p>Verlinden e t al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> developed an annotation system to explore communication in Virtual Reality (VR) environments. In general, annotation in immersive VR systems is restricted, as the user must interrupt the session to interact with objects in the real world, such as notebooks and computer monitors. Verlinden's system overcomes this problem by embedding verbal annotations in the VR space. The annotations are represented as visual 3D markers. When the user activates a marker, the verbal message stored with that marker is played. This system is unique in that it embeds annotations in 3D scenes, but it is limited to verbal annotations and provides no support for annotation filtering. It also limits annotations to a fixed position in a time-based environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Design Issues</head><p>We have extracted, both from the Springmeyer et al. study and from our own experience with scientific visualization, a set of three design guidelines that seem appropriate for an annotation system. These guidelines, discussed below, formed the basis for the design of our system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Guideline 1:</head><p>To support ongoing recording of contextual information, an annotation system must be an integral part of a visualization system. Effective placement and storage of annotations are required.</p><p>Traditionally, annotations to scientific visualizations are recorded on paper or in electronic files, and both the dataset and the files are labeled to mark their association. This separation of data and annotations means that 'some effort is required to find the data features described by annotations. The 3D data space of many scientific applications provides the context in which annotations should be placed. Recording annotations in this space capitalizes on a human's ability to locate information based on its spatial location.</p><p>However, inserting annotations in the data space creates an immediate conflict between the annotation and visualization functions: both compete for screen territory. We do not wish to impose restrictions on the amount of information that can be recorded. At the same time, we do not wish the annotations to obscure data, since information is contained in the data itself. Our approach is to decompose an annotation into 0 an annotation marker, or small geometric object that identifies the position of the annotation in the data space 0 an annotation content in which a user stores information.</p><p>By clicking on a marker, a user can expand the associated annotation to read or edit its content. Separating the annotation's content from the annotation marker in this way allows direct insertion of arbitrarily large annotations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Guideline 2:</head><p>Annotations must be powerful enough to capture information considered important by the user.</p><p>There are different types of information. Tanimoto <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref> distinguishes between data (raw figures and measurements), information (refined data which may answer the users' questions) and knowledge (information in context). Similarly, Bertin <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> considers information as a relationship which can exist between elements, subsets or sets. The broader the relationship, the higher the level of information.</p><p>In our annotation system, we provide support for different levels of information in two ways. First, within each annotation, scientists can record both numerical and textual details, and high-level information specific to fluid flow. This is discussed in section 4.4. Second, the system supports hierarchically organized annotations. The hierarchical structure allows scientists to record facts in separate annotations, and group related annotations in sets that describe broader observations.</p><p>Although some data, such as date of creation and author, are likely to be relevant to all applications, it is possible that knowledge can be captured only when an annotation system is customized for a specific application. The customization would ensure that annotations can represent information relevant in the context of the application. For example, if the data of a particular application is time-varying, the annotation system should provide time-varying annotations that can track the features being described.</p><p>Guideline 3: The user interface (UI) of an annotation system will play a key role in determining its acceptance (or lack thereof) by scientists.</p><p>We considered many established U1 rules <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref> and designed our annotation system accordingly. One rule states that a U1 should allow users to work with minimal conscious attention to its tools. We achieve this goal by using a direct manipulation interface, that is, an interface in which the objects that can be manipulated are represented physically. For example, the volume of data affected by the Magic Lens filter can be controlled directly by moving and resizing the physical representation of the lens. Another design rule states that an interface should provide feedback, e.g., on the current settings of domain variables. In our system, annotation markers give visual feedback on the location of annotations, and marker geometry gives feedback on annotation content.</p><p>Because the geometric data space of fluid flow applications has three dimensions, we considered design issues specific to 3D graphical user interfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. One issue is the complexity introduced by 3D viewing projections, visibility determination, etc. A second issue is that the degrees of freedom in the 3D world are not easily specified with common hardware input devices. A third issue is that a 3D interface can easily obscure itself. We use guidelines outlined by Snibbe et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> to deal with these problems. For example, we provide shadows, constrained to move in a plane, to simplify positioning of annotation markers (see section 4.3.2). We provide feedback on the orientation of the data by optionally drawing the principal axes and planes. We also ensure that annotations do not obscure data, by making it easy for a user to change the viewpoint and resize or hide annotation markers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Implementation</head><p>This section describes the implemented annotation system. We first set the context by describing fluid flow visualization and the development environment.</p><p>Then we discuss the main components of the annotation system: the annotation markers, support for information capture, and interaction techniques.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Fluid Flow Visualizations</head><p>Computational fluid dynamics (CFD) uses computers to simulate the characteristics of flow physics. Computed flow data is typically stored as a 3D grid of vector and scalar values (e.g., velocity, temperature, and vorticity values), which are static in a steady flow, and change over time in an unsteady flow. CFD visualization tools allow a scientist to examine the characteristics of the data with 3D computer displays.</p><p>Interaction with the visual representation is essential in the exploration and analysis of the data, and has three goals: feature identification, scanning, and probang <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>. Feature identification techniques help find flow features over the entire domain, and give the scientist a feel for the position of interesting parts of the flow volume. Scanning techniques are used to interactively search the domain, by varying one or more parameters, through space or through scalar and vector field values. Probing techniques are localized visualization tools, typically used to gather quantitative information in the final step of investigating a flow feature.</p><p>The Computer Graphics Group a t Brown University has developed a flow visualization system, to study modes of interaction with flow tools. The annotation system was built as part of this visualization system. This provided a test-bed for techniques to integrate visualization and annotation functionality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">The Development Environment</head><p>The annotation system was developed using C++ and FLESH, an object oriented animation and modeling scripting language <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>. The FLESH objects defined for the annotation system include annotation markers, lenses, and filters. Some of these FLESH classes have corresponding C++ classes, in which data is stored and compute-intensive operations performed. This allows us to benefit from the power of an interpreted interactive prototyping system and the efficiency of a compiled language.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Annotation Markers</head><p>Annotations are represented in the 3D data space by small geometric markers. Each marker has an associated content which the user can edit a t any time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">Marker Graphical A t t r i b u t e s</head><p>The geometry of a marker gives visual feedback on the content of the annotation. In the fluid flow visualizations system, the user can define annotation keywords (e.g., plume, vortex), and select a geometry to associate with each keyword. Then, when the user assigns a keyword to a n annotation in the system, the annotation's marker takes the associated shape. It is likely that other mappings between graphical attributes of markers and annotation content would also be useful. For example, the color saturation of a marker could depend on the age or priority of the annotation.</p><p>The graphical attributes of annotations are also user-customizable. The size and color of all markers in one level of hierarchy can be changed. We predict that this feature would be useful if many scientists work collaboratively on a data set, and each scientist defines a unique color and size for his markers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Marker Behavior</head><p>Since the function of a marker is simply to identify points of interest in the visualization, its behavior is quite simple. A marker is created when the user presses the annotation push-button. It appears at the point on which the user is focussed, making it easy for the user to position it near the feature of interest.</p><p>Using the mouse, a scientist can translate and rotate markers. He can also project interactive shadows of the marker on the planes defined by the principal axes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>. Each shadow is constrained to move in the plane in which it lies. If a user moves a shadow, the marker moves in a parallel plane. This constrained translation helps to precisely position a marker.</p><p>Markers can be highlighted in response to a filter request. In the current system, the color of a marker changes to a bright yellow when highlighted. This simple approach seems adequate.</p><p>Since the features of unsteady fluid flows change over time, we would like the annotation describing a particular feature to follow the feature's movement in the visualization. The current annotation system provides partial support for this by allowing the user to specify the position of an annotation at any number of points in time. The annotation markers then linearly interpolate between the specified positions in time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Knowledge Stored</head><p>Our annotations can store generic information, as well as information specific to fluid flow applications. The generic information includes keyword, textual summary and description, author, and date. We consulted with fluid flow experts to understand how the information content of annotations could be customized for fluid flow applications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1">Parameters of Visualization Tools</head><p>One of the additions to the annotation system suggested by the fluid flow experts results from the interactive nature of fluid flow analysis. As described earlier, a scientist must insert flow visualization tools (such as streamlines and iso-surfaces) in the data space to see the underlying data. Much time is spent determining which tools most effectively highlight a feature, and positioning and orienting both the tools and viewpoint to best show off the feature being described.</p><p>To support this activity, our concept of an annotation was expanded to include parameters of flow visualization tools. When a user wishes to store the parameters of a set of tools, he or she presses a button to indicate that a set of tools is being saved, and then clicks on the tools of interest. The time-varying location, orientation, size, and other parameters of the tools are saved with the annotation. This can be repeated any number of times for different groupings of tools with different parameters. When an annotation is restored, the user is presented with a list of all saved sets of tools, and can recover each set of tools to see how they illustrate the annotated feature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.2">3D Volume Descriptions</head><p>It also became obvious that annotation markers, which are appropriate for locating point features in a visualization, are not sufficient for CFD applications. Fluid flows contain volume features, such as vortices (masses of flow with a whirling or circular motion) and plumes (mobile columns of flow). We therefore allow users to associate an annotation with a volume of the data space, rather than a single point in the space.</p><p>To specify a volume, the user positions "pegs" that define the region's extreme vertices. The convex hull of the pegs is computed using the quickhull algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and is rendered in either wireframe or transparent mode. Vertices can be added, deleted and moved, and the volume redrawn repeatedly. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> shows a volume which has been defined in this way.</p><p>This implementation provides a simple way to draw volumes. However, since it uses a convex hull, certain shapes, such as a 3D "L" shape, cannot be sketched. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Future Work</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Retrieving the Annotations</head><p>Effective information retrieval and communication requires that a user can easily identify annotations relating to a specific topic, by a specific author, etc.</p><p>The system facilitates such data filtering in two ways.</p><p>First, a traditional database filter allows users to specify selection criteria (such as the annotation author or keyword) via a Motif panel. Markers of annotations that satisfy the search criteria are highlighted.</p><p>A second filter uses the Magic Lens metaphor introduced by Bier et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. A Magic Lens filter is a rectangular frame, placed in front of the visualization, that appears as if it moves on a sheet of glass between the cursor and the display. The lens performs some function on the application objects behind it.</p><p>Four functions are defined for the lens in the annotation system. The first sets the color of all objects, except annotation markers, to gray. This helps users find markers in a cluttered scene. The second displays only annotations that satisfy the criteria specified in the Motif database filter. The third lens function hides all annotation markers behind the lens. Finally, the default function hides all annotation markers and all interaction handles on the visualization tools behind the lens. Other lens functions could be defined; for example, a lens could remove all fluid flow tools except those in the user-sketched volume behind the lens.</p><p>We believe that the Magic Lens filter alleviates the problem of visualization and annotation functions sharing the same screen space. Using the lens, a scientist can choose either to tightly integrate the two functions or to focus exclusively on either visualization or annotation.</p><p>The work described in this paper could be expanded in a number of ways.</p><p>For the fluid flow application, the facility for recording visualization tool parameters could be extended to record view parameters. Annotations could also become more active in the data investigation process. For example, annotation markers could be used as seed points for automatic flow feature-characterization code. The output of the feature-characterization code (i.e., specifications of the feature found) could then be added to the annotation content. Featurecharacterization code could also be used to improve support for time-varying annotations. If the location of an annotation marker were constrained to the feature's position (as found by feature-characterization code), the marker would follow the movement of the feature over time.</p><p>We would also like to implement annotations in other applications and environments. For example, virtual reality environments pose many new research problems. User studies would have to be performed to determine which annotation modalities would be appropriate in this space. If textual annotations were appropriate, we would have to determine where to place the text: floating in space near the marker, or on 2D panels which exist in the virtual space, or perhaps in some other place. New interaction mechanisms for annotation markers and filters should also be developed.</p><p>Finally, we would like to expand the scope of annotations. Springmeyer et al. noted that scientists record their interactions with visualization systems. Perhaps the annotation system could help in recording and examining these edit trails. Also, scientists routinely compare different data sets. The current annotation system could be redesigned to fit in the context of more than one data set.</p><p>We hope that further experience with the current system and its extension to other applications and environments will allow us to evaluate our design guidelines, and develop principles for customization of a general-purpose annotation system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusion</head><p>The importance of annotation and the lack of annotation support in data analysis tools led us to develop a system that integrates annotation and visualization. We hope our system will help scientists by 0 storing annotations with the correct data set 0 providing powerful filters to sort annotations 0 making it easy to relate a comment to a data feature (both are located in the 3D data space) 0 giving team members ready access to the decisions and judgements of other scientists 0 reducing session setup time by easy restoration of visualization tools 0 providing a means of communication between collaborating scientists.</p><p>Initial feedback from scientists indicates that the integration of annotation and visualization facilitates the ongoing recording activity observed by Springmeyer et al. At the same time, the ability to group and filter annotations supports the organization of analysis conclusions, i.e., the describing activity.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The visualisation and annotation system.(See color plates, page CP-31.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>A volume defined as the convex hull of pegs.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The authors thank the members of the Graphics Group at Brown and the Visualization group at CRL for their support. The paper is based on the Master's thesis of the first author, whose attendance at Brown University was made possible by Digital Equipment Corporation's Graduate Engineering Education Program. The work was supported in part by grants from Digital Equipment Corporation, NSF, DARPA, IBM3, NCR4, Sun5, and HP6.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast: A multiprocessed environment for visualization of computational fluid dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bancroft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Merritt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Plessel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kelaita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Globus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. First IEEE Conference on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>First IEEE Conference on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The quickhull algorithm for convex hull</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Barber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dobkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Huhdanpaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-07" />
			<publisher>Geometry Center, U. Minnesota</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report GCG53</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">31BM is a registered trademark of the International Business &apos;NCR is a registered trademark of the NCR Corporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bertin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1981" />
			<publisher>Walter de Gruyter and Co</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sun is a registered trademark of Sun Microsystems. Inc. *HP is a registered trademark of the Hewlett-Packard</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toolglass and magic lenses: The seethrough interface</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Buxton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Derose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SIGGRAPH &apos;93</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH &apos;93</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional widgets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Conner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Snibbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Herndon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zeleznik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Symposium on Interactive</title>
		<meeting>Symposium on Interactive</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">0</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Graphics</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="188" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computer Graphics Principles and Practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>Addison Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Putting innovation to work: Adoption strategies for multimedia communication systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Francik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rudman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization in computational fluid dynamics:a case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Haimes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Second IEEE Conference on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>Second IEEE Conference on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="397" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Herndon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Interactive shadows. UIST Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-11" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Programming in flesh</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer Science, Brown University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mediaview, a general multimedia digital publication system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using deformations to explore 3d widget design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Snibbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Herndon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Conner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SIGGRAPH &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH &apos;92</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="352" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A characterization of the scientific data analysis process</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Springmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Blattner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Max</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Second IEEE Conference on V isualization</title>
		<meeting>Second IEEE Conference on V isualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="352" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Elements of Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tanimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Computer Science Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The application visualization system: A computational environment for scientific visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Upson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Voice annotation: Adding verbal information to virtual environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Verlinden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bolter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Mast</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. European Simulation Symposium</title>
		<meeting>European Simulation Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="69" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
