<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Objective Observer-Relative Flow Visualization in Curved Spaces for Unsteady 2D Geophysical Flows</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Rautek</surname></persName>
							<email>peter.rautek@kaust.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Matej</forename><surname>Mlejnek</surname></persName>
							<email>matej.mlejnek@kaust.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Johanna</forename><surname>Beyer</surname></persName>
							<email>jbeyer@seas.harvard.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jakob</forename><surname>Troidl</surname></persName>
							<email>jakob.troidl@googlemail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hanspeter</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
							<email>pfister@seas.harvard.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Theußl</surname></persName>
							<email>thomas.theussl@kaust.edu.sa</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Hadwiger</surname></persName>
							<email>markus.hadwiger@kaust.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">King Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Visual Computing Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>23955-6900</postCode>
									<settlement>Thuwal</settlement>
									<country key="SA">Saudi Arabia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Harvard University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Visual Computing Center, Thuwal, Saudi Arabia, and TU</addrLine>
									<postCode>23955-6900</postCode>
									<settlement>Wien, Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Core Labs, Thuwal</addrLine>
									<postCode>23955-6900</postCode>
									<country key="SA">Saudi Arabia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Objective Observer-Relative Flow Visualization in Curved Spaces for Unsteady 2D Geophysical Flows</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">received xx xxx. 201x; accepted xx xxx. 201x.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Flow visualization</term>
					<term>observer fields</term>
					<term>frames of reference</term>
					<term>objectivity</term>
					<term>symmetry groups</term>
					<term>intrinsic covariant derivatives</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Fig. 1. Observer motion relative to the time evolution of features: Hurricane Isabel in a time-dependent global wind data set. (Bottom left) The actual path of Isabel (from NHC/Wikipedia). (Top left) Our observer field u automatically follows the motion of Isabel without explicit tracking of its path. The shown path is simply a path line of u. (Right) Feature-relative visualization, focused on Isabel in the center, enabling analysis of its time evolution &quot;in place.&quot; The hurricane appears steady, with the Earth moving inversely underneath.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Flow visualization is concerned with velocity vector fields that describe fluid motion. Since the definition of velocity is the infinitesimal change of spatial position with respect to time, this description depends on the notion of what is considered to be "the same position" over time. Mathematically, this is the notion of a frame of reference, or an observer. A frame of reference is a way of referencing positions in space over time, i.e., a time-dependent transformation of space, with respect to which derivatives are to be taken. (Not an observer as an actual person.)</p><p>For this reason, flow visualization as well as the computation of flow features, such as vortices, in general inherently depend on the chosen frame of reference. An important related concept therefore is invariance with respect to certain changes of reference frame. Galilean invariance <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> refers to frame changes with constant relative velocity, which is inherently related to inertial frames in physics <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[63]</ref>. Objectivity <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> considers frame changes with time-dependent translations and rotations. The standard definition used in visualization and continuum mechanics is the one of Truesdell and Noll <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, which has received significant attention for flow fields since the work of Haller <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. A major basic limitation of this definition, however, is that it is given only for Euclidean space and cannot be used in general curved spaces.</p><p>One area where objectivity is particularly relevant is that of geophysical flows, such as in the Earth's atmosphere or oceans. The natural reference frame, in this case, is rotating <ref type="bibr">[51, p.14]</ref>, i.e., non-inertial, and Galilean invariance is not well-suited. As is common in flow visualization, we only consider motions by themselves (kinematics), not the forces generating them (dynamics). We can therefore consider accelerating reference frames just as easily as inertial frames, because the differences in the forces acting are irrelevant. For example, in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> we consider an airplane as an observer measuring motion relative to its own reference frame. Naturally, this does not change a phenomenon such as a hurricane, but it does change all relative velocity measurements.</p><p>Although the Earth's surface is embedded in a flat 3D space (ignoring relativistic effects), it is beneficial to be able to view the domain where a geophysical flow field is defined from an intrinsic, curved 2D perspective. This not only allows for simplified computations in 2D instead of in 3D, or considering different altitude or depth layers separately; it also corresponds perfectly to the reference frame of circular orbits, such as those of satellites or airplanes moving along great circles around the Earth, as shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. For visualization purposes, it is also common to visualize spherical layers. Moreover, scientists have even discovered that some geophysical fluid systems, such as aspects of our atmosphere or even that of Jupiter <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56]</ref>, can sometimes be modeled in a more realistic way in 2D than in 3D, because the atmosphere is so much thinner than wide. For this reason, it can be crucial to perform computations in 2D, because the physical behavior of 2D turbulence can be radically different from 3D turbulence <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref>.</p><p>With this motivation, we develop general techniques for flow visualization and computation of flow features in curved spaces. For practical relevance, we illustrate results for geophysical flows on spheres. We generalize the notion of observer fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> from Euclidean space to curved spaces. This enables "following" flow features such as vortices, and visualizing the corresponding time evolution of scalar and vector attributes "in place." For example, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 1</ref> shows hurricane Isabel <ref type="bibr">(2003)</ref> in a time-dependent global wind simulation. Our computed observer field automatically follows the motion of the hurricane. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 1 (right)</ref> shows feature-relative visualization, where the observer field makes the motion of Isabel appear to be steady. This enables "feature-centric" analysis, without having to explicitly follow the motion of the hurricane.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Observer Fields and Observed Time Derivatives</head><p>An observer field u(x,t) is a time-dependent velocity field that, instead of describing the motion of particles, describes the motion of a continuous field of observers <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. The path lines of the observer field correspond to the world lines <ref type="bibr">[3, p.8]</ref> of individual spatial locations in the space of an observer that are viewed as being "the same point" over time. If an observer field u describes a rigid motion, it is a Killing vector field <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>. Figs. 2 (a,b,c) depict three time steps of observer fields on a sphere. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref> shows one example input vector field v describing a simple rotating vortex, as it is seen by four different observer fields u.</p><p>The observed time derivative corresponding to a given u(x,t) measures the differential change of an arbitrary input field v(x,t) with respect to the observer motion described by u. This concept was introduced in the context of Euclidean space <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. We define this time derivative, on any differential manifold M, as the differential operator</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">D Dt := ∂ ∂t + L u .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>Here, L u denotes the Lie derivative <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr">Ch. 4]</ref> with respect to the observer field u. In order to "steadify" an input vector field v, e.g., to be able to compute and follow features, we compute observer fields u by minimizing the derivative (D/Dt)(v − u). If <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref> is interpreted as showing four different input fields v, the observer-relative visualization with respect to the optimized field u will always look like <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref> (d).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Mathematical Framework for Curved Spaces</head><p>We develop a novel fully intrinsic mathematical framework for 2D flow visualization and feature computation in curved spaces. Our major contribution is the generalization of a prior Euclidean framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> for the objective computation of observer fields to curved spaces. We compute these fields by solving an energy minimization problem, making unsteady input flows as steady as possible. We first introduce a generalized notion of objectivity for curved spaces. While equivalent to the standard one in Euclidean space <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, ours is fully intrinsic, using the concepts of continuous symmetry groups and group actions on  <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. Observers in curved spaces. An airplane (blue path) and a satellite (red path) are moving relative to the Earth. At each instant in time, with respect to the Earth's surface both fly in the direction of a geodesic (a great circle). Considering the observer (airplane or satellite) as stationary, the instantaneous relative motion of the Earth is a Killing vector field on the sphere, in the opposite direction (right). (a) The Killing field for the satellite is a steady field (assuming the satellite ground track is always the same geodesic); (b,c) The field for the airplane is unsteady: Each instant in time is determined by a different tangential velocity.</p><p>manifolds from mathematical physics. From general symmetry groups, we specialize to observer transformations modeled as elements of the isometry group of a manifold M. To simplify computations, we work with infinitesimal isometries, given explicitly by vector fields on M.</p><p>To be able to achieve this, we derive the differential geometric operators needed to compute observer fields in curved spaces: (1) Observed time derivatives; (2) Approximate Killing fields; and <ref type="formula">3</ref>The velocity gradient tensor ∇v as a covariant derivative <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr">Ch. 9]</ref>, instead of the Jacobian that is commonly used in flow visualization.</p><p>Methodology. Our generalization of objectivity and observer fields to curved spaces requires mathematical machinery from Riemannian geometry and mathematical physics that is not common in the flow visualization literature. For this reason, we summarize background and our notation in the beginning, and provide extensive supplementary appendixes. These techniques enable deriving a powerful generalization of previous flow visualization techniques from flat space to curved spaces in a clean and intrinsic manner. We believe that this powerful methodology can be very useful for flow visualization in general, and that it is worthwhile to introduce it to the flow visualization literature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>The framework presented here extends the work of Hadwiger et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> from Euclidean space R n to curved spaces, focusing on curved twomanifolds. We also model a collection of observers by an observer velocity field describing their motion, which we also compute by solving a least-squares problem such that (1) it is objective, and (2) the input flow field is as steady as possible relative to the observer field. However, the generalization to curved spaces is conceptually and technically challenging. We propose a fully intrinsic generalization, working "inside" the curved space. This results in natural and efficient generalizations, and facilitates computing 2D observer fields via 2D optimization.</p><p>Flow visualization on curved surfaces. All major flow visualization techniques have been extended from flat space to curved surfaces. For example, LIC <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and variants <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60]</ref> have been extended to curved surfaces, either for parametric surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, by texturing triangle meshes <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62]</ref>, or by computing LIC in screen space <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36]</ref>. Image-based texture advection techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67]</ref> have been extended as well, such as image-based flow visualization on surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">68]</ref>. Image space techniques typically project vector fields from 3D to 2D screen space for visualization. We refer to the survey by Edmunds et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Texture atlases have also been used for flow visualization, for example flow charts <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. We similarly use multiple coordinate charts.</p><p>Vector field design on surfaces. We extensively use differential properties of manifolds and vector fields. These are particularly important for computations with vector fields on surfaces, such as vector field design on surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b70">71]</ref>. We refer to the survey of Peng and Laramee <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>. We would like to particularly point out the use of geodesic polar maps and parallel transport along geodesics in the work of Palacios and Zhang <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref>. The notion of covariant derivative, which we employ in our work, is inherently related to parallel transport. Covariant derivatives have been used for mesh processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> and computing vector <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> and direction <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">[69]</ref> fields on surfaces. An important focus is often their discretization on triangle meshes <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, e.g., by using discrete exterior calculus <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. We discretize on triangle vertices in 2D charts, and particularly focus on fully intrinsic 2D computations.</p><p>Interpolation. We use standard barycentric interpolation in triangles. However, spherical barycentric coordinates, i.e., mean value coordinates on the sphere, could also be used for better interpolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.</p><p>Killing vector fields on (Riemannian) manifolds <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> correspond to their infinitesimal isometries. Their flows correspond to the intrinsic isometries of a manifold. Basics of Killing fields for curved surfaces are discussed by Ben-Chen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and by Solomon <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref>; a more advanced treatment is given by Petersen <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>. Approximate Killing fields have been used to compute approximate intrinsic isometries of curved surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, or to design approximate Killing fields on meshes <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. As-rigid-as-possible shape interpolation methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> work directly with isometries instead of with derivatives, and are computed extrinsically.</p><p>Observers. The concept of an observer as well as that of objectivity in Euclidean space has been recognized to be of importance in fluid mechanics <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> as well as in flow visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. A standard reference in continuum mechanics is Truesdell and Noll <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, whose definition for objectivity in Euclidean space is used often <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>.</p><p>Vortex detection and frame invariance. Vortices are an important topic in fluid mechanics <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> and in flow visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. Many vortex detection methods were originally defined for steady flow, such as Sujudi and Haimes <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[61]</ref>, and were later extended to unsteady flow <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>. Galilean invariance of these critera is considered to be important <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. Several known methods are Galilean-invariant, such as Weinkauf et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">[70]</ref>, or the method of Bujack et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The latter jointly considers multiple observers for 2D flow fields. Specific vortex detectors have been developed to be objective by design <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>. Günther et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref> present objective methods for Euclidean space that are generic by building on optimization, making non-objective vortex detectors objective. Other kinds of invariance have been defined, particularly for flow fields, such as rotation invariance <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, or hyper-objective vortices <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</p><p>Flow decomposition methods, such as variants of the Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>, can also be used to remove background flow, corresponding to the harmonic component <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. These decompositions can be computed on curved surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">[64]</ref>. However, they apply only to time-independent fields, or alternatively they have to be applied to each time step individually, without considering time derivatives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">BACKGROUND AND NOTATION</head><p>Our intrinsic framework enables all computations, most importantly the optimization of observer fields, to be 2D for curved surfaces, instead of requiring 3D ambient space computations. We perform all computations in an atlas of 2D coordinate charts <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 4</ref>). This also simplifies visualization computations on curved surfaces, by working directly in charts, for example for path line integration or Line Integral Convolution (LIC), as depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref>. However, already a surface as simple as a sphere cannot be covered by a single chart. All computations in charts therefore need to be independent of the choice of coordinates. We ensure this invariance by using general tensor methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, with the corresponding transformation rules for transitions between charts. </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">M → T M, x → v(x).<label>(2)</label></formula><p>T M refers to the tangent bundle of M, the manifold of all tangent spaces of M, and a vector field is also referred to as a section of T M. Most important, v(x) is an element of the tangent space at x, denoted by T x M.</p><p>Where no confusion arises, we also denote a single vector v(x) by v.</p><p>Coordinate charts map open subsets U ⊂ M of an n-dimensional manifold M to R n . Coordinates on a curved manifold M are thus not given by coordinate vectors, which is only possible in linear spaces, but for each chart by n coordinate functions {x i }, with each x i : U → R. For example, for n = 2, the coordinate functions</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">x 1 , x 2 , or, sometimes, u, v. In contrast, basis vectors live in each tangent space T x M, at x ∈ M.</formula><p>Bases. Vectors are geometric objects independent of any chosen basis. In order to refer a vector v to a basis, we expand it in components as v = v i e i , where {e i } is a basis for T x M, and, in general, the T x M at different x ∈ M have different bases. We employ the Einstein summation convention <ref type="bibr">[22, p.59]</ref>, implying summation over indices occurring twice (once "upstairs" and "downstairs" each), e.g.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">v i e i := ∑ i v i e i .</formula><p>Dual bases. We will also need the concept of a dual basis {ω i }, where ω i (e j ) = δ i j , with the Kronecker delta δ i j = 1 if i = j, and zero otherwise. Each ω i is a covector, or 1-form, which is a linear function mapping a vector to a scalar. The dual basis {ω i } reads off the components of a vector v referred to</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">{e i }, such that v = ω i (v) e i .</formula><p>Metrics. Lengths and angles of vectors are determined in an intrinsic manner by defining a (Riemannian) metric g on M <ref type="bibr">[19, p.35]</ref>, which is a second-order tensor field defining an inner product v, w := g(v, w) on each T x M, varying smoothly over M. The vector norm is then defined as v := v, v 1/2 . Computations with g can use components g i j := e i , e j referred to {e i }, computing v, w as g i j v i w j . We also extensively use covariant derivatives compatible with a given metric g.</p><p>Velocity gradients. An important derived quantity of a velocity vector field v is the velocity gradient tensor field ∇v. In flow visualization, ∇v is often seen as a Jacobian ∂ j v i of partial derivatives in Cartesian coordinates. However, these coordinates do not exist in curved spaces, and We note that even in flat R 2 with polar coordinates, ∂ j v i is not a tensor. This has important implications, such as that a tensor that vanishes in one coordinate system must vanish in all coordinate systems <ref type="bibr">[24, p.82</ref>]. This is not true for ∂ j v i , and thus the Jacobian behaves only as it should in special cases, such as by restriction to Cartesian tensors <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr">Ch.2]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">in general ∇v = (∂ j v i ) e i ⊗ ω j , since ∂ j v i is not tensorial [22, p.241].</formula><p>Our framework requires a more general definition of ∇v as the covariant derivative ∇ j v i , which is standard in mathematical physics. However, we have found no explicit use of this concept in the flow visualization literature. We derive this notion for our purposes in Sec. 6.</p><p>Approximate observer Killing fields. In general, an observer field is allowed to be given by an arbitrary vector field u. However, it makes sense to restrict the motion described by u to be "as rigid as possible." We therefore optimize observer fields such that they correspond to approximately isometric deformations, i.e., to "almost-rigid" motions. In the same vein as Hadwiger et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, we minimize the rate-ofdeformation tensor of u. However, in curved spaces M this computation requires using the covariant derivative ∇u, and the metric g on M.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">OBSERVERS IN CURVED SPACES</head><p>The first crucial notion for us to define is the meaning of an observer in a curved space. In analogy with the standard notion of observer transformations in Euclidean space <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, it is natural to consider observer transformations to in general be time-dependent distance-preserving transformations of the underlying space, i.e., time-dependent isometries. In the general case, however, we have to consider the intrinsic isometries of a smooth manifold M with metric g, 1 corresponding to geodesic distances instead of Euclidean distances. Generally stated,</p><p>Remark. We employ a (non-relativistic) concept of frames of reference postulating that all observers agree on the pairwise spatial geodesic distances of events happening at the same time, and all observers also agree on the time difference between events (i.e., time is absolute).</p><p>Observer transformations are therefore time-dependent intrinsic distance-preserving transformations. Mathematically, we model these observer transformations as paths t → g(t) ∈ G, through a Lie group G, chosen as the isometry group G := Isom(M) of the manifold M with metric g. In our framework, we often also work directly with the derivatives of g(t), forming the corresponding path t → X(t) ∈ g through the Lie algebra g = isom(M), the Lie algebra of infinitesimal isometries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Observers on the Sphere</head><p>Figs. 2 and 5 illustrate this idea for M = S 2 , the standard two-sphere. The motion of the Earth relative to a fixed observer, such as the airplane in <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>, is given by a path of isometries t → g(t) ∈ SO(3), which here are different rotations of the Earth. At any instant in time t, the derivative of this path corresponds to a Lie algebra element X(t) ∈ so(3), which defines an infinitesimal isometry of M. However, X(t) is just an anti-symmetric matrix <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 5, bottom)</ref>. The specific corresponding infinitesimal isometry of the sphere is given by an isomorphism between so(3) and the Lie algebra of Killing vector fields on the sphere <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">(Fig. 5, top)</ref>. This isomorphism is mathematically described by a Lie algebra action (see App. J). In this way, the infinitesimal isometry on the surface of the Earth is the Killing vector field x(t) corresponding to X(t). At each point x ∈ M, this gives a relative velocity vector x(x,t) ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5, top)</ref>. We also know that x describes an infinitesimal isometry of M, because ∇x, as the covariant derivative of x, is anti-symmetric. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> In fact, any Killing field x is uniquely determined by its value </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Observer Fields</head><p>Generalizing further from the concept of one observer, as one timedependent isometric transformation of space, we want to be able to describe an observer field-many observers-on a manifold M as a vector field u on M, where u does not necessarily correspond to an exact (infinitesimal) isometry. One of the most important properties of such an observer field u is that we can compute it such that it minimizes the observed time derivative (D/Dt)(v − u), given an arbitrary input vector field v, whose time-dependent behavior we want to "follow."</p><p>The second important property of an observer field u is that if u is indeed a Killing vector field, it in fact describes a single observer, as defined above. Typically, we want to optimize the vector field u such that it describes observers that are as similar as possible. We do this by quantifying how much (or how "fast," in terms of spatial distance) the observers differ from one global isometry, by computing the Killing energy of the vector field u over M. This is the integral M Eu dA.</p><p>(3)</p><p>The point-wise energy term Eu is given by Eq. 29. Eq. 3 is a scalar measure for how much u differs from an infinitesimal isometry on M. See Hadwiger et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> for a more detailed rationale in Euclidean space. In this work, we now generalize this concept to curved spaces. shows path lines following the motion of the hurricane over time. In this frame of reference, it is hard to compare features of the hurricane "in place," due to its motion. In contrast, the bottom row of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 6</ref> shows a visualization that is relative to an automatically computed observer field u(x,t), following the motion of the hurricane. Since now a "feature-centric" observer is used, the hurricane has become steady. (Now the Earth is moving, relative to the new observer, underneath the hurricane.) Path lines seeded at the same positions as before now clearly highlight the vortex of the hurricane.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Feature-Relative Visualization</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">OBJECTIVITY IN CURVED SPACES</head><p>Given a particular observer transformation t → g(t) ∈ G, it is natural to define that a tensor field is objective if it simply undergoes the same transformation as the observer. Because we model all possible observer transformations as paths through a continuous symmetry group G, i.e., a Lie group, we can now rigorously formulate a generalized concept of objectivity for arbitrary manifolds M in a fully intrinsic manner, using the concept of group action on M with a Lie group element g ∈ G.</p><p>We first summarize the definition of Truesdell and Noll <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[65]</ref>, which is standard in continuum mechanics <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>, but is restricted to Euclidean space. We then introduce our completely general definition that includes curved spaces, but is equivalent in Euclidean space. App. D derives the definition of Truesdell and Noll more generally, illuminating the correspondence between their approach and ours in more detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Objectivity in Euclidean space</head><p>Truesdell and Noll <ref type="bibr">[65, p.41]</ref> define objectivity with respect to a change of reference frame in R 3 via the distance-preserving transformation This entire definition depends on the domain being Euclidean: points are position vectors; the difference between two points is a vector; all tangent spaces are copies of R 3 with trivial parallel transport. This definition is therefore not valid for non-Euclidean (curved) manifolds.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">x * = c(t) + Q(t) x, t * = t − a.<label>(4)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Generalization of Objectivity</head><p>To generalize objectivity, we define this concept as a general notion of tensor fields being invariant with respect to a continuous symmetry group G, which is a Lie group. (Symmetry refers to a notion of being the same.) For example, if the group G is chosen as the isometry group of a (Riemannian) manifold, two tensor fields are "the same" if they are isometric. Two fields being symmetries of each other then means that there exists a group element g ∈ G, such that the transformation rules given below hold. Then, given any time-dependent observer transformation t → g(t) ∈ G, a given tensor field is objective if, for each fixed t, it simply follows the corresponding transformation g := g(t).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.1">Symmetry groups and group actions</head><p>Our notion of symmetry corresponds to the transformation behavior under a group action Φ, with a given Lie group element g ∈ G, where G is the chosen symmetry group. An action Φ, specifically a smooth left action, of a Lie group G on a manifold M, is a smooth map <ref type="bibr">[33, p.209</ref></p><formula xml:id="formula_7">] Φ : G × M → M, (g, x) → Φ(g, x),<label>(5)</label></formula><p>such that for every g ∈ G, the map</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">φ g : M → M, with φ g (x) := Φ(g, x), is a diffeomorphism.<label>(6)</label></formula><p>Here, we focus on the general use of group actions Φ in our context, and defer details to later sections. For now, it is sufficient to understand that the diffeomorphisms φ g will correspond to the flows of specific vector fields on M. These vector fields are generated by the action of the Lie algebra g of the Lie group G on M. See App. J for details. For example, if G is the group of all diffeomorphisms of M, these vector fields are all possible (smooth) vector fields on M. The important case for our framework is choosing the group G as the isometry group of M. The corresponding vector fields are then the Killing vector fields on M, whose flows correspond to the isometries of M. See Sec. 7.</p><p>To obtain a generalized definition of objectivity, a crucial property of the diffeomorphism φ g is that it enables us to use the corresponding differential, or pushforward. See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 7</ref>. The pushforward is a map</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">dφ g : T M → T M,<label>(7)</label></formula><p>where each (dφ g ) x at a point x ∈ M is a linear map</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">(dφ g ) x : T x M → T φg(x) M, v → (dφ g ) x (v).<label>(8)</label></formula><p>The notation <ref type="figure">(•)</ref> x means that the quantity in parentheses is located at x ∈ M, and T x M denotes the tangent space at x. We can simply imagine that the diffeomorphism φ g transforms curves on M, and the differential dφ g transforms their tangent vectors accordingly. See also App. U. In components, the map (dφ g ) x at any x ∈ M can be given by the corresponding n × n matrix. See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 7</ref> for the case of a sphere (n = 2).</p><p>Euclidean space. When φ g is an isometry of M = R 3 , the pushforward dφ g is a globally constant proper orthogonal (rotation) tensor Q, i.e., (dφ g ) x = Q, with the same Q at all x ∈ M. See O'Neill <ref type="bibr">[49, p.107]</ref>.</p><p>Curved spaces. In general, however, the linear map (dφ g ) x is different for different points x ∈ M. In components, each (dφ g ) x can still be given by a matrix, but it will be a different matrix for each point x ∈ M.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.2">Objective scalar fields</head><p>Being objective should mean invariant under transformation, which for scalar fields is trivial. We therefore define that a scalar field f : M → R on a manifold M is objective when, under any diffeomorphism φ g , given by the group action Φ of a symmetry group G, it transforms as</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">f * φ g (x) = f x .<label>(9)</label></formula><p>Abbreviated, we could write f * = f , but it is crucial to note that f * is evaluated at the point φ g (x), whereas f is evaluated at the point x.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.3">Objective vector fields</head><p>We now define that an arbitrary vector field v on a manifold M is objective (with respect to a given symmetry group G), if, under the corresponding group action Φ with any g ∈ G, it transforms as</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">(v * ) φg(x) = (dφ g ) x v .<label>(10)</label></formula><p>We emphasize that v * is an element of the tangent space T φg(x) M, whereas v is an element of T x M. Likewise, it is important to note that the differential (dφ g ) x is a linear map defined on T x M. We can say</p><p>Remark. A vector field is objective, if it is simply pushed forward by any diffeomorphism φ g , defined according to the group action Φ. This definition of objectivity is valid for any smooth manifold where a notion of (smooth) symmetry is defined by a (smooth) symmetry group G.</p><p>Abbreviated transformation rule. For brevity, we can define the action Φ, with g ∈ G, on any vector field v on M, by the differential in Eq. 8, and abbreviate the objectivity criterion of Eq. 10 simply as</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">v * = g v.<label>(11)</label></formula><p>However, it is crucial that the meaning of the transformation represented by g ∈ G in this shorthand notation is given by Eq. 10. In general, g cannot be mapped to the same globally defined matrix, corresponding to the pushforward dφ g , even though this is possible in the Euclidean case. Nevertheless, this abbreviated form makes it easy to see the analogy with the definition of Truesdell and Noll. In Euclidean space, the two are equivalent. See App. D for more details. Our definition, however, gives a well-defined notion of objectivity for arbitrary manifolds M.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.4">Objective tensor fields</head><p>The definition above for objective vectors generalizes to arbitrary tensor fields T, in the way that is derived in full in App. A. Here, we derive the common special case of a second-order tensor field S, interpreted as a linear map of vectors, i.e., S :</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">T M → T M, v → S(v)</formula><p>. Such a <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> 1 tensor field is objective, if under the group action Φ with g it transforms as</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">(S * ) φg(x) (v * ) = (dφ g ) x S (dφ g −1 ) φg(x) (v * ) .<label>(12)</label></formula><p>The pushforward dφ g −1 of the diffeomorphism φ g −1 maps v * from T φg(x) M to the corresponding v in T x M according to Eq. 10 (inverted), and then applies Eq. 10 again to S(v). φ g −1 is the inverse of φ g , meaning φ g −1 (φ g (x)) = φ g −1 g (x) = φ e (x) = x. As in Eq. 11, we can abbreviate</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">S * = g S g −1 .<label>(13)</label></formula><p>However, it is again crucial to note that the meaning of this rule is given by Eq. 12. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Fig. 7</ref> illustrates how the pushforwards of φ g and φ g −1 map tangent vectors between the tangent spaces T φg(x) M and T x M.</p><p>We note that to prove objectivity of the Killing operator K (Eq. 25), which we use for computing observer fields, the general definition of objectivity from App. A is required, since Ku is a 0 2 tensor (App. F.1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Objectivity for Intrinsic Isometries</head><p>To realize the notion of observer transformations as isometric transformations of the underlying space in the general mathematical framework given above, we now consider the group G := Isom(M), i.e., the isometry group of the manifold M. The group action Φ is an isometry, with respect to a given metric g, i.e., a smoothly varying inner product •, • , on M, if for all g ∈ G, and for any two vector fields v, w on M, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">(dφ g ) x (v), (dφ g ) x (w) φg(x) = v, w x .<label>(14)</label></formula><p>As a direct consequence of Eq. 14 holding for the map φ g , we get that for any vector field v that is objective according to Eq. 10, we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">v * φg(x) = v x .<label>(15)</label></formula><p>Infinitesimal isometries and Killing vector fields. Computationally, instead of working with isometries directly, we work with their derivatives, which are infinitesimal isometries, corresponding to the Killing fields on M. See Sec. 7. To describe Killing fields efficiently, we need the intrinsic velocity gradient tensor ∇v of a velocity field v on M.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">GENERAL VELOCITY GRADIENT TENSORS</head><p>For any smooth vector field v given on a manifold M, the velocity gradient tensor ∇v is a second-order tensor field on M that allows computing directional derivatives of the vector field v in any direction. In Cartesian coordinates, ∇v can simply be defined by partial derivatives ∂ j v i . However, this definition cannot be used for intrinsic computations on curved manifolds, because ∂ j v i is in general not a tensor.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Intrinsic Covariant Derivatives</head><p>The covariant derivative ∇v of a vector field v on a manifold M is a second-order tensor field on M, which, at any x ∈ M, maps an arbitrary vector x ∈ T x M to the derivative of the field v in the direction x, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">(∇v) x : T x M → T x M, x → ∇ x v = (∇v) x (x) .<label>(16)</label></formula><p>This notation means that the covariant derivative of a vector field v, evaluated in the direction x, is the vector ∇ x v, which we get by computing ∇v (x). We can refer ∇v to a basis {e i ⊗ ω j }, with ⊗ the tensor product, and write the components as n × n matrix ∇ j v i , with row and column indices i, j, respectively, and n the dimension of M, i.e., for a curved surface n = 2. However, unless the manifold M is flat and Cartesian or affine coordinates are used, </p><formula xml:id="formula_20">∇ j v i = ∂ j v i .</formula><formula xml:id="formula_21">∇ j v i := ∂ j v i + Γ i jk v k .<label>(17)</label></formula><p>In flat space with Cartesian or affine coordinates, all Christoffel symbols vanish <ref type="bibr">[24, p.72</ref>] (Γ i jk ≡ 0), but only in this special case is</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">∇ j v i = ∂ j v i . The Γ i</formula><p>jk determine the covariant derivatives of the basis vector fields {e i }, at each point x ∈ M, referred back to the same basis {e i } at x, i.e., ∇ e j e k = Γ i jk e i , and therefore Γ i jk = ω i ∇ e j e k .</p><p>We note that although Γ i jk comprises n 3 components, it is not a (thirdorder) tensor <ref type="bibr">[24, p.82]</ref>. In general, a connection needs to be chosen <ref type="bibr">[19, p.50]</ref>. We employ the Levi-Civita connection, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> which can be derived intrinsically from the metric of M <ref type="bibr">[22, p.229]</ref>. See App. O, Eq. O.10. Even more easily, if we know an immersion of M into an ambient space R m , as for a curved surface immersed in R 3 , we can obtain the Γ i jk as</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">Γ i jk =ω i ∂ jẽk .<label>(19)</label></formula><p>The tilde symbols denote ambient space (co)vectors, e.g., for M with n = 2 and ambient m = 3, {∂ jẽk } comprises four 3D vectors, and {ω i } comprises two 3D covectors. It is crucial that the {ω i } are chosen such that they correspond to orthogonal projection from R m onto the tangent plane of the surface. See App. Q for a complete calculation for a simple atlas of charts for the sphere. The Levi-Civita connection given by this choice of Γ i jk corresponds to the metric on M that is induced by the immersion of M into the ambient space R m <ref type="bibr">[19, p.39]</ref>. Crucially, however, the resulting Christoffel symbols are nevertheless intrinsic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">ISOMETRIES AND KILLING FIELDS IN CURVED SPACES</head><p>Our framework requires an efficient mathematical description of the intrinsic isometries of the manifold M. A powerful way to do this is to work with the derivatives of diffeomorphisms that are isometries, i.e., to consider infinitesimal isometries. These correspond to specific vector fields on the manifold M, which are called Killing vector fields.</p><p>A vector field u is a Killing vector field on M, if the flow φ t (App. T) that it generates preserves the metric g on M. The most general way of stating this mathematically is to require that the Lie derivative (App. G) of the metric g, with respect to u, must vanish everywhere on M. I.e, L u g = 0. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref> This means that for all x ∈ M, we have (L u g) x = 0. See <ref type="bibr">[46, p.250</ref>].</p><p>The set of all possible Killing vector fields on a given (Riemannian) manifold M constitutes a Lie algebra, which is, in particular, a vector space. This enables us to consider the dimensionality of the set of Killing fields on M, and to write any Killing field as a linear combination of basis Killing fields. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref> shows an example on the sphere. Apps. L and M describe the isometries of the two-sphere in detail, with full calculations. App. K gives more details on Killing vector fields on curved surfaces in general. However, for computing observer fields via optimization (Sec. 9), as the most important part of our framework, we directly evaluate Killing's equation on the unknown vector field u.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Killing's Equation</head><p>A vector field u = u i e i is a Killing field, if an equation known as Killing's equation holds at all x ∈ M <ref type="bibr">[22, p.529]</ref>. However, in its general form this equation is given for covectors, with components u i , and not for vectors, with components u i . The u i can be computed as u i = g i j u j <ref type="bibr">[24, p.88]</ref>, using a metric g, referred to components g i j .</p><p>Killing's equation is then given as</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">∇ j u i + ∇ i u j = 0.<label>(21)</label></formula><p>This is the same as ∇u being anti-symmetric, which is the same as ∇u(x), x = 0 for all x. However, in general it is not correct to simply check whether a component matrix of ∇u is anti-symmetric, because ∇u is a tensor of mixed type (contravariant and covariant indices). Therefore, Eq. 21 is given using the covariant derivative of a covector field <ref type="bibr">[24, p.108]</ref>. In components, referred to a basis {ω i ⊗ ω j }, this is</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">∇ j u i := ∂ j u i − Γ k i j u k .<label>(22)</label></formula><p>We can introduce the vector components u i directly, and write Eq. 21 as</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">∇ j g ik u k + ∇ i g jk u k = 0.<label>(23)</label></formula><p>Applying the product rule for covariant derivatives <ref type="bibr">[24, p.</ref>119], we get ∇ j g ik u k = (∇ j g ik )u k + g ik ∇ j u k = g ik ∇ j u k , because the covariant derivative of the metric vanishes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Therefore, Eq. 21 is equivalent to</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">g ik ∇ j u k + g jk ∇ i u k = 0.<label>(24)</label></formula><p>In matrix notation, we can therefore rewrite Killing's equation as the vanishing of the differential "Killing operator" K applied to the field u,</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">Ku := g ∇u + g ∇u T = 0.<label>(25)</label></formula><p>The tensor Ku is still a 0 2 tensor, just like (∇ j u i + ∇ i u j ). However, Eq. 25 implies that now we can simply check any matrix representation of g ∇u for anti-symmetry, to determine whether u is a Killing field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Killing Energy</head><p>If the expression Ku is not exactly zero, in order to quantify how close to being Killing an arbitrary vector field u is, we use the tensor norm of the tensor Ku to define a scalar Killing energy (see also <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr">Def. 5]</ref>). As for vectors, the tensor norm of a higher-order tensor T is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">T 2 g := T, T g .<label>(26)</label></formula><p>However, the tensor inner product required here, between two covariant second-order tensors T, S, is given by the double contraction <ref type="bibr">[45, p.82]</ref> T, S g := g ik g jl T kl S i j = T i j S i j .</p><p>This is similar to the Frobenius inner product tr(T T S) of matrices, which determines the Frobenius norm tr(T T T) 1/2 . The crucial difference here is that because pairs of covariant and contravariant indices are contracted, Eq. 27 is an invariant tensor expression, giving the same result in all coordinate systems. T, T g = T i j T i j thus is the square of the norm. In matrix notation, we can write the inner product above as</p><formula xml:id="formula_32">T, S g = tr g −1 T T g −1 S .<label>(28)</label></formula><p>We define the Killing energy Eu, of the field u, at a point x ∈ M, as</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">Eu := Ku 2 g = Ku, Ku g .<label>(29)</label></formula><p>Sec. 9.1 defines the Killing energy of M as the integral of Eu over M. Eq. 29 is then the density of the Killing energy of M per unit area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">OBSERVED TIME DERIVATIVES IN CURVED SPACES</head><p>The observed time derivative defined in Eq. 1 measures the differential change of a tensor field with respect to the motion of a given observer field u. We note that D/Dt is, in fact, the time-dependent Lie derivative <ref type="bibr">[45, p.95</ref>] with respect to the flow of the field u. The crucial difference here is the semantic meaning of an observer field u, as an intrinsic part of our operator. Our most important use of D/Dt is applying it to the relative velocity field (v − u), which we minimize to compute the unknown observer field u (Sec. 9). We get (L u u = 0),</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">D Dt (v − u) = ∂ v ∂t − ∂ u ∂t + L u v, = ∂ v ∂t − ∂ u ∂t + ∇v (u) − ∇u (v) .<label>(30)</label></formula><p>Lie derivatives in curved spaces. A basic property of Lie derivatives is that they are independent of the metric g defined on the manifold M, and likewise independent of the connection on M <ref type="bibr">[45, p.96]</ref>. That is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">L u v = ∇v (u) − ∇u (v) , = ∂ j v i u j − ∂ j u i v j e i .<label>(31)</label></formula><p>The expansion in components in the second row above comprises only partial derivatives. The full derivation is given in App. H. Thus, the observed time derivative can be derived solely from partial derivatives, even when the manifold M is curved, including the L u term in Eq. 30.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">COMPUTING OBSERVER FIELDS</head><p>We compute a global observer field u on any two-manifold M with multiple charts using one global linear least-squares solve. The use of a single global sparse linear system is enabled by "baking" all transition maps (their Jacobian matrices) between charts into the system matrix.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1">Objective Function</head><p>Our optimization is conceptually very similar to the approach of Hadwiger et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> for Euclidean space. However, all differential operators have to be substituted by their generalized version for arbitrary manifolds, i.e., covariant derivatives, Lie derivatives, and tensor norms.</p><p>We formulate a global optimization problem to find an observer field u, from the space of all possible fields in some function space V of vector fields (e.g., C n fields) on the manifold M, as the minimizer of</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">min u∈V 1 2 tmax tmin M E + λ D + μ R u, x,t dA dt.<label>(32)</label></formula><p>Here, dA is an infinitesimal area element of M at a point x ∈ M, and the constants λ , μ ∈ R are relative weights. The individual terms are</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">E (u, x,t) := Ku (x,t) 2 g ,<label>(33)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_38">D (u, x,t) := D Dt (v − u)(x,t) 2 g ,<label>(34)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_39">R (u, x,t) := (v − u)(x,t) 2 g .<label>(35)</label></formula><p>The </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2">Global Least-Squares Solution</head><p>To solve Eq. 32, we are looking for the minimizer of the least-squares problem min u 1 2 ||Au − b|| 2 g , with matrix A and vector b as given below. The least-squares solution, weighted with the metric g, is the solution of the normal equations of the weighted least-squares problem given by the square, positive-definite system A T WAu = A T Wb, with</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">A := ⎛ ⎝ K D N ⎞ ⎠ , W := M • ⎛ ⎝Ḡ 0 0 0 λ • G 0 0 0 μ • G ⎞ ⎠ , b := − ⎛ ⎝ 0 ∂ v ∂t v ⎞ ⎠ .<label>(36)</label></formula><p>The matrix M is diagonal, with weights giving the area on M assigned to each vertex element x i , discretizing integration over area elements dA. The other blocks of the matrix W encode g on M, given by the blocks</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">G:= ⎛ ⎜ ⎜ ⎜ ⎝ḡ −1 x1 0 ... 0 0ḡ −1 x2 ... 0 . . . . . . . . . . . . 0 0 ...ḡ −1 xN ⎞ ⎟ ⎟ ⎟ ⎠ , G:= ⎛ ⎜ ⎜ ⎝ g x1 0 ... 0 0 g x2 ... 0 . . . . . . . . . . . . 0 0 ... g xN ⎞ ⎟ ⎟ ⎠ . (37)</formula><p>Here, g xi refers to the n × n component matrix g i j of the metric g at the vertex x i ∈ M. For efficient computation of the tensor norm T g , we use the following approach to convert the tensor inner product in Eq. 27 to a simple contraction of two first-order tensors. We introduce new n-dimensional first-order tensorsT,S, and a symmetricn-dimensional second-order tensorḡ −1 , wheren := n 2 . That is,n = 4 for n = 2. We denote then ×n components ofḡ −1 byḡ st , computed from g i j as g st := g ik g jl , s,t ∈ <ref type="bibr">[1,n]</ref>, (i, j) = σ −1 (s), (k, l) = σ −1 (t). <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(38)</ref> The indices i, j, k, l are given by the inverse of the indexing function</p><formula xml:id="formula_42">σ (i, j) := n • (i − 1) + j, with i, j ∈ [1, n].<label>(39)</label></formula><p>We can use this to rearrange the tensor inner product, to obtain</p><formula xml:id="formula_43">T t := T kl , with t = σ (k, l), S s := S i j , with s = σ (i, j),</formula><p>T s =ḡ stT t , and therefore, T sS s =ḡ stT tSs = g ik g jl T kl S i j = T i j S i j .</p><p>Thus, the tensor inner product T, S g (Eq. 27) can simply be computed as the contractionT sS s . Using this approach, the tensor norm of the Killing energy in the least-squares problem given above is computed by inserting the componentsḡ st (Eq. 38) ofḡ −1 into the matrixḠ above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3">Multi-Chart Optimization</head><p>At each vertex x i ∈ M, there is only one vector for the field u. We store vector components with respect to one selected chart for each x i . However, finite differences to estimate derivatives (App. R) have to be computed in the same chart, even when adjacent vertices are in different charts. We enable this by "baking" all required chart transition maps, i.e., the n × n Jacobian matrices transforming from the coordinate basis of one chart to that of another chart, into the matrices K and D. The elements of these matrices are inserted such that all finite differences are computed using vector components referencing the same chart. More details for implementing this approach are explained in App. S.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.4">Objectivity of Intrinsic Observer Field Computation</head><p>Remark. The computation of the observer field u as the minimizer of Eq. 32 is objective with respect to any observer transformation t → g(t) ∈ G, with G = Isom(M) the isometry group of the manifold M.</p><p>We give proofs in App. F. Except point (4) below, the reasons for this are quite intuitive and can be summarized as follows: (1) The norms used in Eq. 32 are invariant under isometries, because by definition any isometry does not change them (Eq. 14). (2) The Killing energy M Eu dA is time-independent, and measures how much the field u differs from an infinitesimal isometry. Since observer transformations are exact isometries of M, they do not change the Killing energy. (3) A timedependent observer transformation t → g(t), which with G = Isom(M) is a time-dependent isometry t → φ g(t) of M, changes any velocity field on M by point-wise addition of the Killing field corresponding to the derivative X(t) of the isometry. However, the Killing field that is added due to the observer transformation cancels out in the relative velocity field (v − u). (4) The objectivity of the observed time derivative (Eq. 1) is far from obvious. However, Marsden and Hughes <ref type="bibr">[45, p.101</ref>] prove that the time-dependent Lie derivative of an objective tensor field with respect to the flow of any vector field is objective. See App. F.3.</p><p>That is, the norm of all terms in Eq. 32 does not change under the isometry t → φ g(t) of any observer transformation t → g(t), and because the minimizer of Eq. 32 is unique, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, its computation is thus objective with respect to the group action Φ of the isometry group of M.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10">RESULTS</head><p>We have implemented a general framework for flow visualization on curved surfaces, given as triangle meshes, in C++, and OpenGL for rendering. For the sphere, we use six very simple charts, as described in detail in App. Q. We emphasize that the only 3D computations that we use are for initially obtaining the metric of the sphere as a 2D tensor field in each of the charts, and for visualization purposes in OpenGL. All our vector fields are given via 2D components, and all computations required for solving Eq. 32 are fully intrinsic in 2D. We solve the least-squares system given in Sec. 9.2 by using the conjugate gradient solvers provided by the C++ Eigen library, obtaining the minimizer u in multiple iterations. We have also tried direct methods using matrix factorization of the symmetric positive definite matrix A T WA. Due to the size of our grids, conjugate gradients obtain the minimum faster. Data sets. <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref> gives an overview of the data sets that we have used in this paper and the video. We ran experiments with synthetic data sets and with simulated data on the sphere. The optimizations are global. For the earth flow data set we have, however, experimented with two approaches for region of interest optimization to reduce computation times. <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> gives computation times for the conjugate gradient solves to optimize observer fields u. All computations were run on two Intel Xeon E5-2600 processors with 16 cores running at 2.3GHz.</p><p>Visualization. We have adapted the observer-relative visualization methods described by Hadwiger et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> from Euclidean space to curved spaces. Since we need coordinate charts to compute the optimization, we can also use them as texture parametrization for LIC computations in texture space on the GPU. Corresponding to a given observer field u, we compute LIC images of observed stream lines <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>. Likewise, we also compute the geometry of integral curves for observed stream lines as well as for observed path lines. To visualize the time parameter of path lines, we increase the radial distance from the sphere according to the parameter t, scaled by a user-specified factor. This is helpful to see the time evolution of path lines. Additionally, we draw path line shadows on the sphere, to ensure that their position in space can be correctly interpreted. Moreover, we visualize time-dependent scalar fields relative to the observer field via color coding, and in the same way show texture patterns, e.g., Earth or Jupiter textures. We can dynamically switch the observer for any flow field, and directly visualize the corresponding observed fields. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figs. 1, 6</ref>, and 9 show observer-relative scalar fields (planet textures, vorticity magnitude), as well as observed LIC. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figs. 3, 6</ref>, and 8 show observed path lines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.1">Synthetic Data Sets</head><p>Synthetic Vortex. We transform a steady input field of a simple vortex into different time-dependent fields by rotating the input around the vertical axis of a sphere at different angular velocities <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 3)</ref>. The latter correspond to different scalings of the Killing field x 2 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref>.</p><p>From each transformed, time-dependent input field, we compute the corresponding observer field u via optimization. In all cases, the minimizer u of Eq. 32 is a steady Killing field. The observer fields then enable recovering the original steady vortex in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3 (d)</ref>. Relative to its observer field, each unsteady field becomes the original steady field.</p><p>Synthetic Four Centers. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 8(a)</ref> shows four vortices that rotate around each other clockwise, around a common point in the center of the sphere. We show that the observer field u that is computed automatically via optimization recovers a steady field for the four vortices, as depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 8(b)</ref>. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 8(c)</ref>, we then observe the input field in (a) relative to a leftward rotation around the vertical axis of the  sphere. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 8</ref>(e) again depicts the field that is recovered automatically, this time relative to an observer field u, shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Fig. 8(d)</ref>, that rotates clockwise as well as rightward around the vertical axis of the sphere.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.2">Global Planet-Scale Optimization</head><p>Jupiter Vortex Street. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Fig. 9</ref> depicts a 2D von Kármán vortex street centered around the equator of Jupiter. We have generated this data set for testing purposes by mapping a flat vortex street to a sphere by directly mapping a Cartesian x-y grid to a latitude-longitude grid. Earth Flow. For real planet-scale experiments we use open source flow data from the EU Copernicus project. We use global wind data to show that large phenomena like hurricane Isabel (2003) are automatically tracked by the solution of our optimization problem, although no explicit feature tracking is performed. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figs. 1 and 6</ref> show the input flow data and the observed flow fields. We are able to compute an observed flow field that is nearly steady. To get an undistorted visualization that is centered on the hurricane, we can pick one time-dependent Killing field as the observer that travels with the hurricane. The resulting visualization applies the inverse observer motion to the Earth texture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.3">Region of Interest Optimization</head><p>Our approach optimizes for the best observer field u with a global optimization. However, often an optimization of the whole domain at the same resolution level is not necessary, since the user might only be interested in a smaller subdomain. We have tested two methods for this case. We either select a subdomain and run the global optimization only in this subdomain, or we adaptively remesh to obtain different, adaptive mesh resolutions for different regions on the sphere, and then run the optimization over the whole domain. The computation times can be greatly reduced from a full-resolution grid either way <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have presented the first objective, optimization-based framework for computing time-dependent reference frames in curved spaces with the goal of turning unsteady input flow fields into (nearly) steady fields relative to a global observer field. A major motivation for this approach is to enable feature-relative visualization and analysis of the time evolution of features, such as scalar and vector field attributes of hurricane simulations, "in place." A powerful example of this is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 1 (top  left)</ref>, where the path of hurricane Isabel is simply a path line of the automatically computed observer field u. We have seeded this path line manually, but this could also be done algorithmically. Moreover, path lines of u anywhere inside the core region of the hurricane follow the general time-dependent diffeomorphism that constitutes the warping domain of the hurricane. We believe that our mathematical framework has great potential in applications such as studying features of interest in climatology and oceanography in a reference frame-independent way. Our method is objective, meaning that it is invariant with respect to any isometric observer transformation of the input flow field. This enables it to automatically follow the motion of features of interest, and makes it independent of super-imposed motions, including those of moving measurement devices capturing real-world geophysical flow phenomena. Finally, we believe that the fully intrinsic approach that we have taken, and the methodology from Riemannian geometry that we have used in our framework, could provide significant advantages and insight to other areas and applications of flow visualization as well.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>A rotating vortex seen by four different observers. The observers rotate leftward around the sphere (here, around a vertical axis), with angular velocities ω ω ω = −2π, −π/4, −π/8, 0 [s −1 ] (a,b,c,d). All path lines are on the sphere (the depicted shadows), but we visualize the progression of time as increasing radial distance and color (see inset). If these are seen as four different input fields v, minimizing the observed time derivative D/Dt(v − u) gives observer fields u with rightward rotations ω ω ω = 2π, π/4, π/8, 0 [s −1 ]. (d) Observer-relative visualization is the same for all four cases.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Vector fields. A smooth vector field v on a manifold M is a smooth function giving a vector v(x) at every point x ∈ M on the manifold, i.e., v :</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Our intrinsic framework employs a perspective from within a curved manifold M. Thus, all computations on curved surfaces are 2D computations in 2D coordinate charts. Each point x ∈ M has intrinsic differential properties: A (Riemannian) metric, and covariant derivative operators. A vector field v is a vector v(x) in each tangent space T x M. Per chart, each T x M has a coordinate basis {e i }, and a dual basis {ω i }. The symmetric metric tensor field is visualized with glyphs on the right.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>x(x) and covariant derivative (∇x) x at one point x ∈ M [53, Proposition 8.1.4].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Killing vector fields give the infinitesimal isometries of a manifold M, here the sphere S 2 . The Lie algebra elements X, X i ∈ so(3) (bottom) generate the Killing fields x, x i on M (top) through their Lie algebra action. Like the matrices X i , the Killing fields x i are linearly independent, forming a basis of the Lie algebra of Killing fields on S 2 . That is, as we can expand X = aX 1 + bX 2 + cX 3 , we likewise get x = a x 1 + b x 2 + c x 3 , where the latter means point-wise addition of vectors in each T x M at each x ∈ M.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 1 and</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 6illustrate how the computation of an observer field on the surface of the Earth enables focusing a visualization on a feature such as a hurricane. In this example, the input field v(x,t) is given by a time-dependent global wind data set from the European Copernicus project. The top row ofFig. 6</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Feature-centric visualization of hurricane Isabel. (a,b) Pathlines in the original flow field. (c,d) Observer-relative pathlines; the hurricane appears steady. (a,c) First time step. (b,d) Last time step. From (c) to (d), the Earth has moved underneath the steady hurricane. Q(t) is a proper orthogonal tensor (a rotation), c(t) is a point (position vector), and a ∈ R. This transformation assumes absolute time. It is thus sufficient to consider a = 0, disregarding time shifts, giving t * = t.With respect to this transformation, a scalar field is objective if it is unchanged; a vector field v is objective if it transforms according to v * = Q(t) v; a second-order tensor field S, as a linear transformation of vectors, is objective if it transforms as S * = Q(t) SQ(t) T[65, p.42].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>For a curved (or flat) manifold M, the tensor ∇v can, however, always be computed intrinsically as the covariant derivative of v [22, p.241].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>The pushforward of a diffeomorphism φ g is a linear map between the tangent spaces T x M and T φg(x) M. That is, the pushforward(dφ g ) x maps a tangent vector v ∈ T x M to the vector (dφ g ) x (v) ∈ T φg(x) M. The pushforward (dφ g −1 )φg(x) maps a tangent vector in the opposite direction. In components, for a two-manifold M, each pushforward is a 2 × 2 matrix.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Rotating four centers relative to three different observers. Path lines seeded close to the four centers are shown in space-time as inFig. 3. (a) Observer rotating counter-clockwise around the center point between the four vortices. (b) The observer rotation in (a) is automatically removed relative to an optimized observer field u, which corresponds to clockwise rotation: the four centers appear steady. (c) The field in (a) relative to an observer rotating around the vertical axis. (d) The observer field u (path lines) optimized for the field in (c). (e) The field in (c) relative to u from (d).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>integral of E over the domain gives the Killing energy M Eu dA of the observer field u on M. || • || g denotes the tensor and vector norms, respectively, depending on the argument, with respect to the metric g.Discretization. To solve Eq. 32, we discretize the manifold M with a triangle mesh. Vector components are stored at the vertices, and we label the corresponding points on the manifoldM with x 1 , x 2 ,...,x N .The Killing energy term E (Eq.33) is computed by discretizing the Killing operator K (Eq. 25), to compute the covariant derivative terms of ∇u in Eq. 25. The weights for all differential operators to evaluate Ku are stored in a matrix K. We compute partial derivatives via triangle vertex 1-ring neighborhood stencils, computing weighted averages of function values at the mesh vertices. The weights are independent of the actual function values, and can therefore by pre-computed for a fixed mesh geometry and be used for any function on M. See App. R. The observed time derivative term D (Eq. 34) is computed from partial derivatives alone (Eqs. 30 and 31). We compute time derivatives via central differences (in t) on each vertex. The weights for all differential operators to compute D are stored in a matrix D. The regularization term R (Eq. 35) is represented by a matrix N, which is simply an identity matrix times −1, to compute −u. All terms involving the (known) input field v are pre-computed and stored in the corresponding locations of the matrices K, D, and the right-hand side b (see below).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Planet-scale flow patterns observed using LIC. Vorticity is color-coded on a red-blue CCW/CW scale. LIC is used to visualize instantaneous velocities. (a) A vortex street at the equator. LIC cannot show the vortices. (b) The globally optimized observer field that transforms the flow field (a) into a near-steady flow field (c), which shows the vortices in place while the planet is moving underneath instead. Note how LIC of the instantaneous velocity field now clearly shows the vortices.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Data sets with grid/mesh resolution.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Data set</cell><cell># Vert.</cell><cell># Tri.</cell><cell>Time</cell><cell>Time steps</cell></row><row><cell>SYNTHETIC VORTEX</cell><cell>10,242</cell><cell>20,480</cell><cell>0 ...2π</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>SYNTHETIC FOUR CENTERS</cell><cell>10,242</cell><cell>20,480</cell><cell>0 ...2π</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>JUPITER VORTEX STREET</cell><cell>40,962</cell><cell>81,920</cell><cell>0 ... π 2</cell><cell>300</cell></row><row><cell>EARTH FLOW</cell><cell>163,842</cell><cell>327,680</cell><cell>8 days</cell><cell>32</cell></row><row><cell>•EARTH FLOW (SUBDOMAIN)</cell><cell>32,400</cell><cell>64,796</cell><cell>8 days</cell><cell>32</cell></row><row><cell>•EARTH FLOW (ADAPT. RES.)</cell><cell>62,412</cell><cell>124,820</cell><cell>8 days</cell><cell>32</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Computation times for the observer field u.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Data set</cell><cell>λ</cell><cell>μ</cell><cell>CG Iter.</cell><cell>Comp.-time</cell></row><row><cell>SYNTHETIC VORTEX</cell><cell>0.1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1,000</cell><cell>6s</cell></row><row><cell>SYNTHETIC FOUR CENTERS</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>78s</cell></row><row><cell>JUPITER VORTEX STREET</cell><cell>10 3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5, 000</cell><cell>12min</cell></row><row><cell>EARTH FLOW (SUBDOMAIN)</cell><cell>10 13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>3min</cell></row><row><cell>EARTH FLOW (ADAPT. RES.)</cell><cell>10 13</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>10,000</cell><cell>6min</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">A (Riemannian) metric g is required to define the meaning of isometry.<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> It is important to note, however, that checking ∇x for anti-symmetry needs to be done with care, because it is a tensor of mixed type. See Sec. 7.1.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3">This is the unique metric-compatible connection, corresponding to a given (Riemannian) metric g on the manifold M, that has zero torsion[22, p.242].</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4">This (∇g = 0) is the definition of a metric connection[22, p.242].</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>We thank Anna Frühstück for the illustrations and for help with the figures and the video. Hurricane Isabel data courtesy of EU Copernicus project, path from National Hurricane Center/Wikipedia. This work was supported by King Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST), and the KAUST Office of Sponsored Research (OSR) award OSR-2015-CCF-2533-01. This research used resources of the Core Labs of KAUST.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">As-rigid-as-possible shape interpolation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alexa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen-Or</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH 2000</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH 2000</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="164" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vectors, Tensors and the Basic Equations of Fluid Mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Aris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Dover Publications, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mathematical Methods of Classical Mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An operator approach to tangent vector field processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Azencot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ben-Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chazal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ovsjanikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete derivatives of vector fields on surfaces-an operator approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Azencot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ovsjanikov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chazal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ben-Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallel texturebased vector field visualization on curved surfaces using GPU cluster computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bachthaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Strengert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weiskopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Eurographics Symposium on Parallel Graphics and Visualization (EGPGV)</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics Symposium on Parallel Graphics and Visualization (EGPGV)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="82" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector field topology of time-dependent flows in a steady reference frame</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baeza Rojo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2020" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast line integral convolution for arbitrary surfaces in 3d</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Battke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stalling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-C</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization and Mathematics: Experiments, Simulations, and Environments</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="195" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On discrete Killing vector fields and patterns on surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ben-Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Butscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Solomon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Guibas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Eurographics Symposium on Geometry Processing</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics Symposium on Geometry Processing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1701" to="1711" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition-a survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bhatia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Norgard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pascucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-T</forename><surname>Bremer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1386" to="1404" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The natural Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition for open-boundary flow analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bhatia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pascucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-T</forename><surname>Bremer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1566" to="1578" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting features from time-dependent vector fields using internal reference frames</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bhatia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pascucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kirby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-T</forename><surname>Bremer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topology-inspired Galilean invariant vector field analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bujack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hlawitschka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Joy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="79" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging vector fields using line integral convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cabral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Leedom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH &apos;93</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH &apos;93</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="270" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design of 2d time-varying vector fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kwatra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-Y</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1717" to="1730" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector field editing and periodic orbit extraction using morse decomposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mischaikow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Laramee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pilarczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="785" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector Field Processing on Triangle Meshes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>De Goes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Desbrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH Asia 2015 Courses</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">48</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete 2-tensor fields on triangulations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>De Goes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Budninskiy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Desbrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Riemannian Geometry. Birkhäuser</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface-based flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Edmunds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Laramee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Max</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="974" to="990" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using line integral convolution for flow visualization: curvilinear grids, variable-speed animation, and unsteady flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Forssell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Geometry of Physics: An Introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Frankel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Turbulence statistics in a two-dimensional vortex condensate</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Frishman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Herbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">204505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Tensor Analysis and the Calculus of Moving Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Grinfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generic objective vortices for flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Theisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotation invariant vortices for flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schulze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Theisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="817" to="826" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hyper-objective vortices</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Theisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The State of the Art in Vortex Extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Theisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geodesic transport barriers in Jupiter&apos;s atmosphere: A video-based analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hadjighasem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="89" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time-dependent flow seen through approximate observer Killing fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hadwiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mlejnek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Theußl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rautek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1257" to="1266" />
			<date type="published" when="2019" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An objective definition of a vortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fluid Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">525</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining coherent vortices objectively from the vorticity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hadjighasem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Farazmand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Huhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fluid Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">795</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Geometric Mechanics and Symmetry: From Finite to Infinite Dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Holm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schmah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stoica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear Solid Mechanics: A Continuum Approach for Engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Holzapfel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An exact criterion for the stirring properties of nearly two-dimensional turbulence</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica D: Nonlinear Phenomena</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Output-coherent image-space LIC for surface flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="144" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lagrangian-Eulerian advection of noise and dye textures for unsteady flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jobard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Erlebacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Hussaini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spherical barycentric coordinates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Langer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Belyaev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Seidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Eurographics Symposium on Geometry Processing</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics Symposium on Geometry Processing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="88" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image space based visualization of unsteady flow on surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Laramee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jobard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="130" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universal profile of the vortex condensate in two-dimensional turbulence</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laurie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Boffetta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Falkovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kolokolov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lebedev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">254503</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Smooth Manifolds</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Riemannian Manifolds</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GPUFLIC: Interactive and accurate dense visualization of unsteady flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G.-S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tricoche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Eurovis</title>
		<meeting>Eurovis</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flow charts: Visualization of vector fields on arbitrary surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G.-S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tricoche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weiskopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1067" to="1080" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mathematical Foundations of Elasticity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Marsden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<publisher>Dover Publications, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">First Steps in Differential Geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mcinerney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isometries of 2-dimensional riemannian manifolds into themselves</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. National Academy of Sciences of the USA</title>
		<meeting>National Academy of Sciences of the USA</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1936" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="300" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Non-Linear Elastic Deformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ogden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Dover Publications, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'neill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Elementary Differential Geometry</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>revised 2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotational symmetry field design on surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Palacios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Geophysical Fluid Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pedlosky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Higher dimensional vector field visualization: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Laramee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of EG UK Theory and Practice of Computer Graphics</title>
		<meeting>EG UK Theory and Practice of Computer Graphics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="163" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Riemannian Geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Petersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Vortex Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Saffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UFLIC: A line integral convolution algorithm for visualizing unsteady flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;97</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="322" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Flattened fluids help scientists understand oceans and atmospheres</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sokol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="Online:www.wired.com/story/flattened-fluids-help-scientists-understand-oceans-\and-atmospheres" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>posted 27</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Discrete killing fields for pattern synthesis and symmetry detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Solomon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<pubPlace>Palo Alto, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Stanford University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Undergraduate honors thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Comprehensive Introduction to Differential Geometry (5 volumes)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Spivak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Publish or Perish Press. 3rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">LIC on surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stalling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Konrad Zuse Institute Berlin (ZIB)</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and resolution independent line integral convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stalling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-C</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH &apos;95</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="256" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of swirling flow in 3-d vector fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sujudi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Haimes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 12th Computational Fluid Dynamics Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 12th Computational Fluid Dynamics Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="792" to="799" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Line integral convolution on triangulated surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Teitzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Grosso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of WSCG</title>
		<meeting>WSCG</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="581" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Thorne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Blandford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Modern Classical Physics: Optics, Fluids, Plasmas, Elasticity, Relativity, and Statistical Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete multiscale vector field decomposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lombeyda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hirani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Desbrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="452" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Nonlinear Field Theories of Mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Truesdell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Noll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1965" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Differential Geometry: Connections, Curvature, and Characteristic Classes</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image based flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="745" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image based flow visualization for curved surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="130" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directional Field Synthesis, Design, and Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vaxman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Campen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Diamanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Panozzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bommes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hildebrandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ben-Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="545" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cores of swirling particle motion in unsteady flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Weinkauf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sahner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Theisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-C</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1759" to="1766" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vector field design on surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mischaikow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Turk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1294" to="1326" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
