<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Color Icons: Merging Color and Texture Perception for Integrated Visualization of Multiple Parameters</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I-Iaim</forename><surname>Levkowit&gt;z</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Visualization and Perception Reseadl Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Lowell</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>MA</roleName><surname>Lowell</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Visualization and Perception Reseadl Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Lowell</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Color Icons: Merging Color and Texture Perception for Integrated Visualization of Multiple Parameters</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Multiparanreter data collection is becoming increasiirgly conamoti i n niatiy scietatific disciplines. The need exists for iiategrated displays to enable the scientist to see tRe coin.bitied ittforniation, some of which. may tgot be adequately perceived or may not be perceived at all tiheir rriewed individually. At, order for svch displays l o succeed. they must exploit th.e visual perceptual capabilities as much. as possible. W e present a ii.ew techtlique that harnesses color and texture perceptioia t o create iitdegrated displays of two-dinaensional &apos;imagelike &quot; multiparanteter distributions. Tke power of th.e n e v~ tech.irique is denxoiastrated by an example of a syn-&apos; t h s i t e d dataset conaparing it with several other proposed tecAtaiques. W e discuss the nature of studies required t o measure objectitrely and accurately the effechetaess of such displays.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Background</head><p>Multiparameter data collection is becoming increasingly coiiiiiioii in iiiany scientific disciplines. The data can be spatially coherent, such as medical images, satellitae iinages, or geological data for oil exploration; or it, can be iron-cohereat, such as population or census data. But it usually consists of a very large nuiiiber of soiiie higher diniensioaal vectors. The scientist is facc*d witall several images representing different, paranicters, each of which contributes to tlie process of analysis. Detection ancl classification of objects and pat terns ill tlie various iiriages require careful analysis uot only of tlie separate paraiiieters ill&amp;\ idually, but also of relationships among corresponding regions across them. Scanning back and forth aiiiong the separate parameter images positioned side-by-side can he adequatqe only for the aiialysis of crude aspects of relationship; more subtle changes in tlie shape or iiitaeriial st&gt;ructure of corresponding regioiis iiiay be very difficult to analyze. Moreover, in .soiiie cases, stxuctures of intered may not be visible clearly or at all in any one of tlie separate parameters. They niiglit , however, be visible in soiiie appropriately int&lt;egrated display. The need exists for integrated displays to enable the scientist to see tlie combined information. In order for such displays to :jucceed, they must exploit the visual perceptual ~apabilit~ies as much as possible.</p><p>As iiiodern computer graphics aiid display teclinology provide a basis for iiiaiiy protilising ways to integrate multiparameter images, two visually-based techniques are becoining more and more recognized a 3 powerful nieaiis to achieve that. goal: 1. Color codirrg, which exploits humans' powerful color perception [9, 131; and 2. Geomefric coding, which employs shape and texture perception [g, <ref type="bibr">12, 131.</ref> A third approacli, s o i~z f i c a f i o~~ ([4]), wliicli lias showa t.rmieiidous pott.nt.iaI in coiijriiiction with visuallybased techniques. is beyoncl the scope of this article.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Potential Gains from Integration</head><p>We identify t.hree t,ypes of pot,ent,ial gains from int,egrat,ion [IO].</p><p>Type I: Chins in contrast. aiid conspicuousness of s t,ruc t. ures .</p><p>CH3046-0/91/oooo/o164~01.00 @ 1991 IEEE Type 11: Gains in the ability to classify structure types and in the ability to ass0ciat.e spatially disjunct regions of structwes of the same type.</p><p>Type 111: Gains from making structures that are not visible in any single parameter visible by conibining parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Outline</head><p>This article discusses tlie development and evaluation of visually-based integration tecliniques that merge the perceptual powers of color and geometric coding techniques in general. In Section 2, we intmduce tlie notion of an zconographic display as a generalization of standard displays, and we describe briefly t,he two main approaches to visual integration, namely, color integration and geontetrtc integration, as iconographic displays. In Section 3, we present a new colorbased iconograpliic technique, which liarnesses color and texture perception to create integrated displays of multdparanieter distributions. The power of the new technique is denionstrated in Section 4 by an example of a synthesized dataset, comparing it with other proposed techniques. In Section 5 we discuss the nature of studies required t-o measure objectively and accurately the effect,iveness of such displays. Section 6 provides a discussion and direct&gt;ions for future work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Iconographic Integration Techniques</head><p>The iconographic approach provides a general structure for tlie specification and creation of integrated displays of "diparanieter images [9, 12, 131.</p><p>The basic primitive is the won, which is a generalization of a single pixel to higher dimensions having multiple perceivable features and attributes. It enables the representation of multiple values at each spatial location by controlling attributes of the icon's perceivable features.</p><p>Gray-scale pixels in images are the most degenerate form of an icon-a 1 x 1 patch with one attribute of variation, its intensity. Color coding of the 1 x 1 pixel patch provides the simplest extension, which is int roducing tjliree attributes of variation, its tristiiiiulus valries such as lightness, hue, and saturation. By expanding the area of the icon, albeit at potentially significant costs in spatial band-width, tlie icon acquires vistial features aiid attributes, such as shape and other aspects of geometry and color, all of which are datacontrollable. Stereoscopic depth and dynamic properties are other potential extensions.</p><p>We now describe briefly the two main approaches for visual int,egrat.ion; detailed descript(io1is can he found in the cited literature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Color Integration</head><p>In color coding, each icon of the integrated representation is a color patch (txnditionally a 1 x 1 patchi.e., a pixel) whose tristiniulus values are controlled I)y the values of corresponding locations in (up to) t h e e input parameter distributions. Typically, tlie different parameters are niapped to the different coordinates of a color niodel <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[7]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Geometric Integration</head><p>Geoniet,ric coding, originally proposed by Picket t</p><p>[ 1 11, has been dei eloped at the University of Lowt.ll for visualization of large multiparametric databases and is rapidly gaining recognition as a powerful approach to integration, in particular wliere tlie nuniber of parameters exceeds three, which is tlie upper limit for color integration In this teclinique shape perception is utilized to senye local coinbinations of data, wliilr texture perception provicles a sense of glol)al spatial distribution of those It, caii be sho\i ii t,hat. sha.pe and color a.re perceptiially separable fea.tbures; t,liis iiieaiis t,liat, discrimina.t,ion of variations in t,liese two features are percept,ua.lly orthogonal. Lightness and size a.re a,lso sepa.rable. Separable features have t,lie hest pot,ent,ia.l as vehicles for successful coding of data, in part,icula,r for "unniixiiig" of parameters.</p><p>The color icon merges separable feat.ures by using color, slmpe, a.nd textmure percept*ion bo code mult,iple paraniet,ers iiit&lt;o a single int,egrat,ed inia.ge. At. t,lie most, general Irvrl. thrcolor icon is n i l a w a o i l t.lw s c r w i . const,ruct,ed of one-dimensioiia.1 fea.tures (I,ountlaries and a.rea subc1iv:drrs). and t.c\.o-dimeiisioiia.l features (areas defined by t.he subdividers), ailcl {.heir at t,ril,rit,rs (orientat,ion, size, sha.pe, and color). Each of 1.liosr can be cont,rollec globa.lly (e.g., t.lie shape of (. is chosen to be rectangular for all icons), or can be mapped to be contmlled hy a dat.a parainet" ( e . g . , a subdivision point along a linear feat*ure is controlled by 3 parameter value).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">A prototype implementation</head><p>We h v e iiiipleiiieiited a prot,ot,ype of a systeni to visualize data using the color icon. In this prototype, tlie ic,oii is ai1 111 x 71. rect.aiigle ( i n and n a,re globally under user control), see <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. In one variant of the prot,otype, six linear feat,ures are used: two of t,lie edges (one horizoiit,al, one vert,ical), t8he two dia,goiials, mid the two iiiitlliiies. This provides coding of up t,o six paraiiieters (in a.dditioii to the (x, y) spat.ial loca.t,ioii). Tlie reiiia.iiiing t.wo edges are not used so as t.o ma.int.aiii bouiichry coiisisteiicy by avoiding coiiflicts with the lieigllboring spatial points. Those t,wo edges could, however, be used for t.wo additioiial pa.rameters. Tlie fea.tures subdivide the icon's area into several sulmreas. Tlie colors of those subareas a.re iiit,erpola.ted from the colors assigned to t,he linear fea.t,ures. In a.iiot,lier va.riant, t,he fea.tures used are t.he fields result.iiig froiii subtlivicliiig t.he icon's area. This yields a "pie clmrt," t,ype of an icon, wit,h eight. pa.ra,iiiet.er fields ( "slices" ). It seems t,liat t.he linear feat.ure a.pproa.ch provides bet,t,er blending of pa.raniet,er va.lues, while the area. feat,ure one provides bett,er sepa.ra.bi1it.y of pa.rameter values.</p><p>Ea,cli fea.t,ure is iiia.ppt?d to one da.ta. pa.raniet,er. 111 t,lie current, prot.ot,ype t,he att.ribut,e uiicler data corit,rol is the color of t8he featsure; the va.lue of tlie pa.ramet,er detenniiies all three color coordinates of the fea.ture2 via. a point,er t,o a color sca.le. Different paraiiieters may sliare the smie color scale or iiiay point to iiidividual color scales. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows t,he ma.ppings of paraiiiebers to linea,r fea.t,ures as t,lie iiumber of parameters vary from one t80 six.</p><p>A prot.otype syst,em lias heell iinplement,ed on a, variet.y of workst,at.ioiis in C', under X-windows using t,he OSF/Mot.if t,oolkit,. It supports sepamte display, a.iicl indivic1ua.l color sca.le a.ssigniiieiit,s for up to six pa,raniet,ers. A region-of-interest selectmion capabilit,y, which selects corresponding regioiis in all input. ima.ges, allows disphying ImrC of t,he iiiia.ge in tlie iiit,egrat,ed disp1a.y.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Other possibilities</head><p>The general definition of tlie color icon allows many variations:</p><p>0 The number of parameters to be coded can be tripled by liaviiig each parameter control oiily oiie color paraiiicter (such as the lightness, hue, or saturation) of a feature. In such a case, three pa-raiiiet&gt;ers control the color of a feature, whereas in tlie current prototype, one parameter controls t#he color of the feature, coiiipare Figures 1 aiid 3. Different color iiiodels and different mappings of parameters to color coordinates provide atlditioiial diversity of displays.</p><p>0 More t,liaii one parameter can be mapped t,o a linear feature by subdividing its lengt(1i. Subdivision can be fixed globally (e.g., all linear feat,ures are subdivided in tlie middle) or can be data-controlled, where the point of subdivision is controlled by the value of a parameter.</p><p>0 Tlie contributions of different parameters to the colors of the icon can be weighted. Tliis can be achieved algebraically (by using a different interpolatioii functioii to compute the relat,ive contributions) or geoinetrically (by cliangiiig tlie location of int.ersect,ioii point,s, the contributions of different. paraiiiet,ers t,o the colors of t.he icoii are given different, weights). Tlie two approaches can be coinbiiied.   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>. These relationships becoiiie perceivable when integrated a,ppropria.tely, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures G-9</ref>. This illustmtes our conjecture tha.t, in soiiie cases intergrated disp1aj.s 1iia.y be the only effect,ive wa.y to inake some relat,ioiisliips in the da.ta perceivable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.0.1">Image geiieratioii</head><p>To generate tlic: inmges we first. genera.ted smiples from normally distributed random variables, X I , . . . , S e , with 1iiea.n /I, = 0 ancl standa.rd deviat,ioii y = l. Next,, we generated the nega.t,ioiis</p><p>-XI, -.Yz, --X3 aiid the pa,irwise negative a,nd pa.irwise positive correlates as showii in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 1</ref>. Fimlly, we genera.t,ed t,lie images as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>. The images are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref>. Note that. the topbottom differences in the ima,ges are not, perceivable at all in the gray scale representation. On the other hand, those differences are very c1ea.r in t,he color model codings sliowii in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> aiitl in t.Iie color icon co(liiigs sliown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures 7-9</ref>. Tliis denionst,ra.t.es blir potentia.1 gains of Type 111 discussed in Sect.ioii 1.2. One clear a.dvaiit,age cf the color icon t1ispla.y over t.lie color iiiodel oiie is t(1iat. in the former, even using oiily the gray scale for all pa.raniet,ers reveals tJie rela.t,ioiiships</p><p>" D u e to 1iniitat.icais in space and in the nuniber of (:1~1or pictures, we do iivt clenioiist rate here C)IW t.ecluiiqiies with real data; an expanded versior, of t.his paper is available as a Technical Hrport., [SI. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Evaluation Studies</head><p>As we h v e clescril,ed and tleiiioiist.rated above, there a,re iiiany different, possibilities t,o generake iiitegra.t.ed disp1a.y. From a. tecliiiological point of view iiiost, of t81ieni are feasible. However, it. is not possible t.o det,ermiiie their efficacy without evaluation studies wit,li liuiiiaii observers.</p><p>Tlie first, step t.owards evaluateion is selecting a,iid a.cljust,iiig the various imaging variables so as to explore t.he different. coiiibiiia.t,ioiis that are possible. In such a. st,utly, imrticipants t.ry different, viewing va.ria.bles of t.he iiit*egra,ted iiiiagiiig system. Viewing variables iiiclude different, fea.t,ures, a,t.t.ributes of fea.t,ures, t.he shape a.iid size of t.lie icon (different, t,essella.t.ions), pa.ra.inet,er-t,of~at,ure mappings, and color scale selectioii a.iid assigiinieiit. Since the iiuiiiber of combiliat.ions ca.ii he very large, the goal is t&gt;o ideiit,ify particular select.ions a.iitl va.lues t.1ia.t a.ppear to be most. prouiising. Those choices a.re t.lieii used for subsequent,, inore ela.borat,e st,utlies. Such st,utlies eiiiploy  specific tasks siicli as detection, classification, localization, and quanlificatioii of objectas (e.g. detect the esistence of a target in a background, or sp'cify whet lirr tshere is a horizontal or a vertical split in the iniage); larger saiiiple sizes; larger numbers of participants; aiid more rigorous analysis iiiet hods.</p><p>When desigiiiiig such st uclies. hoth real images ant1 syiithesized data should he coiisitlerecl. Real rlat a present. real world prohieins hut iiiay lack informat-ioii about the "truth" (e.g., in iiiedical images, it is not always easy to know whether the image is normal or abiiorinal). The coiiteiit4s of synthesized data is always kiiowii, ancl can be adjusted to test situatioiis for which real data is not kiiowii to Iw available (for example, inter-aiid intra-image relationships like the ones deiiioiistratcd here inay iiot be perceived in real data). However, results from studies using syiithesizecl data iiiiglit not exteiid to the real world</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Discussion aiid Direction for Future Work</head><p>We linve discussed t.he general iiot.ioii of iconographic i ii t,egra.t,ed dinp1a.y.s of iiiu 1 t,ipa,ra.iiie t.r i c cl a. t.a.. Three pot.ei1t.ia.l ga.ins from iiitegra.t.ioii ha.ve I~eeii oii t'lined. Color mid geoiiiet,ric codiiigs for t,he task were briefly reviewed. A new color basecl icoii 1ia.s I~eeii introduced, which eiiiploys hot,li color a,ud t.est.ure percep t ion. Several options of fea.t,ures, a.ttribii tes, ancl mappings of parameters t,o fea.t,ures ancl at,t,rihut'es have heeii preseiit,ed. Examples of images result,ing froiii explorat,ioii3 wit.11 various a.pproaches have been presented. The need for a. taliorough observer perforiiiaiice evaliiat,ioii to det,eriiiiiie t.lie efEca.cy of such displays has beel: eiiipliilsizecl, and t,he nat.iire of such evaluations lias been outlined. Much more work iieecls bo be done both in the development, ancl in t,lie eva.1ualioii of such disphys. More displays ueerl t.o be clrveloped using a large varivty of optioiis siicli as IIir oiies presented 1 . r~. LVitle range esplorat ioiis iicwl t.0 he ca.rrier1 out to iia.rrow clowii t,lie possil&gt;ilit.ic,s to the most proiiiisiiig ones. Thorough st.uclies of perforiiia.iice need t,o lw coiiduct,etl wit.11 t.lie most, proiiiisiiig cotlings. In such st.udies, t.asks like the det,ect.ion, classifica.t.ioii, loca.liza.t,ion, ancl clirant.ifica t.ioii of ol&gt;.jrcts need t.0 be nieascred using tliffrwnt. cocliiig techiiiqurs wit,h sa.iiiple spaces of suficiriit, size t.0 tlraw coi~clusioiis u4t.h st.a.tistica.1 significance.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>lie icoii 'On the other hand. lightness. hue. atid saturation. in parti(-ular at the extremes of the lightliess range. are t t r f + g r r r / . iiieaiiiiig that variations in any oiie iiiiglit rawe perreiwrl vaiiat i o n s 111 the others.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 . 5 Figure 2 :</head><label>152</label><figDesc>The color icon with six linear features (thick lines). The vnlueof the paraiiietc.r ninpptl to a feature deteriiiiiies the color of the feature via a pointer to a color scale. The colors of the iiiscribetl area9 are interpolated froiii the colors of tlie features.G 4Tlie ii-appiiigs of parameters to linear features (thicker lin+s) a s tlir nuiiilwr of' parainetrrs vary from one to six.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>-Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The number of parameters can be tripled: each paraiiieter controls only one of tlie three color coordinates of a feature's color (coinpare toFigure 1).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The t h e e synthesized ima.ges displayed using t,he gray scale. Not,e t1ia.t t,he top-to-bottom differences iii the d a h are not. seen. in dat,a; t.liis provides for displaying such d a h even when color capabilit.ies are not. available.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 :Figure 8 :</head><label>68</label><figDesc>The three synthesized images clisplayed USiiig three color iiioclel cotliiigs.( a ) R(:U, (I,) GLHS [SI, (c) C'IELIJV. Note that the top-to-bottom differeiice io the data is veiy clear in a11 three I I The tliree syiitliesized images displayed witrli the color icon; each parameter is displayed using a separaCe scale (left to right: Heated object, LOCS, Mrtgeii ta ) .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>The t,liree syntJiesizec1 images displayed with the color icon; all three parameters displayed using the gray scale.(See color plates, page 430.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>3 The Color Shape, aiid Integration</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>combinations Icon: Merging Color, Texture Perception for</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Other tessellations, such as hexagoiial or triaiigular, can be used instead of rectangular ones. The advantages and disadvaiit ages of different tessellations need to be assessed.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Pairwise nngativc: positive! Pairwise correlates correlat&lt;es ,Ti4 + s s + s 1 + A-2</cell></row></table><note>0</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 :Illustratioiis with Synthesized 1111- ages</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Pairwise negative and pairwise posit,ive correlates generated for t,he syiit,liesized data.</figDesc><table><row><cell>4 In order to evalua,te t,he capa.lilit.ies of different,</cell></row><row><cell>niechanisiiis to code iiiult.iple paraiiietser images into</cell></row><row><cell>integrated displays, we 1ia.ve developed a set of synt&lt;lie-</cell></row><row><cell>sized images t,liai, possess soiiie known propertie9 aiid</cell></row><row><cell>relationships t.liat, are not, available in rea,] i~iia.ges.~</cell></row><row><cell>Iii yarticuhr, this synthesized d a h set has t,he prop-</cell></row><row><cell>erty t1ia.t struct,ures aiid rela.t,ionships inherent. in the</cell></row><row><cell>images a.re not perceivable when viewed separa.tely,</cell></row><row><cell>see</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">This is only one approacli tu cocling; we cliscuss other approirrlies later.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SPIE.</head><p>The author is grateful to R. Daniel Bergeron and Ronald M. Picket,t for early discussions about this icon. Ronald M. Pickett and Stuart Smith developed and generated the syntliesiaed images for <ref type="figure">Figures 5-9</ref>. Nupur Kapoor and Bogdaii Pytlik implemented the current color icon system.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theory of textural segmentatmion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Praadny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Rosenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Machine Vision</title>
		<editor>J. Beck, B. Hope, and A. Rosenfeld</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Acadeiiiic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="38" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Three-dimensiona.1 features that. pop out in visual search</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Enns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>D. Brogan</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Vzsual Search. Taylor aiid Fraiicis</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Perception of the Visual World</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Houghtoii-Mifflin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1950" />
			<pubPlace>Boston, MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The perceptualization of scient,ific data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grinst8eiii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SPIE &apos;90</title>
		<meeting>SPIE &apos;90<address><addrLine>Santa Clara, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SPIE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="16" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color iiitegrat.ed clisphys of niultimodality tonlographic inia</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Selt*zer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pickett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>D'orsi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ges. Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">248</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Poster presented at, the 76th Annual Meet#iiig of the Ra.diologica.1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Societ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">America</forename><surname>Of Nort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>RSNA &apos;90</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visua.1 a,nalysm of t.ext.iire iii the detection and recogiiitioii of object,s</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pickett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pictiire Proceasiiig aiid Psycho-Pictorics</title>
		<editor>B. S. Lipkin and A. Rosenfeld</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Aca.deniic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pickt:t,t and G . Griiisfein. 1conogra.phic displays for visiializing iiiiilt</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>iclimensiona.l da.t.a.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceediii gs of IEEE Iii iern niio n a1 CO tt fe re rixe on. Systeias, Mait mid C,&apos;yberil.eiics, Beijiiig and Shenyaiig</title>
		<meeting>eediii gs of IEEE Iii iern niio n a1 CO tt fe re rixe on. Systeias, Mait mid C,&apos;yberil.eiics, Beijiiig and Shenyaiig</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Picket</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Selt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">zer. Iconographic displays of mu1 t.ipa.ra.met,er aiid</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">mul</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color icons: Merging color and texture perception for integrated visualization of multiple parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>R-91- 005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedtiigs of the Fzrsi Coiifereiice 711 Vzsualtxtzoil 111 B~o I J J~~~ Coinputzng</title>
		<meeting>eedtiigs of the Fzrsi Coiifereiice 711 Vzsualtxtzoil 111 B~o I J J~~~ Coinputzng</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="66" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Comput.er Science, Univertiniodality iiiiages</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
	<note>At.lanta, GA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Featare analysis in early vision: Evirleiice from search asynimetqries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Treisiiian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorniican</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The design and evaluation of color scales for image data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>R-91-003</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Coniputer Science, University of Lowell</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Available as Teclinical Report</note>
	<note>Submitted for publication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychologtcrrl Revtew</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GLHS: A generalized lightness, hue, and saturation color model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>R-91-004</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer Science, University of Lowell</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
	<note>Submitted for publication. Available as</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GIHS: A generalized color niodel and its use for the represen tat ion of niult i paraiiie ter iiiedical images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Maiheniatacs atid Coniputer Scteiice zit Medtcnl Iiitagziig</title>
		<editor>M.A. Viergever and A.E. Todd-Pokropek, editors</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="399" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
