<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Gray Scale Diagrams as Business Charts</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Feeney</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Infomation and Decision Systems Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">San Diego State University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>92182</postCode>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Gray Scale Diagrams as Business Charts</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Theflood of numeric data in science and technology has prompted new graphic representations called visualization. Business also has a serious need for new graphic representations. One candidate comes from the unlikely gray scale. Gray scale &amp;grams can present large amounts of quantitative information in a compact format. Hundreds of data points can easily be represented in one diagram, using small gray scale squares (or tiles), without visually overloading a viewer. An experiment was done to compare subjects&apos; responses to answer questions from three types of charts, traditional column and line charts and gray scale tile charts. The results showed that questions were answered more correctly and more quickly using gray scale tile charts than using traditional charts. However , subjects reported they experienced more strain using gray scale tile charts.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Two recent developments in science and technology have spurred the growth of visualization of data. One is the need to interpret huge quantities of numbers that have been collected by large scale experiments and other scientific ventures. The computer community has responded to this stimulus by calling for action in the area of visualization and by publishing in textual and video format the results of visualization efforts to date [1] <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. More popular explanations of visualization have also been published <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The second development is the growth of visualization techniques, and the migration of these techniques to less expensive hardware platforms. Many techniques developed on large and super computers are now available on microcomputers. Examples are the set of software available from Spyglass, Inc.</p><p>[4] for the Macintosh, and the soon to be released texture producing software for the Macintosh from the University of Lowell</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>151.</head><p>The growth of business activity and complexity also develops large quantities of numbers. These numbers result from business transactions and records, other measurements of activities, and planning estimates. Numbers in business tend to be more similar in format than numbers in science and technology, with little need for very small or large floating point numbers. The implication is that of all of the visualization techniques developed for scientific data, only certain kinds are applicable to business data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Business Charts</head><p>Historically, the two people given credit for systematically representing numbers in graphical form are J.H. Lambert (1728-1777). a Swiss-German scientist and mathematician, and William Playfair (1759-1823), an English political economist <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Playfair started with a time series analysis of English exports and imports.</p><p>Playfair also produced the first known bar chart [I.</p><p>The major types of business charts, in terms of their element shapes, layout and orientation, are: scatter point, line, area, bar, column, pie and hybrid. They are sometimes given other names because of the use to which they are put. For instance, a variation in the bar chart is often called a Gantt chart when used in a project management Context.</p><p>Business charts can show two-dimensional data, such as the amount of sales of a company over a number of years. Convention dictates the amount of sales be on the vertical axis and time on the horizontal axis. Business charts can also contain three dimensional data. The sales of different departments in a company over a number of years is an example. In this case the departments are usually grouped along the horizontal axis within each year. Three-dimensional data may look more complex in charted form, but can be easily handled by people. A bar chart of company profits by department and year is an example. One feature of the traditional business charts is that they are all based on lengths, angles or areas of the graphic elements. Bar and column charts use line lengths, line charts use angles and pie and area charts use areas to communicate relationships. It is important to note an obvious fact, that all of these charts can be drawn by hand with a pen or pencil. That is how all of them were created initially, someone drawing them by hand.</p><p>However, lines, angles and areas are not the only visual elements which humans can discriminate. We can see differences in colors, textures and gray scales which are not easily produced by pen. With the availability of computer equipment to easily produce colors, textures and gray d e s , they too can be used in business charts. <ref type="bibr">Cleveland [8]</ref> derived an approximate ordering of graphical features in their ability to accurately represent quantitative information. His hierarchy lists position along a scale as the best representation (for example, lines on graphs with grid backgrounds). Next come length, angle or slope, area, volume, and color attributes (hue, saturation and density). Shades of gray are the same as density for black and white. The implication is that a shade of gray may be inaccurate in determining an actual numeric value which it represents, but determining the relative value (comparing one shade of gray to another) is possible and informationally useful.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Gray Scale Charts</head><p>If color duplication were common for business reports, color tile charts, which have advantages over gray scale charts, could be used. However, because black and white duplication is used universally in business this initial research uses gray scales for the experiment.</p><p>Gray scale charts are square or rectangle groupings of tiles that can be different shades of gray.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> only eight levels of gray are shown, but people can easily make comparison judgments of double that number of levels. Numeric amounts are read from the chart by comparing the amount of gray within a given tile with the legend strip. Since the format of the gray scale tile chart is essentially a matrix in design or "plan view" of the tiles, with the third dimension (level of gray) coming out of the page, this kind of chart is simple for a viewer to understand and is economical of space. The <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> gray scale tile chart holds eight times the amount of information as the bar chart to the left.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>. 4 Information from Charts</head><p>When readers are using business charts they look for different types of information from them. Bertin states that information is relationships [9]. For example, in column charts, relationships exist between the column heights and the margin scale, and between the heights of several columns. In a similar manner for gray scale tile charts, relationships exist between tiles in the chart itself and the gray scale legend, and between the gray scale tiles themselves.</p><p>Five kinds of information are discussed here: numeric amounts, comparisons, trends, groupings of similar values and repeated patterns. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1 through 5</ref> illustrate these. The gray scale charts use only eight levels of gray in these examples. In practice, gray scale charts can contain many more levels.  As with all business charts the amount will be only approximate, because typical chart scales cannot be read to last digit accuracy. Also, there are perceptual mechanisms which interfere with perfectly accurate reading in both gray scale tile charts and traditional charts. For example, in gray scale charts the shade of a given tile will look darker when it is set in among lighter sumunding tiles than it would if it were set in with darker tiles. For traditional business charts illusions created by having to sight over interposed graph elements and open white space contribute to inaccurate readings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2)</head><p>ComDansons ' between amounts on a chart are often made by viewers. For example, the department of a company with the most sales for a particular month might be of interest. Traditional charts, one of which is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 2</ref> (left), use the difference in length, height, or area size in doing the comparison. For the gray scale tile charts (as shown here), the darkest of the tiles being compared is the one with the highest value. A black tile has the maximum value for that chart, and a white tile the minimum.   or decrease. Colors and visual textures can also be 5) patterns can be shown on both traditional business charts and gray scale charts as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">Figure 5</ref>. Partly because it contains much more information than a traditional business chart, the gray scale chart seems better suited for spotting recurring patterns. In this gray scale tile chart the sample pattern shown is repeated four times in the chart As in the trend chart, some effort may be required to spot the pattems when trying for the first time. visually grouped.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Experiment</head><p>This experiment was designed to answer the question: Can gray scale tile charts be read? That is, can viewers determine numeric amounts, make comparisons and see trends using gray scale charts? The ability of gray scale tile charts to provide viewers with grouping and pattern information was not determined in this experiment.</p><p>This experiment compared two types of traditional business charts (column and line charts) with gray scale tile charts containing exactly the same information. Fictitious population data from nine census years for 50 towns was presented in each of the three chart formats. <ref type="figure">Figures 6 , 7</ref> and 8 show the column, line and gray scale tile charts used. Only one set of census data was used to develop the charts for the experiment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Method</head><p>SUBJECTS. The subjects were graduate students who were attending a small computers course in the College of Business Administration at San Diego State University. Seventeen subjects, ranging in age from 23 to over 50, participated in the experiment after being requested by the experimenter to do so. Data from fifteen subjects were usable. STIMULUS MATERIALS. The stimuli was an 8-1/2 by 1 1 inch packet (32 pages) containing initial instructions, practice tasks, stimulus pages and in process instructions. The first page contained an outline of the instructions to the students. Several pages, interspersed in the booklet, instructed subjects when to stop and when to proceed. Seven pages had practice tasks on which the subjects could practice and ask questions. Twenty-one pages each contained a task. Each task page had the chart to which the subject had to refer to answer the question. The column chart used is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>, the line chart in <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>, and the gray scale tile chart in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 8</ref>.</p><p>Each task page also contained a question and boxes in which subjects could write the answer and the time code for each task. The column and line charts were produced using Excel (Macintosh) from numbers in a nine element by 50 element mamx. The matrix contained (fictitious) population data for 50 towns for the census years 1900 to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1980.</head><p>The gray scale tile chart was developed using visualization software from Spyglass, Inc. (Spyglass, 1990) using the same matrix of data as the column and line charts. This software produces the color and gray scale displays seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">Figure 8</ref>.</p><p>Three types of questions were asked about the charts. The first, numeric amount, required a single number answer, for example "What was the population of town 17 in 1950?" The second, comparison, asked that the subject compare two or more numbers represented in each chart."After what year did town 29 increase to a population of 7000?" The final kind of question required the subject to look for trends. "Which town, of towns 5 through 10. had the most sudden increase in population?"</p><p>The amount information in the column and line charts used in this experiment was much larger than is usually recommended for good chart design [lo] ill]. However, since the aim of the experiment was to determine if gray scale charts can provide information similar to traditional charts it was essential that all of the charts have the same amount of data.</p><p>DESIGN. A 3 x 3 x Subjects factorial (repeated measures) design was used. The first factor was the chart type: column, line or gray scale tile chart. The second factor was the question type, that is the kind of question asked of the subject. The three kinds were numeric amount, comparison and trend. All of the subjects received all of the tasks in this design. The practice effect of subjects using the charts, beyond the practice charts at the start of the experiment, was not judged to be important. The subjects already had considerable practice using the column and line charts and further practice would not affect their skill. To further control any possibility of practice influencing the outcome, the types of charts were intermixed in the stimulus booklet so that no one type of chart was ever immediately repeated.</p><p>Two dependent measures of correctness of answers and time to do each task were recorded by the subjects. The answers were in the form of numbers, either population amounts, town identification, census years or number of towns. The time was recorded in the form of three letter codes. The subjects wrote the time code immediately after writing the answer to a question and before they went on to the next page. The method of recording individual times for subjects in groups was adapted from a technique [12] developed earlier for film. For this experiment a large television/monitor unit displayed time codes at which the subjects looked after answering the experiment questions. These codes had been prerecorded using a camcorder from an Excel (Macintosh) program which displayed the three letter codes in large letters on a computer screen. The codes changed on the tape every second. The code sequence looks random upon casual observation but is actually constructed systematically and was later decoded by an analysis program. The letter codes discouraged subjects from trying to calculate their own interval times as they might have done if numbers instead of letters had been used.</p><p>PROCEDURE. All of the subjects participated in the experiment at the same time by having the subjects record a displayed letter code after they wrote the answer to a question. A university classroom, containing standard student chair-desks, was used for the experiment. After distributing the stimulus packets the experimenter explained the tasks to be done, and how the subjects were to record answers and time codes. When subjects had done the practice tasks, the experimenter started the experiment. The subjects proceeded at their own pace. The experimental session ended when the last subject finished. No special equipment was used individually by the subjects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>The experimental questions being tested are: can gray scale tile charts be read? If yes, can they provide viewers with the same kind of information as more traditional business charts?</p><p>CHART TYPES column, line and gray scale were used in the experiment. Regarding the task time, a three way ANOVA (subjects x chart type x question type) shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> indicates a highly significant difference (p &lt; .001) in time taken for chart types, column, line and gray scale. Chart 1 shows the task time for subjects by chart type. The gray scale tile charts were actually read faster, on the average, by the subjects (33.3 sec.) as opposed to 52.7 sec. and 52.1 sec. for the other two charts. Furthermore, as a group, the subjects seemed to understand the task involved in reading the gray scale tile charts as least as well as the other charts. The standard deviation for the gray scale charts was somewhat lower than for the others.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, shows a highly significant difference (p &lt; .005).</p><p>Chart 2 indicates that questions relating b the gray scale tile charts were correct more often (94.4%) than the other two charts (90.1% and 86.8%). As in the time data above, there was less individual difference in subjects for the gray scale charts, as indicated by the low standard deviation for the gray scale charts. Results for comtness of responses for question types, <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 2</ref>, indicates a highly significant difference (p &lt; .001). Chart 2 shows that value amount questions were correct, on the average, most often (95.6%). Comparison and trend questions followed in order <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(91.1% and 82.9%)</ref>.</p><p>SUBJECT COMMENTS. When they had finished the experiment tasks, the subjects were requested to write comments on what they liked the best and the least about the three types of graphs. Many said they liked the line chart the best and the gray scale chart the least. Subject comments about the gray scale hurting their eyes or giving them a headache was quite common.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Discussion</head><p>Gray scale tile charts are clearly different looking than traditional column, bar, line, area and pie business charts. The chart elements for the gray scale charts are uniform size squares which cannot be produced by drawing with a pen. The gray scale charts need to be computer produced to be practical. Because of their design, gray scale cham are more matrix appearing than traditional charts and easy for viewers to understand. Based on the results of the experiment subjects can quickly and accurately match the levels of gray in the chart body with the numeric values in legend. The experiment showed that even though gray scale charts are different than traditional charts, they can be used to provide the same kind of information. This experiment does demonstrate that gray scale tile charts can indeed be read and can provide information in the same manner as traditional business charts.</p><p>In this experiment, subjects took less time and had p a t e r accuracy using the gray scale charts than the traditional ones. These results need to be tempered by the fact that the column and line charts contained much more information (450 data points) than is recommended for those chart styles (less than 100 data points). Further, the design of the legends for these charts may not have been the best design, given the large amount of information they contained. The relatively long time subjects took to get information from the traditional charts may have been due to their being overloaded and to the design of their visual elements. This experiment does not conclusively demonstrate that gray scale tile cham can be read faster and with more accuracy than traditional charts.</p><p>The subject comments about the gray scale tile charts being hard on their eyes are important. Using these charts does require close scrutiny of a surface of identical shaped elements. This experiment did require subjects to look at the tile charts intensely for specific information and to do so repeatedly. Looking at these charts in a different environment, say reading a business report, would have less repeated eye focusing requirements. Further, it is not clear from this experiment specifically what characteristics of the chart caused the eye strain.</p><p>Once the characteristics are better understood, modifications of the chart may diminish or eliminate the problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Conclusions</head><p>The results of this experiment point the way for new charts, charts other than pen produd traditional charts. to provide information to users of charted data. These new charts include gray scale charts, color charts and texture charts. Based on this experiment, it seems that reports and publications that need to display large quantities of data points could use gray scale tile charts. Even people who have had no experience with them, can, with a few minutes practice, use them quickly and accurately. It is not possible, based on this experiment alone, to say that gray scale tile charts are faster and more accurate than the traditional charts.</p><p>There are many questions arising from this experiment that need to be answered by further research and experiments. Some of them are: 1) How do gray scale tile charts and traditional charts compare using smaller amounts of data? 2) How are gray scale tile charts at providing information in the form of groupings and patterns? 3) How well do gray scale tile charts do when compared with differently, and possibly better designed, traditional Charts? 4) Are there design variations for the gray scale tile chart that will make it easier to use? Reading amounts from a traditional business chart, such as a column chart, is straightforward. Amounts can be read from gray scale charts also by matching similar shades of gray on the legend (ship on the right) and the chart. The matching task seems more demanding on the gray scale chart, according to the subjects. It should be noticed that gray scale charts can contain many more data points than traditional charts of the same size and not seem visually overloaded. The column chart has 1/8 the number of data points (within the dashed lines) as the gray scale chart. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRADITIONAL COLUMN CHART</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GRAY SCALE TILE ~I-IAAT I</head><p>Comparing two amounts on charts is a simple process. For traditional charts the higher column, longer bar or larger area represents the larger number. With gray scale tile charts, the darker tiles represent the larger numbers.   Patterns, that is, repeated small clusters with the same structure, can be seen in traditional charts. In the column chart unit B follows a particular sequence. In the gray scale tile chart that sequence can be seen in two other places in the chart, one of which is outlined. The third place is vertical in orientation. Traditional charts are limited in showing patterns because the number of elements they contain is usually small compared with tile chart representations. Questions, and the subjects' responses and time codes, were positioned below the chart and are not shown here. This chart (shown 65% size) was used for seven of the 21 tasks in the experiment. The chart contains exactly the same information as the column and line charts. Questions, and the subjects' responses and time codes, were positioned to the lower right of the chart and are not shown here. Notice that the layout of chart elements on this chart is different than the other two charts. This chart looks like a mamx, with a third dimension coming out of the page (shade of gray). The matrix design is probably the reason why gray scale charts can be read faster than the more traditional charts.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>(right) and Figure 8 show gray scale tile charts. Axis units, shown as digits and letter characters in the figure, provide identification for individual tiles. The legend or scale on the right side of the chart provides numeric values for each shade of gray. In</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>1)</head><label></label><figDesc>are often of interest to a chart viewer. Bar. column, and sometimes line and pie charts are used to indicate numeric amounts. For example, an amount might be the gross sales of department A in 1988.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>(left) shows a bar chart which can provide this kind of information. The gray scale chart can also provide a viewer with information in the form of numeric amounts. By comparing a given shade of gray on the chart with the legend strip at the right, the viewer can detemine a numeric amount.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>3 )</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Trends are also important information to viewers of business charts. If a series of chart values are successively larger or smaller, a trend exists. Figure 3 (left) shows a line chart with several trends. The gray scale tile chart on the right also shows trends, as shown in the sample trend indicated. A little effort may be required to spot the trends contained in the gray scale chart, but once you see them, they become obvious. 4)GrouDhg. that is a recognizable sequence of values, can also be shown on business charts.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 4</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>left) presents a column chart with three constant values and a fourth one of less value. The gray scale tile chart also presents that same grouping. Groupings may be entirely of the same value (flat), may have only one difference as in this Figure 4, or may have many changes as in a sawtooth curve. Trends are a special case of grouping, where successive values consistently increase</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>5 ) 6 )Figure 1 .</head><label>561</label><figDesc>Do color tile charts have different information providing characteristics than their gray scale counterparts? What are they? Can textures be used instead of a gray scale in a tile chart? Which textures work the best? [8] Cleveland, W. S. (1985). The Elements of Graphing Data. Wadsworth. Besearch Met hods &amp; NUMERIC VALUES from Charts [9] Bertin, J. (1981). Graphics and GraD hic Information -. Translated from LA Graphique et le Traitement Graphique de 1'Information by W. J. Berg and P. Scott. de Gruyter Publishers. Inc. [lo] Schmid, C. F. and S. E. Schmid (1979). HandbQpk pf GraDhic Presentah. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York. [l 11 Penrose. J. M. Jr., R. W. Rasberry and R. J. Myers (1989). Advanced Bus iness CO mmunicatioq. Kent Pub1 Co., Boston.[12] Feeney, W. R. (1978). Timing individuals in a group using a computer-generated code sequence. a v i o r Besearch Methods &amp; Instrumen ta€iQ!L 10</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>COMPARISON of Amounts on Charts medium small large</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>TRENDS on ChartsTrends on a line chart seem obvious. Trends can also be picked out from a gray scale tile chart. Subjects were able to answer questions about trends on-gray scale charts. This gray scale chart also contains eight times the number of data points as the line chart.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>GROUPING of Chart ElementsGrouping, which is the identification of a single recognizable sequence of values, can be seen in a traditional chart.The same grouping can be seen also in gray scale charts. Colors and visual textures can also be used to visually group information in this way. same pattern pattern (multiple occurrence sequence)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>PATTERNS in Chart Elements Sample pattern: ~~~</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>TOWNFigure 6 .TOWNFigure 7 .</head><label>67</label><figDesc>Column Chart used in ExperimentThis chart (shown 50% size) was used for seven of the 21 tasks in the experiment. The chart contains exactly the same information as the line and gray scale charts.Questions, and the subjects' responses and time codes, were positioned below the chart and are not shown here. Line Chart used in Experiment This chart (shown 50% size) was used for seven of the 21 tasks in the experiment. The chart contains exactly the same information as the column and gray scale charts.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Gray Scale Tile Chart used in Experiment (shown above)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .6233.38 14 12674.13 2 6337.07 42.71 &lt;.001 uestions 2616.13 2 1308.07 11.40 ~0 0 1 ChartxQues 3539.47 4 884.87 5.48 &lt;.001 Errcharts 4154.76 28 148.38 3213.42 28 114.77 EkrChxQu 9038.31 56 161.40 41469.60 134 3 70 60 50 8 40 30 Column chart 2o 10 1 0 4 4</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Results of Analysis of Variance--Task Time</figDesc><table><row><cell>SOURCE</cell><cell>SS</cell><cell>df</cell><cell>MS</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>P</cell></row><row><cell>Subjects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 .SS df MS F P Subjects 2067.56 14 1758.53 2 879.27 8.28 c.005 Questions 3677.38 2 1838.69 20.94 c.001 ChartxQues 2710.22 4 677.56 8.44 c.001 EnCharts 2974.58 28 106.23 2458.40 28 87.80 ErrChxQu 4496.67 56 80.30 Total 20143.33 134 20 [ ! I 10 U . ~~ Value Comparison Trend Chart 2.</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Results of Analysis of Variance--Response correctness Percent of Correct Responses for Three Kinds in time taken for the question types (numeric value, comparison and trend). Each of the three chart types had several examples of each kind of question, so that these results do not contribute to answering the experimental question. The averages shown in Chart 2 show questions dealing with numeric values to be answered, on the average, faster than comparison questions. Trend questions took the longest.</figDesc><table><row><cell>SOURCE</cell></row><row><cell>TYPE OF Q W O N</cell></row><row><cell>of Charts</cell></row><row><cell>QUESTION TYPES. Table 1 shows a highly</cell></row><row><cell>significant difference (p c.001)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization in scientific computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mccormick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Defanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commter G r a~ -hics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shriver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The second tevo lution:visualizatiqn</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Friedhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Benzon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Harry N. Abrams. Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">701 Devonshire Drive, C-17</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Spyglass Sofiware, Inc</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61820</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Champaign</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Institute for Visualization and Perception Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>MA 01854</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Lowell</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Early experimental graphs. British</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The V isual for the JJiWry of Sciew</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tufte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="213" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quantitative Informan &apos;on. Graphics Press</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
