<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualization and Analysis of Multi-variate Data: A Technique for All Fields</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mihalisin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Timlin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schwegler</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mihalisin</forename><surname>Associates</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Honey</forename><surname>Run</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ambler</forename><surname>Pa</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualization and Analysis of Multi-variate Data: A Technique for All Fields</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>&quot;Scientific&quot; Visualization has been driven by t h need to visualize data sets that involve a large number of points andlor many &quot;dimensions&quot; or variables. However, many, or, perhaps all, fields of endeavor that use numeric data (including, finance, market research, management, manufacturing, process control, risk analysis, social services, health sciences, social sciences, physical sciences, computer science, applied mathematics, the engineering disciplines, and a host of other fields) deal with data sets of this type. Asking who can benefit from data visualization is like asking who can benefit from math or statistics. We present a hierarchical technique for visualizing truly multi-dimensional data that can be applied to any or all of these fields. The emphasis will be on visual statistical analysis of either discrete variables or continuous variables that have been sampled on, or binned to, a regular n-dimensional lattice.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Although the need to analyze large data sets of high dimensionality (more than three variables) has been championed' primarily by scientists and engineers it is a need that is shared by a wide range of non-scientists in business, government and academia. For instance, financial data, census data, survey data of all types, socio-economic data and medical records are intrinsically multi-variate and can involve tens or even hundreds of millions of data points, and are of interest to a wide audience of scientists and non-scientists alike.</p><p>The need to visualize and to a large extent to visually analyze data as graphics rather than text numbers is obvious when one speaks of millions or more data points. However, a satisfactory method of graphically presenting data involving more than three variables is not obvious and in fact has occu-pied many investigators over the last several decades. A range of techniques involving projections of the data onto two variable subspaces2 has evolved. Non-projective techniques have also been invented, such as, the parallel axis technique3 and the use of icons or glyphs4. Each of these techniques has been found to be of some utility for visualizing certain types of multi-variate data. Moreover, the projective techniques and the parallel axis technique can be used to provide some types of visual data analysis. However, a satisfactory general method for plotting large multi-variate data sets which allows the user to interactively visualize and to visually analyze his or her data in real time has not emerged from these techniques</p><p>We have invented a new way of plotting large multi-variate data sets which meets these goals. The technique was first reported5in a form applicable only to data for which the variables could be classified into two distinct sets, namely a set of independent variables, and a set of dependent variables with the former sampled at values that form a regular n-dimensional lattice. The technique involves the mapping of the n independent variable dimensions to a single hierarchical horizontal axis with a single dependent variable being plotted on the vertical axis. A set of hierarchicql data driven symbols representing the behavior of the data at points, along lines, in planes, in 3 spaces, 4 spaces, etc. can be defined in a variety of ways. The use of the first instance of the technique, and in particular, its rules for defining the hierarchical datadriven symbols will only be covered briefly here since it and its use in visually fitting multi-variate data, finding minima, maxima, zeros, regions of stability, dominant and irrelevant variables, etc. has been covered previou~lf~9~. Similarly, extensions of the technique by us and othersg to the case of creating two subsets of independent variables, one subset represented hierarchically on the horizontal axis and the other subset represented hierarchically on the vertical axis will not be discussed here. This approach uses color or gray scale to represent the dependent variable and may' or may notg invoke a set of rules for hierarchical data representations. This technique is more appropriate for qualitative visualization of large databases rather than visual data analysis.</p><p>In this article we wish to discuss the general applicability of the single hierarchical axis technique and to explore new ways of representing the hierarchical data-driven symbols that are particularly well suited to a variety of visual analysis tasks including fitting, visual display of distribution and cumulative distribution functions and conditional probabilities, visual determination of significant mean differences, visual factor and correlation analysis and multi-variate "what-if" scenarios. In all instances, the techniques are extremely fast because simple 2-d graphics are used to represent all data dimensionalities and the technique only draws a maximum of -1000 data symbols per screen refresh even though they may represent the behavior of millions or even hundreds of millions of data points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I I I I I I I I</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multi-variate data and the hierarchical axis I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I</head><p>By truly n-dimensional data we mean a list of ntuples, i.e., n associated numbers. One may think of the n-tuples as representing n variables. These variables may be thought of as either a set of n variables with no classification as to "dependent" or "independent" or as n-1 independent variables and 1 dependent variable which may or may not be single-valued. One cannot divide the variables into m independent variables and n-m&gt; 1 single-valued dependent variables and still have an n-dimensional data set. In this case, one has instead n-m instances of data sets of dimension m+l.</p><p>One truly robust way of representing, say n-1 independent variables and 1 dependent variable is to list the n tuples vertically, hence forming n columns by r rows where r is the number of n-tuples. This format can be used to represent any and all possible samplings of points in the n dimensional space, from the most highly regular array or lattice to the most randomly scattered points imaginable.</p><p>When dealing with data points, even of low dimensionality, for example d=3, the classification of the set of points as representing a trajectory or a surface or a volume is not well defined even though viewing the data points may create a psychological impression of a line or surface or volume. The appropriate interpretation may or may not be known to the investigator.</p><p>In the technique to be discussed we may plot data by choosing one of the columns (variables) to be the dependent variable and the remainder to be the independent variables. If the values of the independent variables already form a discrete regular lattice we will proceed to our technique to be discussed shortly. If the independent variables are instead continuous in nature and sampled in a more or less random fashion we can form equal interval bins in the n-1 dimensional space of independent variables and in effect map the independent variable space to a regular lattice. In this approach each bin in the n-1 dimensional space may contain zero or a non-zero number of the original data points. We may of course choose to bin all n variables and to create a new dependent variable, i.e., the number of points in each bin. We will assume that the data of interest is manifestly lattice-like as is the case for categorical variables and for many computationally derived data sets or that it can be cast to a lattice via binning.</p><p>-1 cube The mapping of the multiple independent variables to one hierarchical axis is indicated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure  1</ref> for the case Of 3 independent variables. There are in fact 3!=6 ways of doing this mapping corresponding to which variable is fastest running, which is second fastest, and which is slowest (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig.1</ref>). One may think of the data as consisting of a collection of points or lines parallel to the fastest running variable axis or planes parallel to the fastestl2nd fastest variable plane or as one rectangular parallelepiped. We will give examples for the case where there are no missing values, i.e., an n dimensional surface, n being 4 in the case of plotting a single dependent variable over the 3 dimensional space of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">I zl z[y@, z slowest 4 I x fastest 1 3sauares Y3 y l y l E y l E :: ---. - X X X 21 22 23 1 9 lines / 27 mints I ----* ----. --. --. --. - x x x x x x x x x Y2 Y3 Y1 Y2 Y3 Y1 Y2 Y3 I y1 21 22 23</formula><p>The hierarchical mapping of the independent variables to the horizontal axis seems to imply that the maximum number of points in the n dimensional space is constrained to be of the order of 1000 or so, i.e., the number of pixels along the horizontal of a monitor. However, we are interested in representing millions or even hundreds of millions or more data points. This problem will be overcome by inventing a set of hierarchical (color or gray-scale coded) symbols that will represent the data not only at individual data points but also along data lines, and in 2d, 3d, 4d, etc. data subspaces. If the number of data points exceeds the number of horizontal pixels we will only see the hierarchical data symbols for data lines and/or data 2d subspaces andor data 3d subspaces, etc. A set of tools including a subspace zoom tool will allow us to view any region in the space to any desired resolution so that no information is lost.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hierarchical data symbols and variable widgets</head><p>Shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> are three ways of rendering the hierarchical data symbols using a small simple data set. The set has three variables A, B and C.A, B and C have 3 values namely 0, 1,2. The data was generated by the function D = (A2 + B)e=. Here D is the dependent variable plotted along the vertical and A,B and C are the independent variables plotted along the horizontal axis in the hierarchical fashion described with A being the fastest running followed by B and then C.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> we have coded the variables by grayscale with A being lightest and B darkest. In the color plate A is white, B is blue and C is red. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.   2</ref> the widths of the rectangles are correlated with the corresponding variables. That is, the white rectangles correspond to points which are sampled by moving with the white variable as the fastest running. These rectangles are of width one, i.e., they represent one data point in the space. The blue rectangles represents the behavior of the data over a line in the white direction at a specific value of the blue variable. They are of width 3 and represent the behavior along the line of 3 points. Each red rectangle is of width 3 x 3 = 9 and represents the behavior of the data over a plane, i.e., an A, B or white, blue plane at the specific value of the red variable. This association is easily extended to an arbitrary number of independent variables. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.2</ref> the heights and vertical positions of the hierarchical rectangles are determined by 3 different rules. Each rule is consistent with the concept that the vertical position and/or height of a particular rectangle should reflect the behavior of the dependent variable in the corresponding subspace, i.e., point, line, plane, 3 space, etc. In the top panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.2</ref> the bottom of a rectangle is drawn a t a height that corresponds to the minimum value of the dependent variable in the corresponding subspace and the top of the rectangle is drawn a t the maximum. This method is called "midmax rendering''. In the middle panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.2</ref> the bottom of the rectangle is drawn a t D=O and top is drawn a t the sum of D within the corresponding subspace if the sum is positive. If the sum is negative, the top is at D=O and the bottom is at the value of the sum. This method is called "sum rendering". In the bottom panel of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.2</ref> the bottom of the rectangle is drawn a t the mean in the corresponding subspace minus the standard deviation of the mean while the top is drawn a t the mean plus the standard deviation of the mean. Hence, the vertical location of the center of the rectangle denotes the mean and the vertical extent of the rectangle reflects the uncertainty in the mean (here chosen as 2 standard deviations of the mean). Clearly, other criteria can be used to drive the vertical extent of these rectangles. This method is called "mean rendering."</p><p>The three rules for determining the vertical locations andlor extents of the rectangles shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.2</ref> are simply illustrative. They were chosen because they have obvious utility for common multi-variate analysis tasks. Other rules may be invented to suit a particular task. The software system under development supports user defined rendering rules.</p><p>As discussed in earlier a r t i c l e~,~*~?~ one needs a variety of tools that allow one to permute variables, i.e., change which variable is fastest, or 2nd fastest, etc., zoom to a subspace or lower dimension, i.e., fix a vanable or vanables to a specific value, zoom to a subinterval of one or more variables, sample the space in a more coarse-grained fashion, etc. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig.3</ref> schematically defines a variety of tools. In addition to the tools shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig.3</ref>, one may clone the graph a t any point. One may create as many clones as one likes. The clones may be positioned and sized via the mouse. Each tool has an inverse so that one may recover the initial view of the data. Each tool may be applied to any or all variables once or repeatedly. All of the tools are fully integrated so that one may execute any combination of tools on any number of variables. All of the tools may be applied to any rendering method and one may toggle between rendering methods a t will.</p><p>The animation tool and the general zoom and sub-space zoom tools and their inverses may be applied with auto-scaling of the vertical axis (dependent variable axis) turned on or off. This feature proves to be essential for a variety of tasks including fitting, conditional probability determinations and correlation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The sum rendering method, distributions, conditional probabilities and correlations</head><p>Shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref> is a small data set of low dimensionality drawn using the sum rendering I74 I method. Here the dependent variable (plotted on the vertical) is the number of data entities (for example, companies) while the independent variables A, B and C take on values A,, A2, A3; B1, B2, B3 and C1, Cp, C3, respectively. Hence the 3 dimensional independent variable space represented on the hierarchical horizontal axis contains 3 x 3~3 =27 points. Here A is the fastest running variable followed by B and finally C is the slowest. In general, the total number of data entities (for example, companies) may far exceed the number of data points = 27 or may be far less than the number of data points. The number of entities with a specific set of  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">~3j=1X3itlN(Ai,B,,ck)</ref>. Hence the height of these rectangles vs. Ck constitutes the doubly cumulative distribution function ~3=1~3i3i=1N(Ai,Bj,C~). These rectangles are red (intermediate gray-scale) in color. There are 3 rectangles of this type. Hence, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig.4</ref> visually presents 9 distribution fbnctions of the form N vs. A, i.e., one for each of the 9 choices of fixed variables B and C. These are the 9 sets of 3 white rectangles inside blue rectangles (white inside dark gray-scale). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig.4</ref> also shows 3 single cumulative distributions N w vs. 3, i.e., one for each value of C.</p><p>It is important to note hawever, that <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig.4</ref> does not show all possible distributions. This is due to the ordered nature of the variables along the hierarchical axis. In order to view, for example N vs. B or N m vs. C or NBX vs. A, the variable ordering would have to be B fastest, C 2nd fastest and A slowest. Shown in <ref type="figure">Fig.5</ref> are the 3!=6 possible permutations of the variables and the resulting hierarchical graphs. This collection of graphs can be made manually be using the permute and clone tools and positioning the clones manually or may be defined as a standard tool macro. This collection of graphs shows all possible distributions and single and double cumulative distributions. Moreover, it shows how distributions and cumulative distributions depend parametrically on other variables. For instance, one can follow how N vs. B evolves for differing A but fixed C, etc.</p><p>It is important to recognize that Figs.4 and 5 may also be used to determine conditional probabilities. For instance consider the 1st red rectangle (far left red or intermediate gray-scale rectangle) of width 9 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig.4</ref>. It corresponds to C=C1. If one normalizes the height of this red rectangle to unity, then the height of the 1st blue (darker gray-scale) rectangle inside the 1st red rectangle is the probability of obtaining B=B1 irrespective of the value of A, for C fixed at C=C1. Similarly, the height of the 2nd white rectangle inside of the 1st blue rectangle inside of the first red rectangle is the probability of obtaining B=B1, and A=A2 subject to the constraint C=C1. Similarly, if one normalized the height of the 1st blue rectangle inside the 1st red rectangle to be unity, then the height of the same white rectangle would be the probability of obtaining A=A2 subject to the constraint that C1=C2 and B=B1, etc. In fact, viewed in this way, <ref type="figure">Fig.5</ref> shows all possible conditional probabilities of this sort consistent with the original data. However, one could also ask more complicated questions such as the following: what would be the probability of obtaining either C1 or C2 if only values A1 and A2 (i.e., not A3) were allowed etc. The fully integrated nature of the general zoom, decimate and subspace tools (with autoscaling on or off) allows one to quickly answer these questions visually for a mind-boggling number of cases.</p><p>We should note from <ref type="figure">Fig.5</ref> that A and C appear to be distributed uniformly while B appears to have an exponential distribution. This is probably most obvious if one focuses one's attention on the slowest running variables and hence the double cumulative distributions. If the number of values for A were substantially larger while the number of B and C values remained fixed one would be better able to ascertain whether certain trends seen in noncumulative distributions are significant. For example, consider the case of N vs. A for C=C2 and B=B1 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig.4</ref>. If ten white rectangles showed an exponential decay instead of three the likelihood of it being a fluctuation would diminish significantly, i.e., by a factor of 2'. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig.6</ref> we show a simple example of how correlation between two variables is visually indicated by the sum rendering method. Here a population N is plotted for 2 variables, A and B, with 7 bins and 3 bins respectively. The first set of 7 small rectangles (for B=l) corresponds to the distribution N vs A for B fixed at B=l. The second set of 7 small rect-angles corresponds to N vs A for B fixed at B=2 and the third set corresponds to N vs A for B=3. Note that the most populated A value increases (shifts to the right) as one moves from B1 to B2 to B1. It is this shiR that indicates that A and B are correlated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The mean rendering method vs traditional methods</head><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig.6</ref> the correlation of A and B is indicated in the sum rendering method by a shift in the peak of N vs A as B varies. Next we want to show how correlation is indicated when one uses the mean rendering method to plot the mean of one variable (not the population N) on the vertical versus one or more variables on the horizontal. Consider data consisting of 4 variables A, B, C, and D and 1000 records (N=1000). We will divide A, B, C and D into 5 bins each to form a total of 54=625 bins in our 4 dimensional A, B, C, D space. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig.7</ref> we show a tool macro that displays, in   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">/orp/ete, p g e 421.</ref>) a graph matrix style, the mean of each of the four variables on the verticals, versus each choice of the and C, &lt;B&gt; and A, &lt;B&gt; and C, &lt;C&gt; and A, cC&gt; and B, and &lt;D&gt; and A (if present) are much slowest running variable on the horizontal, with trivial cases such as &lt;A&gt; vs A omitted. For instance, the  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig.8</ref> contains 1000 points. Clearly, the correlations are not as obvious in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig.8</ref> as they are in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig.7</ref>. Traditional graph matrix methods have been augmented2 by dynamic "brushing" which allows one to select a subrange of any variable (e.g., A of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig.8</ref>) and see only the corresponding points in all 12 of the panels of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig.8</ref>. Similarly, one can limit two variables, etc. The hierarchical mean rendering method and in particular, the matrix of graphs displayed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig.7</ref> can be set to show the means when one constrains two variables and only averages over the last remaining variable. Hence each rectangle of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig.7</ref> contains 5 narrower rectangles which correspond to averaging each variable over a line rather than a 2-dimensional subspace (the latter being the rectangles shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig.7</ref>). <ref type="figure">Fig.9</ref> shows the resulting figure consisting of 12 graphs each with 5 wide rectangles and 25 narrow rectangles. For example, the second panel of the top row in <ref type="figure">Fig.9</ref> shows the mean of A over the CD subspace denoted now explicitly as &amp;CD (instead of simply CA&gt;) versus B (wider rectangles) and the mean of A over lines parallel to D denoted as &lt;A&gt;D versus C and B (C being the faster running variable). In order to obtain similar information using the traditional graph matrix method (and brushing) would require that one retain (in one's mind, or, on hardcopy) the results of 320 brushings, i.e., a total of 320 4x4 graph matrices like the one shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig.8</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>The hierarchical graphing methods presented can be used to visually analyze data in a wide variety of ways. Although we have chosen to display small data sets involving only a few variables, the technique can be applied to much larger data sets and still be a realtime visual analysis tool. For instance, a subspace zoom for a dataset involving 10 variables and 1 million bins can be performed in a fraction of a second on a Sun Sparcstation. We are in the process of general-izing the system so that it will support user-defined hierarchical data symbol renderings.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Schematic representation of how a multi-dimensional space is mapped to a hierarchical horizontal axis; shown here for the d-3 case with x, y and z having three values each and ordered so that x is fastest running, then y and then z.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>The function D=(A2+B)eDC with A, B, C = 1,2,3. Here A is the fastest running variable and C is the slowest. Three methods i.e. the midmax, sum and mean methods, are shown. (See co/orp/ate, pago 421.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Schematic representation of the effects of the subspace zoom, general zoom, decimate and animate tools on any variable.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Population data using the s u m method showing 9 N vs. A distributions for 9 values of (B, C), 3 NM vs. B distributions for 3 values of C and a single N m vs. C distribution. (SOO wlorplate, page 421.)A,B and C variable values, say, A=Ai, B=Bj, and c=ck, will be denoted as N(A$jCk.). Each of the narrowest rectangles of width one, inFig.4represents one (of the set of 27) N(AiBjCk) numbers and has a height proportional to N(AiB,C). These rect-angIes are white. Each of the rectangles of width =3 (bluddarkest gray-scale) represents the cumulative distribution X3i=1(NAiyBj,Ck). There are 9 such rectangles corresponding to the 3x3=9 values of BjYCk. Each has a height of C3i,lN(Aj,Bj,Ck).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>An example of two correlated variables using the s u mmethod. (see co/orp/ete, page 421.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>DFigure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>A matrix of conventional graphs showing A vs. B, Avs. C and A vs. D (top row) etc.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>a matrix of mean method graphs. Showing for example &lt;A&gt; vs. B, &lt;A&gt; vs. C and &lt;A&gt; VS. D (top row) etc. ( s e co/orp/ate, ~4~4 2 1 . ) Figure 9. A matrix of mean method graphs showing &lt;A&gt;, &lt;B&gt;, &lt;C&gt; and &lt;D&gt; vs. two hierarchical variables. (! % co</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>top ' Ow shows the mean Of A denoted as &lt;A&gt; versus For comparison to more conventional non-hierar-&lt;A&gt; and D9 &lt;B&gt; and D9 &lt;' &gt; and D9 &lt;D&gt; ure. Note that correlations between &lt;A&gt; and B, &lt;A&gt;Fig.8 which shows the same data as Fig.7 plotted in and B, and &lt;D&gt; and c is Obvious from this type Of figthe traditional graph matrix manne2. That is, the variables A, B, C and D are not binned and their means are not computed. Instead one simply plots A (not &lt;A&gt;) versus B (not binned B intervals), A versus C, etc. Hence each of the 12 graphs of</figDesc><table><row><cell>then</cell><cell>and</cell><cell>D. The strong cor-</cell><cell>&amp;iCal multi-variate graphing</cell><cell>consider</cell></row></table><note>Of</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The authors wish to acknowledge Temple University's support of this research and all of the associated patent filings.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">See entire issue of IEEE Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>which is devoted solely to scientific visualization</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamic Graphics for Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bbecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cleveland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>W.S. Cleveland and M.E. McGill, Wadworth and Brooks/Cole</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Belmont, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Inselberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dimsdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. on Visualization<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A reference Model for the Visualization of Multi-dimensional data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bergeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Eurographics</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics<address><addrLine>North Holland, Amsterdam</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="393" to="399" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schwegler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Scientific Computing and Automation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989-10" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphing in Multiple Dimensions with MGTS</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mihalisin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Suntech J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="375" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mihalisin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gawlinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Timlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="31" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mihalisin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gawlinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Timlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schwegler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. Visualization<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="262" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mihalisin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Timlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schwegler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leblanc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Wittles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. Visualization<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="230" to="237" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
