<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Chemical Kinetics in Fractal Domains</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Neal</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hurlburt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Raoul</forename><surname>Kopelman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department Research Laboratories Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">NASA Ames Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Michagan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Palo Alto</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">CA Mountain View</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>CA, MI</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Chemical Kinetics in Fractal Domains</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Chemical reactions occurring within complex domains, such as fractals, can display behavior which differs radically from the expectations of classical chemical kinetics. Rather than relaxing to a uniform distribution at the steady state, these non-classical systems display large-scale order on many scales. Such self-organization is dificult to measure using the usual statistical techniques, but is visually apparent. Hence visualization is essential to the understanding of these chemical systems. We discuss some of the problems of visualizing chemical kinetics in fractal domains and describe evolution of the visualization as the chemist and visualization scientist collaborated.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Scientific Background</head><p>In natural systems, the environment through which particles must diffuse before reacting frequently plays a determining role in both the rate of the chemical reaction and in the particle distribution. The physical barriers to particle motion may be a consequence of reactions at the interfaces of phases (solid-liquid, solid-gas, etc.), reactions in pores or membranes, or reactions in solid-state materials where traosport follows restricted paths. Diffusion-limited reactions may also depend on various physical parameters such as temperature or pressure. Studying the behavior of chemical reactions in lower dimensional media, such as fractals, is one means for understanding such reactions. These systems display anomalous chemical kinetics which are difficult to understand or to characterize .</p><p>Insight into the physical phenomena can be gamered from computer simulations.</p><p>The diffusion-limited reactions are modeled using random walker simulations. Two different types of random walkers, A and B, are used to model the chemical reactants, and reaction rate mechanisms are simulated which have zero activation energy. Hence, a chemical reaction occurs instantaneously when A and B reactants arrive simultaneously at a site on the fractal lattice. These simulations add A and B reactants at a constant rate and only remove reactants after an A and B pair react.</p><p>CH3046-0/91/0000/0364/$01 .OO 0 1991 IEEE</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">_ _~~~ ~ -. . -</formula><p>Consequently, the number of A reactants is always identical to the number of B reactants.</p><p>Fractal surfaces are ideal models for diffusionlimited reactions in geometrically constrained systems.</p><p>Fractals are geometric structures which are infinitely scalable. They are characterized by the fact that the density does not scale normally with the lengtb scale. In general classical systems, the density scales as p=m/ld where d is the Euclidean dimension (one, two, three, etc.); however, with fractals, the density scales as p = m/ldf where df is the fractal dimension (often a fractional number which is less than or equal to d).</p><p>Large scale computer simulations of these systems under steady-source conditions extend over long time scales (one million time steps or more) and extend over longer and longer length scales so that statistically significant data can be obtained in the limit of low steady-state densities. Although fractal systems are idbite, computer simulations do not permit infinite systems. When working with such structures, it is necessary to work with finite systems and to ensure that several decades are included.</p><p>For the simulations presented here, the planar Sierpinski gasket is used to model the lower-dimensional system. The h c t a l dimension of the Sierpinski gasket is d~1.585. This h c t a l shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> illustrates 5th order Sierpinski gasket. The simulations which we discuss below use Sierpinski gaskets of up to the loth order which include 1024 triangles across the bottom row of the gasket. This system is too large to represent in detail with a direct mapping of a set of pixels to each vertex in the loth order Sierpinski gasket.</p><p>The time evolution of the reactant density and position on the fractal is recorded by storing the actual location of each reactant on the Sierpinski gasket as a function of time. This information is not stomi for each time increment. It is also not sampled at identical time intervals. Initially, the reactant density is zero and then it builds to the steady state density.</p><p>To illustrate the rate of population growth, data is stored every 10 time steps for the first 1000 time steps, then it is stored every 100 time steps for the first loo00 time steps, and every 250 time steps for the duration of the simulation. For simulations of one million time steps, this produces more than 4000 sets of data for each individual simulation. At each of these steps there are approximately 4000 particles. For compact data storage, addresses on the lattice are mapped to a one-dimensional array of numbers.</p><p>The rate of reaction is obtained using a non-linear regression of the particle density as a function of time. In this manner, the rate of reaction, r, has a power-law behavior of r = k[AJx where the reactant density of A, <ref type="bibr">[A]</ref>, is identical to the reactant density of B, and X is the order of the reaction. In the low density regime, the reaction order is X=2.84 which is very far from the classical reaction order of X=2. This is a measure of the anomalous chemical kinetics, but does not provide much insight into the phenomena which cause this to occur.</p><p>Visualization of these systems provided the dramatic Just as it is difficult to quantify this behavior, the visualization of these systems is also difficult. We will discuss below the nature of the fractal surface, its apparent role in the kinetics, and an approach to visualize these systems for simultaneous viewing on both the small scale and the integrated larger scale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Visualization</head><p>One of the difficulties with this project was the discontinuous nature of the data. Unlike many visualization projects data only existed at discrete or image had the annoying property of covering areas smaller than the resolution of our imaging systems. The amount of data was moderate, involving several thousand points over a million steps. There was no a priori reason to expect temporal or spatial correlations and hence we could not anticipate the sampling fresuency required to create a meaningful visualization.</p><p>As with many other visualizations, a large part of the effort was spent preprocessing the data. The data format most convenient for the calculation, storage and transport was not ideal for visualization. As we discuss below, we found that we needed to sort the data points into bins of various sizes corresponding to the order of the displayed S i e r p U gasket. Hence every animation required a different sorting of points. Using an interactive data language (IDL) we were able to build this triangular sorting algorithm into our interactive exploratory visualizations and then use the same procedures for the batch video recording sessions without needing to generate intermediate data or image files.</p><p>Initially the reseatchers displayed their data using simple scatter diagrams generated by a color pen plotter as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 2</ref>  However there were several fundamental problems. First, the symbols had to be large enough to see, which meant that they overlapped and interfered with each other. Hence the perceived spatial distribution depended upon which color point was placed first, and the overall density seemed artificially high. Second since each point was plotted separately, there was no means for blending the colors. This resulted in a distortion of the relative balance between the species. Depending upon the choice of colors, and order of placement, one species might appear to dominate a region when it was in fact in close balance with the other! It was clear that the scatter diagrams would not work for the large scale simulations, where more than one thousand sites were situated along the base of the l0th-order Sierpinski gasket. Hence we turned to a Sierpinski gasket of lower relative order and regional triangles as our visual icon. A sixth-order gasket was the largest order we could view on video and a seventh-order gasket was the largest we could view on still images. Here, the relative order subtracted from ten is the order of the underlying Sierpinski gasket. Each regional triangle within the lower-order gasket spanned many sites of the computational gasket. We therefore assigned their hue by the relative population of the two species within each using a three-valued color table. We also varied the intensity of each regional triangle to reflect the combined population of both species within it, with the brightest triangles being the most highly populated. A sample of this visualization is displayed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure  3</ref>. One or the other species dominates for triangles of magenta or green and they are in balance for triangles of yellow. Now the overall structure of the self-organization is clear. The upper triangle is dominated by one species (magenta) while the lower two are dominated by the other (green). Further within the lower triangles there are smaller triangles dominated by magenta species, which suggested the presence of multiple length scales. With this display we had achieved our initial desires for the visualization. However when viewing the time evolution of the system we were struck by its discontinuous nature -greatly impeding our ability to observe the evolution of the various scales. Hence we reconsidered the visualization.</p><p>Since the data possessed multiple scales we chose to present it as such. We settled upon the use of differing relative orders of Sierpinski gaskets. Further we added the ability to zoom in on subregions of the gasket to fully resolve the computational gasket within specific regions of interest.</p><p>Once again the hue for each triangular site was assigned by the relative population: here they take on two possible values. In addition, the saturation was varied according to this balance: it increased from zero when the species were in balance to unity if one completely dominated. Our algorithm for selecting the intensity of each triangle had to be modified.Since we needed to avoid intensity variations with the order or degree of zoom we chose to vary the intensity with the density of occupied sites rather than the total population within each triangle.</p><p>Fmally we added a map in the corner to display where we were with respect to the entire gasket along with a few details to make the image more visually appealing. We display a sampling of the final visualization in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>. If the reactants behaved classically, all the sites would be grey in these images independent of scale. We can now see the clustering on different scales and follow them in time. The resulting video has proven a valuable tool in demonstrating the large-scale self-organization of such systems and their temporal evolution.  Visualizing Chcmicul Kinetics zti / -~m * t u l I l o~m i i~s , N.E. Hurlburt, L.\V. h a c k e r , and R. <ref type="bibr">Kopelman,</ref>   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>A fifth-order Sierpinski gasket.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>measure of the anomalous kinetic behavior (the ability of these systems to self-organize). At this point, simple measures to quantify the self-organization have not been established. While numeric measures provided an indication of the anomalous kinetic behavior, the insight into the physical phenomena was only gained with the visualization of these systems. This showed a dramatic segregation of reactants. A simulation of two reactants, A and B, resulted in the upper half of the gasket being populated by A particles and the lower half of the gasket being populated by B particles.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. The two chemical species where assigned colors, typically red and blue. The plotter would mark the locations of each species with the appropriately colored symbol. With this means of display, the researchers where able to get some idea of the relative balance and distribution of the species.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Scatter-plot of chemical species</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .(</head><label>4</label><figDesc>See color plates, page 434.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Flgure</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactions in Fractal and Small Dimensions at the Steady State: Anomalous chemical Kinetics and Reactant Self-Ordering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anacker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kopelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Science at The John von Newnann National Supercomputer Center</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cook (Consortium for Scientific Computing:Princeton)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractal Reaction Kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kopelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">241</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1620" to="1626" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
