<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Realistic Volume Imaging</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roni</forename><surname>Yagel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">State University of New York at Stony Brook</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arie</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">State University of New York at Stony Brook</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">State University of New York at Stony Brook</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Qiang</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">State University of New York at Stony Brook</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Shimony</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">State University of New York at Stony Brook</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Realistic Volume Imaging</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>W e present a set of volume visualization tools that are based on the use of recursive ray tracing aa the primary vehicle f o r realistic volume imaging. The visualization tools include shadows, mirrors, specularity, and constructive solid geometry. The underlying representation f o r the ray tracer is a SD raster of vozels that holds the discrete form of the scene. Unlike traditional volume rendering techniques, our discrete recursive ray tracer models many illumination phenomena b y traversing discrete rays in vozel space. Our approach provides true ray tracing of sampled or computed datasets, as well as ray tracing of hybrid scenes where sampled or eomputed data are intermized with geometric models. W e demonstrate that our techniques enhance the understanding of eomplez biome die a1 datas e ts.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>A major goal in computer graphics has been the synthesis of photorealistic images using, among other techniques, recursive ray tracing of geometric models.</p><p>It is not obvious, however, that photorealism enhances the perception of rendered sampled or computed datasets. Nevertheless, the need for enriching our set of visualization capabilities for volumetric datasets in terms of rendering options has already been recognized. <ref type="bibr">Levoy et al.</ref> [15] have used 'artistic devices' (e.g., metallic surface shading, shadows, cutting planes, texturing) to enhance perception of spatial relationships in radiation treatment planning. Shirley and Neeman <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[19]</ref> have utilized mirrors and shadows in surface-based representation of flow fields.</p><p>Our experience also indicates that photorealism tools (e.g., shadows, mirrors, and specularity), if used wisely, have the potential to greatly facilitate insight into volumetric datasets.</p><p>R a y casting methods, in which only primary rays are traced, have been applied to volumetric datasets, such as those arising in biomedical imaging and scientific visualization applications (e.g., <ref type="bibr">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr">201)</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Greene [6]</ref> has applied ray casting to estimate the illumination of a voxel model of stochastically grown plants. Levoy [16, 171 has used the term ray tracing of volume data to refer to compositing of even-spaced samples along the primary viewing rays. Since ray casting follows only primary rays, it does not directly support the simulation of many illumination phenomena such as reflection, shadows, and refraction. The study of ray casting of volume densities has included, among others, a probabilistic simulation of light passing through and being reflected by clouds of small particles [l], as well as the light-scattering equations of densities within a volume grid, such as clouds, fog, flames, dust, and particle systems (81.</p><p>The approach taken in this paper is based on traversing 3 D discrete rays through a 3 D raster of voxels that consists of the discrete fully-digitized representation of the scene. Unlike ray casting, our method considers both primary and secondary rays and thus can create photorealistic images. It exploits the voxel representation for a uniform and simplified treatment. It ray traces sampled and computed volumetric datasets, traditional geometric scenes, or an intermixing thereof [5, 13, 171, such as, a scalpel superimposed on a CT image, radiation beams superimposed on a scanned tumor, or a mirror behind a sampled neuron.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">8D Raster Rsy Tracing</head><p>Our approach, termed 9D raster ray tracing (RRT), operates in two major phases: a preprocessing voxelieation phase and a discrete ray tracing phase. In the voxelization phase, the volumetric dataset is reconstructed and stored in the 3 D raster. The geometric model is digitized, using incremental 3 D scan-conversion algorithms [3, 9-11, 181 which convert the continuous representation of the model into a discrete representation that can be intermixed with the sampled data within the 3 D raster. In the second phase, a variation of the conventional ray tracing algorithm is employed. In conventional ray tracing algorithms analytical rays are intersected with the object list in an attempt to find the nearest intersection. In contrast, RRT employs 3 D discrete rays that are traversed through the 3 D raster. Encountering a non-transparent voxel represents a ray-surface hit.</p><p>Our rendering algorithm is described in detail elsewhere [23], though some of the major advantages in the 3 D raster approach to scene representation, in the context of scientific visualization, should be mentioned. For the geometric objects in the scene, the computationally expensive ray-object intersection calculation is eliminated; instead, RRT relies solely on a fast discrete ray traversal mechanism and a single simple type of objectthe voxel. Consequently, RRT performance is practically independent of the number, complexity, or type of objects in the scene.</p><p>In addition, many view-independent attributes, such as surface normal, texture color, and light source visibility and illumination, can be precomputed during the voxelization phase and stored with each voxel. Furthermore, rasters in general lend themselves to block operations such as bitblt or the 3 D counterpart, uozblt <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[12]</ref>. In particular, the 3 D raster lends itself to voxel-by-voxel Boolean operations which can be performed during the preprocessing stage, simplifying the ray tracing of constructive solid geometry (CSG) models. Block operations add a variety of modeling capabilities which aid in the task of image synthesis by supporting the manipulation of true volumetric objects that have information inside them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Voxeliaation Phase</head><p>Volumetric ray tracing of geometric scenes commences with a preprocessing voxelization phase that precedes the actual ray tracing. In the voxelization phase, the scene is converted into a discrete voxel representation by 3 D scan-converting (voxelieing), each of the geometric objects comprising the scene. A 3 D voxelization algorithm for a given geometric object generates the set of voxels that best approximates the continuous specification of the object and stores the discrete object aa a 3 D array of unit voxels. Each voxel is a quantum unit of volume that has associated numeric values representing some measurable properties or attributes of the real object or phenomenon at that voxel. A voxel is assumed to be homogeneous, that is, it contains information regarding a single object only. The aggregate of voxels tessellates the 3 D grid of voxels, also termed the 3 D raster.</p><p>The voxelieation phase generates, for each surface voxel, its color (or texture color), the normal vector, and two bits per light source to denote whether that light source is visible, occluded, or visible through a translucent material. Actually, the view-independent parts of the illumination equation, that is, the ambient illumination and the sum of the attenuated diffuse illumination of all the visible light sources, can also be precomputed and added to the voxel's color. All view-independent attributes that are precomputed during the voxelieation stage and stored with the voxel are then readily accessible for speeding up the ray tracing phase.</p><p>The normal vector to the sampled or computed surfaces can be estimated either during a preprocessing stage when it is stored with the voxel or during the ray tracing stage. The normal estimation may employ any object-space method such as the contextual shading approach [2], the gray-level gradient approach [7], the biquadratic local surface interpolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>, or the context sensitive approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[22]</ref>. We have chosen to employ a variation of the gray-level gradient approach that examines a larger neighborhood in order to enhance normal integrity.</p><p>Digitization of solids has been traditionally performed by spatial enumeration algorithms which employ point or cell classification methods in an exhaustive fashion, or preferably, by recursive subdivision [14]. However, subdivision techniques for model decomposition into rectangular subspaces are computationally expensive and thus inappropriate for medium or high resolution grids. The 3D scanconversion algorithms we employ (3, 9-11], on the other hand, follow the same paradigm as the 2D scan-conversion algorithms commonly used in 2 D raster graphics. They are incremental, use simple arithmetic (preferably integer-based), and have a complexity that is not more than linear with the number of voxels generated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discrete Ray Tracing Phase</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Visualisation Toole</head><p>Once the discrete representation of the scene is available, a variation of the conventional ray tracer is employed. For each screen pixel, our ray tracer computes the intersections of the pixel ray with the boundary of the 3D raster, defining the two endpoints of the discrete ray. The discrete ray traversal commences at the nearest endpoint, the discrete ray origin, and continues by traversing the 3D dicrete l i e representation of the ray through the 3D raster. The first non-transparent voxel encountered by the discrete ray indicates a ray-surface hit. When a hit occurs, the voxel encountered by the ray is known and its attributes are readily available.</p><p>Each surface voxel also stores the color, illumination, and/or the texture color for that voxel. This information is used for color composition. Since the texture mapping ia view-independent, it ia precomputed during the voxelisation algorithm from a 2D texture/photo map or a 3D texture. There is no need, for example, to recompute the inverse mapping needed for texture mapping for every different viewpoint.</p><p>Since the visibility of the light sources from each voxel is also view-independent, shadow rays are fired from each surface voxel to all light sources during the voxeliration preprocessing stage. The light visibility information is stored in two bits per light source per voxel, denoting whether that light source is visible, occluded, or visible through a translucent material. Only for the third case, a shadow ray are fired at rendering time in order to determine the actual light intensity. This provides a substantial savings, since the vast majority of shadow (or illumination) rays are not fired at all during the rendering phase. Furthermore, as mentioned before, the viewindependent ambient and attenuated diffuse illumination of all the visible light sources are precomputed during the voxelimation stage and stored with each voxel's color. The ray tracing stage has to compute only the attenuated specular illumination for each light source. (In fact, the attenuation percentage can also be precomputed and saved with each voxel.) The sum of all the illudnation values, the recursive reflected and trahsmitted components, and the color/illumination value stored at the voxel, produce the total illumination of that voxel.</p><p>In this section we present a set of tools for enhancing the visualisation of volumetric datasets. These tools are directly supported by the RRT algorithm and are based on the use of a 3D raster aa the underlying scene representation. We list four main tools, shadows, mirrors, specularity, and voxblt, although our approach supports various other tools as well, such as those available through the use of the non-recursive ray casting techniques (e.g., translucency, intermixing, texturing).</p><p>The utility and efficacy of these tools is demonstrated through an example in medical imaging (MRI dataset of a head) and an example from cell biology (volume microscopy of a neuron). The h4RI set consisted originally of 109 slices of 2562 resolution that were reconstructed into a 256' volume by linearly interpolating an additional slice between each consecutive pair of original slices. The biological example is of a cell that has been removed from the sympathetic ganglion of a bullfrog. In the images presented we can observe that this cell still has remnants of its outer sheath that is being eaten away by enrymes and is seen here halfway through the process. The cell has been injected with fluorescent dye and scanned with a BioRad 11 confocal microscope yielding 70 slices of 256' resolution that were reconstructed into a 256' volume by linearly interpolating additional two slices between every consecutive pair of original slices. All images were produced on one 2OMJPS ( 2 5 m s ) processor of an SGI 4D/240GTX with 80M byte of memory. All images are of 256' resolution, some generated with non-adaptive supersampling of four rays per pixel. CPU rendering time is 30-40 seconds without super-sampling and 140-180 seconds with super-sampling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mirrors.</head><p>The appearance of an object in a mirror encompasses, in a single image, two or more views of the same object, thus conveying to the observer extended amounts of information in a familiar set up. Moreover, comparing an image in which an object is reflected in a set of mirrors, with the alternative, in which multiple views of the object are presented separately, it is clear that in the former the relationships between images are obvious while in the latter another step of mental association is required. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure  1</ref> presents two views of our cell in which additional information can be extracted from the attached mirrors regarding the outer sheath (bottom mirror in the left image) and regarding the axon which is the stem that extends out of the cell (right mirror in the right    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shadows.</head><p>When an object casts shadows on simple surfaces (preferably planar), it can greatly assist the observer in grasping the spatial structure of the object. While in previous methods [15] shadows were implemented in a two pass algorithm, in our method they are directly modeled by the RRT algorithm using shadow rays. In <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> one can observe two types of shadows, both adding useful information. One is the object's shadows on the floor and the wall that disclose additional information regarding the structure of the partially dissolved sheath. The other type is the object's self shadow on the inner surface of the eaten tissue which adds to the visual discrimination of these two sub-structures.</p><p>Specularity. Human perception regarding surface orientation relies heavily on observing how light reflects from the surface. Surfaces with high level of reflectivity tend to exhibit large variance of light intensity, they are easier to understand than diffuse surfaces. Therefore, the ability to render reflective surfaces can assist in the comprehension of the scene. The ultimate manifestation of this capability is the reflection of the environment on the observed surface that has the potential to enhance the perception of small variations in the inclination of non complex surfaces. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> demonstrates the difference between ray tracing the MRI head and a mirror where we assume either high surface specularity (right) or diffuse lighting only (left). The perception of surface inclination is obviously enhanced with high specularity in several areas (e.g., cheek, nose, forehead). <ref type="figure">Geometry)</ref>. The uniform representation of sampled, computed, and synthetic data in a 3 D raster facilitates a simple implementation of a rich set of exploration toolsall in an environment that supports realistic rendering. The intermixed scene can be dissected, clipped, filtered, thresholded, etc. as a whole, or any subvolume thereof can be subjected to any of the uozblt (3D bitblt) operators. Moreover, the implementation of the CSG repertoire involves merely a 1D Boolean operation between pairs of voxels. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref> exemplies the usability of the techniques by performing a voxblt operation (oblique cut) on the head and a CSG operation that subtracts voxelieed disks from the reflective polygon generating the mirror in the back. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> : Two views of a neuron cell in whi ch additional information is visible in the mirrors <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>: An MRI dataset and a mirror with eitl ier t 3igh specularib ( :rig1 i t ) or diffuse illumination only (left) <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>: The neuron cell where shadows d iscl ose add i t i on a I i n f orm at i on reg a r d i n a the objecf structure. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>: The MRI head with an oblique cut and a mirror that has been generated by CSG subtractions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Voxblt and CSG (Constructive Solid</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Two views of a neuron cell in which additional information is visible in the mirrors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>An MRI dataset and a mirror with either high specularity (right) or dinuse illumination only (left),</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure :</head><label>:</label><figDesc>The neuron cell where shadows disclose additional information regarding the object structure.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The MRI head with an oblique cut and a mirror that has been generated by CSG subtractions.(See color plates, page 425.)image). In eitherFigure 2orFigure 4the observer can actually view the two sides of the head in a single image.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgment</head><p>This project has been partially supported by the National Science Foundation under grants MIP-8805130 and RI-9008109, and grants from Hewlett Packard and Silicon Graphics. We would like to thank Daniel Cohen for his work on the design and implementation of 3D raster ray tracer. We also thank Rick Avila and Benny Shaviv for their help.</p><p>The bullfrog ganglion dataset is courtesy of Paul R. Adams and Barry J. Burbach of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute Stony Brook, New York.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Light Reflection Functions for Simulation for Clouds and Dusty Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Blinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface Shading in the Cuberille Environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Udupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="1985-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Scan-Conversion Algorithms for Linear and Quadratic Objects</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Visualization, A. Kaufman,</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>lEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="301" />
			<pubPlace>Los Alamitos, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume Rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Drebin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1988-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rendering of Volumetric Data in Molecular Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goodsell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Molecular Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Voxel Space Automata: Modeling with Stochastic Growth Processes in Voxel Space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Greene</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shading 3D-Images from CT Using Gray-Level Gradients</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hoehne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging, MI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="1986-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient Algorithms for 3D Scan-Conversion of Parametric Curves, Surfaces, and Volumes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of EUROGRAPHICS&apos;87 Conference</title>
		<meeting>EUROGRAPHICS&apos;87 Conference<address><addrLine>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>An Algorithm for 3D Scan-Conversion of Polygons</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The voxblt Engine: A Voxel Frame Buffer Processor</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Graphics Hardware 111</title>
		<editor>A. A. M. Kuijk and W. Strasser</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intermixing Surface and Volume Rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">9D Imaging in Medicine: Algorithms, Systems</title>
		<editor>Applications, K. H. Hoehne, H. Fuchs and S. M. Pirer</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Travemunde, West Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="227" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithms for Computing the Volume and Other Integral Properties of Solids: I-Known Methods and Open Issues; 11-A Family of Algorithms Based on Representation Conversion and Cellular Approximation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A G</forename><surname>Requicha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="1982-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume Rendering in Radiation Treatment Planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pirer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rosenman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sherouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Interrante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the First Conference on Visualization in Biomedical Computing</title>
		<meeting>the First Conference on Visualization in Biomedical Computing<address><addrLine>Atlanta, GA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="179" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Efficient Ray Tracing of Volume Data</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Hybrid Ray Tracer for Rendering Polygon and Volume Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics d Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="1990-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithms of Discretization of Algebraic Spatial Curves on Homogeneous Cubical Grids</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mokrzycki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers d Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">314</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume Viualiration at the Center for Supercomputing Research and Development</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shirley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Neeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Chapel Hill Workshop on Volume Visualization</title>
		<meeting>the Chapel Hill Workshop on Volume Visualization<address><addrLine>Chapel Hill, NC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">V-BUFFER: Visible Volume Rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Upson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Keeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ray Tracing Voxel Based Data via Biquadratic Local Surface Interpolation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Webber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-02" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Context Sensitive Normal Estimation for Volume Imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Scientific Visualization of Physical Phenomena, N. M. Patrikalakis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="234" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer Science, SUNY at Stony Brook</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>91.28.06</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of CG International&apos;gl</title>
		<meeting>CG International&apos;gl<address><addrLine>Boston</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="487" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep.</note>
	<note>Discrete Ray Tracing. Submitted for publication. 18.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ma)</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
