<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Palettailor: Discriminable Colorization for Categorical Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kecheng</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
							<email>lukecheng0407@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mi</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
							<email>miamfeng@gmail.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Xin</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Sedlmair</surname></persName>
							<email>michael.sedlmair@visus.uni-stuttgart.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Oliver</forename><surname>Deussen</surname></persName>
							<email>oliver.deussen@uni-konstanz.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dani</forename><surname>Lischinski</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zhanglin</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
							<email>zl.cheng@siat.ac.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yunhai</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sedlmair</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Deussen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lischinski</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Shandong University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with Shenzhen VisuCA Key Lab, SIAT</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">VISUS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Stuttgart</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="laboratory">and Shenzhen VisuCA Key Lab, SIAT</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Konstanz University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Germany, China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Hebrew University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Jerusalem</settlement>
									<country key="IL">Israel</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Palettailor: Discriminable Colorization for Categorical Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">received xx xxx. 201x; accepted xx xxx. 201x.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Color Palette</term>
					<term>Discriminability</term>
					<term>Multi-Class Scatterplot</term>
					<term>Line Chart</term>
					<term>Bar Chart</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Fig. 1. Results for different types of categorical data visualizations: (left) Palettailor versus Colorization [6]; (center) Palettailor versus Tableau [30]; (right) Palettailor versus Colorgorical [10]. Our system integrates the creation and the assignment of colours to a visualization in a data-aware manner.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Visualizing categorical data in statistical graphics such as bar charts, line charts, or scatterplots is most commonly realized by encoding each category (or class) with a unique color. One major task during visual analysis is then to discriminate between the different classes. While it is well-known that class discriminability is strongly influenced by the assigned colors <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17]</ref>, finding an appropriate set of colors for the different classes in a specific visualization is still a complex and time-consuming endeavor, even for experts.</p><p>The most common way to obtain an appropriate color mapping is to find a good color palette first and then assign the colors to classes in the best possible way. To ease this procedure, a few color palette tools have been provided, such as ColorBrewer <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref> or Colorgorical <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>, which allow users to select highly discriminable and preferable palettes. Since the creation of such palettes ignores the specific data of a visualiza-tion, a good palette might still not be optimal to visually discriminate classes in different forms of visualization. Hence, users often need to try different palettes and color assignment schemes until the desired result is achieved. Recently, Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref> proposed a method that automatically assigns colors of a given palette to classes of multi-class scatterplots by maximizing their discriminability. This technique enables users to bypass the second stage of the standard color assignment process, but it is limited to scatterplots and still requires the author to select a good palette. In contrast, Chen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> proposed an automatic color selection approach for multi-class scatterplots by searching discriminative colors in the a* and b* channel of the CIELAB space. However, leaving out L* channel often does not allow to find colors with high enough discriminability, especially when the number of classes is large. Since such an approach directly colorizes multi-class scatterpots without any input palette, we refer to it as Colorization in this paper.</p><p>To fill this gap, we propose Palettailor, a data-aware color palette generation framework, that automatically generates categorical palettes with maximized discriminability for different visualization types. To achieve this goal, we adapted three color-scoring functions: Point Distinctness <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref>, Name Difference <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>, and the Color Discrimination constraint. The first function is measured from the visualizations, while the last two terms from the palettes. By doing so, we combine the two stages of palette selection and color assignment to a single framework. Users only need to specify weights of the different color-scoring functions and background color to create suitable palettes. In terms of these functions, our notion of "data-aware" mainly refers to the spatial distribution and cardinality of categories in a given scatterplot, while data semantics can be reflected by, e.g., constraining color names (see Section 5.1). As far as we know, few existing color palette generation tools take all these factors into account.</p><p>To realize this idea, we customize state-of-the-art class separation measures <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> for designing color-based class discriminability. Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref> measure Point Distinctness by using a K-Nearest-Neighbor-Graph with taking the two nearest neighbors per point, but we hypothesize that this might not work for all cases since the KNN method would only connect with k neighbors and might not be able to accurately characterize local class separability. Instead, we suggest to use an α-shape <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[34]</ref> graph that connects a set of points within an α-ball so as to better characterize the local discriminability.</p><p>With such a pre-computed geometry-based class separation, an optimal color palette can be found by evaluating all possible solutions and then ranking them accordingly. The color space, however, is too large for an exhaustive investigation and so we propose a customized simulated annealing algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[26]</ref> to rapidly and efficiently obtain a near-optimal solution. In doing so, we can generate the palettes for scatterplots and other types of visualizations with 40 classes in less than 15 seconds.</p><p>We evaluated our approach through carefully designed scatterplots and line charts by comparing our colorized results with the ones produced by the state-of-the-art palettes (e.g.,Tableau <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[30]</ref> and Colorgorical). We first conducted a pilot study for each visualization type to justify whether our design is valid. We then carried out an online study with three tasks for a scatterplot: the first two tasks investigated how well our generated palettes help users to discriminate classes, while the third task aimed at finding out if our results align with user preferences. Similarly, we carried out another online study for a line chart with a discrimination task and again measuring the alignment with user preferences. The results show that our method is able to produce palettes optimized for class discrimination and aligned with user preferences for different chart types that are more effective than state-of-the-art palettes in most cases.</p><p>On the basis of our method, we implemented a web-based palette generation tool that allows users to generate suitable palettes for multiclass scatterplots, but also for other categorical visualizations such as bar and line charts. In summary, the main contributions of this paper are:</p><p>• We propose a data-aware approach based on simulated annealing for automatically generating color palettes for different visualiza-tion types. It is based on user-defined weights for three different scoring functions and extends state-of-the-art separation measures (Section 3). • We quantitatively evaluate the resulting color palettes and visualizations, and compare the results with state-of-the-art color palettes; online user studies show the usefulness of our approach (Section 4). • We present an interactive tool 1 that demonstrates the practical applicability of our method and helps exploring categorical information visualizations (Section 5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>Since we focus on color palette generation, related work is divided into color palette creation and color palette optimization. For the generation of color ramps, a slightly different color assignment problem, we refer readers to recent surveys <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">37]</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Color Palette Creation</head><p>Creating a categorical color palette that enables viewers to distinguish between data elements is a crucial task for many visualizations. Previous attempts have derived practical guidelines based on perceptual constraints, such as "colors should be well separated" <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>, "should not compete with each other" <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[32]</ref>, and "should not be unappealing" <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[38]</ref>. Following these guidelines, a few interactive color palette creation systems have been developed. Healey <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> proposed to choose representative colors from ten hue regions in Munsell's color space, while maximizing the perceptual distances between them. Maxwell <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref> selects colors that maximize the discriminability between classes, but also takes into account their spatial distribution. Their approach has two major limitations. One is that the generated colors are not aesthetically pleasing or easy to see; and the other is that it defines perceptual distances based on the so-called maximum scaled difference, which might not align well with human perception. We want to find a much more general solution. Colorgorical <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> also overcomes this drawback, but does not take into account the data distribution. The resulting palettes might thus not allow to discriminate classes in given data or in a particular visualization. The Colorization method proposed by Chen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> automatically selects colors for multi-class scatterplots in the CIELAB color space to yield a maximal color distinguishability. This technique targets the same problem as ours, but has three main drawbacks: (i) using density to encode class separability does not lead to an accurate measurement; (ii) leaving L* as a user-adjustable parameter and only optimizing a* and b* values limits the approach to a 2D plane in CIELAB and does not provide enough colors with large color differences; (iii) using Euclidean Distance for computing color distances leads to generated colors that are often at the boundary of the 2d plane due to the optimization. Our method avoids these drawbacks. Another approach for designing discriminable palettes is to use prefabricated ones. A typical example is ColorBrewer <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>, an online tool for generating color palettes optimized for choropleth maps. Although ColorBrewer offers different high-quality palettes for different cardinalities, it does not allow users to customize them. Colorgorical <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> enables users to customize palettes by specifying desired hues, but it does not take the underlying data into account and thus cannot customize colors for specific classes or visualizations. Our data-aware approach inherently offers such flexibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Color Palette Optimization</head><p>Once a color palette is selected, users often want to refine the colors until a desired set is achieved and then find a proper assignment to the categories within the data.</p><p>Color Optimization. Optimizing a selected color palette can be performed by applying different criteria, such as optimizing data comprehension, aesthetics, energy saving, or helping with color vision deficiency (CVD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[39]</ref>. Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[35]</ref> introduced a knowledge-based system that employs established color design rules to optimize chosen colors for discriminating spatial structures in 2D and 3D visualizations. Chuang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> proposed to optimize color palettes with the goal of lowering the energy consumption of display devices, and Machado et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref> presented a physiologically-based model for simulating color perception so that the refined palettes can efficiently improve the visualization experience for individuals with CVD.</p><p>Lee et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref> proposed to measure the visual saliency of each visible point of a class and used this metric to optimize palettes for better class discrimination. This method takes the color contrast against the background into account, however, it aims to optimize the given color palette in terms of spatial adjacency of the given data. In contrast to their work, our approach directly produces discriminable colors for different categorical visualization types such as bar or line charts; furthermore, we also incorporate color contrast with the background into the discriminability measure.</p><p>Rather than optimizing palettes for a specific visualization, Fang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref> provided an approach for maximizing perceptual distances among a set of given colors. Although this approach can incorporate various user-defined constraints, it is independent of the given data and thus the produced visualization might not clearly show the different class structures in the data.</p><p>Color Assignment. Assigning colors properly to different classes is a crucial step in categorical data visualization. Assuming that categorical values have semantics, Lin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> propose a method that automatically matches each value to a unique color from a given palette. Setlur and Stone <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[28]</ref> use linguistic information to generate semantically meaningful colors. Since most classes in a visualization might not have clear semantics, Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref> allow user modification and customization within their optimization framework. To that end, they take spatial adjacency into account, but require a discriminable palette first. Our approach unifies palette creation and color assignment into a single procedure and is also able to adapt to user wishes. In addition, it supports palette completion and introduces semantics by handling color names. By constraining color selection with user-specified color names, our approach could also be extended to achieve data semantics-based colorization similar to existing approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">28]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Given categorical data with m classes</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">C = {C 1 , ••• ,C m },</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">arg max P E(P) = ω 0 E PD + ω 1 E ND + ω 2 E CD ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where each class C i is assigned a unique color c i and each weight ω i is a value range from 0 to 1. In the following, we will introduce the constraints we use for optimizing the colors in different visualization types: Point Distinctness(PD), Name Difference(ND) and Color Discrimination(CD), and then describe how we solve the overall optimization problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Scoring Functions</head><p>Since scatterplots are the most commonly used chart type with points as visual marks, we decided to use them to illustrate our method. The arguments, however, also hold for other types of visualizations, as shown later.</p><p>Point Distinctness. Similar to <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref>, we define the distinctness of a data point x i from its neighbours using a color mapping P as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">α(x i ) = 1 |Ω i | ∑ x j ∈Ωi Δε(c i , c j )g(d(x i , x j )),<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where the Ω i are the nearest neighbors of x i with c i = P(l(x i )), c j = P(l(x j )) color mapping functions, Δε is the perceptual color distance metric called CIEDE2000 <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[29]</ref> and</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">g(d(x i , x j ))</formula><p>is a distance-based function that assigns large weights to nearby points and small weights to distant points; we used g(d) = 1 d in our implementation. In contrast to Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref>, we define Ω i using an α-Shape graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> instead of a KNN graph. The reason for this is that nearest neighbors within of an KNN graph may have an arbitrarily large or small distance to the point of interest. Although the distance-based function g(d) helps for reducing the influence of neighbors with large distances, having neighbors with only small distances might result in a colorization that is hard to discriminate. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2(a)</ref> shows an example where the two well-separated clusters enclosed by the rectangle receive similar colors for the KNN-based approach and are thus hard to distinguish. In contrast to this, the α-Shape graph connects only points that are neighbors in the Delaunay graph and in addition their α-balls intersect (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2(d)</ref>). This property allows us to select the closest neighbors of a given point within a certain radius. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2(c)</ref> shows the colorization result, now the two nearby clusters enclosed by the rectangle can be discriminated easily.</p><p>The colorization results for the same scatterplot using these two different graphs are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 2</ref>(a,c).Since the two nearby clusters highlighted by the rectangle are well separated and dense, the k nearest neighbors of each point belong to the same class in the KNN graph and the point distinctness is zero; this leads to similar assigned colors for the two clusters. In contrast, point distinctness computed from the α-Shape graph takes into account only neighbors within a given radius and therefore results a discriminable colorization.</p><p>Point Distinctness is defined as the sum of the Point Distinctness of all points in each class:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">E PD = m ∑ j=1 n j ∑ i=1 α(x j i ).<label>(3)</label></formula><p>Name Difference. Two colors might be perceptually different but are referenced by the same name, confusing color selection. For example, the color "Violet" is perceptually different from "Dark Purple", but they are often referred by the same name "Purple", making it difficult to reference them by name in a visualization. To model such namecolor associations, Heer and Stone <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref> introduce the concept of Name Difference (ND), that measures the probability of two colors having the same name. It was used by Colorgorical <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> for generating palettes with perceptually separated colors. For a palette, its ND is defined as the minimal Hellinger distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref> between the probability distributions of all color name pairs. Another option is to compute the cosine distance, the angle between the two distributions:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">ND(c i , c j ) = 1 − cos(T ci , T c j ) = 1 − T ci T c j ||T ci ||||T c j || ,<label>(4)</label></formula><p>Where T is the name count matrix for the color terms, with T c the row vector for color c. Due to its simplicity and familiarity, we use the cosine distance to measure the name difference of two colors. For a palette, our goal is to compose it as much as possible from colors with different color names, thus its overall Name Difference is defined as the average value of all color pairs:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">E ND = 2 m(m − 1) ∑ i = j∈M ND(c i , c j ).<label>(5)</label></formula><p>Color Discrimination. Since the spatial distance between marks might influence the perception of color differences <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, we employ a hard constraint into our optimization: each two colors should have a minimal CIEDE2000 distance of 10, so that each pair of colors can be distinguished even for large spatial distances. Meanwhile, the minimum color distance should be as large as possible to protect the optimization from reaching unsatisfying results. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>(a) shows that without using the color discrimination constraint classes with small overlap might be assigned improper colors: the green and limegreen classes are hard to distinguish, also the green and cyan classes. In addition, we also take the background color c 0 into consideration to prevent the optimization from generating colors indistinguishable from the background, see </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">E DC = min 0≤i = j≤m Δε(c i , c j ).<label>(6)</label></formula><p>To achieve good optimization results we need to balance the three terms. For the Point Distinctness, we use a normalized weight relative to an initial score at the beginning of the optimization taken from a random palette that satisfies basic requirements. Based on out experiments Name Difference is multiplied by a factor of 2.0, while the Color Discrimination constraint is multiplied with a factor of 0.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Extension to Line and Bar Charts</head><p>We extended our method to generate color palettes for other categorical visualizations such as line and bar charts. We achieved this by interpreting these charts as special cases of scatterplots, which allowed us to fit them into our optimization framework. We are well aware of the fact that this is a very simple form of implementation, but the results are promising. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4</ref> illustrates the process. To colorize a line chart, we discretize the lines into equidistant points and process them the same way as the points of a scatterplot. Note that we discretize line segments with large slopes result into more point samples, indicating that such lines need to be discriminated stronger from each other.</p><p>A bar chart is different from a line chart in that nearest neighbors are pre-defined by the adjacent bars. Thus we treat every bar as a single point class with a center at the middle of the bar; its nearest neighbors are the two adjacent bars. An example is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4(c)</ref>, where we took the length of the connecting lines between each two center points as the distance of the corresponding bars. In addition, we used the reverse function g(d) = <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> d to scale up distances of bars with similar heights for better distinguishing them. Our technique achieves high-quality results compared to state-of-the-art palettes and is more flexible and steerable, some results can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 4(b,d</ref>). Due to the space limits, we show more results in the supplemental material. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Simulated Annealing</head><p>Our method takes categorical data with m classes as input, then iteratively tries to find an optimized color palette, with each color assigned to a class. Similar to Gramazio et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>, we filter out strongly disliked colors whose luminance value is in the range of L ∈ <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr">75]</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">Q = P t 6:</formula><p>if random(0, 1) &lt; 0.5 then</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7:</head><p>randomly disturb one color of Q </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">ΔE = E(Q) − E(P t )</formula><p>15:</p><p>if ΔE &gt; 0 then <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">P t+1 ← Q</formula><p>17:</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">else 18:</formula><p>with probability exp(ΔE/T t ),</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">P t+1 ← Q 19:</formula><p>end if</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>20:</head><p>if E(P best ) &lt; E(Q) then <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">P best = Q 22:</formula><p>end if 23:</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">T t = αT t , t ← t + 1 24: end while</formula><p>Starting with a high "temperature" and an initial guess, the method iteratively updates the palette, while gradually lowering the temperature until convergence is achieved. During this procedure, intermediate results worse than the current iteration can be accepted with a probability related to the "temperature". If the cooling of this temperature is slow, it is more likely to reach the global optimum. Algorithm 1 shows the details of our implementation. It has three customized components: generating a new solution, palette refinement by imposing hard constraints, and finding the optimal colorization. In the following we explain each of these components in detail. In line with suggestion of previous works <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>, we use the following values: cooling coefficient α = 0.99, initial temperature T = 100, 000 and end temperature T end = 0.001. The effect of different parameter values and number of iterations on the final result is shown in the supplemental material.</p><p>Initialization of P (line 1). We found that using random initialization can generate reasonable results in most cases. Although P can also be initialized by any existing good palette, the results are almost the same as the ones produced from random initializations. Since existing palettes also might not have enough colors, P 0 is set to a random initialization by default.</p><p>Generating a new solution (line 6-10). With the initial palette P 0 = {c 1 ,c 2 ,...,c m }, we create the new solution by two different ways: adding a small random offset to each component of the randomly selected color c i in P, or by randomly exchanging two colors. These two ways of updating unify the generation of the palette and the color assignment in a single process that assigns each class its most appropriate color.</p><p>Palette refinement by imposing hard constraints (line <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>. To guarantee that all colors in Q are sufficiently discriminable, we check if any pair of colors would be closer to each other than a noticeable difference threshold τ, which is suggested to be 10, cf. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. If this is the case, we randomly perturb these colors until the differences between all color pairs are larger than τ.</p><p>Finding the optimal colorization (line <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>. After palette refinement, we score the created palette Q as well as the previous one P t <ref type="bibr">(line 14)</ref> to decide whether to accept this solution or not (line <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>. Our goal is to generate a discriminable visualization and hence we preserve the best result for each iteration (line 20-22).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Time Complexity</head><p>We implemented our algorithm using JavaScript and tested it on a computer with an Intel Core i7-7700HQ processor with 32GB memory. The point distinctness can be decomposed into two steps <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref>; thus, the input data can be pre-computed and we separate this pre-processing step from the simulated annealing algorithm. In this way, the performance of our method is not related to the number of data points but instead depends only on the number of classes.</p><p>In each iteration of the optimization we apply the scoring functions two times, with a time complexity of O(m 2 ). For a total number of iterations t, the time complexity for the whole algorithm is O(tm 2 ). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref> left shows that the optimization can find reasonable palettes for scatterplots with 20 classes in less than 3s and for 40 classes in less than 15s. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 5</ref> right shows the convergence curves, our method has a number of strong oscillations at the beginning and then oscillates more smoothly until it converges. We checked all generated palettes with 40 classes and found that the distances of all color pairs were larger than the noticeable difference threshold <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Thus, we assume that Palettailor can generate 40 or more discriminable colors, of course only under the assumption of side-by-side comparison <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">EVALUATION</head><p>We evaluate the quality of our palette generation method by comparing the resulting visualizations from our method with those from the existing methods: Tableau <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[30]</ref>, Colorgorical <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> and Colorization <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>As shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>, the existing palette generation methods have different levels of automation. For fully manual (Tableau) or partly manual methods (Colorgorical), we compared our method with both a best and a worst/random palette result (more details below). To test these methods, we conducted two experiments through Amazon Mechanical Turk (AMT) with 155 participants in total. Experiment 1 focuses on multi-class scatterplots, while Experiment 2 tests our approach on line charts. We test the different methods with two types of tasks: discrimination tasks and preference tasks. In discrimination tasks, we ask participants questions that necessitate them to visually separate, or "discriminate", data from differently colored classes/lines. In preference tasks, we ask them about their subjective preferences between visual encodings with colors from the different palette generation methods.</p><p>Discrimination hypotheses. For discrimination tasks, we had the following hypotheses: H1 Palettailor's results are not worse than the best cases from the manual process of designer-crafted palettes (Tableau Best) and auto-generated palettes (Colorgorical Best). H2 Palettailor's results are better than the worst or random cases from the manual process of designer-crafted palettes (Tableau Worst) and auto-generated palettes (Colorgorical Random). H3 Palettailor's results are better than the existing fully-automated method (Colorization).</p><p>Besides discriminability, we also want to find out that whether our results are aesthetically preferred by people or not, thus we have the other two hypotheses:</p><p>Preference hypotheses. In terms of preference tasks, we have the following hypotheses: H4 The preferences of Palettailor's results are not worse than designer-crafted palettes (Tableau). H5 Palettailor's results are preferred over the auto-generated palettes (Colorgorical and Colorization).  <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[30]</ref>, Colorgorical <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> and Colorization <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, together with our proposed method Palettailor. These methods adopt different palette generation processes that have different levels of automation (shown in the middle columns). For example, Colorgorical's process involves automatic color palette generation and manual color assignment, meaning that it needs manual effort to assign the colors from the palette to the visualization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Experiment 1: Scatterplot Experiment</head><p>In this experiment, each participant completed one of three tasks from two different discrimination tasks and one preference task. As stimulus we used 30 multi-class scatterplot datasets for each task. For coloring the classes, we included six palette conditions -one from our method and the other five from existing methods (see right column of <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">Experimental Design</head><p>Tasks &amp; measures. We tested two discrimination tasks, and one preference task.</p><p>• Counting (discrimination) task. Following the methodology by Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref>, we asked participants to count the number of classes in a scatterplot and to choose an answer among several options. For each participant, we recorded the time taken for each trial, and counted the errors by calculating the differences between the actual number of classes and the participant's response. The counting task focuses on global discriminability. We reported the error measure as time is not of primary interest for our hypotheses. • Comparison (discrimination) task. Following the methodology by Gleicher et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>, we asked participants to judge which of two specified class centroids was higher and to choose a value from a choice with two-alternatives. For each participant, we recorded the time taken and error(0/1) for each trial. The comparison task focuses on local discriminability. • Preference task. Participants were shown a series of image pairs, each containing two scatterplots selected from two different conditions: one from Palettailor and the other from a benchmark condition. For each figure, the participant was asked to choose the plot they preferred. A neutral choice button was also provided. To avoid potential carryover effects between tasks, we measured preference on the colored visualizations as a stand-alone task, instead of measuring it in the context of each discrimination task.</p><p>Conditions &amp; sample palette generation. As shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>, we have six conditions in total, one from our method (Palettailor), and the other five conditions from the existing methods (Tableau Best, Since Tableau is a designer-crafted method, we included two conditions to mimic the best and worst discriminable results generated from the manual process. In a situation, for example, where the class number m is smaller than 10, a designer needs to manually choose m colors from the Tableau 10 palette. We run Wang et al.'s color assignment method <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref> on the Tableau palette and select the first m colors with the highest and lowest scores for generating what we call Tableau Best and Tableau Worst conditions. We repeated this process multiple times and used the most suitable palettes as the final version in the experiment.</p><p>For Colorgorical, we specified the parameters in a way that we received a Low-Error setting: 20% Perceptual Distance, 40% Name Difference, 40% Pair Preference (see original paper for more details <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>). We repeatedly generated 5 palettes with these settings via their tool and randomly chose one of them. We then applied the color assignment process from Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[36]</ref> to simulate a designer's optimized assignment, and used a random assignment to represent a common default result (Colorgorical Best and Colorgorical Random conditions). We directly used Chens method <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> as the condition Colorization, since it is a fully-automated process. For Palettailor, the palettes were generated using the default weight setting of our method: <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1]</ref>. Pilot tests showed that this setting performed best among different weight settings.</p><p>Scatterplot dataset generation. We used 30 multi-class scatterplot datasets with 6 to 10 classes in the experiment. Each dataset had two target classes that were meant for comparison. We generated the data points of the target classes using the method by Gleicher et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>. The data points were placed according to a uniform random distribution in a 400 × 400 area, the height difference between these two classes was 30 pixels. Additionally, we generated the rest of the classes (distractors) using Gaussian random sampling and randomly placed them in an 500 × 500 area. This way the distractors have two kinds of relations to the target classes: intersecting them and including them. We used the Gaussian process to control the overall properties of each class such as size and density <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[27]</ref>. To simplify the variety of visual shapes we defined sizes to be large or small, and densities to be sparse or dense. Hence there were four types of classes: Experiment organization. We used a between-subjects layout in the experiment to test the effects of 6 conditions using 30 datasets. We did not adopt a within-subjects design (i.e., each participant going through all the 180 condition-dataset combinations) because this would lead to unwanted learning effects, as one would see each dataset repeatedly six times. Thus instead, we had each participant to see different subsets of datasets for different conditions. As shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 1</ref>, we used a Latin Square arrangement for the combination of datasets and conditions to avoid ordering effects. Thus there were six participant groups, each having 30 trials, every participant was assigned to one of the groups.</p><p>Pilot study &amp; power analysis. We conducted a pilot study to check the experimental setup. It was also used to infer first insights about the effect sizes to be expected, the effect sizes were fed into a power <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. Participants recruited for the formal study. G# specifies the participant group (more details see text) <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Task  Participants  G1  G2  G3  G4  G5  G6  Counting  4 7  9  9  9  7  6  7  Comparison  3 3  6  5  6  5  5  6  Preference-1  2 5  5  5  5  5</ref>  Participants. We recruited 105 participants for the main experiment using a crowd sourcing platform. According to the completion times in the pilot study, we paid each $2.5 for the Counting Task, $1.5 for the Comparison Task and $0.5 compensation for Preference Task, in order to exceed the US minimum wage. All the participants gave us their informed consent, and no participant reported color vision deficiency.</p><p>Procedure. Each participant went through the following procedure:</p><p>(1) viewing the instructions of the task and completing two training trials (except Preference Task); (2) performing the task as accurately as possible based on the instruction to do so; and (3) providing basic demographic information. See the supplemental material for more details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">Results</head><p>Following the methodology of previous studies, we analyzed the results using 95% confidence intervals, and also conducted Mann-Whitney tests to compare the differences between conditions. We selected this more conservative, non-parametric test as we observed in the pilot study that some measures were non-normally distributed. We also computed the effect size using Cohen's d, i.e., the difference in means of the conditions divided by the pooled standard deviation. In addition, we checked the data collected for both pilot and main studies, and found no significant interaction effects between datasets and conditions, so we focus on reporting the main effects.</p><p>Discriminability. <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>(a)&amp;(b) show the error results for the counting and comparison tasks, including effect sizes and p-values. Here, we focus on the analysis of error. We also measured time, but as it is not of primary interest for our hypotheses we provide the results in the supplemental materials. The results are generally aligned with our discriminability hypotheses (H1-3).</p><p>First, we compared Palettailor to the best cases of the manual processes, i.e., Tableau Best and Colorgorical Best. We found that the Palettailor condition has significantly less errors (p = 0.029) than Colorgorical Best in the counting task. We did not observe other significant differences between these conditions. The result indicates that our approach appears not to be worse than the best cases of manually designer-crafted palettes and auto-generated palettes (H1), and might even lead to a better performance in the counting task.</p><p>Second, we compared Palettailor to the random or worst cases of the manual processes, i.e., Tableau Worst and Colorgorical Random. We found that in the counting task, Palettailor has a significantly lower error rate (p &lt; 0.001) than Colorgorical Random. In the comparison task, Palettailor has a significant lower error rate (p = 0.042) than Tableau Worst. This partially confirms H2 that our method is better than some of the manually created worst or random cases for certain discrimination tasks.</p><p>Finally, Palettailor is clearly better than the Colorization method, for both the counting task and the comparison task (p &lt; 0.001). Thus, H3 is fully confirmed and our method is indeed better than the existing fully-automated method in terms of discriminability.</p><p>Preference. For each comparison within the preference experiment, we assigned a preference score, i.e., 1 for preferring Palettailor, −1 for preferring another condition, and 0 for a neutral choice. We aggregated the scores for each pair containing Palettailor and a benchmark condition, e.g., Tableau Best -Palettailor. An average score value greater than 0 indicates that Palettailor is preferred over the other condition, and vice versa. The results are summarized in <ref type="figure">Fig. 7(d)</ref>.</p><p>We found that Palettailor is significantly preferred over the designercrafted palettes: Tableau Best (p = 0.014) and Tableau Worst (p &lt; 0.001). This finding is not aligned with our hypothesis H4. We also found that Palettailor is significantly preferred over Colorgorical Best (p &lt; 0.001), yet there is no clear preference between Palettailor and Colorgorical Random or Colorization. This observation partially aligns with H5 and will be further discussed in Section 4.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Experiment 2: Line Chart Experiment</head><p>In addition to scatterplots, we also applied our method to line charts and evaluated its effectiveness in Experiment 2. We used 30 line chart datasets for each task as stimulus. The setup of Experiment 2 was similar to Experiment 1; the differences between the two will be described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">Experimental Design</head><p>Tasks &amp; measures. Each participant completed one of two tasks:</p><p>• Slope (discrimination) task. Following the methodology by Javed et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>, we asked participants to find out which line had the largest increase and to choose an answer among several options. For each participant, we recorded the error (0/1) and time taken for each trial. Similar to Experiment 1, we focused on reporting the error measure, see the supplemental materials for the details on time. • Preference task. Similar to Experiment 1, each participant was shown a series of image pairs, each containing two line charts, one from the Palettailor condition and the other from one of the benchmark conditions. The participant was asked to choose the one s/he preferred.</p><p>Conditions &amp; sample palettes. In contrast to Experiment 1, we only tested five conditions in total, our method (Palettailor), as well as Tableau Best, Tableau Worst, Colorgorical Best, and Colorgorical Random. We did not include Colorization as it is not applicable to line charts. We used the same process as in Experiment 1 to generate the sample palettes for every condition.</p><p>Line chart dataset generation. We generated 30 different line charts with 6-10 lines following a carefully designed method. Every line chart had a target line with the largest increase; other lines with smaller increases were used to distract participants. We generated the target line with an increase of 0.35, with every point being within [k − 0.175, k + 0.175] (k is a random number and k ∈ [0, 1]). Then we repeated the process to generate the rest of the lines, each with an increase less than 0.3, i.e., every point within [k − 0.15, k + 0.15]. Each line chart was displayed in an 400×400 area, thus the minimum difference of increase between the largest and other lines on the screen is 0.05 × 400 = 20 pixels. See the supplemental material for more details. The other aspects of the experiment were similar to Experiment 1. We used a between-subjects layout to avoid unwanted learning effects. We had 30 datasets and 5 conditions, the participants were divided into five groups, each going through a subset of 30 condition-dataset combinations. We conducted a pilot study including 11 participants from a crowd sourcing platform. As shown in <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>, we recruited 50 participants in total for Experiment 2. Each participant went through the same procedure as that in Experiment 1, and was paid $1.5 for the Slope Task and $0.5 compensation for the Preference Task to exceed the US minimum wage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">Results</head><p>Discriminability. <ref type="figure">Fig. 7(c)</ref> shows the error results for the slope task. We observed no significant differences between Palettailor and Tableau Best or Colorgorical Best, which indicates that our approach is not worse than the best cases of manually designer-crafted palettes  Hypothesis E1 E2 H1 Discriminability is not worse than the best manual cases. ** ** H2 Discriminability is better than the random manual cases. * H3 Discriminability is better than the automated method. ** NA H4 Preference is not worse than the designer-crafted palettes. H5 Preference is better than the auto-generated palettes. * * * and auto-generated palettes (H1). Also, we did not observe clear differences between Palettailor and the worst or random manual cases, i.e., Tableau Worst or Colorgorical Random. This finding does not aligned with H2. We discuss the detailed implications of these results in the next section.</p><p>Preference. The results are summarized in <ref type="figure">Fig. 7(e)</ref>, where an average preference score larger than 0 means that Palettailor was preferred over the other condition, and vice versa. We found that Palettailor is preferred over the designer-crafted palettes: Tableau Best (p &lt; 0.001) and Tableau Worst (p &lt; 0.001). This finding does not align with our hypothesis H4. We also found that Palettailor is preferred over Colorgorical Best (p = 0.002) and Colorgorical Random (p &lt; 0.001), which aligns with H5.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Discussion</head><p>The results of the two experiments are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 3</ref>. In terms of discriminability, we found that Palettailor appears not to be worse than the best cases of color generation processes that involve manual steps (i.e., the Tableau Best and Colorgorical Best conditions). We also found that Palettailor is more effective than some less-optimized manual cases for certain tasks (e.g., the Colorgorical Random condition in the scatterplot-counting task). Furthermore, Palettailor is consistently better than the fully-automated approach (i.e., Colorization).</p><p>The results indicate that Palettailor can automatically generate palettes that are not worse than those from the manual approaches, and that are more discriminable than those from the fully-automated palette generation approach.</p><p>However, although the results regarding discriminability are generally aligned with our hypotheses for the scatterplot experiment, we found no significant differences in the line chart experiment. One possible explanation is that the visual complexity of a line chart is generally lower than for a scatterplot. Thus, having discriminable clusters in a scatterplot may aid more to people's visual performance than having discriminable lines in a line chart. This leads to the necessity to further explore how Palettailor can benefit visual perception when applying it to different visualization types.</p><p>In terms of preference, we observed that Palettailor is preferred over designer-crafted palettes (i.e., the Tableau palettes), and that it is also preferred over some auto-generated palettes for certain visualizations (e.g., the Colorgorical palettes for scatterplot visualizations).</p><p>From our results it seems like that visualizations with brighter colors were generally preferred (i.e., the Palettailor, Colorization and sometimes Colorgorical palettes), and yet the designer-crafted palette Tableau was less preferred. There are several potential explanations. It is possible that the preference of bright colors is due to the cultural background of the participants <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[25]</ref>, given that all the participants were recruited from the US. Another explanation is that for some people, when looking at visualizations with bright colors, they may gain cognitive ease <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[33]</ref>. In other words, they may be biased towards believing that it would be easier to tell apart clusters or lines (i.e., performing discrimination tasks), no matter whether the colors could truly aid discriminability. The result can also potentially be explained by affective response <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, i.e., more saturated colors are strongly correlated with intensity and positive impressions. Such affect might have caused higher rates of the brighter palettes. Future research may benefit the design of Palettailor in supporting people's aesthetic preferences. <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref>. A screenshot of our interactive system. Users can load different datasets and generate suitable color palettes. If they are satisfied with a result, they can download the image or export the palette definition to use in their own system. We also offer a history for users to find their previous results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Limitations</head><p>The goal of our user study was an initial exploration of the effectiveness of our method. We thus focused on benchmarks from systematically generated datasets and sample palettes. At the same time, we fixed or limited some of the other factors, which may affect the generalizability of the study results. Although our proposed method is capable of supporting a variety of visualization types, in the study we only chose two types: scatterplots and line charts. While these are common visualization types, we did not cover visualizations with larger area marks, such as bar or area charts. In addition, our method is capable of tailoring palettes based on the background color, but for the study, we chose a white background as it is the most commonly used canvas color to display visualizations. Lastly, in our study we measured aesthetic preferences as a stand-alone task to avoid potential carryover effects. However, it might be possible that people's preference would change based on the tasks they are doing. Further studies need to be conducted to comprehensively examine these factors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">INTERACTIVE SYSTEM FOR COLORIZATION</head><p>Based on the automatic approach presented above, we developed an interactive color palette generation system <ref type="figure">(Fig. 8</ref>) that allows users to feed in personal preferences when looking for good colors. After the user uploads his/her data, different color palettes will be produced automatically. Users may also edit color palettes based on their preferences. A history and other interactive features support the user in finding a desired color palette.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">User Interaction</head><p>Our system provides three main ways to interact with color palettes: adjustable palette generation, constrained palette generation, and palette completion.</p><p>Adjustable palette generation. Users can adjust the weights of the three scoring functions to generate palettes with different emphasis. For example, if a user wants to emphasize on local discrimination, then s/he can turn up Point Distinctness or turn down Color Discrimination or Name Difference. If a user wants to create a palette composed of as many color names as possible, s/he can turn up Name Difference.</p><p>Constrained palette generation. Users can also specify preferable colors for palette generation. We use 11 universal basic color terms (blue, brown, green, orange, pink, purple, red, yellow, black, grey, and white) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> as our Hue Filter. For example, when a user selects some colors for generating a color palette, our system will automatically search for optimized palettes within the respective ranges. As our algorithm takes the background color into account, we also allow users to specify a background color and adjust the luminance range accordingly.</p><p>Palette completion. Our system enables users to fix colors of a palette. Once some colors are fixed, our system will evaluate the current palette as well as the data characteristics, and search for optimized other colors to complete it. User-specified Hue Filter with "green" and "blue"; (c) After clicking on colors to lock them, our system completes the palette automatically.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Case Study</head><p>We conducted a case study with a data expert to evaluate the usability of our system. The dataset we used for this study was the CIFAR10 dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> that includes classification results for images of ten object classes (e.g., cats, ships). The expert first used the default settings of our system to automatically produce a palette for assigning colors to different objects in the dataset. Seeing the result in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 9</ref>(a), she was able to easily discriminate every class. After generating multiple palettes with our default settings, she used the Hue Filter and chose two preferable colors ("green" and "blue"). The result is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 9(b)</ref>. Even though all colors are variants of blue and green, it is still possible to discriminate all classes. However, the expert preferred the previous results by our default setting, so she used the history to find the results. Rather than generating a totally new palette, she wanted to preserve some colors. So she clicked on these colors to lock them and produced another palette, shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 9</ref>(c). Overall, she was very satisfied with the system and used all our modalities to create a good palette.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSION</head><p>We presented Palettailor, a data-aware approach for producing color palettes for categorical visualizations that allows a better visual discrimination of classes while being visually pleasing. This goal is achieved by a simulated annealing-based optimization, which we feed with three scoring functions: point distinctness, name difference, and color discrimination constraint. We evaluated Palettailor through a crowd-sourcing study, which empirically demonstrated that our produced palettes allow for good class discrimination, are preferred by users, and can do that fully automatically. Our current measure of point distinctness is based on position and color of the points in the underlying visualizations. However, class discriminability in human perception is also related to many other factors such as mark shape, mark size, and rendering order <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>. In the future, we would like to extend our model to incorporate such factors as well. Weighting the point distinctness by the number of points in each class is able to generate reasonable results in most cases. However, it might de-emphasize classes with fewer data points, such as outliers. To address this issue, we will integrate a user-steered parameter so as to assign priorities to small categories. In addition, we would also like to let our technique support more visualization techniques such as pie charts and parallel coordinates. We also want to include the generation of color palettes for people with color vision deficiencies.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>we assume to have a point set X = {x 1 , ••• , x n } where each x i is associated with a class label l(x i ) and the j-th class (with n j data points) consist of {x j 1 , ••• , x j n j }, j ∈ M = {1, ••• , m}, the background color is represented by c 0 . We formulate the search for a color palette P = {c 1 , ••• , c m } as an optimization problem with the objective function E(P):</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Comparison of nearest neighbors definitions in KNN graphs and α-Shape graphs. (a) Results generated by a KNN graph using only point distinctness: the generated colors are hard to discriminate; (b) Nearest neighbors of the selected point in the KNN graph; (c) Results generated by α-Shape graph only using point distinctness: the generated colors are easily to discriminate; (d) Nearest neighbors of the selected point in the α-Shape graph.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Colorization results based on different optimization criteria: (a) without Class Discrimination constraint; (b) without considering background color making it hard to see points of one class; (c) integrating the white background into the optimization lets the class appear in a dark color; (d) integrating the black background color into the optimization changes the colorization of many classes in order to create the necessary contrast.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 (</head><label>3</label><figDesc>b),(c),(d) for illustration. The formal definition of the Color Discrimination is:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Converting line and bar charts to point-based representation for colorizing them: (a) each curve in a line chart is discretized into equidistant points; (b) colorized line chart; (c) for a bar chart, the center of each bar is represented as a point and connected to its two adjacent bars for forming the graph; (d) colorized bar chart.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Time complexity of our method: (left) optimization time versus number of Classes. (right) energy level E(P) versus number of iterations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>large &amp; dense (n = 100, σ = 50), small &amp; dense (n = 50, σ = 20), large &amp; sparse (n = 50, σ = 100), and small &amp; sparse (n = 20, σ = 50). See the supplemental material for more details.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>example, the power analysis (with an effect size Cohens d of 0.4, alpha of 0.05 and beta level of 0.8) suggested a minimum number of 24 participants for detecting a meaningful difference between Palettailor and Colorgorical Best in the counting task.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>CIFAR10 dataset: (a) Palette generated by default setting; (b)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Simulated Annealing for Colorization 1: randomly initialization P 0 2: best palette P best = P 0 3: t = 0 4: while T t &gt; T end do</figDesc><table /><note>and hue values H ∈ [85 • , 114 • ]. To find m colors with maximal energy with respect to Eq. 1, we use Simulated Annealing [1], a stochastic opti- mization method for finding optima. In comparison to the optimization adopted by Pham and Karaboga [26], Simulated Annealing yields better results at comparable run times, this way also facilitating an interactive generation of palettes. Algorithm 15:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Organization of Datasets for the Discrimination Tasks: 30 datasets × 6 conditions. C: condition; G: participant group.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>C1</cell><cell>C2</cell><cell>C3</cell><cell>C4</cell><cell>C5</cell><cell>C6</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 1</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G2</cell><cell>G3</cell><cell>G4</cell><cell>G5</cell><cell>G6</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 2</cell><cell>G6</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G2</cell><cell>G3</cell><cell>G4</cell><cell>G5</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 3</cell><cell>G5</cell><cell>G6</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G2</cell><cell>G3</cell><cell>G4</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 4</cell><cell>G4</cell><cell>G5</cell><cell>G6</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G2</cell><cell>G3</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 5</cell><cell>G3</cell><cell>G4</cell><cell>G5</cell><cell>G6</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G2</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 6</cell><cell>G2</cell><cell>G3</cell><cell>G4</cell><cell>G5</cell><cell>G6</cell><cell>G1</cell></row><row><cell>...</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 29</cell><cell>G3</cell><cell>G4</cell><cell>G5</cell><cell>G6</cell><cell>G1</cell><cell>G2</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset 30</cell><cell>G2</cell><cell>G3</cell><cell>G4</cell><cell>G5</cell><cell>G6</cell><cell>G1</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Tableau Worst, Colorgorical Best, Colorgorical Random, and</cell></row><row><cell>Colorization).</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Results for scatterplot and line chart experiments: For each task (e.g., the counting task in the scatterplot experiment, marked as Scatterplot -Counting Task), we give a confidence interval plot and a statistic table. In the table, for each condition we provide the statistics including the mean with 95% confidence interval (μ ∼95%CI), the W-value and p-value from the Mann-Whitney test, and the effect size (d ∼95%CI). For the discrimination tasks on the left, we conducted statistical tests to compare Palettailor to every other condition, and provide W or V values, p-value and effect size (d ∼95%CI) accordingly in the tables.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="5">Discrimination Tasks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Preference Tasks</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">(a) Scatterplot -Counting Task</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">W p-value</cell><cell></cell><cell>(d)</cell><cell>Scatterplot -Preference Task</cell><cell>V</cell><cell>p-value</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tableau Best</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.79~[0.67, 0.94]</cell><cell>28385</cell><cell>0.46</cell><cell></cell><cell>Tab</cell><cell>Palettailor</cell><cell>0.19~[0.02, 0.34]</cell><cell>5880</cell><cell>0.014</cell><cell>0.2~[0.04,0.37]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Tableau Worst</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.87~[0.74, 1.01]</cell><cell>26919</cell><cell>0.67</cell><cell></cell><cell>Tableau W</cell><cell>Palettailor</cell><cell>0.27~[0.11, 0.42]</cell><cell>6624</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell><cell>0.29~[0.13,0.47]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Colorgorical Best</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.99~[0.86, 1.11]</cell><cell>24277</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.2~[0.01,0.38]</cell><cell>Colorgor</cell><cell>Palettailor</cell><cell>0.29~[0.13, 0.43]</cell><cell>6649.5</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell><cell>0.32~[0.14,0.51]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Colorgorical Random</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.24~[1.12, 1.36]</cell><cell>20065</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell><cell>0.46~[0.28,0.66]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Colorization</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.59~[1.42, 1.76]</cell><cell>16963</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell><cell>0.72~[0.53,0.91]</cell><cell>Colorgor</cell><cell>Palettailor</cell><cell>5680</cell><cell>0.11</cell></row><row><cell>Scatterplot</cell><cell cols="4">Palettailor Palettailor Colorization Colorgorical Random Colorgorical Best Tableau Worst Tableau Best (b) Scatterplot -Comparison Task 0.9 1.2 1.5 Error</cell><cell>1.8</cell><cell>0.80~[0.69, 0.91] 0.25~[0.18, 0.32] 0.36~[0.29, 0.43] 0.34~[0.27, 0.40] 0.31~[0.24, 0.38] 0.46~[0.38, 0.53] 0.26~[0.19, 0.33]</cell><cell cols="2">W p-value 13509 11745 12192 12597 10674 0.82 0.11 0.3 0.042 &lt;0.001</cell><cell>0.23~[0.03,0.45] 0.43~[0.21,0.66]</cell><cell>5147.5 (a value greater than 0 indicates that Palettailor 0.87 0.0 0.3 0.6 Preference Discriminability: Palettailor's results are Color Palettailor is preferred over the other, and vice versa) comparable to the best cases of manu-Preference: Palettailor's results are al-crafted palettes (e.g., Tableau Best), consistently preferred over the results sometimes better than the random cases of manual-crafted palettes, both their of manual-crafted palettes for certain task best and worst/random results. There (e.g., Colorgorical Random in the counting is no significant difference between task), and consistently better than existing fully-automated method (Colorization) across two scatterplot tasks. Palettailor's results and the fully-auto-mated method (Colorization).</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell>0.3</cell><cell>0.4</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Error</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Linechart</cell><cell cols="2">(c) Colorgorical Random Linechart -Slope Task Colorgorical Best Tableau Worst Tableau Best</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.59~[0.51, 0.66] 0.63~[0.55, 0.69] 0.58~[0.50, 0.65] 0.68~[0.61, 0.75]</cell><cell cols="2">16380 15586.5 16396.5 14885.5 W p-value 0.83 0.68 0.57 0.13</cell><cell></cell><cell>(e)</cell><cell>Linechart -Preference Task Colorgor Palettailor Tableau W Palettailor Tab Palettailor</cell><cell>0.45~[0.30, 0.58] 0.25~[0.07, 0.38] 0.35~[0.19, 0.47]</cell><cell>V 7560 5848 6555</cell><cell>p-value 0.002 &lt;0.001 &lt;0.001</cell><cell>0.51~[0.3,0.74] 0.27~[0.1,0.43] 0.4~[0.21,0.59]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Palettailor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.61~[0.53, 0.67]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Colorgor</cell><cell>Palettailor</cell><cell>0.33~[0.18, 0.46]</cell><cell>6697.5</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell><cell>0.37~[0.19,0.55]</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">0.50 0.55 0.60 0.65 0.70 0.75 Error</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.0 Preference 0.3</cell><cell>0.6</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>The summary of results. E1 and E2 indicate the scatterplot and</figDesc><table><row><cell>line chart experiment. (**) means a hypothesis is confirmed; (*) means</cell></row><row><cell>partly confirmed.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">http://www.palettailor.net</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A stochastic approach to combinatorial optimization and neural computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aarts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Simulated Annealing and Boltzmann Machines</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SepMe: 2002 new visual separation measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aupetit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sedlmair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi: 10.1109/ pacificvis.2016.7465244</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affective color in visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bartram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Patra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2017 CHI conference on human factors in computing systems</title>
		<meeting>the 2017 CHI conference on human factors in computing systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1364" to="1374" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Basic color terms: Their universality and evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Berlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<publisher>Univ of California Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of spatial distance on the discriminability of colors in maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brychtová</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Çöltekin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cartography and Geographic Information Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual abstraction and exploration of multi-class scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1683" to="1692" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy aware color sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weiskopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-8659.2009.01359.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Categorical colormap optimization with visualization case studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Walton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Delahaye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Storchak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tvcg.2016.2599214</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="871" to="880" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perception of average value in multiclass scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Correll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nothelfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Franconeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tvcg.2013.183</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2316" to="2325" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colorgorical: Creating discriminable and preferable color palettes for information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gramazio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Laidlaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schloss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi: 10.1109/ tvcg.2016.2598918</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ColorBrewer.org: an online tool for selecting colour schemes for maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harrower</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4324/9781351191234-18</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Cartographic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Choosing effective colours for data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Healey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/visual.1996.568118</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Conf. on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Conf. on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="270" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color naming models for color selection, image editing and palette design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1145/2207676.2208547</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1007" to="1016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical perception of multiple time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Javed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mcdonnel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Elmqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="927" to="934" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimization by simmulated annealing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gelatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Vecchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">220</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4598</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="680" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Learning multiple layers of features from tiny images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krizhevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>Citeseer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceptually driven visibility optimization for categorical data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Seidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tvcg.2012.315</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1746" to="1757" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selecting semantically-resonant colors for data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fortuna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cgf.12127</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3pt4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A physiologicallybased model for simulation of color vision deficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Machado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2009.113</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1291" to="1298" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing geographic classifications using color</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maxwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1179/caj.2000.37.2.93</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Cartographic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards perceptual optimization of the visual design of scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Micallef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Palmas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oulasvirta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Weinkauf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2017.2674978</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1588" to="1599" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colorcat : Guided design of colormaps for combined analysis tasks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mittelstädt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jäckle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Stoffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2312/eurovisshort.20151135</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eurographics Conference on Visualization (EuroVis) : Short Papers</title>
		<editor>E. Bertini</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="119" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The Eurographics Association</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visualization Analysis and Design. AK Peters visualization series</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Munzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/pacificvis.2016.7465242</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Boca Raton, FL</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The making of continuous colormaps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nardini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Samsel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bujack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bottinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Graphics</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tvcg.2019.2961674</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An ecological valence theory of human color preference</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schloss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8877" to="8882" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Intelligent optimisation techniques: genetic algorithms, tabu search, simulated annealing and neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Karaboga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<publisher>Springer Science &amp; Business Media</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A taxonomy of visual cluster separation factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sedlmair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tatu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Munzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tory</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1467-8659.2012.03125.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3pt4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1335" to="1344" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A linguistic approach to categorical color assignment for data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Setlur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tvcg.2015.2467471</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="698" to="707" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The ciede2000 color-difference formula: Implementation notes, supplementary test data, and mathematical observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi: 10. 1002/col.20070</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Color Research &amp; Application</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.tableausoftware.com/" />
		<title level="m">Tableau Software. The tableau visualization system</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Task-driven color coding</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tominski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi: 10. 1109/iv.2008.24</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf. on Information Visualisation</title>
		<meeting>Int. Conf. on Information Visualisation</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="380" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Envisioning information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tufte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Goeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Benson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Graphics press Cheshire</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>CT</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Judgment under uncertainty: Heuristics and biases. science</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kahneman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1124" to="1131" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The γ-neighborhood graph</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Veltkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Geometry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color design for illustrative visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Giesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mcdonnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zolliker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tvcg.2008.118</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1739" to="1754" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimizing color assignment for perception of class separability in multiclass scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sedlmair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-W</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Deussen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2018.2864912</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="820" to="829" />
			<date type="published" when="2019" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Generating color palettes using intuitive parameters</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wijffelaars</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vliegen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E.-J</forename><surname>Van Der Linden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="743" to="750" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Escaping RGBland: selecting colors for statistical graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zeileis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hornik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Murrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.csda.2008.11.033</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Statistics &amp; Data Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3259" to="3270" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of colormaps in visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/tvcg.2015.2489649</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. &amp; Comp. Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2051" to="2069" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
