<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualization for Aerodynamic Design of Helicopter Rotor Blades</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">David</forename><surname>Kerlick</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Boeing Information and Support Services, Research and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bellevue</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualization for Aerodynamic Design of Helicopter Rotor Blades</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Visualization, animation, and simulation techniques are applied to the problem of rotor design for helicopters. Periodic unsteady experimental velocity data (laser Doppler velocimetry or LDV) in two dimensions and velocity data derived from simulated vortex systems in three dimensions are compared using the same visual tools. Animations show the development of rotor wake systems and induced velocities over time. Modified particle trace integration schemes are used to calculate steady streamlines and unsteady particle paths for both kinds of data. In an extension of this work, a virtual environment (VE) system was used to view the wake vortex system and an interactive probe was used to explore the induced velocity field. Future work will enable interactive visual debugging and simulation steering.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1</head><p>Helicopter Rotor Design</p><p>The design of helicopter rotor blades presents one of the greatest challenges to flight vehicle designers because the design is intrinsically aeroelastic, that is, the structural and aerodynamics properties of the blade interact in a complex and inseparable way. The aerodynamic forces cause the blade to deform, which in turn changes the flowfield produced by the blades, and so on. The phenomenon is also intrinsically unsteady. In the case of level flight considered here, the motion is periodic; in the general (and harder) case, such as maneuver or gusts, the unsteadiness is transient.</p><p>Failure to control aeroelastic effects or to predict bladevortex interactions (BVI) can lead to excessive noise, vibration, fatigue, and failure of components. <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref> For this reason, experimental measurements of the flowfield surrounding blades, and computer simulations of the blade structure and the vortex wakes produced by the blades are required for the understanding of BVI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Experiment and Simulations</head><p>This paper recounts an effort made by the Boeing High-Performance Computing Program to make the results of experiments and simulations usable to designers. We decided to use a comprehensive set of similar tools to visualize the blades and the flowfield. The experimental data was taken on a 2D grid of points in the flowfield, whereas the simulation is in three dimensions. Fortunately, modern visualization environments allow the presence of multiple cameras in their geometry viewers, so that it is possible to take views of the simulation which correspond to the experimental setup.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Visualization and Animation with AVS</head><p>We chose AVS [2] as a visualization environment for several realsons. First, it has a finite element viewer that supports line-type elements, which can be employed to represent vortex elements. Second, AVS can run on heterogeneous workstations over a network, and also on our CRAY YMIP-EL compute server. Third, AVS modules are readily available to drive our video animation recording devices (Lyon-Lamb and Abekas). Finally, AVS includes co-routines which allow simulations to be run with separate threads of control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Veiiocity Measurement</head><p>The experimental measurement of flowfield velocities in the region of a BVI is described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, and a diagram of the experimental geometry is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. In the experiment, a blade revolves at 1325 rpm. The results were averaged over several thousand revolutions, and stored at 1024 azimuthal positions. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> shows a typical position in which a blade is crossing the measurement grid. Note that the blade cartoon in the picture is at a nominal position, and may be different in the actual physical experiment..   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> shows that there was a consistent bias in one of the measurements (near x = 30, z=l, lower right), probably a transducer error. When we examine the time-varying part of the data, this outlier can be factored out, though it causes a distortion in nearby streamlines when they are integrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Fourier Analysis</head><p>The data, even though averaged over many revolutions, still show some noise, as is clear in the video of the raw data. To examine this, we ran the data for a complete rotation of the rotor through a fast Fourier transform, implemented by encapsulating the BCSLIB <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> routine as a remote AVS module on a CRAY computer and examined the data in frequency space using AVS. We found that the signal generally occurred in multiples of four times the rotation frequency, corresponding to the periodicity of the four-blade rotor, with other frequency components showing only noise. Therefore we a produced a dataset that was an average over the four blade passes in each revolution. This data looks less noisy, and it is this data that was used to make the animated sequences of velocity, vorticity, and particle traces in the video.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Streamline and particle traces</head><p>Having obtained a blade-period-averaged representation of the unsteady velocity, we added back the steady velocity and the freestream velocity to obtain the total velocity at the experimental points. We then computed constrained particle traces, restricted to the 2D grid, from this velocity field, as is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> and the video. We did this using a standard implementation of a fourth-order Runge-Kutta scheme [S] with linear interpolation in both space and time for the velocity evaluations. Note that this integration ignores any third-dimensional component to the velocity, which was not measured in the experiment. The video sequence corresponding to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref> shows the paths of particles during a blade passage. The apparent motion of particles through the blade is an artifact of the averaging process, since only average blade positions are represented.  Rotor Wake CFD Simulation</p><p>The second part of the project was the visualization of the simulated three-dimensional flowfield produced by a rotor in level flight, corresponding to the conditions of the experiment. The simulation code TECH-01 <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> models the rotor blades as lifting lines, and uses a system of linear vortex elements <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Figures 4 and 5)</ref> to represent the wake as it is produced by the moving blades and convected along the flowfield. Structurally, the blades are approximated by discrete lumped masses connected by elastic elements. The simulation proceeds by an iteration between the aerodynamic forces on the blades and the blade structural responses, calculated in the frequency domain, until a specified level of convergence is achieved. This simulation can run for several hours on a supercomputer. A paral-lel version of TECH-01 for a message-passing architecture that runs either on the IBM SP-2 computer or on a cluster of workstations is being studied in another part of the Boeing High-Performance Computing Program.</p><p>Previous work on producing visualizations of the rotor wakes were restricted to 2-D pen plots at predetermined views. A few years ago, an animation of a single case took several months of effort to produce using custom hardware and software. The purpose of the present project was to provide an interactive visualization capability using offthe-shelf tools like AVS so that visualization and animation could be made a regular part of the rotor design process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Vortex Representation of the Flowiield</head><p>In TECH-01, the flow velocity field is represented as the linear superposition of the contributions of discrete vortex segments, usually arranged end-to-end in curved filaments. A single segment is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>, and a typical wake system is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>.  The vorticity is a vector whose direction is from A to B and whose magnitude varies linearly from A to B. In order to calculate the velocity V(P) induced by a single segment at a field point P, we integrate according to the Biot-Savti law:</p><p>Here, 1 is the normalized distance along the segment from A to B and o(l) is a linear scalar function shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>. For linear o(l), the integral has a closed form solution. This induced velocity calculation, originally a FORTRAN subroutine in TECH-01, was also encapsulated in an AVS module to calculate the induced field at a prescribed set of points. For a system of filaments, the velocity vectors due to each segment are superimposed at every point P where the velocity is to be evaluated.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref> shows a typical vortex wake composed of segments tha.t is output from TECH-01. In AVS, we used ucdtype elements (unstructured cell data, finite elements) to represent the segments. A program was written to read the FORTRAN output from TECH-01 and convert it into AVS data types. A different set of filaments is produced at each azimuthal position; in the present case data for 24 positions is output. For solutions with II blades, the corresponding solution is taken to be the same solution (I/n) revolutions later. Additional data were stored in each element, depending on the type of visualization desired. For example, blade of origin, or the scalar vortex strength are represented this way. Also, TECH-01 distinguishes several regions of the wake (near, mid, and far), and these were entered using a material type. A video segment illustrates the wake regions for a single blade and for the four blades in the experiment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Interactive Visualization</head><p>With the Biot-Savart integration available as a module in AVS, we now have the tools at our disposal to calculate and visualize induced velocities in space. We can do this interactively using the rake tools provided by AVS for CFD data. In particular, we can create a rake of points which corresponds to the locations at which the experimental measurements were made and examine the crossflow component of the simulated velocity at interpolated times corresponding to the measurements. We can also create an AVS camera such that its view is always pointed at the rake. Visual comparison of the animations of experimental and simulated data shows good qualitative agreement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Streamlines and Particle Traces</head><p>Since the simulation is fully three-dimensional, it is also possible to produce animations of the traces of particles through the rotor during a blade passage. An animated sequence in the accompanying video shows the trace of a line of particles released before the passage of a blade. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref> shows the final state of that sequence. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Visualization in a Virtual Environment</head><p>As an extension of our work we looked at the importation of simulation data into a proprietary virtual environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> consisting of a FakeSpace BOOM, a multiprocessor advanced graphics workstation, and a six degree-of-freedom Polhemus position tracker. The purpose of the investigation was to see to what extent the immersive effect of VE can be used to understand the BVI. Preliminary tests indicate that the effect of immersion is useful, but it is made much more useful with the availability of interactive tools that can be used in a VE.</p><p>To this end, Henry Sowizral, of Boeing's Virtual Reality Laboratory, created a simple interactive tool to show the induced velocity along a rake positioned by the user. Present computational capabilities preclude the calculation of all the Biot-Savart integrals in the required frame interval (less than 100 msec), so the velocities at a dense rake of points were pre-computed, and the velocity field obtained by linear interpolation.</p><p>We anticipate that advances in the system architecture will eventually make it possible to provide updates for small rakes using the exact integration formulas. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Ongoing Work and Summary</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Simulation Steering and Debugging</head><p>We have successfully demonstrated the value of animation in a post-process environment. Now we are investi-gating the possibility of creating animations while the simulation is still in progress. We have implemented a version of TECH-01 as an AVS co-routine, so that it is possible to view some simple features of the solution, such as the convergence residuals, as the solution is computed. It is possible to display partially complete wake systems can be displayed as they are being created (e.g. at the predictor or corrector stage for each azimuthal position). Unfortunately, this would require substantial re-engineering of TECH-01. A promising alternative is the use of advanced debugging tools, such as those developed for AVS on the Connection Machine, to allow the building of customized viewers of TECH-01 arrays as finite elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Complete Design Cycle with Optimization</head><p>In the design of a rotor, several other simulation programs are used besides TECH-01. An acoustics simulation, and a more detailed, full potential code for CFD are also used. Embedding the complete design cycle with multiple simulation codes requires a more complicated execution model than the dataflow model supported by AVS 5.0. We are currently evaluating AVS Express, with its data reference model and customizable execution model, as well as some proprietary software, as a basis for this architecture. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>flow Perfurba fion Vefo.city Artmufh 118 -47.66 deg.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Typical Velocity MeasurementA quick look at the data in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Particle Traces in Crossflow Plane 3</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Discrete Vortex Segment</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Typical Rotor Wake System 3.2 Animation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Simulation Particle Traces</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">(See color plates, page CP-4'2)</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1070">-2385/95 $4.00 0 1995 IEEE Proceedings of the 6th IEEE Visualization Conference (VISUALIZATION '95) 1070-2385/95 $10.00 © 1995 IEEE</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the 6th IEEE Visualization Conference(VISUALIZATION '95)</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the 6th IEEE Visualization Conference(VISUALIZATION '95)1070-2385/95 $10.00 © 1995 IEEE</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Helicopter Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wayne</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
			<publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Users Manuals</title>
		<idno>AVS5.0 and AVS Animator</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>Advanced Visual Systems, Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Wahham MA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Laser Velocimetry and Blade Pressure Measurements of a Blade-Vortex Interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gorton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Poling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dadone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<publisher>American Helicopter Society</publisher>
			<pubPlace>St. Louis, MO</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>49th Annual Forum</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BCSLIB FORTRAN Users Manual</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Boeing Computer Services</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Flannery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Teukolsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Vetterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Numerical Methods in C</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rotor Wake Modeling for High Speed Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bliss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dadone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wachspress</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987-05" />
			<publisher>American Helicopter Society</publisher>
			<pubPlace>St. Louis MO</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>43rd Annual Forum</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Henry</forename><surname>Sowizral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Karel</forename><surname>Zikan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>private communication of unpublished work</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
