<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Interval Volume: A Solid Fitting Technique for Volumetric Data Display and Analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Issei</forename><surname>Fujishirot</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yuji</forename><surname>Maedat</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hiroshi</forename><surname>Satot</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Information Sciences $ Doctoral Program in Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Ochanomizu University University of Tsukuba</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>112</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Japan Ibaraki 305</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Interval Volume: A Solid Fitting Technique for Volumetric Data Display and Analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Volume visualization</term>
					<term>surface fitting</term>
					<term>isosurface</term>
					<term>Marching cubes</term>
					<term>atomic collision</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper proposes as a generalization of isosurfaces, interval ,volume, which is a new type of geometric model representirzg 30 subvolume with field values belonging to a closed interval. A dominant surface fitting algorithm called Murching cubes is extended to obtain Q solid fitting algorithm, which extracts from a given volumetric dataset a high-resolution podyhedral solid data structure of interval volume. Rendering methods for interval volume and principal related operations are also presented. The eflectiveness of this approach is illustrated with a 40 simulated data from atomic collision research. l Well-tuned surface rendering software and geometry engines can be utilized for interactive display and manipulation of isosurfaces. These advantages make SF algorithms still play a complementary role together with DVR algorithms, which can produce more intuitive images of the entire volumetric object, but are inherently computationallyexpensive in spite of many endeavors of optimization.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Turning our eyes to the nature of sampled or simulated datasets reveals that they may have structural ambiguity of the target object, or errors caused by measurement, mathematical modeling or numerical computation.</p><p>If we do not take these into account, there may occur some cases where extracted isosurfaces do not have any meaningful information for our exploratory purposes.</p><p>Volume visualization is a methodology used for realizing the inner structure and complex behavior of 3D volumetric objects [5, 61. According to <ref type="bibr">Elvins [3]</ref>, existing volume visualization algorithms fall into two major categories: Surface Fitting <ref type="bibr">(SF)</ref> and Direct Volume Rendering(DVR).</p><p>SF algorithms extract from a given volumetric dataset, isosurfaces, i.e., contour surfaces with constant-field value, to be rendered geometrically instead of the entire volume, while DVR algorithms project in some way the entire dataset semitransparently onto a 2D screen without any aid of intermediate geometrical primitives.</p><p>Since SF algorithms merely visualize a part of the target volumetric object at a time, users might not comprehend the structure and behavior of the object correctly unless they always keep in mind the existence of the unseen remaining part. However, if a spatiallycoherent dataset is given, SF algorithms are known to have the following advantages over DVR algorithms:</p><p>For example, it is well known in the biomedical area that boundaries between materials are unequivocal, making it difficult to se ment the regions using a single density value <ref type="bibr">[2, 16 .</ref> 'i It has been reported that discrepancy in field values is possible to be induced from organic changes in materials during measurement (e.g., fading effect in confocal microscopy). Also, the limitation of measurement methods could be a principal error source of sampled datasets (e.g., ultrasonography). Needless to say, there is known a wide spectrum of mathematical models for natural phenomena and numerical computation schemes in terms of precision and stability. Therefore, geometrical structures to be extracted from such a volumetric dataset are required to accept an allowance in field values.</p><p>l Some quantitative information related to isosurfaces can be easily obtained.</p><p>l A set of surface patches is more spatially-efficient than the original lattice structure, establishing an economical volume storage and transmission environment.</p><p>This paper proposes a new type of geometric model called Interval Volume, which is a generalization of isosurface with a strict field value, and represents a 3D subvolume with field values belonging to a closed interval. We extend a dominant SF algorithm called Marching Cubes (MC) [7] to obtain a solid fitting algorithm, which extracts from a given volumetric dataset, a high-resolution polyhedral solid data structure of interval volume. Interval volume is used not only for visualizing Region Of Interest (ROI)s with some allowance in their field values, but also for performing the quantitative analysis of ROIs more flexibly than isosurfaces.</p><p>(See color plates, page  The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. In the next section, the definition of interval volume is given, and it is proved that interval volume deserves to be a generalization of isosurface. The interval volume approach is compared with related work in Section 3. Section 4 provides the outline of the solid fitting algorithm using simple 2D examples. Section 5 is devoted to the presentation of interval volume rendering and some representative related operations. Section 6 uses a 4D simulated data from atomic collision research to illustrate the effectiveness of the approach. Section 7 concludes the paper with some remarks on future research directions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Interval Volume Definition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Source Volume</head><p>For simplicity, it is assumed here that a source volume is given as a regular voxel dataset and that each voxel has a single scalar field. Adjacent eight voxels constitute an axis-aligned rectangular prism, called a cube.</p><p>First, a continuous volume V is defined as a pair <ref type="bibr">(S, d)</ref>, where S is a finite rectilinear region in the 3D Euclidean space: S={(2,y,2)ER3~0&lt;x~z5,0~y~zy,0~Z~z~}, and d is a field function (field hereafter), which maps S into a finite closed interval <ref type="bibr">[dmin, d,,,]</ref> <ref type="table">(c  R)</ref>. Then, we have to consider the discrete representation of V, which is used internally by a visual computer, because V is not always given analytically. S can be discretized into C by imposing on S a lattice of even-spaced (n, + l), (nY + l), (n, + 1) voxels, along 2, y, z-axes, respectively, that is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">c = {(x;,y. zk),xi=i.lz y.=JI, k . I, (i=Ol:.. t 3 ) zi = - nz n y 12, , Q, j = 0,. . . , ny, k = 0,. . . , nl)}.</formula><p>The total number N of cubes is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">N = n, x ny x n,.</formula><p>Let 6 denote a restriction of d on C. When we use C instead of S, we lose the field value d(p) at an arbitrary point p in each cube (except for its vertices). So we use a numerical scheme I, which trilinearly interpolates d(p) from the field values at the vertices of a cube to which p belongs.</p><p>Finally, the discrete representation VD for V can be defined as the following triplet: VD = (c, 6, I).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Interval Volume</head><p>Interval Volume IV(cy,,f?) is defined as a subset of V such that for any p E S, d(p) belongs to a single finite closed interval [a, /3]. Specifically, IV(a, P) = lb, 4p))lp E S, c-t I: d(p) I P, &amp;in 5 Q, P 5 &amp;mz}-</p><p>In the next section, we will develop an efficient algorithm to transform a discrete volumetric dataset VD to a high-resolut,ion discrete interval volume IV,. Here, the word "high-resolution" means that IV, holds certain geometrical structures at sub-voxel level. Under the assumption that the trilinear interpolation is adopted as I? IV, will be a polyhedral solid which is represented with a set of directed polygonal patches, retaining inside it the original field values of VD. The polygonal information can be systematically managed using the vertex-based boundary model, which is a simplified version of B-reps <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>.</p><p>Interval volume IV(cr, /?) has different meanings according to how we specify its interval [a: p].</p><p>First, IV(d,;,&gt; d,,,) = V, and IV(a, ok) = IS(a), where IS(Q) is an isosurface with the field value Q. This fact leads to a characteristic operation on interval volume, called focusing, which will be described in Section 5.2.</p><p>Next, IV(cu-E? o+e) (E &lt;&lt; d,,, -dmin) can represent a practical counterpart of isosurface IS(a) taking into account some allowance 2~ about cr.</p><p>For example, consider a volume Vp~hf (n, = ny = n, = 2" -1; I, = 1, = I, = 25 -1) of perturbed primitive for the Blobby Model, whose field b(r) is given as a function of the distance r from the center of the volume, as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">S(T) = (Z8 -1) x e-'.Osr + 3 x ,rnnd(-l,l)&gt;<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where rand(-1, 1) denotes a uniform random variable ran 'ng <ref type="bibr">[-I, l]</ref>. The second term in the right hand of Eq. 7 1) is intended to perturb the concentrically spherical field distribution with a virtual noise supposed to arise during the phase of volumetric data acquisition. <ref type="figure">Fig. l(a)</ref> shows a strict isosurface which is generated from V.DBM, where we can see that the perturbed field distribution makes the isosurface distorted. On the other hand, <ref type="figure">Fig. l(b)</ref> shows an interval volume with a field interval of small length, which is generated from the same volume VP,,.</p><p>The outer surface of the interval volume is semi-trazrsparently rendered, while the inner surface remains opaque. Both surfaces are assigned the same color. More sophisticated rendering of interval volume will be discussed in Section 5.1.</p><p>If we want to see the genuine concentrically spherical distribution from V'BM, we should make use of interval volume in order to attenuate the effect of the perturbation term. At the same time, interactive control of interval allows us to investigate the properties such as magnitude of errors hidden in the original volume. In these respects, interval volume could be used as a more effective volume exploration tool than isosurface when some ambiguities and errors are expected to exist in a given volumetric dataset.</p><p>Furthermore, let us suppose that we are given a trivial volume VD(C~), whose field value is a constant a. There are no known SF algorithms which can explicitly generate ISo from V~(CY), which is the digital representation of IS(a). If we do not know in advance lsosurface ISo <ref type="formula">100</ref>Interval volume <ref type="bibr">IVD(97.5,</ref><ref type="bibr">102.5)</ref> that the isovalue LY is distributed uniformly over the volume, this absence of isosurfaces can be interpreted in two ways:</p><p>l The given volume does not have a voxel whose field value is Q.</p><p>l The given volume is properly included by a uniform region enclosed by ~SD(CY).</p><p>Such an ambiguity can be resolved by interval volume. Since IVD((Y, o) becomes Vo(cr), the boundaries of V~(cy) are selected and displayed, while Iv~(y, y) becomes 4 for y # Q. Hence, we can understand even in the visualization phase that the isovalue Q is distributed uniformly over the volume.</p><p>Based on the above-mentioned expressiveness, interval volume can be considered to be a generalization of isosurfaces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Related Work</head><p>In order to selectively render a subset of volume which is equivalent to IVD( Q, p), we can choose an alternative approach using DVR, which uses an opacity transfer function having a local support defined over the interval <ref type="bibr">[o, p]</ref>. But this approach has the following two drawbacks:</p><p>l Because the DVR approach is viewpointdependent, after geometrical operations are executed on a volume, re-projection is needed for visualizing the transformed volume.</p><p>l For example, an additional evaluation of rayobject segments makes it possible for the raycasting method to get some quantitative information, such as solid measure and surface area, of interval volume-like regions. However, in general. the obtained values tend to vary according to the direction of viewing rays.</p><p>Rather, it should be noted here that the necessity of explicit and compact data structures for fast manipulation and analysis as well as display of volume was already suggested by Udupa, et al., who proposed in their paper <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref> th e semiboundary data structure for binary volume data. Also, t,here can be found some similarities between interval volume and Shell data structure <ref type="bibr">[16]</ref>, which is an extension of the semiboundary to multi-valued volume data. Shell is a structural model for representing fuzzy boundaries between adjacent materials, and defined as a subvolume each cube of which satisfies together with its neighbors a certain condit,ion relevant to a closed interval of assigned opacity. But there can be observed the following three differences between interval volume and shell:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">l l l 4</formula><p>The main purpose of shell is limited to the reduction of spatial complexity and fast manipulation of volumes containing fuzzy boundaries.</p><p>Since shell rendering is performed in a cube-bycube manner. we can obtain precise visualization results only when the resolutions of volume and pixel plane are almost of the same order.</p><p>The interval volume extraction algorithm, which will be described in the next section, could be extended to structured(non-axis-aligned hexahedral) volumetric datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Extracting</head><p>Interval Volume</p><p>In this section, we extend the MC al f orithm ['i] so as to extract an interval volume Ir/, a,/J) from a given volumetric dataset Vo. Let us assume that the basic MC algorithm is modified with an auxiliary algorithm, such as Asymptotic Decider(AD) [ll], for resolving some ambiguities in polygonal patch configuration.</p><p>There are two alternatives to extend the MC algorithm.</p><p>One is to use the combination of threevalued classification (below interval; inside interval; and above interval) of eight vertex voxels of each cube for determining a proper polyhedral block pattern of interval volume. The total number of classified voxel combination equals 6,561 (=38). As in the case of the original MC algorithm, rotational and mirroring symmetries could be taken into account to reduce the number to a certain degree. However, we can not ignore that the AD sub-algorithm increases the final number of polyhedral block patterns.</p><p>Alternatively, in this paper, we take advantage of set operations on special interval volumes. Briefly speaking, to yield IVL)(CY, ,/3)? we first generate for each cube the polyhedral blocks representing IVo <ref type="figure">(a, d,,,)</ref> and Ib(&amp;in, P), and then calculate the intersection of those blocks. Hereafter, the former is called o-cube, and the latter P-cube.</p><p>The number of polyhedral block patterns for both special cubes is the same as that of polygonal patch patterns in the original MC algorithm. Therefore. the computational complexity of the interval volume extraction algorithm is expected to be in the same order O(N) as that of the MC algorithm.</p><p>Below, the interval volume extraction algorithm is described in more detail from the viewpoints of its local procedure and global consideration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Local Procedure</head><p>In order to generate CY or P-cube, we just add the following two modifications to the procedure-for each cube in the original MC algorithm: o According to (L or ,Ll, select either positive or negative half region of a cube whose boundary is given in part by the isosurface ISo or 1So(p). This selection can be based on the field values at vertex voxels.</p><p>l To enclose the selected region, add part of the cube boundaries as temporary boundary patches of the polyhedral blocks.</p><p>Due to the limitation of space, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.2</ref> selectively shows six polyhedral block patterns for a-cube and /3cube, which correspond to the patch patterns O-5 for isosurfaces used in the original MC algorithm <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref>. The same extension principle can be applied to the making of remaining nine patterns for o-cube and ,&amp;cube [8]. a-cube: ~&lt;a se P-cube: o&lt;p&lt;o For brevity, we will explain in 2D how to construct polyhedral blocks for interval volume within a single cube. Note that related 3D terms such as cube and isosurface are used below without any notice.</p><p>Suppose that we are given a cube shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>, where o denotes that the field value at the corresponding voxel is greater than or equal to a target value, and o otherwise. We can see an isosurface with the target value created by the MC algorithm, which is delineated as an oblique linein the square. If the target value is the lower value LY of the interval, o-cube becomes the upper-left trapezoidal region. Else if the target value is the upper value /3, P-cube becomes the lower-right triangle region. Note that as <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref> depicts the case that cr = /?, the intersection of a-cube and ,&amp;cube becomes the isosurface ISo itself '. Nelct, let us consider a more general case that Q &lt; ,S, where there should be a non-empty intersection of a-cube and P-cube <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">(Fig. 4)</ref>. The number beside each vertex means the result of voxel classification. We assign -1 for a voxel whose field value is less than a, and 1 for a voxel whose field value is greater than /3. In this case, the intermediate-value theorem promises that two points having CY and p appear on the two edges connecting -1-voxel and 1-voxel. Two arrows indicates the normal vectors of cy and ,&amp;cubes, each of which is directed to its internal region. The intersection of these cubes is the hatched quadrilateral, which is equivalent to IV~(cr,/3) block. Note that the quadrilateral has part of two cube boundaries as its sides, as depicted with thick line segments. For the cases in 3D, an efficient algorithm to calculate the intersection of two polygons is employed to determine the part of cube boundaries [8].  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Global Consideration</head><p>Now, let us shift our focus int.o the problem of topological consistency of polyhedral blocks for interval volume in adiacent cubes. We can show that nolvhedral blocks are always connected consistently, be&amp; fitting from the AD sub-algorithm <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Fig. 5)</ref>. The right cube is the same as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>, while the left cube has a different polyhedral block pattern from the right cube. The number 0 beside the vertex at the lower-left corner means that the voxel's field value is within the interval <ref type="bibr">[a, p]</ref>.</p><p>An analysis of the nature of the trilinear interpolation scheme I reveals that whenever a cube has a face-connected neighbor, the patches on the shared boundary of the cubes are omissible <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">(Fig. 5</ref>). If we do not delete such a boundary patch, the total number of patches becomes O(iV) in the worst case, spoiling the effect of relatively low complexity in the geometric approach to volume visualization. Furthermore, by transitively decimating nontrivial (non-coaxial) coplanar patches, we can obtain the necessary and sufficient set of polyhedral blocks for representing interval volume in the entire volumetric dataset. This operation is an extension of the triangle patch decimation for isosurfaces <ref type="bibr">[13]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Interval Volume Rendering and Operat ions</head><p>This section describes the rendering methods for interval volume and three principal operations on interval volume: focusing; solid operations; and morphological measurements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Rendering</head><p>Interval volume can be displayed as an opaque solid. The normal vector of an IV0 patch is interpolated using I from field gradients at eight vertex voxels of a cube to which the patch belongs <ref type="bibr">[7]</ref>. So the conventional smooth shading methods are applicable to the display of IV,.</p><p>Considering that IV, also retains field values of VD in its internal region including boundaries, we can use color transfer function to attach colors onto the boundaries of IVo(a,/3).</p><p>Note that in a case that IVD does not intersect the outer boundaries of VD, we can see the only single colored boundary of IVD as far as the trilinear interpolation scheme is used as 1. To explore IV, topology, it is effective to display the hidden internal boundary simultaneously by making the external boundary semi-transparent.</p><p>Of course, in a case that IV' intersects the outer boundaries of VD, we have to visualize the change in field values on the boundaries based on the color transfer function.</p><p>Furthermore, IV0 could be volumetrically rendered instead of I'D to peer into the change in field values inside Iv,. In this case, the number of voxels to be traversed is considerably decreased, making the rendering faster. If this method is applied to Tipg,?f shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>, more smooth concentrically spherical field distribution would be visualized.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Interval</head><p>Volume Operations (a) Focusing One of the meaningful navigating operations on interval volume is focusing, which controls the length of the interval to make interval volume approach the target isosurface. When errors in field value of a given volumetric dataset are relatively large, it is sufficient to obtain an interval volume wit.h an appropriate allowance.</p><p>As described in Section 3, the effect of focusing could be obtained by the control of the local support of opacity transfer function in DVR. However, users in general may want to modify their viewpoints through the course of exploration. Recalculation of viewpointdependent DVR requires O(N), while the geomet.rical transformation and re-rendering of II/o are expected to require only O(N2i3).</p><p>(b) Solid operations Here, three representative solid operations on IVD are described.</p><p>a Cutting operation We can cut IV, along an arbitrary plane. Coloring the cross-section allows us to directly explore the inner structure of ROI specified with IVD. 0 Composition of multiple interval volumes When we want to construct IV0 having multiple intervals, we can first construct an IV, for each single interval, and then take the union of them.</p><p>l Efficient multi-scalar volume visualization It is very important to investigate mutual relationships among fields of a multi-scalar volumetric dataset. One possible way is to perform DVR with respect to some field efficiently within a ROI specified with IVo for another field.</p><p>(c) Morphological measurements Quantitative measurement is indispensable for better understanding of the target objects. IvD is a geometric model which is also suitable for several measurements such as surface area and solid measure. Actually, the surface area of IV0 can be calculated by summing up all the surface areas of polyhedral patches. In the current implementation which will be described in the next section, the solid measure of II'D are calculated by count,ing subcubes which are generated using an octree-like subdivision of cubes. The depth of subdivision is up to three for the sake of temporal efficiency. A similar method is used to calculate numerically the field integral D(a, p) wit,hin interval volume IV(a, ,9) at a precision that subvoxel structure is linearly approximated: from which, we can derive the field average over the ROI, providing a navigat.ing information for fast focusing. Moreover field deviation could be used as a measure of volumetric spatial coherence.</p><p>6 Implementation and Results</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">"Interval volume" Module</head><p>We developed a pilot. module called "Interval volume" executable on a commercial visualization software AVS vers.5. which is based on the moduleoriented dataflow paradigm <ref type="bibr">[l]</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6</ref> shows a network editor's window, where we can see the control panel of "Interval volume" module on the left., and a typical module network including the "Interval volume" module in the workspace on the right. volume" module and</p><p>The control panel consists of many dial and toggle widgets. The Low value and High value dials are used to specify a! and /3 of II'D(C%, fi) to be extracted, respectively.</p><p>The Opacity dial allows us to control the opacity of interval volume's boundary whose field value is o or p, which can be selected exclusively with the Low or High toggles on the right of the dial. The Backface cull toggle is used to control the visibility of back faces. If turned on, the invisible mode is selected. This toggle is effective only when either of the Low or High toggles is turned on. We can cut interval volume along the three axial directions. The Flip X, Flip Y, and Flip Z toggles are used to alt,ernate the cutting status for YZ, ZX, and XY planes, respectively. The locations of these planes can be determined through the three Excavate dials on the top of the toggles. The three t.oggles at, the bottom allow us to control the computability of surface area; solid measure; and field integral of the current interval volume with the selecbed interval values.</p><p>As seen from the module network, "Interval volume" takes a volumetric dataset from "read volume" and transfer function specifications generated from "generate colormap", and produces a geometry type of data representing interval volume to the rendering module called "geometry viewer". The "color legend" module disnlavs the current color-to-data value manping. The **'volume bounds" module is connected io display the extent of a given volumetric data. An popup window displays an interval volume and its measurement data; volume. generated from a 2 x 2 x 2 sample 6.2</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visualizing</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proton-Hydrogen Atom Collision</head><p>To illustrate the effectiveness of the interval volume approach, we chose simulated 4D data of proton (H+) -hydrogen atom (H) collision, which is a simple ionatom collision problem, but very important in that the problem has a wide spectrum of applications such as nuclear fusion, material sciences and radiology. The purpose here is to investigate how the incident proton affects the behavior of an electron around the target hydrogen atom.</p><p>Suppose that a proton comes into collision with a hydrogen atom with relative velocity ZI = 1 atomic unit.s 2 and that the impact parameter b is set to 0.1 atomic units 3 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">(Fig. 7)</ref>. The setting of these parameter values makes the problem fall into the category of intermediate energy collisions, and thus we can adopt a well-known semi-classical approximation to formulate the governing equations for the phenomenon. The details of the formulation can be found in <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref>. Conventionally, the physicists have explored the collision problem by plotting 2D graphs of the simulated time-varying transition probabilities for each orbital. However, such a graph forces the physicists to imagine how the collision occurs in 3D. Instead, we will get a comprehensive illustration of the simulated collision by visualizing the distorted electron density distribution volumetrically. <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref> shows nine snapshots excerpted from an animation of the collision simulation.</p><p>The numerical computation was done on a Stardent TITAN 3OOOV system (CPU: R3000 x2, Clock: 32MHz; RAM: 64MByte). It took approximat,ely almost one day to get lo4 time steps of 61 x 61 x 61 volumet,ric datasets. Each snapshot was visualized with interval volume IV~(90,120) 4, whose low (outer) densitv boundary is semi-transparently rendered. The rendering was done on an SGI Indy system (CPU: R4000, Clock: 100MHz; RAM: 64MByte). For getting each snapshot, it took just a second.</p><p>The proton is coming from the left side into the visualization domain.</p><p>It is easily observed that a time-varying distortion of electron density distribution around the hydrogen atom was induced by the positive charge of the marching proton.  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 9</ref> illustrates four typical interval volume images of the 4th volume dataset in <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref>, which are rendered using the methods described in Section 5.1. Through the intensive use of these methods, we can get more meaningful information from each of the datasets.</p><p>We conclude this section with an interesting application of interval volume measurement.</p><p>In the ionatom collision research, it is very important to investigate how far the elecbron cloud spread at each moment. This can be measured by the exist.ential possi-  <ref type="bibr">C,</ref><ref type="bibr">Y,</ref><ref type="bibr">ZPe/dZ,</ref><ref type="bibr">(3)</ref> IV(a,P"&gt;'z,)</p><p>where p being the electron density. Eq.(3) is a special case of Eq(2). If we are given Pa, we can use the measurement capability of interval volume to search for cy suchthat P((-Y,~,,, ) = PO in a trial and error manner. For example, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 10</ref> shows <ref type="bibr">1V~(17.887,255)</ref>, which sabisfies the condition that P(17.887,255) = 0.500. The electron cloud is cut by the right boundary of the volume. On the cross-section, we can see the distribution of electron density directly. Even after the collision, electron cloud is still stretched towards the proton which is going away from and located far in the right of the visualization domain. Note that this type of interval volume's boundaries can give the true extent of density cloud, because the bigger the possibility PO is given, the larger the extent of interval volume becomes. Therefore, we are now creating another animation from the same 4D collision simulation data using this dynamic interval selection methodology. Also, automatic selection of a such that P(a,pmaz) = PO is very attractive as an inverse problem of conventional style of visualization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Concluding Remarks</head><p>This paper has extended the concept of surface fitting, and presented interval volume as a generalized geometric model for indirect volume visualization. Major contributions of this paper include: <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>: Interval volume specified with electron existence possibility.</p><p>l An MC-based solid fitting algorithm to construct interval volume from a given volumetric dataset was developed.</p><p>l Interval volume display and analysis methods were presented. In particular, interval volume can make visualization and measurement reliant on each other, achieving a more sophisticated volume realization environment.</p><p>To make interval volume extraction algorithm faster and interactively usable for larger volumetric datasets. we can take advantage of e.xisting op-Gmization a proaches to the MC algorithm, such as parallelism <ref type="bibr">[4 : P discretization[lO]</ref>; adaptive mesh size determination:</p><p>and hierarchical min-max spatial indices such as BON0 <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref>.</p><p>n-e are now considering the applicability of interval volume to a particular medical application problem to explore 3D brain in MetachromaGc Leukodystrophy, where the focusing capability is expected to play an important role in specifying scattered accumulation of lipid in cerebral cells <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref>.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Practical isosurface with interval volume.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Polyhedral block configuration for a-cube and P-cube.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>: a-cube and P-cube.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Interval volume in a single cube.INote that in general, IV~(a,a) &gt; ISo( SeeFig. 6.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Interval volume in adjacent cubes.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Control panel of "Interval a typical module network on AVS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Proton-hydrogen atom collision.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 8: Interval volume ulated collision animation snapshots excerpted from sim-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>4The entire interval ized onto 8 bit range. of obtained density values normal-Four interval volume rendering methods. (a) Solid display (b) Semi-transparent display (c) Cutting (d) Cutting and semi-transparent display bility P(cy, P,,,~) of electron: P(cy, Pm,,) = JJJ P(.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the 6th IEEE Visualization Conference(VISUALIZATION '95)1070-2385/95 $10.00 © 1995 IEEE</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="21">atomic units = 2.19 X lOa cm/set 31 atomic units = 5.29 X lo-lo cm</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the 6th IEEE Visualization Conference(VISUALIZATION '95)</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Fujishiro had benefited from continuous discussions with Professor Arie E. Kaufman and Dr. Xiaoyang SIao during his stay at SUNY at Stony Brook, NY under the research scholarship .5-WAKA-36 from the 5Iinistry of Education, Science and Culture of Japan.</p><p>The authors would like to thank the reviewers for their valuable comments to improve t,he quality of this paper.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advanced Visual Systems, Inc.: A%% Module Reference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">:</forename><surname>Carpevter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hanra-. *?iolume</forename><surname>Rendering</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Elvins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">A Survey of Algorithms for</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="194" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Computer Graphics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Massively Parallel Isosurface Extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hinker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Visualization &apos;92</title>
		<editor>Kaufman, A. E.</editor>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;92</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="83" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Volume Visualization</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yagel</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching Cubes: A High Resolution 3D Surface Construction Algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Interval Volume-Based Display and Measurement of 3D Volumetric Objects</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Maeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Doctoral Program in Engineering, University of Tsukuba</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Master Thesis</note>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An introduction to solid modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>M&amp;ntyl%</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Computer Science Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discretized Marching Cubes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Montani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scateni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scopigno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Asymptotic Decider: Resolving the Ambiguity in Marching Cubes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="90" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proc. Visualization &apos;91</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of Volume Visualization to Ion-Atom Collisions (1) : Volume Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yoshigaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fujishiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 44th Annual Conference of Information Processing Society of Japan</title>
		<meeting>44th Annual Conference of Information essing Society of Japan</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="371" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in Japanese</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-Dimensional Visualization of Brain for Metachromatic Leukodystrophy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">J A</forename><surname>Zarge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tachino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Maeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fujishiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sakuraba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Satake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aoki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Udupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Odhner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fast Visualization, Manipulation, and Analysis of Binary</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IEEE CGSrA</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Octrees for Faster Isosurface Generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Udupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Odhner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wilhelms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Gelder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE CG&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ACX TOG</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
