<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">F&apos;low Visualization in a Hypersonic Fin/Ramp Flow</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hans-Georg</forename><surname>Pagendarm</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">DLR German Aerospace Research Establishment</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D37073</postCode>
									<settlement>Gijttingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Gerhold</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">DLR German Aerospace Research Establishment</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D37073</postCode>
									<settlement>Gijttingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">F&apos;low Visualization in a Hypersonic Fin/Ramp Flow</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>A recent study of a flow detail of an engine intake of future ground to orbit transport systems provided extremely complex data from numerical pOw simulation and experimental flow visualization. The data posed a challenging problem to pOw visualization, computational flow imaging (CFI), and the comparison of experimental imaging techniques versus computational imaging techniques. Some new visualization techniques have been implemented to provide compact representations of the complex features in the data. It turned out to be most useful to combine various specialized techniques for an icon-like representation of phenomena in a single image in onier to study interaction of fEow features. Some lessons were learned by simulating experimental visualization techniques on the numerical data.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Specification of the flow problem</head><p>Future hypersonic transport aircrafts or aircrafts for ground to orbit transportation will make use of huge air-breathing turbo-ramjet-engines probably powered by liquid hydrogen. The necessary thrust of such a vehicle of 90 meters length at hypersonic speeds of Mach number 5 or 6 will require intake sections of the engine duct with a cross section of 26 m2. This data was specified for the "german hypersonic reference concept". The length of the forebody and the complex geometry in the comers of the intake section ( <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>) will result in a complicated flow field with shock/boundary layer interaction which is difficult to predict. On the other hand, this part of the flow might have a severe impact on engine performance since disturbances which occur in the intake region will cause irregularities in the engine inflow. It is important to understand the flow details to come up with an optimized design of the intake and ensure the necessary thrust of the engines. In certain situations the interaction of various flow phenomena may lead to local peeks in pressure and heat conduction which eventually may cause structural damage. This has occurred in the past on comparable aircraft such as the well known X-15.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 1</head><p>High speed transport aircraft and simplified detail of the intake comer. The sketch on the bottom right shows the fin/wedge configuration used for the numerical flow simulation.</p><p>The flow field was studied at the German Aerospace Research eistablishment (DIR) in Gijttingen using a numerical simulation by solving the compressible Reynold-averaged Navier-Stokes equations [ 11. Various statistical turbulence models were applied. Experimental investigations of the flow field were conducted in the Ludwieg-tube wind tumtel of DIR in Giittingen <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>. As a result of the extremely complex flow field visualization turns out to be a necessary 1001 to understand the physics. Since interaction phenomena play an important role in this case it was desirable to apply or develop compact visualization methods which allow to represent various flow phenomena in a single image and see how they intluence each other. While visualization was essential for the aerodynamic research the demanding application also triggered the implementation of advanced visualization methods. The need to compare the results to experimental flow visualization lead to a study on issues of comparative visualization [3] and even the simulation of experimental flow visualization techniques. This work was performed in a fruitful cooperation with F. H. Post and W.C. de Leeuw of Delft University of Technology in the Netherlands. In this paper we will give a short overview about the visualization techniques involved in the study of the fin/wedge flow field.</p><p>2 Visualization of the fin/wedge flow field</p><p>It is beyond the scope of this paper to discuss the details of the aerodynamic research. These results are available in a phD thesis <ref type="bibr">[4]</ref>. Here we will demonstrate the use of specialized visualization technology. The flow field is dominated by a region of separated flow near the plane of symmetry in front of the fin. The separation induces a separation shock which interferes with the bow shock. Underneath the separation shock the separated flow turns into a vortex system which develops downstream and in span direction to produce a horseshoe vortex system. Aside of the fin the separation shock and the bow shock interfere with the ramp induced shock. The ramp shock interacts with the boundary layer on the fin surface and causes another separation. The study of separation phenomena require the visualization of the near-wall flow field. A representation of the flow near the wall may be obtained from the numerical flow field by the use of skin friction lines. In the windtunnel separation phenomena are often visualized using oil flow pattern A first attempt to directly compare the location of separating flow between numerical simulation and wind tunnel experiment was done by projecting wall friction lines into a photographic image of the oil flow pattern in the wind tunnel. . In order to demonstrate the feasibility and usefulness of the time-surface concept a brute force approach was implemented. Using an existing streamline algorithm a particle path is integrated backwards from all grid nodes in the data. Thus the travelling time for a particle from the entry into the domain to each grid point may be evaluated. Time-surface can be generated using a standard iso-surface algorithm.</p><p>Time surfaces were used to study discontinuous behaviour across shock waves and the complex evolution of the flow field in the vincinity of vortices.</p><p>Animated time surfaces were found to be particularly useful. <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> tries to illustrate this with a series of frames from an animation. The fin/wedge data turned out to be very fertilizing for further visualization activities. The visual similarity of the oil flow patterns and textures known the spot noise visualization technique of van Wijk [lo] suggested to try to simulate the experimental oil flow visualization technique starting from the numerical data using texture maps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F-</head><p>xived from the numerical simulation of the flow by using spot noise texture maps.</p><p>A detailed analysis of the flow properties which could be used to scale the parameters of the spot noise texture generation [ll] suggested an algorithm using the convergence of the field of the flow velocity vector as a scaling parameter. <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> shows the simulated oil flow pattern which may be compared to the experimental oil flow pattern visible in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig.  3</ref>. Due to the limited space a side-by-side comparison is not given in this paper. More details may be found in <ref type="bibr">[ll]</ref>. Many features are found where the simulated texture is in good accordance with the experimental oil flow pattern. There are also regions which exhibit differences between simulation and experiment. Such differences gave rise to a discussion of their reasons. Often the final explanation points to lack of accuracy either in the experimental visualization process or the numerical simulation. Sometimes differences in the boundary conditions of the numerical simulation with respect to the experimental set-up were found to be responsible. The simulation of an experimental </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Future</head><p>The complex application illustrated the value of dedicated visualization technology when analysing flow behaviour for the optimization of modem high speed transport aircrafts. The use of comparative visualization allows to precisely validate numerical simulation versus windtunnel experiments even where the windtunnel provides mainly flow visualization and only few measurements of flow quantities. Comparative visualization to an extend as shown here had not been applied before. The intention to perform comparative visualisation therefore was not known when the experiment was specified. Comparative visualization demands for being taken into account from the beginning. In the future data acquisition will be adapted in order to ease the direct comparison of result both on the data level as well as on the image level. Computational flow imagery was demonstrated for the case of spot noise textures versus oil flow pattern. Similar approaches for other exPerimental flow visualization techniques and optical measurement technique offer a large potential especially in the hypersonic flow regime. This, however, will require further implementation of dedicated flow visualization techniques. While numerical flow simulation data is ready at hand for a number of complex aerodynamical problems there is limited access to experiments which allow for comparative visualization due to the huge costs of such experiments. Therefore further research in the CFI field will be oriented toward given activities in aerodynamic research. <ref type="table">PI   PI   PI   151</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">PI</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Phenomena in the fin/wedge flow field: bow shock, intersecting with ramp shock and the shock over the separation region in front of the fin all represented by the transparent surface, primary horseshoe vortex visualized by the red stream ribbon through the vortex core, secondary vortex visualized by the blue ribbon close to the wall of the finFig. 2provides an overview about the most important features in the flow and their location in 3D-space. The method to extract shock waves from a field of discrete numerical flow data was described earlier[5]. A compact representation of vortices is given by stream ribbons as reported in[6].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Wall friction lines from the numerical simulation in comparison with the oil flow pattern of the windtunnel experiment. (image reprinted from [ 61) Fig. 3 applies one of the comparative visualisation approaches listed in [3], the so-called image level comparison to the fin/wedge problem. Data visualization and comparison as shown above served to understand the data and verify the numerical simulation versus the windtumtel experiments. Comparative visualization was important in this case because due to technical restrictions windtunnel experiments provides only few measured data. Results of windtunnel experiments were mainly recorded as visualization on photos or videos. Image level comparison was also performed for the location of shock waves and vortices with respect to their traces in the oil flow, see [6] for details. Another technique offering deeper insight into flow behaviour is the construction and visualization of time-surfaces. This technique has been suggested by van Wijk [7],[8]. Similar to the other techniques the time-surface computation was implemented by adding a new module to DIR's in house visualization system HIGHEND [9]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>visualization technique, often called computational flow imagery [ 121, allowed to learn more about sources of errors and problems in the wind tunnel flow visualization methods as well as in the numerical flow simulation process.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the 6th IEEE Visualization Conference(VISUALIZATION '95)1070-2385/95 $10.00 © 1995 IEEE</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical Simulation of Blunt-Fin-Induced Flow Using a Two-Dimensional Turbulence Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gerhold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ICHMT Int. Symp. on Turbulence, Heat and Mass Transfer</title>
		<meeting>of ICHMT Int. Symp. on Turbulence, Heat and Mass Transfer<address><addrLine>Lisbon</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-08-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Investigation of the Hypersonic Turbulent Flow Past a Blunt Fin/Wedge Configuration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gerhold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Krogmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>AIAA-93-5026</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>5th Intern</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Aerospace Plane and Hypersonic Technology Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Munich, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-12-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative Visualization -Approaches and Example</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Pagendarm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization in Scientific Computing</title>
		<editor>M.G%el, H.Miiller, B. Urban</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Wien</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="108" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Numerische Simulation und Analyse der turbulenten HyperschalIstromung urn einen stumpfen Fin mit Rampe</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gerhold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>DIR-FB 94-19</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>will be published in english as ESA TT132I soon</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Pagendarm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Seitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">An algorithm for Detection and Visualization of Discontinuities in PI PI [81 PI PO1 WI PI Scientific Data Fields Applied to Flow Data with Shock Waves</title>
		<editor>P. Palamidese</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Ellis Horwood Workshop Series</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Visualization in Scientiftc Computing</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feature Detection from Vector Quantities in a Numerically Simulated Hypersonic Flow Field in Combination with Experimental Flow Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Pagendarm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<editor>R. D. Bergeron, A.E. Kaufman</editor>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;94<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="123" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implicit Stream Surface</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of Visualization &apos;93</title>
		<editor>G.M. Nielson, D. Bergeron</editor>
		<meeting>of Visualization &apos;93</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="252" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three Ways to Show 3D Fluid Flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J S</forename><surname>Hin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>De Leeuw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications v01</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994-09" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">HIGHEND, A Visualization System for 3D Data with Special Support for Postprocessing of Fluid Dynamics Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-G</forename><surname>Pagendarm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>M</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Grave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lclous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Hewitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Visualization in Scientific Computing</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual Simulation of Experimental Oil-Flow Visualization by Spot Noise Images from Numerical Simulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sixth Eurographics Workshop on Visualization in Scientific Computing</title>
		<editor>W.C. de Leeuw, H.-G. Pagendarm, F.H. Post, B. Walter</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chia, Italy; Vienna</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="318" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings Siggraph &apos;91</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing flow with CFI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Havener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Leslie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aerospace America</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
