<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Astronomers and their Shady Algorithms</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gooch</surname></persName>
							<email>rgooch@atnf.csiro.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Telescope National Facility</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CSIRO</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Macquarie University Sydney</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">N.S.W</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2121</postCode>
									<country key="AU">AUSTRALIA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Astronomers and their Shady Algorithms</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The vast quantities of data which may be produced by modern radio telescopes have outstripped conventional visualisation techniques available to astronomers. While research in other areas of visualisation finds some application in astronomy, problems peculiar to the field require new techniques. This paper presents a brief overview of some of the problems of visualisation for astronomy and compares different shading algorithms.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>1.1</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Astronomical Data</head><p>Historically, astronomical data were obtained by hand-sketching a section of the sky observed through an optical telescope by an astronomer.</p><p>Later, PhD students were given this tedious job. Technological advances permitted photographing the sky, producing more accurate images. For the last 50 years, astronomers have had a new tool: the radio telescope. By processing the raw data collected from radio telescopes, we can produce images of how the sky would appear if our eyes were sensitive to radio frequencies. Just as in the visible world, the radio world consists of many frequencies. Because many large astronomical objects have large differences in relative velocity, these differences may be detected by radio telescopes, with the velocity changes corresponding to frequency shifts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.2</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Data Explosion</head><p>With the advent of modern radio synthesis telescopes, such as the Australia Telescope Compact Array, astronomers are able to collect and process very large quantities of data. While previous radio telescopes were limited to observing in one or a few frequency channels, advances in techniques have greatly increased both the spatial and spectral resolution of these instruments.</p><p>Older instruments yielded images of regions of the sky with a resolution of 256x256 pixels, with perhaps 32 frequency channels. Conventional techniques to visualise these data sets involved displaying the images in sequence (movie tools) and mosaicing the images. Three-dimensional data were being viewed with tools designed for two-dimensional data.</p><p>Modern radio telescopes can routinely yield images with 256x256 pixels, with 256 channels, and are, in principle, capable of producing images with 8000x8000 pixels with 8000 channels. This is a vast leap in spectral resolution. With such a large number of channels, it becomes far more difficult for the astronomer to integrate all the channels together in the mind and ga.in a global insight of the entire data set. Clearly, new visualisation technologies must be investigated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Volume Rendering</head><p>At the Australia Telescope National Facility, we have had considerable success using volume rendering to visualise astronomical data. While we have experimented with both surface rendering as well as volume rendering tools, we have found the latter to be more successful. The focus of this technique is to make best use of the astronomers' spatial recognition functions.</p><p>By presenting data three-dimensionally, the astronomer may identify structure in the data which is not obvious by using conventional tools. Once this structure is identified, the astronomer may proceed to further analysis, possibly by extracting threedimensional regions and processing these further. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> for work in this area.</p><p>An important caveat is that radio astronomy spectral-line data sets represent two spatial dimensions and one frequency dimension.</p><p>This does not prevent us from displaying these data as if they were in three dimensions. However, the astronomer needs to be aware that the display 1s a projection of phase space, not physical space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.1</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations of Standard Volume Renderers</head><p>Many existing volume-rendering tools are designed for solids and fluids which are purely absorptive.</p><p>In addition, the data-gathering techniques result in da.ta with high signal-to-noise ratios. In contrast, objects observed in radio astronomy contain regions of emission and absorption with very low signal-to-noise ratios. Volume-rendering tools for radio astronomy need to take account of this fact. Particular attention must be paid to the shading algorithms used, but even simple shaders (such as "maximum voxel" and "voxel sum") are far more effective in revealing structure than non-volume-rendering techniques traditionally used by astronomers.</p><p>While those techniques (See color plates, page CP-47)</p><p>were suitable for revealing two-dimensional structure, the astronomer missed much of the three-dimensional structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.2</head><p>Shaders We find that a radiative transfer ("hot gas") shader is particularly helpful in volume-rendering astronomical data. This is similar to the conventional radiosity shader used in medical visualisation except that no backlighting is used: the object itself provides all the radiation (similar to a cloud of hot gas in space). The shading algorithm is given below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">IP'=I*y+P*(l-$1 (1)</formula><p>where P is the accumulated pixel intensity, I is the assigned voxel intensity over a segment of the ray path and y is the assigned voxel opacity. P is computed independently for the red, green and blue components, for each pixel on the screen. This "hot gas" shading algorithm may be used in a variety of ways, with each shader offering certain advantages and disadvantages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Substances</head><p>The choice of I and y in (1) may be made by dividing the range of voxel values into N arbitrary ranges (N is typically 8) and choosing a particular colour (red, green and blue I) and opacity for each range. This is called a table of "substances", a term inherited from medical visualisation. This shader represents the data (which are in reality continuous) schematically, which is useful because it highlights distinct boundaries in the intensity profile of the data. In particular! regions of emmission and absorption may be readily differentiated by choosing different colours. This shader is also very effective in hiding noise (see <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>). However, it suffers from the fact that astronomers find it difficult to choose and configure the substance table. Despite many improvements in the user interface, many astronomers still avoid this shader.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Continuous RGB</head><p>This shader provides a continuous (smooth) mapping between voxel value and assigned intensity and opacity. The opacities are computed using the following algorithm:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">1 ^/i = (i/256)" 1<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where i is the index number of a voxel and ranges from 0 to 256. By adjusting CY the emphasis may be shifted with ease between high-valued voxels (bright features) and low-valued voxels (features close to the noise). A standard colourmap manipulation window provides simple (though limited) control of the parameter 1 in (1). See <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Continuous Greyscale</head><p>This shad'er is similar to the above shader, except that only one value of P is computed per screen pixel. The intensity values are computed thus:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">pqzijq (3)</formula><p>where i is the index number of a voxel and ranges from 0 to 256. The intensity contribution of voxels ma.y be shifted. easily between high-valued voxels (bright features) and low-valued voxels (features close to the noise) by ,adjusting /3, Because this shader produces a single value per image pixel, the user may change the colour look-up table interactively, an operation which requires m-rendering using the above two shaders, a time-consuming operation. This shader was the most commonly used by astromers. See <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>Astronomers have indicated that they can extract more science than was previously possible from their data using the visualisation tools we have developed. By taking advantage of the spatial recognition and integration powers of the brain, which is designed to recognise three-dimensional moving objects, features which may not appear using conventional techniques become readily apparent using the volume-rendering tools, especially when a viewing a movie of the rotating data set. Objects that would appear as a number of faint, disjointed fuzzy patches in individual images are clearly defined in three dimensions. Astronomers have been known to extract information using conventional techniques, then to find previously unknown features in their data when they used the new visualisation tools.</p><p>The choice of shading algorithm depends not only on how much information is presented to the user and its ability to highlight features of interest, but also the ease with which the shader parameters may be adjusted.</p><p>Some of the highest quality images were produced using the "Hot Gas-Substances" shader but, despite this, users favoured the "Hot Gas-Continuous Greyscale" shader. Clearly, there is no one perfect shader; a variety is required to fit the variety of da.ta and the variety of users.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Summary</head><p>Visuali,sation of three-dimensional data sets specifically for radio astronomy will continue to develop. The field is currently in its infancy. While more general visualisation of three-dimensional data sets is at a slightly more advanced stage (but by no means mature), the problems unique to radio astronomy result in a field of research which has much scope. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :Figure 2 :Figure 3 :</head><label>123</label><figDesc>NGC253 rendered with Hot Gas-Substances shader NGC4631 rendered with Hot Gas-Continuous RGB shader NGC4631 rendered with Hot Gas-Continuous Greyscale shader</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the 6th IEEE Visualization Conference(VISUALIZATION '95)1070-2385/95 $10.00 © 1995 IEEE</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>I thank Ray Norris and Tom Oosterloo for idea.s and contributions to the visualisation project.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Challenge of Visualising Astronomical Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Norris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ADASS III, ASP conference series 61, i994</title>
		<editor>D. R. Crabtree, R. J. Hanisch &amp; J. Barnes</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Space and the Spaceball</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gooch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ADASS IV, ASP conference series 61, f995</title>
		<editor>R. A. Shaw, H. E. Payne &amp; J. J. E. Hayes</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">V&apos; lsualisation: from Data to Understanding</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gooch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">WARS 95, Australian Academy of Science National Committee for Radio Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
