<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Reinforcing Visual Grouping Cues to Communicate Complex Informational Structure</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Juhee</forename><surname>Bae</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Reinforcing Visual Grouping Cues to Communicate Complex Informational Structure</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2014.23469</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:09+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Visual grouping</term>
					<term>visual hierarchy</term>
					<term>gestalt principles</term>
					<term>perception</term>
					<term>visual communication</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Fig. 1. The five grouping cues used in isolation and in reinforcing combination in our second study. These visuals are simplified for illustration, experimental visuals were more complex. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity, prx=proximity, and aln=alignment)</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>How can people tell that the spots behind those leaves are not unrelated shadows, but a leopard? Psychologists call this ability visual grouping, and have studied it for almost a century. For nearly as long, designers have been exploiting our visual grouping ability to add meaningful structure to their graphics. But almost from its beginning, design practice has also outstripped psychological research, with visuals using combinations of grouping cues to communicate such complex structures that even today, psychologists have not researched them in any great detail.</p><p>As the means of visual communication become much more avail- able, and today's information demands make using visual communication well more important than ever, tools for creating visuals are not keeping pace. While users have many tools that make it easy to create visuals, few help them build visuals that communicate clearly. Communication is much more successful when the information it contains is well organized. How can users organize information visually? Gestalt psychology and its principles of visual grouping <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> give them a starting point, but complex information demands complex structure, and as we make clear below, research on combining Gestalt principles has not yet answered all the questions visual communication raises. If we are to create better tools for visual communication, we need a better understanding of visual communication itself. Our research examines several different combinations of visual grouping cues, and how effectively they communicate complex, hierarchically structured information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>Our work is inspired by Richard Mayer and his theory of multimedia learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, or learning from words and pictures. A crucial assumption of that theory is that humans actively process visuals to construct a coherent mental representation of their experiences. This cognitive processing involves paying attention to select relevant information, organizing that information into a meaningful knowledge structure, and integrating that structure with existing knowledge. Many knowledge structures are possible, but five basic structures are processes describing a cause-and-effect chain, comparisons of elements along several dimensions, generalizations outlining main ideas and supporting details, enumerations compiling sets of related items, and classifications analyzing a domain into subsets. The corresponding structures are flow charts, matrices, trees, lists, and hierarchies. Well designed multimedia, Mayer says, should have a coherent structure, and provide the learner with guidance that helps them build the correct structure.</p><p>With their theory of visual hierarchy, graphic designers strive to provide that guidance to viewers. Indeed their work regularly goes beyond the frontiers of perceptual psychology. Yet with their traditional focus on the practical, their theory does not often provide the detailed guidance needed by novice designers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Gestalt grouping</head><p>In the early 20th century, the Gestalt school of psychology developed several laws describing how people infer structure from what they see, a process they called visual grouping <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. They include similarity (similar items are grouped), proximity (neighbors are grouped), common fate (similar movements are grouped), symmetry (reflected items are grouped), good continuation (or alignment, with segments of the same curve grouped), and closure (segments of the same container are grouped). Relatively recently, Palmer and Rock <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref> introduced connectivity (linked items are grouped) and common region (items in the same container are grouped).</p><p>In the natural world, the grouping cues described by Gestalt laws exist in abundance, and often conflict with different cues suggesting competing organizations of our environment. How do people combine multiple cues and resolve those conflicts? We organize the research addressing these questions into three sets: work studying grouping cue combinations including proximity, connectedness, and common region.</p><p>Research shows that proximity often dominates similarity <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>. Yet domination depends on cue strength, with proximity weakening as inter-item distance increases, and similarity weakening with reduced viewing time. Kubovy and van den Berg <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref> review a great deal of the literature on the simultaneous presence of these two cues and suggest that in fact they operate additively: they reinforce or interfere with one another in direct proportion to their strength.</p><p>Han's work <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> showed that reinforcing similarity cues with agreeing connectedness cues made groups much easier to perceive, while combining proximity with connectedness had little effect. Palmer and Beck <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> found that conflicting similarity and connectedness cues made groups harder to perceive. Interestingly however, when they reinforced similarity with connectedness, groups became slightly more difficult to perceive. To explain this, Palmer and Beck introduced the notion of intrinsic grouping cues, which depend on properties of the grouped items themselves and include similarity (shape and color) and proximity (position); as well as extrinsic cues, which depend on other items and include connectedness (linking contours) and common region (surrounding contours). Reliance on extrinsic grouping cues therefore implied additional items and more complex visuals, making groups a bit more difficult to perceive.</p><p>Palmer and Beck <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> also found that conflicting similarity and common region cues made groups much more difficult to perceive, while reinforcing cues made groups slightly more difficult to perceive. Recently, Luna and Montoro investigated combinations of common region with proximity or similarity <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Conflicting cues made grouping more difficult, while reinforcing cues made grouping easier. Their results supported an additive model for combinations with extrinsic grouping cues, much like the model for intrinsic cues proposed by Kubovy and van den Berg <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Grouping in visualization</head><p>Although not extensive, there is work exploring applications of visual grouping in the field of visualization. In his book Visual Think-ing for Design, Ware discusses widespread use of Gestalt grouping to communicate semantic structure, but he does not discuss the complex combination of grouping cues <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Ziemkiewicz and Kosara <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> experimentally verify this mapping of the visual to the semantic, and suggest that it may also be influenced by viewers' physically based interpretation (e.g. gravity) of what they see.</p><p>Wattenberg and Fisher built an analysis engine that extracts grouping from imagery <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. They point out that the structure of visualization should match the structure of the data and convey its intention. Rosenholz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> improved on Wattenberg and Fisher's analysis engine by generalizing it to sense color and orientation, and making it simpler to extend the tool to detect other perceptual features as well. The tool responded to Gestalt proximity, similarity, and good continuation stimuli much like people would, and was able to convincingly extract structure from text, textures, interface, information graphics, and visualizations. Later, Rosenholz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> studied the use of the tool in the design process, finding that it could be helpful. However, as Wattenberg and Fisher point out, these algorithmic models need experimental validation.</p><p>While the above research is certainly useful, it does not provide a complete solution to the problem of helping novice designers synthesize good visuals. For example, how should grouping cues be combined to communicate complex informational structures containing groups within subgroups? Existing research does not provide a clear answer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">STUDYING DISJOINT COMBINATIONS OF GROUPING CUES</head><p>To begin answering our questions, we performed some experiments examining how Gestalt grouping cues can be combined to communicate complex informational structures. Our first experiment examined a disjoint approach, with each cue communicating different subsets of the structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Methods</head><p>We limited the complexity of the information structures we attempted to communicate to hierarchies containing two grouping levels: groups (outer) and groups-within-groups (inner). In these hierarchies, any leaf is an item to be organized, any internal node directly descended from the root is the parent of an outer group, and any internal node within an outer group is the parent of an inner group. With a disjoint approach, one grouping cue communicated the outer groups, the other, the inner groups. For example, in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>, common region communicates outer groups (and not inner) while color communicates the inner groups (and not outer).</p><p>We then used a two-factor 5 outer grouping cues×5 inner grouping cues between-subjects design, with both independent variables outer and inner groupings using one of five grouping cues: common region, connectedness, color similarity, proximity, and alignment. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2</ref> illustrates these five grouping cues in disjoint combination. 250 people recruited through Amazon Mechanical Turk (117 male, 133 female, aged from 18 to 73), participated in the experiment online. Heer and Bostock <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> found that Amazon Mechanical Turk can produce reliable results in graphical perception experiments, as long as concerns of overlap, completion and quality are addressed. Our study addressed these concerns by recording when Turkers participated in multiple experiments, rewarding them only when tasks were completed, and requiring them to perform verifiable pre-qualification tasks. All Turkers had normal or corrected-normal vision and passed a color-blindness test. They were paid $1.50 for their effort and 10¢ as bonus for every correct answer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Apparatus and Stimuli</head><p>Our online test environment displays a visual on the left and hierarchical dialogue on the right <ref type="figure">(Figure 3</ref>). At the beginning of each trial, we fill the dialogue with elements representing the items in the visual (usually text). Participants can input the hierarchical structure they perceive by creating one or more grouping folders, and moving the elements in the dialogue using their mouse. Participants can also remove empty folders and expand or collapse the hierarchy as desired. The five grouping cues used in disjoint combination in our first study (disjoint combination indicated in 'outer grouping cue, inner grouping cue'). These visuals are simplified for illustration, experimental visuals were more complex. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity, prx=proximity, and aln=alignment) <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>. Grouping letters with same colors (A and F) in a practice task in our first study Because participants used their own equipment, we did not have direct control of their display, but we told participants an 800×600 pixel monitor was a minimum.</p><p>We drew our experimental information content and visual stimuli from five real world examples: a warning sign, a toothpaste product label, and three captured websites: a Google search's results, a Facebook wall, and an Amazon product category. Two experimenters viewed these examples, recorded the structure they perceived in independently, and then discussed and resolved their differences to reach agreement on the information structures depicted in the examples. For each example, we then extracted no more than 20 items (limiting task complexity), and without changing the items themselves, created 25 new stimuli depicting the portion of the information structure containing those items ( <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>).</p><p>The five practice stimuli viewed by all participants (last five stimulus of <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>) illustrate how we applied Gestalt cues to communicate visual structure. Here the items were simple letters, while the same grouping cue was applied at both the outer and inner levels. Each stimulus used a different grouping cue. For example, the common region practice stimulus places A and B in one outer group and C, D, and E in another; with C and D in an inner group.</p><p>To maintain internal validity, we attempted as much as possible to apply each cue in isolation. Because some cues are naturally related, this could lead to some awkward-looking stimuli. Alignment may be the most telling case: without proximity, not all items will be close together, making grouping much more difficult to perceive. Although this reduced external validity, we felt it a useful trade-off in this initial experiment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Procedure</head><p>Participants began the experiment by performing five practice trials. If they successfully completed three of those trials, they performed five recorded trials, each depicting a different real world example. These were ordered for each participant using two 5×5 Latin squares. We determined which five of 25 grouping treatments a participant sawand by varying their order, limited any fatigue or transfer effectsby assigning them to one row in each Latin square, with one Latin square ordering the cues applied for the outer grouping, and the other ordering the cues applied for the inner grouping. In this way, every participant saw every grouping cue used for outer grouping and for inner grouping. With 125 participants performing five recorded trials each, we collected 625 user described structures, or 25 trials per disjoint combination of grouping cues.</p><p>We first obtained informed consent from the participants, and presented them with written instructions describing their grouping task. In particular, we ensured that participants understood that groups could contain groups, and that a trial was not complete until they created at least one group. They then performed five color deficiency tests. If they completed all five correctly, they performed five practice trials, with the correct answer being displayed after each. If they performed at least three practice trials correctly, participants were asked to provide their age and gender. They then performed five recorded tasks, without any feedback. On average, participants needed 30 minutes to complete the experiment, with about 20 minutes dedicated to the recorded tasks.</p><p>As dependent measures for each trial, we collected the informational structure input by the participant -our focus in this paper. We measured the correctness of that structure by obtaining the tree edit distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> between the depicted and the participant's structures, which counts the operations (e.g. add, delete) needed to transform one tree to another.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Hypotheses</head><p>How should two grouping cues be combined to communicate a twolevel structure (containing groups with subgroups) successfully? With <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref>. Toothpaste label stimuli with common region (containment) communicating the outer groups, and color similarity in the inner groups disjoint grouping cues (each cue communicating different groups), how does a viewer know that one grouping cue applies at the outer level, and the other at the inner? We believe this cue-to-level mapping is a crucial component of successful structural communication with disjoint grouping cues, and two of our three hypotheses focus on it.</p><p>Hypothesis 1: Using the same grouping cue at both inner and outer levels will usually communicate poorly. Communicating two grouping levels is difficult with only one cue. With intrinsic cues (proximity, alignment and similarity), spatial and color resolution is limited. Extrinsic cues can add grouping elements (containers or links) as needed, but used in isolation as in this study, connectedness can only communicate the cue-to-level mapping topologically. Because the presence of a container within a container indicates this mapping so clearly, common region may be the lone exception to this rule.</p><p>Hypothesis 2: When using two different grouping cues, communication is clearer when the outer cue dominates the inner cue. Since the global knowledge structure indicated by outer groups is more important than the detail indicated by inner groups, it should be communicated as clearly as possible. Since Gestalt research shows that proximity, connectedness and common region often (certainly not always) dominate similarity (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>), we expected that treatments using proximity, connectedness or common region on the outer level would be among the most successful.</p><p>Hypothesis 3: Alignment is best used to communicate inner groups. Alignment is inherently one-dimensional, limiting its communicative potential. Used in isolation (for example, without proximity), it is even more difficult to understand since grouped items may not be adjacent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Results and Discussion</head><p>Gender and age had no significant main effects, so we do not discuss these further below.  <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> shows average perceived structure correctness for each treatment. We analyzed the effects of the inner and outer grouping cue variables on perceived structure correctness with a two-factor ANOVA. <ref type="table">Table 2</ref> shows the analysis results. Both main effects were significant, indicating that the cues used to communicate outer and inner grouping changed the effectiveness of structural communication. The effects' interaction was also significant, indicating that the specific combination of inner and outer grouping cues used also affected communication effectiveness. For example, the common region-common region treatment was most effective at communicating informational structure, and in pairwise comparisons was significantly more effective than any intrinsic-intrinsic treatment. The alignment-alignment treatment was least effective in communicating structure, and in pairwise comparisons was significantly less effective than any treatment using common region to communicate outer grouping, while its effectiveness did not significantly differ from any other treatment using alignment to communicate outer groups.</p><p>We found good support for hypothesis 1. In pairwise comparisons, none of the connectedness-connectedness, color-color, proximityproximity or alignment-alignment treatments differed from one another significantly, and as a group they were among the least effective at communicating knowledge structure. As we have outlined above, as the treatment that communicated best overall, the common regioncommon region combination was a glaring exception.</p><p>Results provided mixed support for our hypothesis 2. Since Gestalt research shows that common region, connectedness and proximity often dominate other cues, we expected that treatments using these cues to communicate outer grouping would be most effective. This held true with one surprising exception: treatments using color to communicate outer grouping were just as effective as treatments using connectedness and proximity. In particular, the color-common region and color-connectedness combinations communicated well, were not significantly different from one another, and were only marginally different from the most effective treatment, the common region-common region combination. In fact, common region and connectedness cues were the best communicators of inner level grouping overall.</p><p>Analysis also revealed strong support for hypothesis 3. Alignment was the worst communicator of both inner and outer grouping, though it was a better communicator of inner than outer grouping, with the common region-alignment combination particularly effective. Clearly alignment is difficult to use without reinforcement by other cues.</p><p>Overall, participants did well understanding fairly sparse depictions of structure, with inner and outer grouping each encoded by exactly one cue. With one combination of cues (common region-common region), they approached a perfect understanding of the information structure.</p><p>Two of the three results from our study of disjoint cues remind us of the limits of using grouping cues in isolation. Indeed in graphic design practice, most groups are communicated with multiple, reinforcing cues. As we performed the first study, we made two observations that argue further for reinforcing cues. First, many cues depend on proximity: both proximity and alignment are positional, placing items within common region's containers requires some proximity, and connectedness is not very effective if the items it links are widely scattered. Second, some cues are "persistent": they can rarely be completely removed from a visual. Consider proximity and alignment: when items are distant or misaligned, rather than perceiving nothing about their grouping, viewers will understand that the items are not related. In contrast, when common region, connectedness or color similarity are not used, viewers make no inferences about grouping.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">STUDYING REINFORCING COMBINATIONS OF GROUPING</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CUES</head><p>Therefore in our second study we examined combinations of reinforcing cues, with all cues each communicating the entire knowledge structure. We improved external validity by studying the interaction of these cue combinations with visuals that consist primarily of either images or text, in low or high densities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Methods</head><p>Our methods in this study had many similarities to the previous study. We focus on the differences in method in this section.</p><p>We again examined the communication of two-level hierarchical information structures. With the reinforcing approach, one to five cues all communicated the entire structure, including both inner and outer groups. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figures 1 and 2</ref>   <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>. Significant main effects on accuracy of structural communication using disjoint combinations of grouping cues, as measured by tree edit distance. We used a three-factor 31 cue combinations (between)×2 visual densities (within)×2 visual types (within) mixed design, with the reinforcing cue combinations involving the same five grouping cues used in the previous study (2 ∧ 5 -1 = 31). We did not include a completely unstructured combination because it would be unrealistic, we could not obtain an accuracy measure for it, we did not want to frustrate the participants, and were confident that significant differences would be found without it.</p><p>Visual density indicates the percentage of stimuli area that was occupied by content. For low density, this was 10%, for high, 40% (quite crowded). Visual type represents the dominant content of the stimuli: text or imagery. For image-dominant visuals, 85% of pixels describing content were dedicated to images, for text-dominant visuals, 93% of pixels describing content were dedicated to text, where content is visual elements not including grouping elements such as boxes or links. The same web pages used in the previous study (Google search results, a Facebook wall, and an Amazon product category) were our text dominant stimuli, while a Netflix home page, a Pinterest board, and a Google Image search result were our image dominant stimuli.</p><p>372 people recruited through Amazon Mechanical Turk (178 male, 194 female, aged from 18 to 61), participated in the experiment online. All had normal or corrected-normal vision and passed a colorblindness test.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">Apparatus and Stimuli</head><p>Our online test environment was very similar to that in the previous stimuli, with two differences: six practice stimuli were either image or text dominant, and participants could also input "how much they liked" the stimuli from 1 -indicating "strongly dislike" to 5 -indicating "strongly like".</p><p>For each, we extracted no more than 17 items of content (limiting task complexity), and without changing the items themselves, created 31 new stimuli, one per cue combination, depicting the portion of the information structure containing those items (one per cue combination, for example, <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>).</p><p>We constructed low and high density versions of each example by scaling the visual elements (text or imagery) to fill the required percentage of stimuli area. Each stimulus used a different cue combination, visual density, and visual type. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> illustrates the 31 cue combinations with simple letter stimuli, used here only for illustration. The first 26 cue combinations depict the same structure: G is not grouped, E and F form an outer group, and all other letters form an outer group with two inner groups.</p><p>Practice stimuli contained small collections of plants, animals or places organized into simple two level classification structures. Half were text dominant, half image dominant; half high, half low density. Two used two grouping cues, the other two used three, and the rest used four grouping cues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">Procedure</head><p>Participants began the experiment by performing five color tests and then six practice trials. If they successfully completed four practice trials, they performed six recorded trials. Within those six trials, each participant saw all six content examples. Half were low and half were high density; half were text-and half were image-dominant. We determined which cue combinations a participant saw by randomly ordering the 31 combinations and repeating the order across participants. Since 31 is not divisible by 6, the order shifted by one trial on every sixth participant and every cue combination appeared equal number of times in each trial. Visual density and visual type were ordered so that each level appeared equally in each trial. With 372 participants performing six trials each, we collected 2232 user described structures, or 18 trials per cue combination×visual density×visual type triple.</p><p>Only seven of 372 participants also took part in our first study. On average, participants needed 33 minutes to complete the experiment, with about 22 minutes dedicated to the recorded tasks. As dependent measures for each trial, in addition to input structure, we recorded trial time, and the participant's rating of the stimulus's appeal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Hypotheses</head><p>How should grouping cues be combined to communicate informational structure successfully? We expected that our study would indicate the following:</p><p>Hypothesis 1: Using reinforcing cues improves communication clarity (reduces edit distance). As the number of cues communicating a knowledge structure increases, viewers will perceive a structure more accurately as measured by tree distance, and more easily as measured by time.</p><p>Hypothesis 2: As visual density declines, communication clarity will improve. Lower visual density leaves more room for structural grouping to operate.</p><p>Hypothesis 3: Proximity and alignment will affect structural communication even in their absence. As "persistent" cues, we expected their absence to communicate not a lack of structure, but a different structure. We therefore anticipated that these cues would have significant and particularly strong effects and interactions.</p><p>Hypothesis 4: Many cues rely on reinforcing proximity. The dependence of alignment, connectedness and common region on proximity leads us to expect strong interactions between proximity and each of these other cues.</p><p>Hypothesis 5: Text dominant visuals rely more heavily on spatial arrangement than image dominant visuals. Reading requires a very regular spatial processing of text, so we expected a matching interaction between visual type and proximity and/or alignment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Results</head><p>We performed three analyses. The first per cue combination analysis treated each combination as an experimental level. The second reinforcement analysis grouped combinations by the number of cues they contained, and treated each of those as a level. The third per cue analysis treated each cue as a different experimental variable, with each cue being present or absent. We discuss all main effects, all twoway interactions and some three-way interactions. Gender had no effect on any of our three measures and older people spent more time (F(38,2193)=6.873, p&lt;0.001) completing tasks. Because of the limited nature of these effects, we do not discuss gender and age below. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 6</ref> shows average perceived structure correctness, trial time, and preference for each cue combination. We analyzed the effects of cue combination, visual density, and visual type with a three-factor (31×2×2) ANOVA. We detail significant effects on distance and preferences in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">Per cue combination analysis</head><p>Cue combination, visual density, and visual type all had significant effects on distance <ref type="table">(Table 3</ref>). Reinforcement universally lowered the distance and improved understanding of the structure. On the other hand, denser (6.95 for low and 8.72 for high density) and imagedominant visuals increased distance, reducing structural understanding (7.38 for text-and 8.29 for image-dominant visuals). The interaction between cue combination and visual density was significant by the distance measure <ref type="table">(Table 3</ref>). Pairwise comparisons showed that when visuals were dense, viewers had a particularly hard time understanding the depicted structures when grouping cues were less reinforced (fewer cues were used).</p><p>Cue combination had a significant effect on the time measure (F(30,2108)=6.897, p&lt;0.001), with means for each combination in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 6</ref>. Reinforcement generally reduced time.</p><p>In addition, cue combination, visual density, and visual type all had significant effect on preferences (means <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 6</ref>, ANOVA <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>). Participants preferred reinforced cues. There was slight preference for lower density (2.88 for low and 2.64 for high density) and a stronger preference for imagery (2.93 for imagery visuals and 2.59 for text). (Even though viewers understood structure in text-dominant visuals better.) The interaction between visual density and visual type significantly impacted preference. Preferences for lower density were much stronger with text-dominant visuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Reinforcement analysis</head><p>Our reinforcement analysis grouped cue combinations by the number of cues they employed. This created an experimental variable with five levels. Data was unbalanced across this new variable, so we used a compensating (5×2×2) ANOVA. With this analysis, we can measure the effects of reinforcement more directly than in the per cue combination analysis.</p><p>Reinforcement, visual density, and visual type all had significant effect on distance <ref type="table">(Table 4</ref>). The means for each cue combination are in <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>. The effects of visual density and type mirrored those in the first study: text-dominant visuals were easier to understand, but image-dominant were preferred; while low density visuals were easier to understand, and also preferred. The new reinforcement variable had the effects one would predict from our per combination study: increasing reinforcement improved structural understanding, and was preferred. It also lowered task times (F(4,2225)=10.49, p&lt;0.001).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.3">Per grouping cue analysis</head><p>Our per grouping cue analysis grouped trials by whether or not a certain cue was employed. It created five experimental cue variables with two levels each (used or not). Data was unbalanced across each of these variables since we did not have an all cues absent combination, so we used a compensating (2×2×2×2 ×2×2×2) ANOVA. With this analysis, we can measure the effects of each cue more directly than in the per combination analysis.  <ref type="table">Table 5</ref>. Distance, trial time, and preference means for the per grouping cue analysis. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity, prx=proximity, aln=alignment)</p><p>We detail means in <ref type="table">Table 5</ref>, and main effects and interactions on the distance, time, and preferences in <ref type="table">Tables 6, 7</ref>, and 8 respectively.</p><p>Effects on Distance All variables had significant main effects on structural distance <ref type="table">(Table 6</ref>). With the exception of alignment, each grouping cue -common region, connectedness, color similarity, and proximityreduced distance and improved structural understanding. However, alignment increased distance. As in the previous per cue combination and reinforcement analyses, low density and textdominant visuals reduced distance.</p><p>All variables except visual type interacted with common region. Connectedness, color similarity, alignment harmed structural communication without common region, but had no effect with common region. High visual density harmed communication without common region, but had less harm with common region. There were also two other interactions with alignment. Connectedness improved structural communication without alignment, but with alignment, improvement was more modest. Visual type had no effect without alignment, but with alignment, it was harder to communicate structure with textdominant visuals.</p><p>In three way interactions, the powerful effects of common region masked several two-way interactions. The two-way effects we discuss below were only present when the common region cue was not used. This includes the connectedness and alignment interaction we discussed in the previous paragraph. Without proximity, alignment had no effect. With proximity, alignment harmed structural communication. Proximity improved communication especially well when visual density was low. Proximity improved communication more with textdominant visuals. In image-dominant visuals, density had no effect, but with text-dominant visuals, high density harmed communication.</p><p>Effects on Time Common region and proximity had significant main effects, with each reducing time ( <ref type="table">Table 7)</ref>.</p><p>The two-way interaction of common region and proximity mirrored the same interaction's effect on distance. With common region, proximity had no effect on time. Without common region, proximity reduced time. Common region and visual density also interacted. With common region, using lower density visuals reduce time. Without common region, visual density had no effect. Finally, without connectedness, proximity had no effect. With it, proximity decreased time.</p><p>Once again, the powerful effects of common region masked some two-way interactions. The two-way connectedness-proximity interaction we discussed in the preceding paragraph was only present without common region.  <ref type="table">Table 8</ref>. Significant main effects and interaction of grouping cue, visual density, and visual type on the preference for the per grouping cue analysis. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity, prx=proximity, aln=alignment)</p><p>effects on time mirrored those on distance, with proximity lowering times more for text-dominant visuals. Effects on Preference All grouping cues except alignment had significant effect on preference <ref type="table">(Table 8)</ref>, with the use of a grouping cue being preferred. Low visual density and image-dominant visuals were preferred.</p><p>There were five significant two-way interactions. With common region, viewers preferred the use of connectedness, but without common region, they had no preference. The relationship of common region to proximity mirrored the distance and time interactions. With common region, viewers had no preference, but without common region, they preferred the use of proximity. With common region, viewers preferred image-dominant visuals, but without it, their preference was stronger. With alignment, viewers had a slight preference for the use of color, but without it, their preference for color was stronger. Similarly, with alignment, viewers had a slight preference for the use of proximity, but without it, their preference for proximity was stronger.</p><p>Common region masked or partially masked some significant twoway interactions. With common region, proximity and connectedness did not interact. Without common region, when proximity was used, connectedness increased preferences strongly, while when proximity was not used, adding connectedness had no effect. With common region, proximity and density had significant but fairly weak interacting effects. When proximity was used, visual density did not affect viewer preferences, while when proximity was not used, viewers preferred lower density visuals. Without common region, proximity and density had stronger interacting effects. When proximity was used, viewers preferred lower density visuals, while when proximity was not used, viewers had no preference. With common region, visual density and visual type had significant but relatively weak interacting effects. When visual density was low, preferences were uniformly high. When visual density was high, viewers preferred image-dominant visuals. Without common region, no matter what the visual density, viewers preferred image-dominant visuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Discussion</head><p>Hypothesis 1: Using reinforcing cues improves communication clarity. We found strong evidence in support of this hypothesis, with the accuracy of the knowledge structures participants perceived improving rapidly as reinforcement increased. In addition, viewers preferred reinforced structure, and were able to understand and input them more rapidly. The levels of structural accuracy viewers reached in this reinforcement study were much higher than in our first disjoint study, which leads us to speculate that any possibility of competition between grouping cues should be avoided.</p><p>Hypothesis 2: As visual density declines, communication clarity will improve. We also found strong support for this second hypothesis. In all three of our analyses, viewers preferred low density visuals, and were able to perceive knowledge structures with greater accuracy in low density settings. When common region was not used, lower density visuals improved structural clarity, and increased proximity's affectedness and appeal. These interactions with proximity provide some evidence that lower density visuals improve clarity by giving some grouping cues the visual space they need to be effective.</p><p>Hypothesis 3: Proximity and alignment will affect structural communication even in their absence. We found some support for this hypothesis as it applies to proximity. Proximity had the second strongest effect overall on both perceived structural accuracy and preferences. Proximity's interaction with connectedness demonstrated its effect in absence: without proximity, structures communicated by connectedness took much longer to understand. However, proximity did not interact with grouping by color, and its interactions with common region and connectedness limited its effects: proximity had little effect when common region cues were present, and when connectedness cues were not present.</p><p>We found no support for hypothesis 3 as it might apply to alignment. In fact, our application of alignment was problematic: rather than improving structural understanding, it harmed it. In order to follow the overall design of our reinforcement study, we were forced to develop a method for communicating two-level structures without the use of any reinforcing cues. The obvious solution to communication of multi-level structure with alignment is outlining, however this technique relies heavily on proximity. Our alignment-only solution, relying on horizontal location to communicate outer groups and vertical location to communicate inner groups, was not effective, and did not permit us to examine this portion of hypothesis 3. In fact we are not at all certain that an effective alignment-only method for communicating hierarchical structure exists. It may be that for communicating complex structures, alignment is best used in support of other grouping cues.</p><p>Hypothesis 4: many cues rely on reinforcing proximity. We found limited support for this hypothesis, which was based on the observation that every cue we used except color was spatial in nature. Without proximity, they should therefore be less effective. An interaction with connectedness supported the hypothesis: without proximity, viewers understood knowledge structures much more slowly. However, as we have just discussed, our use of alignment was problematic, and common region -by far the most powerful grouping cue -was equally effective, with or without proximity.</p><p>Hypothesis 5: text dominant visuals rely more heavily on spatial arrangement than image-dominant visuals. We found strong support for this hypothesis. When common region was not in use, proximity cues improved the understanding of text-dominated visuals, and enabled viewers to reach that understanding more quickly. Only textdominated visuals were sensitive to the problems introduced by our alignment solution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">GENERAL DISCUSSION</head><p>Disjoint grouping and dominance Perception research shows, and our own research largely confirms, that when cues are disjoint (communicating different structures), they often interfere with one another in complex ways. Were the dominance of one cue over another easy to predict, designers might make good use of disjoint grouping combinations for aesthetic effect, but such grouping is rare in professional design practice. Our own results suggest that disjoint grouping combinations should be avoided, with the possible exception of disjoint combinations with common region. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 6</ref> shows, visual grouping's effects on viewer preferences closely mirrored its effects on viewer understanding, with clearer communication almost always being preferred. This was also true of visual density. Visual type was the primary exception: while viewers understood text-dominant visuals more clearly, they preferred imagery. This apparent contradiction will be familiar to experienced designers. Does this mean that good understandability implies good visual appeal, at least with respect to visual grouping? Our results are good evidence of correlation; further research is needed to demonstrate any causality. In HCI, research on the relationship between usability and aesthetics has found evidence of an asymmetry in causality, with good usability improving aesthetics, but not the reverse <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. It seems quite possible that understandability will have a stronger relationship to visual appeal than usability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visual understanding and preferences As</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">LESSONS FOR DESIGNERS</head><p>In this section we distill our results into principles that can guide novice designers as they create visuals. We have one general lesson:</p><p>Reinforcement Using multiple cues, each communicating the same structure, is a reliable way for novice designers to add structural clarity to their visuals. In our research, this sort of reinforcement improved communication accuracy and speed, and was preferred by viewers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Lessons by grouping cues</head><p>Common region Common region is a very powerful grouping cue. In our experiments, using it resulted in the most accurate, fastest, and most preferred structural communication. Moreover, common region can compensate for the lack of other reinforcing grouping cues and eliminate the harmful effects on structural communication of high visual density. Finally, for responsive design on displays of varying size, common region is particularly useful because its property of containment is independent of position and size.</p><p>Connectedness Connectedness is a more challenging cue to use. In our studies, viewers took the most time interpreting the structures communicated by it and only had a stronger dislike for alignment. Connectedness should be reinforced with proximity. In our results, using connectedness slowed structural communication and was not preferred unless it was reinforced with proximity. This recommendation might be explained by the visual language required for successful communication through graphs. An unorganized graph is not a clear form of structural communication: successful communication requires systematic layout, including aligning nodes, minimizing link distance, and use of internal nodes.</p><p>Color similarity Color is an effective communicator of simple structures. For more complex structures, it should be reinforced strongly. Because of its non-spatial nature, it rarely interacts with other grouping cues. This might explain its effectiveness in our first experiment as a communicator of disjoint outer groups and should make it useful for responsive designs.</p><p>Proximity In our experiments, proximity was the second most effective grouping cue, as measured by distance, time, and preference. Its effectiveness can be improved by reinforcing connectedness. Proximity is particularly effective in text-dominant and low density visuals.</p><p>Alignment Whenever possible, alignment should be used with strong reinforcement. In our experiments, alignment was the least effective grouping cue as measured by distance and preferences, and among all grouping cues, only alignment reduced the accuracy of structural communication. It may be that alignment is better used for non-structural communication such as sequence. Good alignment is especially important with text-dominant visuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Lessons by content</head><p>Visual density Structural communication is clearer and preferred with low-density visuals. If designers must use high-density visuals, common region can make communication effective but reliance on proximity should be reduced. Lowering density is particularly important when content is text-dominant.</p><p>Visual type This will not surprise designers, but viewers prefer image-dominant visuals. However, it may be surprising to learn that structural communication is more difficult in visuals dominated by imagery. Proximity is an especially powerful grouping cue with textdominant visuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>We begin our conclusion with a discussion of some limitations of this study. First, we did not vary the complexity of the structures or information participants viewed. We anticipate that the effectiveness of many grouping cues would improve as complexity drops; since we believe our levels of complexity were already somewhat challenging. Next, as designers know and Mayer's work implies, effective visual communication is about much more than communication of hierarchical structure. In particular, non-hierarchical structures are common, sequence may be just as important as hierarchical relationships, and we did not address emphases or importance. Third, ours is not truly an end-to-end study of visual communication and understanding. For example, we did not examine knowledge transfer as defined by Mayer and other learning science researchers, using test questions testing what viewers learned. Finally, although we asked viewers whether they liked the stimuli they viewed, we did not rigorously study the aesthetics of our stimuli. We believe strongly that the aesthetic quality of a visual is a crucial contributor to its effectiveness.</p><p>Despite these limitations, we believe our work makes an important contribution to the science needed for more general communicative applications of visualization. Our research is a unique synthesis of concepts from learning science (active learning and structural organization), design (visual hierarchy), and psychology (Gestalt cues and measurement of cognitive structures) to answer pressing questions about the use of visualization technology in broader communicative domains. Our research frames these questions in a testable form, finds useful answers to them, and discusses their meaning in a general applied context. This work has made clear the importance of future research that could address the research limitations raised above, including communication of sequence and emphasis, as well as the relation of effective communication to aesthetics.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The five grouping cues used in disjoint combination in our first study (disjoint combination indicated in 'outer grouping cue, inner grouping cue'). These visuals are simplified for illustration, experimental visuals were more complex. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity, prx=proximity, and aln=alignment)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Some text and imagery visuals in low and high density. Content here shows an Amazon example for the text-dominant visual and Google Images for the image-dominant visual. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity, prx=proximity, aln=alignment)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Tree edit distance, trial time (in seconds), and preference means for the per cue combination analysis. Darker red, yellow, and blue indicate more accurate, quicker, and preferred forms of communication. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity, prx=proximity, aln=alignment)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Manuscript received 31 Mar. 2014; accepted 1 Aug. 2014 ate of publication 2014; date of current version 9 Nov. 2014. For information on obtaining reprints of this article, please send e-mail to: tvcg@computer.org.</figDesc><table><row><cell>.</cell><cell>D</cell></row><row><cell>11 Aug.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>8 Digital Object Identifier 10.1109/TVCG.2014.23469 8 9</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>contrast the reinforcing and disjoint approaches.</figDesc><table><row><cell>independent variable</cell><cell cols="2">ANOVA of edit distance F p</cell></row><row><cell>outer group</cell><cell>F(4,1225)=31.824</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>inner group</cell><cell>F(4,1225)=6.149</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>outer×inner</cell><cell>F(16,1225)=2.037</cell><cell>p=0.009</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3 .Table 4 .</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Significant effects on edit distance and preferences for the per cue combination analysis.Fig. 7. Distance and trial time decline (i.e. understanding improves) as reinforcement increases. Preference grows with more reinforcement. Significant effects on edit distance and preferences for the reinforcement analysis.</figDesc><table><row><cell>independent variable</cell><cell cols="3">ANOVA of edit distance F p</cell></row><row><cell>cue combination</cell><cell>F(30,2108)=75.023</cell><cell cols="2">p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>visual density</cell><cell>F(1,2108)=35.945</cell><cell cols="2">p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>visual type</cell><cell>F(1,2108)=9.607</cell><cell cols="2">p=0.002</cell></row><row><cell>cue combination×visual density</cell><cell>F(30,2108)=1.712</cell><cell cols="2">p=0.01</cell></row><row><cell>independent variable</cell><cell cols="2">ANOVA of preference F</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>cue combination</cell><cell>F(30,2108)=23.152</cell><cell cols="2">p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>visual density</cell><cell>F(1,2108)=31.227</cell><cell cols="2">p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>visual type</cell><cell>F(1,2108)=63.872</cell><cell cols="2">p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>visual density×visual type</cell><cell>F(1,2108)=11.526</cell><cell cols="2">p=0.001</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The masked proximity-visual type interaction's</figDesc><table><row><cell>number of</cell><cell>independent</cell><cell cols="2">ANOVA of time</cell></row><row><cell>cues</cell><cell>variable</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>single cue</cell><cell>cmn prx</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=110.69 F(1,2208)=29.53</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001 p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn×prx</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=26.30</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>two cues</cell><cell>cnc×prx</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=6.16</cell><cell>p=0.01</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn×density</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=4.72</cell><cell>p=0.03</cell></row><row><cell>three cues</cell><cell>cmn×cnc×prx cmn×prx×type</cell><cell>F(1,2128)=4.11 F(1,2168)=4.36</cell><cell>p=0.04 p=0.03</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Table 7. Significant main effects and interaction of grouping cue, vi-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">sual density, and visual type on the time for the per grouping cue anal-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">ysis. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similarity,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">prx=proximity, aln=alignment)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>number of</cell><cell>independent</cell><cell cols="2">ANOVA of preference</cell></row><row><cell>cues</cell><cell>variable</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=448.23</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cnc</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=16.27</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>single cue</cell><cell>col prx</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=38.20 F(1,2208)=63.52</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001 p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>visual density</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=30.33</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>visual type</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=63.32</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn×cnc</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=19.64</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn×prx</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=44.08</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>two cues</cell><cell>col×aln</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=6.90</cell><cell>p=0.01</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>prx×aln</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=30.86</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn×type</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=6.91</cell><cell>p=0.01</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn×cnc×prx</cell><cell>F(1,2128)=14.89</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>three cues</cell><cell>cmn×prx×density</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=5.88</cell><cell>p=0.01</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cmn×density×type</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=4.47</cell><cell>p=0.03</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>number of</cell><cell>independent</cell><cell>ANOVA of edit distance</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cues</cell><cell>variable</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=1401.63</cell><cell>p&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cnc</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=71.01</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>col</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=46.10</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>single cue</cell><cell>prx</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=158.10</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>aln</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=14.91</cell><cell>p=0.0001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>visual density</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=32.16</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>visual type</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=7.98</cell><cell>p=0.005</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×cnc</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=98.22</cell><cell>p&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×col</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=58.19</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×prx</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=162.25</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>two cues</cell><cell>cmn×aln</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=10.27</cell><cell>p=0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cnc×aln</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=8.38</cell><cell>p=0.004</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×density</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=6.56</cell><cell>p=0.01</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>aln×type</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=5.73</cell><cell>p=0.02</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×cnc×aln</cell><cell>F(1,2128)=15.59</cell><cell>p&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×prx×aln</cell><cell>F(1,2128)=4.02</cell><cell>p=0.045</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>three cues</cell><cell>cmn×prx×density</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=13.6</cell><cell>p=0.0002</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×prx×type</cell><cell>F(1,2168)=8.58</cell><cell>p=0.003</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cmn×density×type</cell><cell>F(1,2208)=6.84</cell><cell>p=0.009</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Table 6. Significant main effects and interaction of grouping cue, visual</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">density, and visual type on the edit distance for the per grouping cue</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">analysis. (cmn=common region, cnc=connectedness, col=color similar-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ity, prx=proximity, aln=alignment)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors wish to thank Agnes Gall, Anne McLaughlin, and Douglas J. Gillan for their valuable feedback, and the Turkers who participated in our studies.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perceptual grouping by similarity and proximity: Experimental results can be predicted by intensity autocorrelations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ben-Av</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vision research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="853" to="866" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uniform connectedness and classical Gestalt principles of perceptual grouping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Humphreys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perception &amp; Psychophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="674" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crowdsourcing Graphical Perception: Using Mechanical Turk to Assess Visualization Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bostock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="212" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principle of Gestalt Psychology. London, Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul Ltd</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1935" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The whole is equal to the sum of its parts: A probabilistic model of grouping by proximity and similarity in regular patterns</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kubovy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Den</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactions between intrinsic principles of similarity and proximity and extrinsic principle of common region in visual perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Luna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Montoro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perception-London</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1477" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Multimedia Learning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common region: A new principle of perceptual grouping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="447" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The repetition discrimination task: An objective method for studying perceptual grouping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perception and Psychophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rethinking perceptual organization: The role of uniform connectedness</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Rock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychonomic bulletin &amp; review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do Predictions of Visual Perception Aid Design?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rosenholtz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dorai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Applied Perception</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An intuitive model of perceptual grouping for HCI design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rosenholtz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Twarog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Schinkel-Bielefeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wattenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGCHI 2009</title>
		<meeting>SIGCHI 2009</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1331" to="1340" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is beautiful really usable? toward understanding the relation between usability, aesthetics, and affect in hci</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Tuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hornbaek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Opwis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bargas-Avila</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Human Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1596" to="1607" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A century of Gestalt psychology in visual perception: I. Perceptual grouping and figure-ground organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wagemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Elder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kubovy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Heydt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1172" to="1217" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visual thinking for design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A model of multi-scale perceptual organization in information graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wattenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simple fast algorithms for the editing distance between trees and related problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shasha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM Journal of Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1245" to="1262" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laws of attraction: From perceptual forces to conceptual similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ziemkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kosara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1016" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
