<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Attribute Signatures: Dynamic Visual Summaries for Analyzing Multivariate Geographical Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cagatay</forename><surname>Turkay</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Attribute Signatures: Dynamic Visual Summaries for Analyzing Multivariate Geographical Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2014.23462</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:10+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Visual analytics</term>
					<term>multi-variate data</term>
					<term>geographic information</term>
					<term>geovisualization</term>
					<term>interactive data analysis</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Fig. 1. Attribute signatures (right) are dynamically created in response to an interactive geographic selection sequence (left) that follows the coastline from South Gloucestershire to St Ives on the north Cornwall coast where each output area is represented with an orange dot. The signatures show how the average values for 41 attributes vary as the selection moves. The trace of the brush sequence is linked to the signatures-the faded points and the vertical dashed lines on the signatures are linked to the location highlighted on the map. A small holiday resort, Lynton (green rectangle), is characterized by the high proportion of population in the hotel and catering industry. Fishing &amp; agriculture towns, such as Hartland (red markers), are characterized with low population densities where population is in mostly detached houses.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>• Cagatay Turkay, Aidan Slingsby, Jo <ref type="bibr">Wood, and</ref>  Multivariate data are common in various application domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> and understanding how these relate is important when investigating the domain-specific phenomena. Exploratory visualization is an important means to do this <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>. In some domains, data have a strong geographical component which dominates variation. Examples include population demographics, multivariate spatial interaction models, species distribution models and land-use models. Knowing how multiple attributes vary over space is critical in interpreting the phenomena that these data and models represent. For example, understanding population characteristics is of great importance for governments and agencies involved in providing services and designing policy. Interna- tional agencies and governments invest heavily in maintaining accurate statistics about changes in demographics, employment levels, migration and other related statistics. In some cases, the dominant and most interesting aspect of variation relates to geography. Designing mechanisms to support the exploration of the geographical variation in multiple attributes simultaneously is challenging since geographical distributions tend to be heterogeneous and are often strongly related and influenced by topographic features <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Whilst "everything is related to everything else but nearby things more so" <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>, such relations vary according to the scale at which measurements are made <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Some phenomena, such as population density, vary greatly -a phenomenon that is highly dependent upon the extent of the spatial units used to measure it as well as the location at which it is measured. Understanding how attributes vary over geography and over the different scales involves the design challenges that we discuss in this paper. The visual and interaction mechanisms we propose are designed to support analysis of geographical data by addressing these challenges.</p><p>In this paper, we consider key issues associated with the geographic variation of multivariate data and develop approaches to support those working with such datasets. We suggest visual encodings and interaction mechanisms configured for this activity. We design, discuss and demonstrate how this can be done using map brushing in multiple coordinated views that show how multiple attributes vary in geographical space, extent, and resolution. In doing so, we demonstrate a series of effects that are indicative of the kinds of complexities associated with multivariate geographical analysis. Our contributions involve:</p><p>• approaches for investigating the role of location, spatial extent and spatial resolution in multiple attributes concurrently; • plausible visual encodings and novel interactions that facilitate this analysis while maintaining the spatial context; • illustrating why the consideration of these multiple aspects is important through geographical exploration of multivariate data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">ANALYZING GEOGRAPHICAL DATA</head><p>The special characteristics of geographical space often require particular approaches and methods, developed over the past three decades in geographical information science.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Graphical depiction</head><p>Maps are often appropriate means for graphically depicting geographical variation in data. However, this is only really effective where there are few attributes. Since maps already use position-and size-related visual variables, visual variables for depicting other attributes are limited. Choropleth maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> and geographical heatmaps <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref> convey data using different aspects of colour, including lightness, saturation and hue <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Bi-and multi-variate colour schemes that use these different aspects of colour can depict multiple attributes concurrently. These work particularly well where the attributes are related -such as when aspects of topography are visualized concurrently <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Additional attributes can be added by combining more visual variables or by using glyphs or other embedded matrices, but often at the expense of the geographical resolution at which the data are displayed -a data rich example is Dorling's use of non-continuous population cartograms containing Chernoff faces coloured using a multivariate scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Even these judiciously designed examples can depict a limited number of attributes concurrently in their spatial context. Interactive techniques are widely used to help make sense of many variables. These often avoid the problem of depicting spatial variation directly by facilitating geographical filtering. This usually results in non-geographical graphical depictions of the multiple attributes for one location only <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, but visual variables in such graphics may be used to encode aspects of space -such as distance from the selected location in geocentric parallel plots <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. These methods equally apply to spatial variation between two non-geographical attributes -as in a generic scatterplot. However, the nature of geographical information, in particular the scale, often requires the use of specific methods. For example, Butkiewicz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> allowed selection at variable spatial scales. The interactive nature of these interfaces makes geographical comparisons equivalent to that of animation, except the user has the control to direct the animation -often with a geographic emphasis. Although animation can be an effective means to present trends, it does not allow trends to be detected well <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>. Harrower <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> suggests using visual benchmarks to aid memory in the cartographic context, a technique used in Wood's traces <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54]</ref> for interactively comparing topographic features at a sequence of locations. Alternatively, non-temporal forms of comparison may be preferable. Gleicher et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> identify difference, juxtaposition and superposition as candidate means of presenting multiple geographic selections, examples of which were implemented by Slingsby et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Related to this are multiple coordinated views <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref> in which geographical filtering through brushing <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> on a map updates other views that depict multivariate data for the brushed subset, used by Haslet et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> for identifying the statistical outliers in space. Similarly, Ferreira et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> made use of spatial queries that are reflected and compared in linked visualizations of spatio-temporal data. Our work adds to these interactive methods by making the variation (i.e, the interaction axis) an integral part of the visualizations to enable a concurrent analysis of many variables on different scales.</p><p>A different approach is to use dimension reduction techniques such as PCA and clustering/classification to select or generate derived attributes that aim to summarise important variation in a way that can be mapped <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Spatial statistical modelling such as kriging or geographically-weighted regression can produce geographicallyvarying parameters and residuals that can be mapped to give insight into the multivariate phenomena <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. We preclude the former approach from our work since we focus on exploring how all attributes respond geographically.</p><p>Putting into perspective -Visualizing how phenomena change over space and time has been investigated in the GTDiff method by Hoeber et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> and by Kehrer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> who present examples of change maps in their design study on small multiples. These techniques and most of the visualization methods already discussed above <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51]</ref> are good examples of how one can get an overview of the changes at a high scale and often for a single location or variable. Our approach, on the other hand, provides insight into patterns at different scales depending on how the interaction is carried out by the analyst, i.e., we take a highly explorative approach in curating the dynamic graphics. In that respect, our methods are complementary to the existing techniques that provide an overview of the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">The nature of geographical variation</head><p>Many geographical phenomena are strongly influenced by topographic features (coastlines, rivers, roads, relief), political boundaries and economic activity. As such many geographic data sets contain edges, boundaries and directional variability. Thus important variation may be along linear features as well as distributed through Euclidean representations of space. Different aspects of the phenomenon may vary independently at different geographical scales. We distinguish three aspects of space that are the basis of our analysis: location, scale extent and scale resolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>:</p><p>Location -the geographical point at which a measurement is made. Scale extent (or domain) -the geographical extent around a location that is under consideration -defining an area <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>. Increasing the extent is often likely to increase the number of data points for which multiple attributes are considered at any location.</p><p>Scale resolution -the amount of detail that is considered in characterising a location <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. It may be related to sampling strategy or data availability. The nature of the summaries will change as they are computed at these different spatial resolutions -an understanding of which reveals the scales at which homogeneity or heterogeneity exist in different aspects of population.</p><p>Summary statistics derived from geographic data are strongly dependent on the spatial units used <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, in terms of both extent and resolution. Being able to investigate these and their geographic variation can help us make more informed interpretations of data, explore their sensitivities and understand the nature of the phenomena that we mea- sure. For example, consider income -a variable that is not collected in the UK census. We may find differences at a regional scale in the average and variance of income between the north and south. Comparing the averages and variances at more local levels will tell us whether differences in income involve solely these national phenomena or more local processes, or a combination of each.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">An example dataset</head><p>We </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">FRAMEWORK AND DESIGN</head><p>The different perspectives on geographical variation provide us a structure that we build upon in designing and developing our analysis methods. In the following, we start with a framework that sets the structure of our analysis space. We then discuss interactive visual methods to address the various parts of this space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Framework</head><p>We consider geographical variation in terms of spatial location (SL), spatial extent (SE) and spatial resolution (SR) as introduced in Section 2.2. In <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, these forms of geographical variation is illustrated. Within our framework, we enable an analyst to interactively determine and vary one of these aspects. The possibilities for investigating the effects of these aspects of geography on the analysis of multiple attributes are summarised in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 1</ref>. For each exploration, we vary any one of these characteristics, holding the others constant as shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 1</ref>. This variation is facilitated through interactive inputs and map brushing. We refer to this interactively determined aspect as the axis of variation. Our framework then moves on to representing the characteristics of this variation through the use of one or more statistics that are visualized simultaneously. These views often have a comparative nature, thus reported against a baseline. This comparative axis is referred to as the axis of comparison. These aspects determine the design choices we make in the following section where we define attribute signatures.</p><p>The axis of variation can either be continuous or discrete. Notice that this variation character is reflected in our notation presented in  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Attribute Signatures</head><p>An attribute signature depicts a user-defined geographical variation of an attribute using one or more summary statistics as a sparkline <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>. For each attribute, we construct a single attribute signature and arrange these using ordered juxtaposition <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> as a series of small multiples (see <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>, right). These can be ordered in various configurations according to their similarity (section 3.6). The small multiples view is a component of a multiple-coordinated views environment in which interactive selections can be performed on location, extent and resolution on a map view. Brushing in multiple coordinated views is common, with Mondrian <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> and Improvise <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> being particularly elegant examples. One example of linking signatures to a map view can be seen in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. Here, the user performs a sequence of selections on the map and the attribute signatures are generated dynamically in response to support SLc type (i.e., continuous location) analysis. Since we are varying location (by moving the selection on the map), location becomes the variation axis on the signatures. For each point on x-axis, a comparative statistic (e.g. normalized difference between means) is computed between the selection and the baseline (Sections 3.4 and 3.4.1). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Axis of comparison</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Axis of variation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparison baseline</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Interactivity for generating attribute signatures</head><p>Three modes of geographical brushing relate to the three geographical aspects under consideration. In each case, a user can vary one aspect while the others remain constant ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 1)</ref>. Each of these modes allows these aspects of geography to be varied continuously or discretely.</p><p>Spatial location (SL). The zoomable map enables geographical selections (SL) to be made along a continuous path or at an ordered set of discrete locations, each of which is at a constant spatial extent (SE) and spatial resolution (SR). This interaction and visual encoding enables us to identify geographic patterns and anomalies between places or along trajectories of varying fractal dimension.</p><p>Spatial extent (SE). Keeping the brush at a fixed location (SL) and using a constant spatial resolution (SR), varying the extent of the brush area selects increasingly larger or smaller geographical areas. The corresponding attribute signature response indicates the distance at which different aspects of population remain homogeneous at a fixed location. This interaction and visual encoding is designed to reveal structure in the scale-based variation of multiple attributes concurrently at any location, as in a work by Dykes and Brunsdon <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</p><p>Spatial resolution (SR). Fixing the location (SL) and spatial extent (SE), but varying the spatial resolution (aggregation level) reveals differences caused by generating statistical summaries from different aggregations of data. Attribute signatures indicate the effect of reporting these data using different spatial units. This interaction and visual encoding supports analysis of the effects of aggregation on statistical summaries at a single location -a key component of the MAUP <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, the analysis of which results in what Openshaw has described as a "modifiable areal unit opportunity".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Statistical summaries for comparison</head><p>In response to the interactive selections on a map, we dynamically compute statistics to help investigate how attributes vary along the axis of variation. We employ a multiple-coordinated views approach, in which brushing on a map geographically conditions the data. Each attribute is summarised with a summary statistic relating to this area using Turkay et al.'s methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> whereby a statistic λ , e.g., a descriptive statistic such as mean µ or standard deviation σ , is computed using only the data points that are selected S i at a particular location i on the variation axis. We then compare these "locally" computed results λ S i to a baseline value λ B i to calculate the difference at location i with: ∆ i = λ S i − λ B i similar to difference plots by Turkay et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. These computations are undertaken in real time for all the attributes, and ∆ i and λ are vectors of size p -the number of attributes in the data.</p><p>During an interactive session, the user selects (i.e., incrementing i) either location or scale (either extent or resolution). In response, a new comparison computation is performed on the fly and the resulting difference is depicted in each attribute signature. This mechanism enables us to dynamically create the signatures in real time.</p><p>We can describe variation in a number of attribute statistics in the signatures (see Turkay et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> for a complete list). However, since the comparison of means is a common analytical task <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, we compute the differences for the mean values of each attribute between the selection and a baseline by default, i.e., λ = µ. Moreover, to achieve a more robust comparison between the means, we normalize this difference with the standard deviation of the attribute. The resulting measure is known as the effect size <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> and is a robust version of the difference between the means of two sample sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.1">Baselines</head><p>The interpretation of what is observed on an attribute signature depends on how we set the baseline according to the analytical question we want to tackle. In suggesting baseline alternatives, we take a similar approach to Kehrer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> who discuss a model to design comparative small multiples for structured data. Unlike their work, our baseline design is also applicable to unstructured data. In our approach, we offer:</p><p>• No baseline</p><p>• Constant baseline Uses the same value for the whole axis of variation, λ B i = c, ∀i ∈ N. The interpretation is then based on what we set as the c value. If we want to compare, for instance, each location to the national average, c value is set to the average values for all the attributes using the entire data set. Alternatively, we enable the user to set any statistics computed locally as the c value. One example could be to compute the mean values of the attributes for London and save these as the baseline. After such a setting is done, the signatures then display the difference to London average. This option is useful, for instance, when an analyst is trying to understand the local variations within a city. Another alternative is to use statistics computed for a particular variable and generate visualizations of relative differences or correlations, e.g., displaying correlations of all the variables with the age variable. • Varying baseline Varies the baseline with the axis of variation, e.g. computing a local average λ B i as we vary location on the map. This is, however, a special case where we compute the same local statistics over different datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.2">More dimensions: time and scale</head><p>Each attribute may have more than one dimension, for example it may be measured at different times and scales. We consider data recorded for each of the 41 census attributes in two successive censuses here (2001 and 2011) and released at four different resolutions: Output Area (OA), NUTS3, NUTS2, NUTS1. Our approach enables this kind of comparison by computing the local statistics at the same location for different datasets. For example we can compute the differences for all variables between the two census years. Our difference computation becomes</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">∆ i = λ S i 2011 − λ S i 2001 .</formula><p>As a result, attribute signatures display the difference -temporal change in this case -between two values for a local selection. Such computations make use of the fact that the two datasets relate to the same physical location and S i is determined by the actual physical boundaries set through a selection on the map. This capability enables us to carry out comparative analysis even if two datasets are sampled or aggregated differently -as is so in the case of OAs we analyze where 2.6% of OA locations changed between 2001 and 2011 <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>. The nature of geographic phenomena means that such changes were not spatially independent, but the approaches used here remain relatively robust to such changes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Visual design alternatives</head><p>The nature of variation and the number of attributes we encode in a single small multiple determines the design of attribute signatures. Examples of these design alternatives are provided in Section 4.</p><p>• Single sparkline: where the variation axis is continuous and the analyst wants to observe a single statistic or the difference to a baseline, we employ a signature attribute with a single sparkline. • Multiple sparklines: where the variation axis is continuous and the analyst wants to observe the response of several statistics or their differences to baselines for each attribute, we switch to signatures with multiple sparklines, i.e, drawing several lines to represent the λ S i values as i changes and supporting comparison through superposition. • Bar charts: where the variation is discrete, and the analyst wants to observe a single statistic or the difference to a baseline, we use discrete bars to communicate the discrete nature of the variation.</p><p>One example where such visualizations are employed could be the comparison of different cities. • Multi-bar charts: where the variation is discrete, and the analyst wants to observe the response of several statistics or their differences to baselines for each attribute, multi-bar charts (or stacked bar charts) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> in which small multiple bar charts for individual selections of location, resolution or extent are interleaved on the variation axis, seem an appropriate solution. Although, we do not demonstrate the use of this visualization in our examples, we include this option for the sake of completeness. Notice here that the small multiples are designed to reflect the variation (as an axis) that is interactively determined by the analyst. In order to complement these dynamic views by providing an overview of the distribution of all the variables over the space, one can make use of small multiples of heatmaps or choropleth maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6">Supporting Interactive Exploration</head><p>Since we design attribute signatures as part of an explorative analysis framework, we develop additional interactions to enhance the use of this visualization method. Here, we suggest three mechanisms to aid: the comparison between the attributes, the investigation of the relations between the variation of location and scale with variation of attributes, and the generation of structured selection sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.1">Reordering attribute signatures</head><p>Attribute signatures are arranged in a 2D table which can be ordered column-by-column by the characteristics of the signature. To order the signatures, we first let the user select an attribute of interest by clicking on the small multiple. At this stage, we make use of the fact that each signature can be treated as a trajectory defined in 2D space. Thus, we compute the Euclidean distance between the selected attribute and the others. We then place the selected attribute to the top-left corner of the small multiple table and order all the other attribute signatures in a descending order of similarity with this first one. The most similar attribute is placed below the first one in the first column and so on, i.e., a column by column ordering. This mechanism helps the analysts to quickly spot the attributes that behave similarly (following the selected one within the same column) or very differently. This can be seen as a quick mechanism to represent groupings visually. Alternatively, one can also order the signatures according to the values at a particular location at i. This method, on the other hand makes it possible to compare the attributes for a particular location, or a scale.</p><p>An important point to mention here is that there are alternative ways and alternative distance measures <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> to order these signatures. One mechanism that can be employed here is to include a 2D ordering as suggested by Schreck et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.2">Linking signatures</head><p>To more effectively study how the attributes vary over space, we display the path along which the map was brushed or display the set of discrete locations selected. This has the effect of leaving trails on the map. This allows us to see how attributes vary as we move along the trail on the map. Highlighting the interaction location along the x-axes of all signatures ensures that signatures are interactively linked to each other (via small dots displayed on the sparklines) and to the location and extent on the map at which the summary statistics are computed (via a path and a rectangle showing the selection). Moreover, bidirectional linking between the map and attribute signatures enable the identification of locations, extents or resolutions at which variations in the statistics occur. This type of linking between the map and abstract visual representations is shown to be effective in understanding the urban structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and supporting multi-focus analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.3">Key-framed brushing</head><p>Spatial traces are created through selection sequences in which selection brushes are dragged across the map. Although this provides flexibility in performing an analysis, there might be arbitrary patterns in the signatures due to the pace that these selections are defined, i.e., how slow/fast the user moves a selection. In order to support users in developing their selection sequences, we introduce a semi-automated interaction mechanism called keyframed brushing. This method aids the user in quickly defining selection sequences that are precisely structured, by making equally placed selections that follow a straight line. This provides a regular spatial sample across any linear transect. In this mechanism, the user defines two or more brushes (according to their analytical goal) just as one might define key frames in computerassisted animation <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Using these key brushes, a sequence of inbetween brushes are generated automatically over a linear path that connects these key brushes. After the brush sequence is computed, the system starts traversing through this without the need for further input by the user.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">ANALYSIS EXAMPLES</head><p>The way in which attribute signatures are used to reveal structure, variation and features of interest in geographic data is demonstrated through a series of analysis examples in which attribute signatures are built interactively. We present these examples in line with the analysis alternatives outlined in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 1</ref> within the description of our framework.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Continuous geographical variation (SLc)</head><p>Here, we vary spatial location continuously along a user defined path.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">Geographically-significant linear features</head><p>Geographical features influence human activity. Where these are linear, this category of exploration can help investigate how this affects population characteristics along the feature (e.g., Dorling's work on demographic differences along London's Central Line underground railway <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>) or perpendicular to it (e.g., the effect of the proximity of railway stations on house prices <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>). These features can be both natural such as coastlines, mountain ranges, or man-made such as roads or city boundaries.</p><p>One of these features, coastlines, are interesting linear geographical features that have strong impacts on human activity. Areas on the coast tend to have particular characteristics with high levels of residents reliant upon tourism, fishing industry and in retirement. In our first example in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>, we investigate the coastline from just north of Bristol to the north coast of Cornwall. We drag the brush along the coast, holding the spatial extent constant. Resulting attribute signatures shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> depict the different characteristics of the towns and cities. Locations along the path can be highlighted interactively and their position shown in the attribute signatures. For example, the area highlighted in green in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> is indicated with a vertical line on each signature, allowing statistical summaries for all attributes to be compared to that location. The attributes that show the greatest change along this section of coast are settlement-related, such as population density, housing type, working from home and certain types of employment. We order signatures by their similarity to employment in agriculture or fishing (upper left) to investigate characteristics of settlements where this characteristic dominates. As expected, this characteristic is most closely associated with locations with low population density, thus with more detached housing and fewer flats. Hartland is a good example, with high fishing and agriculture employment (red arrows) and low population density. The same is true for Lynton in Devon (highlighted in green), a small town popular with tourists, characterized by hotel employment, fewer jobs in manufacturing and elderly residents. The way in which variables vary as resort towns are peppered along the coast is evident. Some attributes vary little and are independent of these characteristics, such as the proportion of residents of Black and Indian ethnicity, which is consistently low in the South West other than around the city of Bristol.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">Transects through cities</head><p>The structure of cities has long been studied in urban geography <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref> and various models of their structure have been proposed, including Burgess' concentric structure with the 'central business district' centrally, Hoyt's concentric and wedge model and more modern polycentric model <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, with multiple centers of economic activity.</p><p>Inspired by Duany's concept of the 'urban transect' <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, we explore transects through London (a polycentric city) and Leicester (a monocentric city). We employ our key-framed brushing mechanism to create a linear west-east transect that starts at the westernmost outskirts of the city, passes through the center and continues to the eastern outskirts ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4)</ref>. We report values in attribute signatures using effect size and local baselines so we can compare local variation in cities.</p><p>Attribute signatures across London <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. 4)</ref> are variously shaped as m <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. 4, marked 1)</ref>, v (2), u (3) or n (4) -highlighting differences between inner and outer London, with significant differences in central London for the m-shaped signatures, such as for commuting using public transport (1). The brush extent is not small enough to differentiate between these different centres as was apparent in along the coast in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. The lack of symmetry as we move across London reveals interesting structure, such as the low proportion of home workers (5), high proportion of infants <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> and proportion of adults separated or divorced <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> at the eastern fringes of the city compared to the west. These figures vary significantly despite other similarities between the east and west ends of the city relating to population density <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref>, and the data on commuting (1). In Leicester, the very sharp dips or peaks at a single location at the city centre for attributes such as % of detached houses <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>, % of children (9), or % people living alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> reflects the concentration of students and young professionals living in apartments in this part of town, which is distinct in character from the other locations along the selected path. This is typical of a monocentric city and the variation is captured with the scale of the extent used here. Note, however that as is the case in outer London example, the city is asymmetrical in terms of population characteristics. The attribute signatures are skewed as they highlight the more densely populated East of Leicester that is dominated by terraced housing <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref> and high levels of employment <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>, infants (13) and residents identifying themselves as being of Indian, Pakistani or Bangladeshi origin <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</p><p>In addition to the above analysis, we consider different statistical measures concurrently -for example the median and interquartile range. These two robust measures of the center and spread of the data distribution are shown using superimposition in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> through multiple sparklines. Generally, the more atypical values in the center with respect to the baseline show low variation <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(marked 1,2,3</ref>), suggesting they are more homogenous, further indicating the distinctiveness of city centers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.3">Comparing the 2001 and 2011 Census</head><p>Populations are highly dynamic, as captured officially every ten years in the UK census. For each attribute, we can compare data for the past two censuses, those undertaken in 2001 and 2011. To investigate this change, we again create a linear transect through London that generates signatures using the temporal comparison computation. <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref> allows us to see that some attributes have changed consistently across London, such as households with no central heating (as housing improved) and increasing privately rented accommodation (highlighted). In other cases, attributes in West London are relatively stable while East London displays more evident demographic change. Proportions with a higher education qualification, of unemployed, belonging to minority ethnic groups and living in detached housing are up in London's east over the last decade. We will not speculate as to the reasons for these changes, but draw attention to the fact that these interactively selected comparative graphics support precisely this activity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Discrete geographical variation (SLd)</head><p>Here, we compare distinct places. Rather than moving a brush along a path, we allow discrete locations to be selected. We compared the populations of six most populated cities in England. In order of population, these are London, Manchester, Birmingham, Leeds, Liverpool and Southampton. Rather than using sparklines, we use bar charts to emphasise the discrete nature of the locations and our axis of variation. The discrete locations are ordered by population from left to right in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 7</ref>, where bar charts are sized against a national baseline so that comparisons are meaningful. As an additional visual variable, we color the bar charts to reflect the number of samples that is represented with a bar. This mechanism informs the user about the ordering of the bars and aims to support their association with the cities.</p><p>Strong demographic differences are apparent, but these do not appear to vary by city size, suggesting other reasons for these differences. London consistently shows the largest difference from the national mean. In terms of housing, London stands out for having a high proportion of its residents in privately rented accommodation and in flats. Liverpool is an outlier in terms of a number of attributes including the foreign born, long term illness, employees in health and social work and households with non-dependent children. Southampton is the smallest city of the six. Its center was rebuilt in the 1950s for car usage, so, as expected, public transport for commuting is low and the households with more than two cars is high.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Continuous geographical extent variation (SEc)</head><p>Keeping geographical location constant and studying how statistical summaries of multiple attributes vary for changing geographical extent can help reveal the geographical scales at which characteristics of the population vary. We can do this by centering the map on a location and attribute signatures will update as we zoom in or out. Thus, the axis of variation is the spatial extent rather than spatial location. The result is a scalogram <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, which tend towards the global mean as the extent increases.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 8</ref>, we start with selecting a number of OAs around Charing Cross Station in London (London's central point) and continuously zoom out to cover the whole country keeping the center constant. The rate at which attributes converge to the national mean varies. Most of the attributes vary at local scales. For instance, the black African population (dashed circle) displays local variations within the city, although this attribute is significantly higher than the country average in London. Such local variations are clear indications of a need for local analysis rather than comparisons to global averages. We highlight two scales, the two maps on at the top of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 8</ref>, where most of the attributes change significantly. The first of these corresponds to Central London, where there are changes the housing stock (marked with circles). The second of these corresponds to a scale that covers outer London. Demographics vary significantly at this scale, % of Indian, Black African, and foreign born population see a decrease at this larger scale. For public transport, although comparably higher across the whole city, its use increases further (top-left signature) for the area between inner and outer London. This relates to the fact that many travel to the city center for work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Discrete geographical extent variation (SEd)</head><p>We consider an area focussed on the city of Leicester at four different spatial extents derived from the hierarchical NUTS aggregation. The graphics in <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref> show how the 41 variables vary at these 4 spatial extents. In many cases, the City of Leicester -the smallest extent we consider here, represented by bars on the left of the graph -is different from other regional extents. Levels of car ownership, use of public transport, home working and housing variables vary markedly from the other regions. However, some attributes vary more continuously. Population density, occupancy levels, and those of Indian origin change more gently as scales increase. Rather than showing an abrupt distinction between city and elsewhere, the differences between city and region are more diffuse suggesting that different processes are occurring at a different scale. The proportion of Indian origin population varies relatively linearly from high at the local level to less than the national average when the East Midlands as a whole is considered. Other variables are far less scale dependent. For example, many aspects of employment structure vary little as extent changes around this location suggesting that the processes that govern any differences in employment structure operate at larger or smaller scales than we detect here. <ref type="figure">Fig. 9</ref> orders the attribute signatures according to attribute type, but reordering according to the degree to which attributes are scale dependent can help with this analysis. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Discrete geographical resolution variation (SRd)</head><p>Summary statistics are computed and reported at various standard output scales. Here we analyse the effects of these differing levels of resolution by keeping location and extent constant whilst varying the scale of resolution at which the statistics used in calculating our summaries are aggregated. We make use of the different NUTS levels here, aggregating the data according to these discrete levels. Our constant selection of extent covers all points within Greater London <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">(Figure 10)</ref>. The attribute signatures display differences (using effect size as the measure) between London and the whole nation at scales from fine to coarse, i.e., OA, NUTS3, NUTS2, and NUTS1. The baseline in all cases is kept constant as the national average computed at OA level. The attributes respond differently to aggregation. For instance, when 'manufacturing' is considered at OA level, we see that London is below the national average. However, as this comparison is made with larger administrative regions (NUTS1), the difference is even more significant. Similar patterns are observed for % working in wholesale and retail and those with higher education qualifications. These attributes are more sensitive to variations in resolution than others. For certain attributes, such as % people working in agriculture &amp; fishing, the aggregation level does not affect the results -this indicates that analysis on this variable can be undertaken at any level of aggregation safely. Although, we do not show the results here, when we vary the location, the resolution-related behaviour of the attributes changes, i.e., the relation between the scale resolution and the attributes is location dependent. Considering such variability is highly challenging without the support of interactive visual approaches. <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 1</ref> outlines the various analysis alternatives that are possible over the different perspectives in geographical data. We use this table as a guideline to perform the analysis cases in the previous section. Although we demonstrate most of these alternatives, we have not included an example for the continuous variation of geographical resolution (SRc). Varying this continuously by distance would produce statistical summaries that could be visualized using the sparkline technique shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 8</ref>. Wood <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> applies this technique in the context of geomorphometry. In the design of our framework (Section 3.1), one decision we made to frame our discussion is the consideration of the axis of variation to be one-dimensional. However, one can easily think of analysis questions that relate to the variation of two of the aspects we determine in this paper, i.e., any two aspects from SL, SE, SR. One example of this could be varying the location SL and geographical extent simultaneously, e.g., comparing the response of the attributes in six distinct cities (discrete location) over locally varying NUTS level based extents (discrete extent) -in other words, generating an output similar to <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref> for each selection location on the map. Such an extension suggests a significantly wide domain of analysis possibilities, especially when variation characters, whether discrete or continuous, are also considered, i.e., 6 2 • 2 = 30 combinations. One challenge that immediately surfaces with this extension is to establish designs that could enable each particular type of analysis. Spatio-temporal analysis involves a whole host of decisions about the nature of the variation that is of interest. Visualization can help explore the possibilities and enable us to find combinations that are of interest for certain places and phenomena, but we are far from knowing precisely what is likely to be important when. Such questions about this analysis space call for more systematic study where multiple aspects of spatial variation are investigated concurrently. With this paper, we move into this large analysis space and introduce a framework and visual methods that set the ground for such a study. An aspect of variation that needs further investigation is time. Although we have only discussed geographical variation in Section 3.1, the same principles apply to time and all the concepts in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 1</ref> apply: TL (a point in time), TS (the varying period over which events are considered -a temporal extent) and TR (the resolution at which measurements are made -whether these are daily, hourly or decennial recordings). In this paper we treat time differently and do not include it as a varying aspect in our examples. Instead, we consider time as an inherent part of our statistical computations (Section 3.4 and 4.1.3). In order to demonstrate our approach over time at its full extent, mechanisms that can vary time and computations to accommodate this variation need to be incorporated. One option here is to extend the interactive temporal summaries suggested by Turkay et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>. One difference is the cyclic nature of time -in order to represent this, different granularities of time can be treated as the variation axis and a specific cycle can be selected as the baseline, a similar approach is taken by Kehrer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION AND FURTHER WORK</head><p>One question regarding the statistical computations relates to the number of points selected by a brush, i.e., the sample size. Summary statistics such as those computed here are known to be unreliable in the case of low sample sizes. In the demonstration cases used in this paper, the OAs used as data points are already aggregated representations (of an average of just over 300 households). Thus, the computed statistics are less affected by the low size of data points. However, for most datasets, where there is no such aggregation, the consideration of the sample size is important. This number can be used as one measure of uncertainty of an observation. This information can be highlighted as an additional measure as in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> or can be represented as a visual encoding over the trail drawn on the maps.</p><p>In order to support the user in generating well-defined selection patterns for the dynamic signatures, we introduce the concept of key-framed brushing in section 3.6.3. There are, however, several ways to develop this mechanism further. Currently, when in-between frames are generated, we place them on equal steps over the visualizations' projected coordinate system, alternatively, one can constrain such auto-generated selections with actual geographical distances, e.g., moving the selection by 1 km. at each step. Moreover, the extent and the shape of the selection can be varied in relation to well-defined criteria. A number of alternatives are: constraining the number of samples selected by a selection, keeping a constant mutual overlap within two consecutive selections, or a selection that automatically snaps to a geographically defined unit such as administrative borders. Such extensions could result in more systematic but more constrained ways of exploring the data interactively.</p><p>Selection is binary in the examples presented here and the selected extents are of arbitrary quadrilateral shape. In this paper, we use a binary selection mechanism in our calculations and this might lead to discontinuities where the selection moves from scarcely to densely populated parts of the data. This might be useful for particular tasks, for instance, to determine abrupt changes in the population. However, for tasks where discontinuities are not required, employing a selection mechanism with a variable kernel size with weighted selections <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref> could be preferable. Scalability : The use of small multiples that involve the interactive computation of statistics opens up questions on two aspects of scalability: available screen-space and computational resources. When the number of variables is high, the small multiples can become small and hard to read -a fact that has been raised in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref>. In such cases, a strategy to take is to use a filtering approach based on how much a variable changes, i.e., hiding those variables that have not changed significantly unless they are not of particular interest to the analyst. Alternatively, representative factors can be generated to reduce the number of variables and the response of these factors can be visualized instead -a method that has been effective in analyzing very high-dimensional data <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref>. The second scalability issue relates to maintaining the interactivity while several statistics are computed. In our prototype, we use efficient vectorial data structures to speedup the computations and no delays are observed in the computations. However, for very large datasets where the computations are becoming an issue, progressive computation systems and sampling strategies can be employed <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Our stated aim is to develop techniques to help understand how multiple attributes vary over space as a means of gaining knowledge of the phenomena represented by geographic data. Attribute signatures meet that need relatively effectively, enabling us to see how characteristics of geography vary across scale, space and time. The scenarios presented in Section 4 demonstrate that using attribute signatures in an interactive context can reveal how the "multivariate analysis of population characteristics" varies with respect to the location and scale, and how we can assess changes in these characteristics over time. This analysis makes it evident that when all variations of location, scale, and time are considered concurrently the investigation becomes unwieldy. One option is to select a location, a scale and a time to undertake analysis -perhaps arbitrarily. This is often deemed an easy and satisfactory option, perhaps because of a lack of alternatives, but the result will be an incomplete picture. Another is to use interactive enquiry-based mechanisms for analysis to sift, select and understand the characteristics of the geographical data and their variability. This more progressive approach can take advantage of the multi-variate, multi-scale, multi-location view afforded by attribute signatures.</p><p>The framework, techniques and tool that we present here facilitate this activity through a structured set of analytical perspectives and associated visualizations and computations. Through a structured sequence of examples we demonstrate several forms of uncertainty related to an observation when the different locations, scales and temporal aspects are considered. Being able to access these different representations of the data and perform comparative visual analysis on them simultaneously is important in dealing with the characteristics of geographic data that make them interesting. It enables us find and present the stability of the numbers that we compute to describe geography and use broad visual channels to show how they vary using visualization methods that are applicable to a broad range of multivariate geographic data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>illustrates how these aspects are represented in an instance of an attribute signature. The axis of variation (x-axis) represents either SL, SE or SR. The variation in the attribute along the axis of variation is depicted using one or more summary statistics compared to an appropriate baseline (Section 3.4). The resulting comparative values are then visualized along the axis of comparison (y-axis).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>An attribute signature represents changes in a single (or more) attribute along the axis of variation. The x-axis is the axis of variation, corresponding to the geographical aspect (location, extent or resolution) interactively defined by the user. The y-axis represents change in the computed statistics in response to this, comparing dynamically computed values to an appropriate baseline.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>A transect through the centers of London (polycentric city, left, top) and Leicester (monocentric city, left bottom) using keyframed brushing. Attribute signatures for London (centre) and Leicester (right) are ordered by similarity to that at the top-left of each series of small multiples. The numbered attributes are discussed in the text.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .Fig. 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Median (orange) and inter-quartile range (green) values for a linear transect going through London (seeFigure 4). Most attributes that have larger values in the center have low variation (marked 1,2,3). Comparing 2001 and 2011 census as we move from West to East London. East London shows changes in more attributes than West London indicating more dynamic demographics over the last decade.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Comparing six cities in the UK ordered according to population from left-to-right: London, Manchester, Birmingham, Leeds, Liverpool, Southampton. Attribute signatures are grouped by attribute type. Notice that the coloring is mapped to the number of samples selected, i.e., higher number of samples are darker blue.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>The scale extent is varied continuously from OAs around Charing Cross Station in London and extending to cover the whole UK. Most attributes show variations at local scales, e.g. the black African population (dashed circle). Moving from central London (left) to outer London (right), we observe changes in transport, and housing (black circles).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>The levels of aggregation are varied for a constant extent and location in London with a fixed baseline (some multiples omitted). Bars in the multiples are ordered from fine grained resolution to coarse. While the % in agriculture &amp; fishing attribute (right bottom) is invariant across all aggregation levels, the variation of the % manufacturing attribute (left top) is highly dependent upon the level of aggregation used.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Jason Dykes are with the Dep. of Computer Science at City University London, UK. E-mail:</figDesc><table /><note>{Cagatay.Turkay.1, Aidan.Slingsby.1, J.D.Wood, J.Dykes} @city.ac.uk.• Helwig Hauser is with the Department of Informatics at University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway. Email: Helwig.Hauser@uib.no.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 1 ,</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>i.e., SLc vs. SLd. For example, spatial location can be varied continuously (SLc) along a linear feature of interest (e.g. a motorway, river or coastline) or can be a set of discrete locations (e.g. cities or reg- ularly sampled points) that are geographically distant from each other (SLd). Equally, spatial resolution can be varied continuously or in discrete steps through a spatial hierarchy of administrative geography (such as the various levels of the NUTS).</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank Dan Vickers for providing the 2001 census variables and Sarah Goodwin for providing those for the 2011 census.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Space, time and visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Demsar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dransch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dykes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Fabrikant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M.-J</forename><surname>Kraak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tominski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Geographical Information Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1577" to="1600" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geovisualization of dynamics, movement and change: Key issues and developing approaches in visualization research</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dykes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Fabrikant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wachowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3-4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is special about spatial data? Alternative perspectives on spatial data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Anselin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">National Center for Geographic Information and Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of the MAUP on image classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Arbia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Benedetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Espa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geographical Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brushing scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cleveland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color use guidelines for mapping and visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization in modern cartography</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="148" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color representation of aspect and slope simultaneously</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Marlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ASPRS Autocarto Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="328" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multifocused geospatial analysis using probes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Butkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wartell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1165" to="1172" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The problems of computer-assisted animation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 5th Conf. on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques, SIG-GRAPH &apos;78</title>
		<meeting>of the 5th Conf. on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques, SIG-GRAPH &apos;78<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1978" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="353" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Legible cities: Focus-dependent multi-resolution visualization of urban relationships</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wessel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kosara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sauda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1169" to="1175" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Customizing computational methods for visual analytics with big data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Choo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE CG&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of railway stations on residential and commercial property value: A meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Debrezion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rietveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Real Estate Finance and Economics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive feature specification for focus+ context visualization of complex simulation data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Doleisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Symp. Data visualisation 2003</title>
		<meeting>Symp. Data visualisation 2003</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="248" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A new social atlas of Britain</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dorling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<publisher>Chichester England John Wiley and Sons</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The 32 Stops: The Central Line. Penguin UK</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dorling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to the special issue: The transect</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Duany</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Urban Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geographically weighted visualization: Interactive graphics for scale-varying exploratory analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dykes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Brunsdon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1168" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seeking structure in records of spatiotemporal behaviour: visualization issues, efforts and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dykes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mountain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computational Statistics &amp; Data Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="603" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual exploration of big spatio-temporal urban data: A study of new york city taxi trips. Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Poco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Vo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Freire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2149" to="2158" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual comparison for information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Albers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Jusufi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lineup: Visual analysis of multi-attribute rankings</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gratzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gehlenborg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Streit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2277" to="2286" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visual Benchmarks: Representing Geographic Change with Map Animation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harrower</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Pennsylvania State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic graphics for exploring spatial data with application to locating global and local anomalies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haslett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Unwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Statistician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring geo-temporal differences using gtdiff</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hoeber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Harding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Enguehard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Devillers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pacific Visualization Symposium (PacificVis)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="146" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied multivariate statistical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wichern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>Prentice Hall Upper</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Saddle River, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A model for structure-based comparison of many categories in small-multiple displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kehrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Piringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Groller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2287" to="2296" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the issues of scale, resolution and fractal analysis in the mapping sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">-N</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Quattrochi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Professional Geographer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping the results of geographically weighted regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Cartographic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://j.mp/onsDX" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Office for National Statistics. Census Dataset Finder -Data Explorer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measures of effect size for comparative studies: Applications, interpretations, and limitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Olejnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Algina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contemporary Educational Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The modifiable unit areal problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Openshaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
			<publisher>Geobooks</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Norwich</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Similarity search in trajectory databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Pelekis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kopanakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marketos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ntoutsi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Theodoridis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">14th Symp. Temporal Representation and Reasoning</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="140" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effectiveness of animation in trend visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Stasko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1325" to="1332" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of urban movements: polycentric activity and entangled hierarchical flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Batty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barthélemy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15923</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visual cluster analysis of trajectory data with interactive kohonen maps. Information Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schreck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bernard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Von</forename><surname>Landesberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kohlhammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="29" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring uncertainty in geodemographics with interactive graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Slingsby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dykes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2545" to="2554" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thematic cartography and visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Slocum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Prentice hall Upper</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Saddle River, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Changes to Output Areas and Super Output Areas in England and Wales</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tait</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractals and scale dependencies in topography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Scale in Geographical Information Systems</title>
		<editor>N. Tate and P. Atkinson</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Chichester</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="51" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive data visualization using mondrian</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Theus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Statistical Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical data exploration and geographical information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Theus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Exploring geovisualization</title>
		<editor>J. Dykes, A. M. MacEachren, and M.-J. Kraak</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A computer movie simulating urban growth in the detroit region</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tobler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Economic Geography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sparklines: Intense, simple, word-sized graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tufte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Beautiful Evidence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brushing dimensions -a dual visual analysis model for high-dimensional data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Filzmoser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2591" to="2599" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing cancer subtypes using dual analysis in caleydo stratomex</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Streit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE CG&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representative factor generation for the interactive visual analysis of high-dimensional data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lundervold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lundervold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2621" to="2630" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visual analysis of temporal cluster structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Parulek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Reuter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="711" to="720" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Small multiples, large singles: A new approach for visual data exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Den Elzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="200" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introducing the national classification of census output areas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vickers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rees</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Population Trends</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="380" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Building highly-coordinated visualizations in improvise</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Weaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Symp. Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="166" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The history of the cluster heat map</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wilkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Friendly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Statistician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Complex spatial systems: the modelling foundations of urban and regional analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Pearson Education</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multim im parvo -many things in a small place</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Exploring Geovisualization</title>
		<editor>J. Dykes, A. MacEachren, and M.-J. Kraak</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="324" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geomorphometry in LandSerf</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Geomorphometry: Concepts, Software and Applications</title>
		<editor>T. Hengl and H. Reuter</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="349" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
