<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Temporal Views of Flattened Mitral Valve Geometries</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pepe</forename><surname>Eulzer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sandy</forename><surname>Engelhardt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nils</forename><surname>Lichtenberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Raffaele</forename><surname>De Simone</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kai</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Temporal Views of Flattened Mitral Valve Geometries</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2019.2934337</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Mitral valve</term>
					<term>quantification</term>
					<term>medical visualization</term>
					<term>parameterization</term>
					<term>spatio-temporal visualization</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The mitral valve, one of the four valves in the human heart, controls the bloodflow between the left atrium and ventricle and may suffer from various pathologies. Malfunctioning valves can be treated by reconstructive surgeries, which have to be carefully planned and evaluated. While current research focuses on the modeling and segmentation of the valve, we base our work on existing segmentations of patient-specific mitral valves, that are also time-resolved (3D+t) over the cardiac cycle. The interpretation of the data can be ambiguous, due to the complex surface of the valve and multiple time steps. We therefore propose a software prototype to analyze such 3D+t data, by extracting pathophysiological parameters and presenting them via dimensionally reduced visualizations. For this, we rely on an existing algorithm to unroll the convoluted valve surface towards a flattened 2D representation. In this paper, we show that the 3D+t data can be transferred to 3D or 2D representations in a way that allows the domain expert to faithfully grasp important aspects of the cardiac cycle. In this course, we not only consider common pathophysiological parameters, but also introduce new observations that are derived from landmarks within the segmentation model. Our analysis techniques were developed in collaboration with domain experts and a survey showed that the insights have the potential to support mitral valve diagnosis and the comparison of the pre-and post-operative condition of a patient.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The human heart contains four valves, which are crucial to direct the blood flow. The mitral valve (MV) separates the left atrium and ventricle (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref>). The open MV lets oxygenated blood enter the left ventricle in a state of the cardiac cycle called diastole. The blood is then pushed into the body in a state called systole, while the closed MV prevents a backflow into the left atrium. The MV consists of two leaflets, usually referred to as anterior and posterior leaflet. They are connected to the inner walls of the heart by a ring-like structure called mitral annulus. The leaflet tips are connected to papillary muscles in the ventricle by chordae tendineae. During systole, pressure is exerted towards the ventricular side of the leaflets, while the attached chordae prevent the leaflets from flipping into the atrium, holding them in a colliding position, thus closing the valve.</p><p>If the closure function of the MV is impaired, blood is leaking back into the left atrium and ultimately into the pulmonary circulation during systole. This condition is referred to as mitral regurgitation. It is the second-most-often surgically treated heart valve defect <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Malfunctioning valves can be replaced by a full prosthesis, however, MV repair is the preferred option, if possible <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Restoring MV function through reconstructive surgery is a highly complex procedure, which includes different surgical approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Therefore, a thorough assessment of each patient's case is necessary. In standard clinical routine, pre-operative visual analysis of MV behaviour is mainly restricted to ultrasound imaging. Today, a common modality is 3D transesophageal echocardiography (3D TEE), which provides real-time volumetric data of the heart apparatus <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>. However, the time-dependent convoluted anatomy of the MV is difficult to be fully understood, even on volume renderings of TEE data. Important clinical pathology indicators can usually not be assessed at a glance, as physicians need to rely on animation-based methods to interpret valve movements over the cardiac cycle, which can be time-intensive and exhausting. Therefore, advanced visualization techniques have the potential to improve clinical MV analysis w.r.t. pathology assessment, treatment planning and post-surgery evaluation.</p><p>We developed a visualization framework, which provides novel and enhanced views facilitating MV analysis. We worked in close cooperation with domain experts, i.e., cardiac surgeons and experts in computer-assisted surgery. Our tool builds upon patient-specific segmentations of the MV <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Valve attributes indicative of pathologies are extracted based on geometrical properties of these models. They are then integrated into the visualizations, providing physicians with the possibility to explore these values directly on the valve surface. Several views allow an efficient evaluation of feature correlations and representation of time-dependent data. We improve upon a method to transfer a 3D MV mesh into a 2D parameter domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>, providing a flattened depiction of the convoluted valve surface. Then, the temporally resolved 3D surfaces are integrated into one depiction (3D+t), resulting in a view of the valve geometry, which is not constrained through the drawbacks of animation. We further show, how the flattened valve can be analogously transferred to a novel 2D+t view, providing a guidance space for time-dependent exploration of surface parameters, as well a method to find points of interest over the cardiac cycle and assess valve deformations that have previously been impossible to visually analyze. Additionally, we implemented supplementary views, which abstract the valve movement over the cardiac cycle. We separate the movement property into changes in direction and position and allow both properties to be independently examined. In summary, our main contributions can be described as:</p><p>A design study of combined 2D and 3D visualizations, which incorporate the temporal dimension of patient-specific MV data directly, without the need for time step iteration or animation.</p><p>Methods to visually assess quantifiable feature variations based on temporal deformation of MV geometry.</p><p>Novel concepts to abstract and visualize the overall movement of the MV inside the heart.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>Related work encompasses prior approaches to visualize MV models and methods focused on creating 2D abstractions from 3D data in medical context, which we will leverage to create a framework for MV analysis that incorporates the temporal dimension.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Visualization of Mitral Valve Models</head><p>Visualization of 3D MV models has been studied mostly in terms of modeling and simulation. It is common to apply color maps to express the magnitude of error introduced by segmentation or simulation algorithms in comparison to a manual segmentation done by an expert. This has for example been demonstrated to indicate differences in simulated and observed valve closure <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref>. Areas with high discrepancy can thus be quickly assessed, which might give hints regarding possible improvements of the simulation algorithm. Similarly, Burlina et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> used computed closed configurations of MVs, which they overlaid and registered with a mesh segmented from 3D TEE.</p><p>Methods based on color coding have also been proposed to display clinically relevant indicators. Rim et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> visualized the distribution of contact pressure between the anterior and posterior MV leaflets, as well as the overall stress distribution on the valve. While they initially introduced these color maps to show an advantage of simulation methods, which incorporate leaflet-to-cordae contact interaction, they later used these mappings to display stress distributions before and following virtual posterior leaflet resection <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>. Pouch et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> demonstrated a similar approach. They estimated a pressure field on the leaflet surface using finite element analysis and displayed a contour map, showing the regional characteristics of this parameter. They also visualized radial thickness of leaflets using a similar mapping.</p><p>Color coding clinically relevant quantitative values can enhance evaluation of MV pathology. However, a precise analysis of parameter distributions can be restricted by the complex leaflet morphology. Models of MVs are generally created in the 3D domain, which poses two main problems: First, the resulting leaflet geometry requires a range of different viewing angles to be correctly assessed. While this can be solved through an interactive display of the models, geometrical self-occlusions are almost always inevitable, regardless of the viewing angle. Therefore, the entirety of the valve surface is never visible at once and not all areas of quantitative value maps can be compared against one another. Second, a 3D geometrical object does not incorporate temporal information; however, all parts of the MV anatomy are constantly moving. Thus, the domains of clinical MV analysis, as well as simulation and modeling, could benefit from MV visualizations, featuring comprehensible overviews of the whole valve surface and the inclusion of time-based information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Flattening Geometry in Medical Context</head><p>A common approach to simplify convoluted geometry extracted from medical datasets is to facilitate parameterization techniques to flatten a usually 3D object into a 2D plane. Formally, parameterization describes the process of finding a bijective mapping between two surfaces, which can be embedded in distinct dimensions. Usually, the expression refers to mappings between 3D and 2D Euclidean spaces. In this scenario, the latter contains a subset labeled parameter domain. Visualization of such a planar parameter domain provides a view on the whole surface geometry at once, making all areas visible and comparable. Quantitative assessment of object characteristics can then be supported through an application of feature-specific color maps. If the flattening algorithm provides consistent views, the results can also be compared across different data sets, for instance, to examine properties before and after surgical intervention. A general overview of mesh parameterization techniques can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</p><p>A broadly explored domain of flattening-based medical visualization is colon analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. Related fields include brain surface analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39]</ref> and flattening or straightening regions of interest in the circulatory system <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref>. All of these techniques commonly attempt to reduce the dimensionality of complex 3D structures and provide a map, which can help to identify areas requiring further investigation and visually assess quantifiable indicators of pathologies. Furthermore, flattened depictions of medical datasets can allow systematic localization <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, statistical shape analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> and even help with the registration of different scans or image modalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref>. A recent state of the art report <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> reviews a large variety of medical visualization techniques focused on planar representations.</p><p>A flattening technique has been demonstrated for aortic valve prosthesis by Born et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Here, 2D representations of surgically implanted stents were created to visualize several parameters of interest, namely radial forces, stent compression, and calcium thickness, through the application of color maps. The maps are contained within a rectangular parameter domain and are designed to facilitate analysis of complication co-occurrences post surgery. Recently, a method for flattening the MV was introduced <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and additional usability features have been suggested <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>. In contrast to the approach of Born et al., a more general usage scenario is targeted, providing physicians with possibilities to plan for or evaluate MV surgeries. There are a multitude of possibilities for treatment of malfunctioning MVs <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and therapeutic decisions are dependent on a variety of factors, predominantly parameters derived from the diseased valve. Therefore, preservation of valve anatomy is focused, i.e., retaining the patient-specific shape and size, which results in a parameter space, where the boundary develops freely. In the following sections, we will improve upon this flattening algorithm and introduce more sophisticated methods to deal with the temporal dimension of MV data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Visualization of Spatio-Temporal Data</head><p>The traditional approach of using animation to facilitate exploration of spatio-temporal medical data has often been observed to be timeconsuming and tedious. This holds especially true for visualizations of the cardiovascular system, where the diagnostic evaluation of multifield data poses a challenge due to the complexity of dynamically changing parameters, which are typically dependent on the cardiac cycle. To address these problems, van Pelt et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> developed flower glyphs, which are designed to display the temporal evolution of different blood flow simulations. The glyph consists of circles that are arranged clockwise and connected with stripes that encode the time variation. Furthermore, the flower glyphs are evenly distributed over the surface. The biggest disadvantages are the limited number of time steps shown and the missing encoding of quantitative values.</p><p>Köhler et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> presented a 2D plot to explore a scalar field on aortic flow data. Angular and radial components were used to encode the time steps as well as the aortic segments. Later, Meuschke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> extended this idea to improve the spatial correspondence of the anatomical sections of the aorta. For direct encoding of scalar fields on the surface, Meuschke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> proposed a plot that divided the surface into several regions. Afterwards, a plot similar to the bull's eye plot was created, color coding every region and time step, such that interesting areas can be identified. Oeltze et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> provided a ring glyph that encodes scalar fields of cardiac perfusion data as well as their anatomical context. Tominski et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> introduced the pencil glyph. By using different sides of the pencil, data can be displayed on the faces. Meuschke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> altered these glyphs and proposed 3D violin plots, where the radius represents the change over time. They also used bar charts <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, where distinct information can be encoded through height and color. Then, temporal information can be visualized by observing change of the bars over time.</p><p>In general, proposed ideas map the 4D data into lower-dimensional domains, where it can be visualized using abstractions, e.g., plots, glyphs, parameter domains and color codes <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Also, linked depictions of distinct data representations can help to emphasize different parameters and their coherences. This results in visualizations that allow faster and more reliable assessments, as well as the simultaneous investigation and comparison of multiple data sets. To the best of our knowledge, we implemented the first framework for integration and visualization of spatio-temporal heart valve data sets, which addresses the drawbacks of animation-based analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">REQUIREMENT ANALYSIS</head><p>In clinical routine, the evaluation of MVs is mainly based on ultrasound methods like TEE, as these provide real-time feedback of the constantly moving valve anatomy. In case of detected MV pathologies, treatment strategy is usually decided using a visual and semi-quantitative assessment of the 2D and 3D TEE data. While most workstations allow the data to be depicted with a volume rendering approach, the convoluted and time-dependent shapes of the MV leaflets remain difficult to assess visually. Past research has focused on segmentation and triangulation of 3D MV models from 3D TEE volumes, including the enhancement of laborious manual segmentation through the implementation of refined automatic and semi-automatic methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>. The resulting models can further be used as a baseline for automatic quantifications and sophisticated visualizations, which could significantly enhance multimodal valve analysis. Recently, an advantage of providing clinicians with a flattened depiction of such models and color coding pathology indicators directly onto the surface was demonstrated, which manifested in an increased pathology detection rate compared to pure 3D models <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>.</p><p>During evaluation of this flattening algorithm and ensuing discussions with domain experts, we distilled main properties of the MV, which in clinical routine cannot be assessed or can only be insufficiently determined, but have the potential to be relevant during MV analysis. Our domain expert group can be divided into one expert in computer-assisted surgery, one anesthetist and three cardiac surgeons. Simple 2D distance measurements of the MV that are commonly assessed using slices of TEE data include the coaptation height, which is the height of colliding leaflet tissue in a closed valve and the tenting height, describing the distance from the leaflet coaptation (where the valve closes) to its annulus. 2D measurements are ambiguous because they depend on appropriate slice selection, which may result in underor overestimation of the quantifications <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Of interest are more complex measurements, such as the coaptation zone area, which can only be derived from a model representation and are therefore not easily available in clinical routine. Also, simple properties like the diameter of the valve are computed. Clinicians often evaluate the severity of prolapses, i.e., parts of the leaflets which are flipped back into the left atrium, and they also take the overall shape of the valve into account. Both can be challenging to abstract from ultrasound imaging.</p><p>We intend to address intricacies in MV quantification by deriving and visualizing geometric properties from patient-specific 3D+t models. We extend coaptation height to coaptation area, displaying a property of the whole valve as opposed to features of individual slices. Similarly, we believe the area of prolapsed tissue can be computed from the geometric model. While some of these values have been calculated before <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref> and are also accessible in certain commercial products that allow for valve modelling, we aim to approach a more comprehensive visualization of these parameters, by the inclusion of time-dependent variables. The time step at peak systole is certainly the most important in valve analysis, as this is where the highest pressure is exerted onto the valve. However, exploring a single time step of the cardiac cycle constitutes an insufficient solution, as MV motion and deformation over time may be indicative of pathologies. Current solutions in this domain are usually based on animation, which requires a high degree of user interaction, until the most relevant valve characteristics are detected, as different phases of the cardiac cycle can only be indirectly compared against one another. Also, insufficient temporal resolution in the data sets appears as a "jumping" of the leaflet surfaces when viewed in 3D. Consequently, a continuous movement is often not provided when viewed in animation mode. This can only be partly improved by juxtapositions of time steps, as the number of displayable views is limited and it can be mentally exhausting to connect multiple images. Our goal is, therefore, to abstract valve movement and orientation, while simultaneously displaying leaflet behavior over time and visually emphasizing essential parameters. In general, the framework should direct physicians towards the most interesting points in the cardiac cycle. Our main requirements can be outlined as follows:</p><p>R1 Quantitative assessment of important MV properties is possible at a glance. R2 Time-dependent feature variations can be determined without animation or iteration of time steps. R3 The movement of the valve and changes in its orientation during the cardiac cycle can be understood.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">VISUALIZING MITRAL VALVE PROPERTIES</head><p>We build our methods upon patient-specific MV surface models segmented from 3D TEE <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Most of these models are also resolved over time, which results in several distinct 3D models of a MV, representing different time steps in the cardiac cycle. To visualize these models and their correspondences over time, we implemented a framework consisting of six linked views (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>). The first view shows a single 3D model of the MV. The second view shows the equivalent parameter space, i.e., the flattened 2D model. Both of these views feature an overlay of the same color map, which the user can specify. Furthermore, the displayed point in time of the cardiac cycle can be set with a slider, if multiple time steps of the current valve data exist. The third and fourth view provide the user access to the temporal dimension of the valve geometry. The third view visualizes all time steps of the 3D models, while the fourth view equivalently shows changes over time w.r.t. the 2D geometry. The two remaining views further abstract time-dependent data and are sized smaller than the other views. The fifth view abstracts variances in orientation and the sixth view positional changes of the valve over time. In the following, we describe the individual views in more detail and outline their interactive connection. We start with a description of our data sets and provide an overview of the valve flattening algorithm, as some of the other visualizations are dependent on this representation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Input</head><p>Our MV surface models are generated from 3D TEE with the method from Engelhardt et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. The extraction algorithm is semi-automatic and meshes can be generated for an arbitrary number of time steps. The resulting models contain separate geometry for the two leaflets, which extensively simplifies the estimation of the valve coaptation zone, an important parameter in the quantitative evaluation of the MV. Also, certain landmarks are semantically represented: points that lie on the mitral annulus, which are at the top of each model and the commissure points between the two leaflets. This can be utilized during the flattening process. Due to restrictions in TEE resolution, the models do not contain information about the chordae tendineae or papillary muscles. The valve models are output with a resolution of around 5000 vertices. We base our work on scans collected from 33 patients, who were clinically diagnosed to have a regurgitation due to MV prolapse (17 patients), a functional mitral regurgitation (5 patients) or a healthy MV <ref type="bibr">(11 patients)</ref>. From these scans, surface models of the MV were created by physicians using the method from Engelhardt et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. The temporal dimension was assessed for 30 data sets, which means several models were created per scan, relating to different discrete points in the cardiac cycle. The temporal resolution ranges from 10 to 39 extracted time steps per scan. This way, we can compare different discretization degrees of the cardiac cycle. In total, this results in 596 individual triangulated 3D MV models, against which robustness of our algorithms and visualizations has been tested.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Mitral Valve Flattening</head><p>We use the flattening process described by Eulzer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, as it develops a free boundary while targeting area preservation and thus emphasizes anatomical valve features. The procedure is now quickly reviewed, as it is the basis for many following operations. We also highlight improvements to the original proposal. To achieve consistent views, the 3D model is always cut alone the lateral commissure (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig  1)</ref>. The cylindrical valve is then virtually unrolled into a flattened representation, displaying the anterior leaflet on the left and the posterior leaflet on the right with the annulus on top and coaptation zone at the bottom.</p><p>The annulus is independently parameterized first, as its length and shape can be an important indicator in clinical MV analysis. Only after that will the rest of the surface be mapped to the 2D domain, while the annulus remains fixed to its initial configuration. This allows a high amount of control over the general shape of the 2D view, which is determined by the annulus layout, resulting in intuitively comparable outcomes across time steps and different data sets. Following standard notation, the 2D parameter space axes are denoted with u and v. We map the annulus' height to the v-coordinate of the parameter domain and its length in u-direction, while preserving the overall arc length. As the annulus is a ring-like structure, it naturally lies within a plane. We approximate this plane and can thus measure the height of the annulus, regardless of its orientation in 3D space. An intuitive approach to compute the annulus plane would be to use the least-squares method. However, this approach often leads to unexpected and undesirable results, i.e., under-or overestimation of the annulus' height (cf. Sec. 5). We achieved better results with a landmark-based plane, defined through three points: the two commissure points on the annulus, which form a natural axis through the MV and the barycenter of the posterior annulus, which usually approximates a planar layout perpendicular to the direction of the valve opening. The two commissure points are always manually specified during segmentation, as they mark the point where the leaflets connect. Therefore, their position is assumed to be comparatively accurate. This also has the effect that the parameterized annuli all pass through v = 0 at their commissures, making multiple profiles directly comparable. The third location is averaged across several points and thus mitigates noise. This construction method also puts additional emphasis on the height of the valve's saddle horn w.r.t. the rest of the annulus, as it is not used in the construction of the plane. This height can be an important indicator of pathology, as functional mitral regurgitation can be associated with a more planar shape of the annulus and therefore a lower relative position of the saddle horn <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>.</p><p>After the annulus has been parameterized, the leaflet geometry is placed below. We first find a valid configuration of the parameter space, i.e., an initial layout without triangle-flips or self-intersections. This is done by approximating iso-u curves on the 3D surface, which run from annulus to coaptation zone. Corresponding vertices are mapped to a shared u-coordinate, while their geodesic distance is preserved in v-direction.</p><p>We then apply a third step, where we optimize the position of leaflet vertices, while keeping the annulus fixed to its original shape. We <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>: Color maps quantifying local surface properties indicative of pathologies. Valves are shown in 3D and 2D. a) Normal valve with color map corresponding to leaflet height relative to annulus plane. Note that the area around the saddle horn is supposed to be above the plane, the remaining leaflet area should be below. b) Pathological valve with leaflet prolapse. The area of the prolapse, as well as its location can be determined based on the color map. c) Normal valve with color map corresponding to coaptation, i.e., distance between leaflets. d) Pathological valve with coaptation map. The flattened overview can be used to identify areas where the coaptation zone is not closed and leakage is probable. Due to self-occluding geometry, this is not obvious from the 3D model alone. target a representation where physicians are able to perform area and length assessments based on the flat view. Perfect isometry, i.e., the preservation of all proportions intrinsic to the surface, is generally impossible <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. We therefore target to approach isometry by minimizing distortions of the model's edge lengths, which also leads to a minimization of area deformation. The valve mesh is modelled as a network of springs, where each 2D edge targets to reach a rest-length as observed in its 3D counterpart. Similar methods have been proposed to simulate MV closure <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>. If the 3D mesh consists of vertices p i , corresponding to uv-coordinates q i and the set N i contains the indices of all neighbors of p i , a per-vertex edge length energy can be described as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">E i = 1 |N i | ∑ j∈N i ||q i − q j || ||p i − p j || + ||p i − p j || ||q i − q j || .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>We minimize this energy by iteratively displacing points q i to better locations. We found a number of five global iterations to be sufficient for further processing, as E i converged after that point and usually no further improvement of distortion minimization ensued. Displacement is based on the direction of a summed spring force F , calculated using the model's edge lengths:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">F i = ∑ j∈N i k i ||p j − p i || − ||q j − q i || q j − q i ||q j − q i || .<label>(2)</label></formula><p>In contrast to the original proposal of this method <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, where the stiffness parameter k i was set to a global constant, we now use k i to shift the distortions in parameter space to less important regions. In discussions with our medical expert group we found the 2D view to have promising potential for assessment of prolapsed leaflet area. Degenerative leaflet prolapse is the most common etiology for surgical intervention, accounting for about 60% of MV operations <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Thorough analysis of prolapses is therefore of utmost importance. Prolapses are parts of the leaflets which are flipped into the left atrium during systole. We therefore define a prolapsed vertex to be above the previously specified annulus plane. To accurately portray the area of prolapses, the relaxation step of the parameterization should focus on such regions. This is why we interpolate the stiffness parameter k i in Eq. (2) according to a gradient of vertex distance to the annulus plane. The annulus plane normal is constructed to point upwards, to where the left atrium would be. </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">k i = 1 2 1 +d i 5 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>resulting in an value of k i = 0.5 for vertices on or below the annulus plane, k i = 1 for vertices with a high probability for being prolapsed with d i ≥ 5 and linear interpolation in-between. This allows prolapsed regions in the parameter space to relax first, transferring inevitable distortion towards regions of less interest in clinical context. Representations of the 3D and flattened 2D valve geometry corresponding to single time steps can now be visualized. To quickly determine the severity of prolapsed regions, a color map can be used, which encodes d i (cf. left side of <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>). The coaptation zone describes where the leaflets collide during systole. If the coaptation is not fully closed, the valve is leaking. There are indications that the size of the coaptation area is related to the risk of mitral regurgitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. To make this property visually accessible, the distance towards the opposing leaflet is computed for every vertex and displayed using a second color map (cf. right side of <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref>). When viewing these mappings, the 2D MV representation helps to simplify the convoluted valve geometry and makes it possible to see the whole valve at once, allowing a direct comparison of the distribution of surface properties. We also explicitly compute some of the most important features numerically, including values for coaptation and prolapsed area, as well as valve diameter and circumference. If desired, users can view the results in tabular format, e.g., to gain reference values for fast assessment and comparison.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Visualizing the Temporal Dimension</head><p>The MV properties do not only vary across the surface domain, but are also constantly changing over time, which is a major challenge in creating a thorough visual representation. A discretization of the temporal domain results in several captures of valve surface geometry during the cardiac cycle. These time steps of 3D and 2D representations can be iterated or juxtaposed, with neither approach being a perfect solution. Especially high temporal resolutions, with 20 or more time steps, are cumbersome to analyze when only one point in time can be shown at once. Therefore, our further concepts intent to visualize and abstract from a representation, which combines all discrete points in time in one depiction. Displaying 3D geometries of all time steps at once at first results in a densely tangled object, which does not naturally convey temporal valve behavior. We simplify this object through transparency mapping, emphasizing essential features of the valve. We then provide easier visual access to the temporal dimension and quick selection possibilities through a 3D extension of the established 2D parameter domain. Furthermore, we abstract movement of the valve in two quickly readable representations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.1">Relating Time-Dependent Samples of 3D Mitral Valves</head><p>In the course of a cardiac cycle, the shape of the MV leaflets is dynamically changing. During systole, the closed valve exhibits a shape between a funnel and disc, while in diastole it features a more cylindrical layout. The leaflet motion is an essential general valve property, where physicians are interested in several aspects: the leaflets should not contain prolapsed parts and the coaptation zone should be sufficient to close the valve during peak systole, when the highest pressure is exerted on the valve. Being held by the chordae, the line of coaptation should not extend above the annulus plane. Inhomogeneous deformations of leaflets can be indicators of pathology and generally also impair a uniform appearance of the coaptation <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. Apart from the leaflets, variations in other parts of MV anatomy can be similarly helpful during analysis, even if their movement is less pronounced. Alterations of mitral annulus geometry, e.g., due to infarction, can lead to moderate to severe mitral regurgitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Additionally, the overall movement of the mitral annulus plays an important role in pathology assessment, as the asynchronous movement of the annulus and the valve as a whole may participate in the pathogenesis of mitral regurgitation <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>.</p><p>To make these time-dependent variables visually accessible, we provide a view on the combined 3D geometries of an arbitrary number of time steps. We design this visualization to emphasize important valve features and guide the user's attention to the most interesting time steps. A transparency mapping is applied to make all time steps visible. As the meshes have a high number of intersections, we utilize depth peeling to provide an accurate representation of transparency. Features are displayed with different degrees of dominance, depending on their importance and readability.</p><p>First, the overall variation of the annulus is shown, by rendering all annulus curves simultaneously. The relative positioning of the MV geometries from one data set is analog to their spatial relations within the cardiac cycle, as the relation between the TEE probe and the heart stays fixed. To make time steps belonging to diastole visually discernible from systolic time steps, a gray (open valves) to green (closed valves) color spectrum depending on the coaptation area percentage is employed. This also allows comparison of different valves, as a valve with a generally smaller coaptation area will feature less saturated systolic annuli as a valve with high coaptation area. In a normal valve, the annuli should be distributed homogeneously (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4)</ref>.</p><p>Second, regions of prolapse are highlighted. Analogously to the view of individual time steps, we apply a per-vertex color map corresponding to the signed distance d i towards the annulus plane. We focus on areas above the annulus plane, as these are suggestive of leaflet prolapse. Regions with d i ≥ 1mm (accounting for approximate leaflet thickness) are assigned yellow to red color values and also an increase in opaqueness. The mapping not only indicates the existence of a prolapse, but can also help to localize it (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>). This can be an important asset, as often only parts of the leaflets are affected by prolapses and restorative surgery needs to be planned accordingly. A normal valve typically only shows regions with positive d i at points where the annulus is above the annulus plane, which usually holds mostly true for the anterior saddle horn. Other regions with positive d i are highly indicative of prolapses, especially around the coaptation zone. In contrast to the visualization of a single time step, where only prolapses of a specific point in time can be assessed, the 3D+t view provides information to the user comparable to a density distribution. Combining several time steps reduces uncertainty w.r.t. prolapse location, which might exist in individual 3D models due to inhomogeneous valve movement and possible segmentation errors. Third, the coaptation zone is emphasized. In addition to the existing mapping of d i , we now also employ a color map regarding coaptation distance c i . Regions with c i ≤ 2mm are coded with a green color gradient and an increase in opacity. None of the valves in our data set showed significant problems regarding the interference of these two color maps. Prolapses and closed coaptation usually do not overlap, as a prolapse close to the leaflet tips typically infers an opened and as such leaking part of the valve. Highlighting the coaptation area in all time steps results in an intricate view, where individual zones cannot be visually distinguished. We, therefore, restrain the mapping to the time step most interesting to the physician, which lies at peak systole (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>). We estimate that this time step corresponds to the 3D valve with highest coaptation area percentage in one data set. This allows the user to see whether the valve completely closes at the point where the leaflets have maximum contact. We further emphasize the position of peak systole by marking the corresponding annulus in a dark green coherently across all views.</p><p>Fourth, we hint at the movement of the remaining leaflet parts, whose area is rendered in white with high transparency. Since we want our framework to apply to an arbitrary number of time steps, the user is given the option to adapt the transparency seamlessly with a slider. This also allows control over the dominance of previously highlighted features, e.g., setting transparency to zero will result in a view showing only the features. Displaying the remaining leaflet area allows an approximate assessment of the spatial range of leaflet movement over the course of the cardiac cycle, i.e., the user can assess the bounds leaflets move in (cf. right side of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 4</ref>). With view from above, the user can analyze the time-dependent shape and homogeneity of the coaptation line.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.2">Stacking Flattened Mitral Valve Depictions</head><p>Even though the 3D+t visualization is built to highlight essential features, it may still prove difficult to read. This is attributed to the fact that even 3D geometry of single points in time often is complex and usually there is no perspective from which the entirety of the surface is visible at once. The inclusion of temporal information through the rendering of multiple geometries only intensifies this problem, which results in the complication that some geometrical properties cannot be appropriately assessed. For instance, the variation of leaflet sizes cannot be sufficiently analyzed using the 3D+t view. Annuli variation can be determined on a global scale, but the order in which annuli deformations or transformations might occur is not accessible. Connecting the annuli or color coding their appearance based on the order of their time steps does not solve this problem, as the curve geometry is convoluted and there are too many intersections. Ultimately, our goal is to make essential surface properties intuitively accessible; however, we do not want to omit geometry or hide data from the user, especially due to the high relevance of the clinical use case.</p><p>A visualization that has already proved to be useful regarding simplification of the complex 3D valve surface, is the depiction of an unrolled or flattened surface. The flattening algorithm is tailored towards the creation of comparable 2D surfaces. The height of the annulus always relates to the u-axis, which corresponds with the 3D annulus plane. Due to the construction of the plane, essential landmark positions are parameterized uniformly: the annular commissure points lie at u = 0 and the height of the anterior saddle horn can be compared against the rest of the valve, as it does not impact the plane approximation. Dimensions of the annulus can be assessed, as its arc-length is preserved and the size of the leaflets can be compared, since the parameterization targets equiareal results. We, therefore, extend the 2D valve representation and provide the user with an additional view, where we incorporate the temporal dimension into the flattened depiction as well (2D+t).</p><p>As the parameter space of each valve is embedded within 2D using uv-coordinates, we set the temporal dimension along a third axis w. Since this dimension is discrete w.r.t. an arbitrary number of points in time, the resulting view shows a stack of flattened MVs in order of their time step. We apply color maps to annuli and leaflets, which are identical to their counterparts in the 3D+t depiction. This improves coherence across the views, but also allows users to derive additional valve parameters from the 2D+t. For instance, the occurrence of prolapses can be quickly assessed, as the stack of flattened depictions does not contain geometry intersections and red-coded regions can be allocated to their respective point in time. Similarly, the time step at peak systole can be identified at a glance and the extent of its coaptation area can be analyzed at once. The color of annuli also allows easy perception of the number of cardiac cycles in the data set, since systolic states appear as green annuli clusters in the 2D+t view.</p><p>Due to the discrete representation of the w-axis, a visual correlation between consecutive annuli is uneven and changes in their shape and height cannot be judged at a glance, but require the user to interpret the curves from different viewing angles. To improve the perception of annulus movement over time, we therefore also propose a visualization of interpolated annuli vertices over w, which results in a surface as can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>. We apply Gouraud Shading to this surface, such that changes of the annulus in w-direction can be observed continuously.</p><p>Using the surface as a reference, the user can easily differentiate between homogeneous and inhomogeneous annulus deformations, which results in a smooth or uneven surface, respectively. Because all annuli are virtually registered to the u-axis, this assessment is not distorted through movement of the whole valve or the surrounding parts of the heart, as it is in the 3D+t view. Therefore, annulus deformation can be pursued on the surface in w-direction.</p><p>The surface can also be used to gain a quick overview of the most interesting time steps. The surface geometry would currently only convey information through its shape, however, we believe it can be further enhanced to help users gain a quick overview of the most interesting time steps. We therefore also propose to map color to the surface, which is indicative of prolapses at the respective points in time. For each surface point, we sample the uvw-space in a negative v-direction and observe d i . We apply a red gradient to the surface which relates to the sum of samples with d i &gt; 1mm. A comparison of the surface representation based on a normal and prolapsed valve can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Fig. 5</ref>.</p><p>Analogously to the navigational aid provided by the single time step 2D map, the 2D+t view offers users the possibility to explore the parameter space, which is now also time-resolved. In the 2D view, we provide users with a means to mark points of interest, which will then also be displayed on the respective surface point in the 3D view. We applied a similar function to the 2D+t view. Users can pick out time steps of interest through the selection of the corresponding annulus. This time step is then marked in all other views (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>), while the single time step 3D and 2D views will change to display the specific geometry at the selected point in the cardiac cycle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.3">Visualizing Orientational and Positional Change of the Mitral Valve</head><p>We showed how the convoluted valve geometry could be simplified by providing a flattened surface visualization and we also described how this 2D depiction could be extended to make previously imperceptible time-dependent variable changes of the MV possible. The 2D+t view is designed to focus on leaflet and annulus deformations over time and it deliberately excludes depiction of the global valve movement inside the heart. The outline of this movement can be seen in the 3D+t view, however, due to the overlapping geometry, direction and order of this movement cannot be sufficiently interpreted. One of our formulated goals states that an assessment of the valve's overall motion inside the heart should be possible (R3). Therefore, we employ two additional views, in which we abstract the general valve movement from its specific geometry. We split the movement property into relative changes in orientation and position, making these properties independently examinable.</p><p>To abstract overall positional change of the MV, we track the 3D annulus barycenter over time, as this central point is indicative of the valve's general position. Connecting the barycenter across time steps results in a polyline (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6, top)</ref>. We color the line segments according to the global annulus color scheme, which makes it possible to differentiate between systolic and diastolic states of the valve. As the orientation of the lines would be unclear w.r.t. the anatomical layout of  Experts were asked to select the more accurate plane. In this case, the left plane is landmark-based and the right plane was constructed using the least squares method.</p><p>the valve, we link this depiction to the camera of the 3D+t view. This means, scaling and rotating of the time-resolved 3D models automatically translates into equal transformation of the polygonal chain. This way, the user always sees the valve models and the abstraction of their positional shift from the same perspective.</p><p>Movement of the MV does not manifest in a translation alone, as the ventricle might also be rotating slightly. The orientation of the MV can be understood as an axis around which the annulus evolves. As we have already computed the plane in which the annulus lies, we can use the plane normal to describe the valve's spatial direction. We want the user to be able to perceive the angular variation between the normals of the extracted time steps. Therefore, we propose a depiction of these normals, where angular deviation from the mean normal can be observed. We render each normal as a point around the origin in xyz-space. A color is assigned to each point, which is equal to the color of the corresponding annulus in the 3D+t and 2D+t view. We then fit a spherical cap through these points, whose center is defined by the mean normal. We use a ten-degree cap, as we observed the valves in our data set to feature plane normal variations within that range. A color gradient corresponding to the degree between a surface point and mean normal is applied (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6, bottom)</ref>. The changes in valve orientation can thus be observed in terms of angular variance. These variances can not only be interpreted on a linear axis, but as a spherical distribution, which makes it possible to understand which spatial directions the valve is leaning towards. It can be observed whether the valve's orientation stays relatively consistent or not, which might be a possible pathology indicator (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6, bottom)</ref>. A connection between the two views can be made by selecting the valve time steps in the 2D+t view. This marks the corresponding time step in all visualizations, including a point on the orientation plot and the position polyline (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">EVALUATION</head><p>Our methods target to fulfill a set of requirements, specified in the context of clinical MV analysis. Geometric features of the MV are critical factors in pathology detection and treatment planning. We hypothesize that our proposed visualizations allow quantitative assessments of these parameters (R1) and facilitate understanding of their temporal development (R2), as well as the general movement of the MV (R3). In order to test whether we met our requirements, we conducted an evaluation with six domain experts, four of which are cardiac surgeons and two are technical experts w.r.t. computer-assisted MV surgery. The evaluation was performed in three steps: first the experts were introduced to the framework, then they were asked to fill out a questionnaire regarding suitability of our visualizations and finally we assessed the appropriateness of the annulus plane construction, as many of our methods are highly dependent on its approximation.</p><p>Participants were first shown the views containing a single time step of valve geometry. The correspondence between the 3D valve and the flattened depiction were explained, as well as the different kinds of color maps and their indications for pathologies. Participants were given time to get familiar with the controls and the possibility to iterate the time steps of a data set. We then explained the extension from the 3D view to 3D+t and analogously 2D to 2D+t, as well as the intentions behind the movement abstractions. Participants were able to explore data sets with a varying amount of time steps and of different classes, including normal, pathological and one example which was assessed post-surgery.</p><p>After they familiarized themselves with the framework, participants were asked to fill out a questionnaire, during which they still had the option to use the program. As all participants, including the technical experts, are well acquainted with the standard clinical procedures of MV surgery, they all received the same questions. In the following, the results and spoken comments of the experts will be summarized. To assess whether all experts agreed that the geometrical features of the MV we focused on are of general importance, we first asked participants to rate their relevance w.r. Experts agreed that all of the listed geometrical features were significant regarding pathology analysis.</p><p>The second part of the questionnaire was specific to our temporal visualizations, as the views showing singular time steps have already been reviewed <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. For each of the time-dependent views, participants were asked to rate its suitability regarding MV assessment on the same scale as before. Each view was associated with a set of assertions referring to the fulfillment of R1-R3. All experts found the 3D+t view convenient to get an overview of the MV movement and to assess prolapsed areas of the leaflets (S(++) = 2, S(+) = 4). Most participants regarded the slider for transparency adjustment as being useful (S(++) = 1, S(+) = 4, S(0) = 1) and four of the six experts found the size of coaptation to be discernible in the 3D+t view (S(++) = 1, S(+) = 3, S(0) = 2). Regarding the 2D+t view, participants positively remarked the advantage of the navigational features, in particular the ability to select specific time steps in order to highlight them inside the other views. They found this view to be helpful to differentiate systolic and diastolic time steps and to identify those with possible prolapse (S(++) = 3, S(+) = 3). Most experts found the 2D+t view to have promising potential for the assessment of annulus shape change over the cardiac cycle (S(++) = 2, S(+) = 3, S(−) = 1). They agreed that the orientation plot (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6</ref>) is suitable to discern valves with high and low directional variance (S(++) = 2, S(+) = 4). Furthermore, they could interpret motion of the whole valve inside the heart using the position path (S(++) = 2, S(+) = 4) and all experts stated they could understand the orientation of the path due to the linkage to the 3D+t view perspective.</p><p>At the end of the questionnaire, we assessed the experts' preference regarding the different exploration methods for the spatio-temporal data. We asked them whether, in a clinical scenario, they would prefer to iterate individual time steps of data sets or have views accessible, which incorporate the temporal dimension directly. Four of the six experts immediately expressed preference for views combining all time steps. Due to the dynamical nature of the valve analysis problem, they claimed these views to be more appropriate to evaluate the whole valve at once. However, one expert stated he would prefer the iteration-based views, as he found them less ambiguous and thus easier to interpret. Lastly, one participant remarked he would appreciate the option to have both types of views accessible, i.e., independent and integrated time steps. In particular, he pointed out that some pathological valves resulted in a convoluted 3D+t view, due to their turbulent motion, at which point he would rather rely on individual representations of the time steps. For all other purposes, he would rather use a view with direct time step integration.</p><p>Many of the proposed methods rely on the construction of the annulus plane. It is used as a local frame of reference not only during parameterization, but also for the assessment of leaflet height, as well as the approximation of valve orientation. We tested a construction of a plane based on the least squares method and a plane dependent on landmarks of the model (cf. Sec. 4.2). During development and implementation of the methods, we hypothesized that the landmark based method results in a more accurate annulus plane. To test this hypothesis, we showed the participating experts image pairs of differently constructed annulus planes and asked them to select the more accurate one. In each image pair only one valve model was portrayed, so the planes could be directly compared against one another. One plane was constructed using the least squares approach and the other with the landmark-based method. An example of an image pair can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 7</ref>. Order of methods was randomized and the experts did not know which plane corresponded to which method. Each expert was shown five image pairs and asked to select the more accurate plane in each of them. Out of the 30 resulting instances, experts selected the landmark-based plane 27 times.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">DISCUSSION</head><p>The evaluation indicates that our tool offers considerable potential to enhance clinical MV analysis. Experts deem geometrical features of the MV a crucial factor in assessment of pathologies. These features are difficult and sometimes impossible to analyze, when using standard methods, such as TEE. We showed that an extraction of triangulated MV models can provide a basis for feature estimation and advanced visualization. Using our novel views, experts were able to intuitively perform quantitative assessment of important valve properties, such as prolapsed regions and coaptation zone (R1). The majority of experts agreed that the integration of time-dependent data into one depiction allows better analysis of the valve's features, as compared to animation-based representations. They found our proposed 3D+t and 2D+t visualizations to accurately portray valve behaviour over the cardiac cycle (R2). The only criticism referred to the sometimes convoluted 3D+t view. This emphasizes the necessity of different perspectives on the data, which we included in form of the 2D+t view, as well as the two views focused on movement abstraction. Experts agreed that they could facilitate these abstractions, in order to better understand valve movement and changes in its orientation (R3), which was not possible in this way with state-of-the-art methods. We therefore conclude that our main requirements for the proposed framework have been met.</p><p>Limitations. While most experts regarded the integration of all time steps into one depiction as beneficial towards a reliable clinical analysis, two of our evaluation participants expressed a preference for viewing individual time steps independently in some scenarios. Our framework supports simultaneous display of all six views (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 2</ref>), which gives users the option to use either method or combine them. However, we found that on displays with a resolution lower than 2560 × 1440 pixels, if all information is displayed at once, details of the visualizations might be difficult to perceive. Additionally, if several valve data sets are to be compared against one another, it is advisable to either only contrast some of the possible views or to use multiple monitors.</p><p>Our approach is also specific to the MV and relies on an explicit method of model generation. Although we tested stability and robustness of the proposed methods against 48 data sets, we did not generalize the approach to models created with different methods or models of other structures, e.g., different kinds of heart valves. We are confident, however, that the proposed methods could be generalized to other valve models, if they are obtained in a way that labels the required landmarks, i.e., annulus and commissure points. A further problem with valve modeling is that dependencies exist, not only regarding the segmentation method, but also regarding the expert who performs the segmentation. It has been observed that inter-observer variability can be relatively high, i.e., there are differences between models created by distinct experts from the same TEE data set. We found that these discrepancies also affect the visualizations of these models. In particular, models created by one of our experts showed a higher degree of movement in the orientation plot and position path. This has to be taken into account, especially when contrasting data sets segmented by different experts.</p><p>Improvements. Some experts noted that the movement path in its current form conveys the linearity of the valve's positional change, however, it remains difficult to determine the scale of the movement w.r.t. different directions of 3D space. A 3D indicator of scale, such as a system of labelled axes or a bounding box enclosing the path, could facilitate additional measurements. Similarly, the orientation plot could be enhanced by integrating a form of visual guidance, referring to the layout of the valve. For instance, locations of landmarks could be added to the plot, such as arrows pointing into the approximate direction of the saddle horn or commissure points, making the plot more intuitively readable.</p><p>We also need to draw attention to the fact that in order to increase the clinical viability of the proposed methods, further systematic evaluation of the observed effects is required. As with all organic processes, MV pathogenesis is different from case to case. Even in our data set we made the observation that not all pathological valves move turbulently and not all normal valves display a homogeneous behaviour. Therefore, the properties that can be assessed from the proposed visualizations need to be studied systematically for a large collective of MV data sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSION</head><p>We presented a framework for visual exploration of time-dependent MV geometries. The visualizations target facilitation of clinical MV analysis through novel and enhanced depictions of patient-specific valves. We use a combination of six linked views, which offer the ability to perform an in-depth examination of MV properties indicative of pathologies. We address the drawbacks of animation or time step iteration by introducing novel views, which directly integrate the temporal dimension. In order to simplify convoluted mesh geometries, we base parts of the visualizations on a flattened valve surface, which we obtain through parameterization. The computation of the parameter space is tailored towards the requirements of MV analysis, e.g., we shift inevitable distortions into regions of less relevance in a clinical context.</p><p>Discussions and evaluation with domain experts showed that our tool has high potential to enhance the current clinical processes of MV analysis. Our proposed methods focus on properties of the MV, which are difficult to assess and quantify using typical modalities like TEE. The experts were able to utilize the tool to determine severity of a variety of pathology indicators and also localize these characteristics directly on the valve surface, as well as understand their variances over the course of the cardiac cycle.</p><p>In the future, we believe the visualizations to be a promising basis for further quantitative assessments. Properties like contact pressure or stress distribution have been computed before <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33]</ref>, as well as pressure fields and radial leaflet thickness <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>. A visualization of these properties could also benefit from our approaches to flatten convoluted leaflet geometry and to integrate time-dependent variances.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Manuscript received 31</head><label>31</label><figDesc>Mar. 2019; accepted 1 Aug. 2019. Date of publication 16 Aug. 2019; date of current version 20 Oct. 2019. For information on obtaining reprints of this article, please send e-mail to: reprints@ieee.org, and reference the Digital Object Identifier below. Digital Object Identifier no. 10.1109/TVCG.2019.2934337</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>MV anatomy. a) Position of the MV between the left atrium and ventricle. Attached chordae tendineae and papillary muscles hold the valve in a closed position, when blood is pushed into the body. b) Top of the closed MV as seen from the left atrium. The anterior leaflet (A1-A3) and the posterior leaflet (P1-P3) are often partitioned into the shown segments [6]. c) MV leaflets cut at the lateral commissure and flattened.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Views of our proposed framework. 1: 3D view. An interactive 3D MV model corresponding to a single time step of the data set is shown. Different color maps can be applied. The current color scheme is based on leaflet height. 2: 2D view, showing the flattened geometry analogous to 1. 3: 3D+t view. All time steps in the data set are shown simultaneously, while important features are emphasized. 4: 2D+t view. The flattened geometries of all time steps are stacked and the annuli are interpolated to a surface. The currently selected time step is marked in all views. 5: Variation of valve orientation over time. 6: Variation of valve position over time. Camera perspective is linked to 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Normal valve (top) and a valve with leaflet prolapse (bottom) shown in the 3D+t view. A view from above helps to identify regions of prolapse and homogeneity of the coaptation zone. Note that the pathological valve does not sufficiently close, thus there is no continuous green coaptation zone visible. A perspective from the side allows to determine variance of the annulus and shape of the opened leaflets.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Normal valve (top) and a valve with leaflet prolapse (bottom) shown in the 2D+t view. A homogeneous surface indicates a stable mitral annulus. Dents in the surface, as can be seen in e), are common with pathological valves, which often have a more turbulent annulus. Rotating the view to a side perspective allows to compare leaflet size changes over time. The spacing of the w-axis can be determined by the user. Collapsing this axis gives a representation as in c) and f). The distribution of prolapsed areas and coaptation can thus be assessed. Note how this view also emphasizes the difference in annulus and leaflet homogeneity, when comparing normal versus pathological valves.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Top: Paths extracted from positional change of the mitral annulus, a normal valve (left) and a prolapsed valve (right). Systolic states are marked in green. Bottom: Corresponding plots of the valves' orientation over time. The scale measures deviation from the mean orientation, which is at the centre of the spherical cap.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Image pair as shown to experts during evaluation of the annulus plane.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>t. clinical decision making, using a fivepoint Likert scale (−−, −, 0, +, ++). Participants assigned the highest importance to coaptation and prolapse area (S(++) = 5, S(+) = 1), followed by tenting height, leaflet size and annulus dimensions, as well as position of the saddle horn (S(++) = 3, S(+) = 3). Movement of the annulus was also considered important (S(++) = 2, S(+) = 4).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The work was supported by the German Research Foundation (DFG) project 398787259, EN1197/2-1, DE 2131/2-1 and LA 3855/1-1.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Straightening tubular flow for side-by-side visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Angelelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2063" to="2070" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear virtual colon unfolding</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Bartroli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Konig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Groller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="579" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantification of mitral valve anatomy by three-dimensional transesophageal echocardiography in mitral valve prolapse predicts surgical anatomy and the complexity of mitral valve repair</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Biaggi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jedrzkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gruner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meineri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Karski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vegas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tanner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rakowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ivanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American Society of Echocardiography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="758" to="765" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stent maps -comparative visualization for the prediction of adverse events of transcatheter aortic valve implantations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Born</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sündermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Russ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gessat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Vis Comp Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2704" to="2713" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient-specific modeling and analysis of the mitral valve using 3d-tee</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Burlina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sprouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dementhon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jorstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Juang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Contijoch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yuh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mcveigh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Information Processing in Computer-Assisted Interventions</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="146" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Carpentier&apos;s Reconstructive Valve Surgery. Saunders</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Carpentier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Filsoufi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Maryland Heights, Missouri</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anatomically constrained surface parameterization for cortical localization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Clouchoux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Coulon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rivire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cachia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mangin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rgis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med. Image Comput. Comput. Assist. Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Baumgartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gohlke-Bärwolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanrath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Horstkotte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mügge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schäfers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Flachskampf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Klappenvitien im Erwachsenenalter. Clinical research in cardiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="620" to="641" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards automatic assessment of the mitral valve coaptation zone from 4d ultrasound</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Engelhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lichtenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Al-Maisary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Simone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roggenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Karck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Meinzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Functional Imaging and Modeling of the Heart</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">9126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="145" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitral valve quantification at a glance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Eulzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lichtenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Arif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brcic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Karck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Simone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Engelhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Bildverarbeitung für die Medizin</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="296" to="301" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cortical surface-based analysis. ii: Inflation, flattening, and a surface-based coordinate system</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Sereno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="207" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Isolated mitral valve surgery: the society of thoracic surgeons adult cardiac surgery database analysis. The Annals of thoracic surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gammie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chikwe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Badhwar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thibault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vemulapalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thourani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gillinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rankin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ghoreishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="716" to="727" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis of the mitral coaptation zone in normal and functional regurgitant valves. The Annals of thoracic surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gogoladze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Donnino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ribakove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Greenhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Galloway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Grossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1158" to="1161" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Distortions of the mitral valve in acute ischemic mitral regurgitation. The Annals of thoracic surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Iii</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hiramatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G S J</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M. L Henry</forename><surname>Edmunds</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1026" to="1031" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colon flattening using heat diffusion riemannian metric</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gurijala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Vis Comp Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2848" to="2857" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anisotropic mass-spring method accurately simulates mitral valve closure from image-based models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pedro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Functional Imaging and Modeling of the Heart</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="240" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Image-based mass-spring model of mitral valve closure for surgical planning</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Perrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pedro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6918</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69180</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anatomy of the mitral valve</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>suppl 4</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A pipeline for computer aided polyp detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Qiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Vis. Comput. Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="861" to="869" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesh parameterization: Theory and practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hormann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Polthier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sheffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Course presented at ACM SIGGRAPH</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-dimensional plot visualization of aortic vortex flow in cardiac 4d pc-mri data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Köhler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meuschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fischbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gutberlet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">BVM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="61" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of flattening-based medical visualization techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kreiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meuschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mistelbauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ropinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput Graph Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="597" to="624" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitral valve flattening and parametermapping for patient-specific valve diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lichtenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Eulzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Romano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brčić</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Karck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Simone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Engelhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Under review at IJCARS with major revision</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing residue surface proximity to interpret molecular dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lichtenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Menges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ageev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A P</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Heimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Imhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput Graph Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="390" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual analysis of aneurysm data using statistical graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meuschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wickenhöfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Vis Comp Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="997" to="1007" />
			<date type="published" when="2019" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semiautomatic vortex flow classification in 4d pc-mri data of the aorta</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meuschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Köhler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comp Graph Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combined visualization of vessel deformation and hemodynamics in cerebral aneurysms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meuschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Voß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Beuing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Vis Comput Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="761" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Placenta maps: in utero placental health assessment of the human fetus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Miao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mistelbauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karimov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alansary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Damodaram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Story</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Hajnal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Vis Comp Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1612" to="1623" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ingels Jr. The effect of pure mitral regurgitation on mitral annular geometry and threedimensional saddle shape</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Carlhäll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bothe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Timek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Oakes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Daughters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of thoracic and cardiovascular surgery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="565" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glyphbased visualization of myocardial perfusion data and enhancement with contractility and viability information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Oeltze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hennemuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Glaßer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kühnel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">VCBM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semiautomated mitral valve morphometry and computational stress analysis using 3d ultrasound</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pouch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yushkevich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jassar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vergnat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Iii</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sehgal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jackson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of biomechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="903" to="907" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personalized computational modeling of mitral valve prolapse: virtual leaflet resection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">130906</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of leaflet-to-chordae contact interaction on computational mitral valve evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomedical engineering online</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient-specific mitral leaflet segmentation from 4d ultrasound</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tenenholtz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Perrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Marx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pedro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="520" to="527" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Live 3-dimensional transesophageal echocardiography: initial experience using the fully-sampled matrix array probe</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sugeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Shernan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Salgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Weinert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Raman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jeevanandam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dupont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Settlemier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Savord</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American College of Cardiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="446" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asynchronous movement of mitral annulus: an additional mechanism of ischaemic mitral regurgitation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Szymanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Klisiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Cardiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="512" to="516" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vesselmap: A web interface to explore multivariate vascular data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Qiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C.-K</forename><surname>Shene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="92" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3d information visualization for time dependent data on maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tominski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schulze-Wollgast</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Information Visualisation</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Information Visualisation</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="81" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geometric atlas: modeling the cortex as an organized surface</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Toro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Burnod</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1468" to="1484" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative blood flow visualization for cerebral aneurysm treatment assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Van Pelt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gasteiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lawonn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meuschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Preim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput Graph Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supine and prone colon registration using quasi-conformal mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Marino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gurijala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans Vis Comp Graph</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1348" to="1357" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards patient-specific modeling of mitral valve repair: 3d transesophageal echocardiographyderived parameter estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kanik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mansi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Voigt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ionasec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Subrahmanyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sugeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yuh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Image Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="599" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parameterization of 3d brain structures for statistical shape analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5370</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
