<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Computer Animation Representing the Molecular Events of G protein-coupled Receptor Activation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zoya</forename><surname>Maslak</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Art</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Douglas</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Steel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center for High Performance Computing</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Utah</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Computer Animation Representing the Molecular Events of G protein-coupled Receptor Activation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The molecular events involved in the activation of G proteincoupled receptors, represent a fundamental biochemical process. These events were selected for animation because the mechanism involves both a ligand-receptor conformational shape change, and an enzyme-substrate conformational shape change. Expository animation brought this biochemical process to life.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>One can derive motion from different information. When the information is data containing time steps, a simulation can be depicted. The data fixes the timing for a simulation. When the information is a story based on the scientific literature, an expository animation can be created. An animator creates the timing for an expository animation. The root meaning of animation is Òto give lifeÓ. In our animation project we have attempted Òto give lifeÓ to a foundational biochemical process: the molecular events involved in the activation of G proteincoupled receptors. The project combined the collaborative efforts of a biology post-doctoral researcher, a fine arts graduate student animator and a project director. It targeted scientific researchers in biology.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">PRODUCTION</head><p>First a story was developed in consultation with a small group of local biology researchers. The story was developed to be moving, in both the physical sense, and in the intellectual sense. We wanted a story to have interesting physical movement to animate and to be a compelling story worth telling. _________________________________ *** 155S 1452E, Rm. 405 CHPC, University of Utah Salt Lake City, UT 84112, USA mcdermott@chpc.utah.edu</p><p>Once there was a solid story, a story board was drawn. The story board provided a focus for discussion with our local biology researchers about the appearence of the story to be told. Based on the story board, models could be designed. There was an extensive search for existing data to define models. Shape, color and texture of models were chosen to support the story. Model sheets were drawn characterizing the movement of the models throughout the entire story. Further discussions took place with our local biology researchers to characterize the movement of the models and to set the environment into which the models would be set.</p><p>Only after all this preliminary work was time devoted to creating models for the animation and computer animation software for the movement. SoftImage 3D Animation Software was chosen for its balance between complexity of modeling and ease of use by an animator. Models as well as an environment for these models were produced using SoftImage 3D.</p><p>The story was broken down into a series of scenes. Subsequently, line drawing of the animation, followed by 1/2 resolution double-time flip books of the animation, and finally 30 frames-per-second video resolution rendered images were produced for each of the scenes. As each scene unfolded many discussions took place about the appearence and movement with our local biology researchers.</p><p>After approximately a yearÕs period of time and many hours of reviewing animation, we produced 8 scenes consisting of some 7,000 final rendered images. The images were transferred to a SoftImage Digital Studio for editing, where voice over and music were added. From a digital video master, analog video duplicates have been produced for viewing in this yearÕs video proceedings as a companion to this case study paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">SCIENCE</head><p>A schematic for G protein-coupled receptor activation ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>) in current used in textbooks <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Initially, neither the ligand molecule nor the G protein complex is associated with the receptor ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1a)</ref>. Once the ligand binds to the outside of the receptor <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1b)</ref>, the G protein complex attaches to the inside of the receptor. A molecule of GDP detaches from the receptor-G protein complex and is replaced by a molecule of GTP <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1c)</ref>. This allows the G protein complex to come off the receptor and dissociate into it's respective subunits <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1d)</ref>. The alpha subunit/GTP diffuses to a molecule of an enzyme adenylate cyclase, binds to it, activates it, and initiates a cascade of cAMP production <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1e)</ref>. Eventually, the GTP is hy-drolyzed to GDP, and as a result the alpha subunit/GDP falls off the adenylate cyclase and re-associates with the other G protein subunits <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Fig. 1f</ref>). The ligand dissociates from the receptor and the system returns to its starting conditions, awaiting reactivation( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1g</ref>). . Starting with the amino acid sequence of a receptor, this model has been constructed to take into account secondary and tertiary structural features of the receptor including alpha-helical and betasheet regions, hydrophilic and hydrophobic domains, the seven trans-membrane domains, as well as intracellular cytoplasmic loops and extracellular receptor-binding regions. Until the complete X-ray crystal or NMR structure of such a receptor is solved, such diagrams represent the best overall model of G protein receptor structure. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">DESIGN</head><p>There were design problems to be solved for models, colors and animation. The models were designed to capture both an appearence and a movement, colors were used for identity and activity of the models, animation was used to depict both interaction between models as well as activity within a model.</p><p>Models made use of techniques that supported both overall shape, and the internal movement of a model. The neurons were created by using of B-spline tubes ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref> below &amp; <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 6</ref> color plate).The B-spline tubes were chosen so that the animated models strongly resembled the image of physical neurons ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref>). Because of the dynamic nature of the biochemical process of the G-protein Coupled Receptor and Adenylate Cyclase enzyme activation, the best tools we found were Meta ÐClay modeling and Meta-Clay shape animation (   Because the range of colors available for video is considerably less than the range of colors for painting or film, the colors for models were chosen from a constrained range. Shading of a single hue was used to depict activity of a model. Low intensity, quiet colors were chosen for the inactive receptors ( Textures were used to depict both shape change and activity. A 3D texture was applied to the model of simple static polygonal sphere representing the nucleus of the neuron model <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 11</ref> color plate).</p><p>The main concern of our animator was to create a believable consistent movement through the medium, combined with clear and easy-to-understand changes of shapes. The environment depicted objects immersed in a liquid-like substance. Camera fly-throughs were performed to move the viewers point of view through out the environment without any visible ÒcollisionsÓ with objects. The complexity of the nucleus was depicted by the choice of an animated 3-D texture. To depict the activation and deactivation of the receptor and enzyme, a combination of shape-animation and color animation were used. Meta-Clay shape animation allowed for complex yet subtle changes within the G protein receptor model <ref type="figure">(Figure 9</ref> color plate), and more dramatic changes within the model of the Adenylate cyclase enzyme <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 12 color plate)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">EDITS</head><p>Video production creates a "package" to contain information and "frames" results in a way that it is easily understood. From the start of our project we planned on delivering our animation in video. An archival form, as well as a final product can be repeatedly viewed and easily distributed.</p><p>The visual editing was straight forward due to the preplanning of our animation. During the visual editing some animation errors were seen and they were corrected. These errors were not seen prior to the visual editing. Previously, we viewed flip books of the animation by repeating frames two or three times, this was due to the amount of time needed to render these flip book. At the time of the visual editing we were viewing all of the full frame images for the first time, hence some errors.</p><p>The voice-over attempted to achieve a delicate balance between images and words. A script was developed while viewing the animation of each scene played over and over in a loop. There were the traditional clashes between script writer, our biology post-doc, and the director. The script writer kept asking to stretch the final animation in order to fit more words. In the end the timing of the animation won out and the words were reduced.</p><p>The many hours of work developing our script allowed us to record the entire voice-over in one take and fit it directly to the entire animation. This was a brilliant stroke of good fortune.</p><p>Initially, music was composed in three sections by Uri, a friend of ZoyaÕs, who was only looking at the story board. The first section was light and fit much of the animation. The second section was somewhat more dramatic and appropriate for the more active portions of the animation. The third section was very dramatic and may have sent our viewers home in tears, so that this music was not used in this animation project.</p><p>The final music composed by Uri, while viewing a draft edit of the full animation on video tape. This composed music was appropraite in both pace and mood for our animation. The music fit exactly in time and was recorded in one entire pass of the full animation. This was another brilliant stroke of good fortune.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">VIEWS</head><p>An abstract and a video tape of our animation were submitted to the 17 th International Meeting of ÒMolecular Modeling in the LargeÓ, organized by Art Olsen, Director of the Molecular Graphics Laboratory of Scripps Research Institute. Art has been producing computer graphics and computer animation of biological processes for many years. Our submissions were accepted <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[4]</ref> and put in a session where there was an invited paper entitled, ÒVisualization of the Receptor-G-Protein Inter-faceÒ by Garland Marshall, Center for Molecular Design, Washington University. This invited speakerÕs title seemed as if it related directly to the content of our animation. Only after we had heard the invited presentation delivered were we sure that our submission would indeed be a unique contribution to the meeting.</p><p>We delivered our presentation and showed a video tape of our animation which were both very well received by the attendees. Most attendees felt that the events protrayed were an accurate representation of the scientific literature. The only point raising scientific controversy was the loose tethering of the complex attached to the membrane. On this point, there was a division of opinion, which usually characterizes a point that is not fully understood.</p><p>Two still images from our animation ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figures 6 &amp; 7 color plate)</ref> were rendered at 3000 lines and plotted at 22Ó by 28Ó. These images were framed and submitted to the 1998 Molecular Graphics Art Show curated by David Goodsell of Scripps Research Institute <ref type="bibr">[5]</ref>. Both stills were accepted for the exhibit and were well receiced at the opening of the exhibit by the attendees and other contributing artists.</p><p>Teresa Larsen, a member of the Molecular Graphics Laboratory of Scripps Research Institute, who produced an expository animation entitled ÒLooking Into HIVÓ, juried the exhibit <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6]</ref> and attended the meeting. She entered into lengthy discussions about the experience we have gained during our project relating to the experience she has accumulated over a number of years. An indepth exchange took place between individuals aspiring to the same lofty goal of portraying scientific stories with animation.</p><p>Fred Brooks of the University of North Carolina, who has worked for many years on visualizing biological processes, also attended the meeting. This community questioned our use of music and our seemingly continuous portrayal of time. We responded that the music was used to help both the flow of the animation and to provide an underlying supporting mood for the animation. As to the question of timing, we brought to their attention that within a scene there is the portrayal of an event but that between each scene there may well be additional time due to the nature of the Brownian motion of the objects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">CONCLUSION</head><p>An animation project benefits from many contributions, such as people, moving story, story board, model sheets, modeling, wire frame animation, flip-book animation, rendering, frame storage &amp; transfer, visual edit, script, voice over, music, audio edit. Considerable effort was made to achieve a balance in the many contributions so that the finished production would possess an over-all high quality.</p><p>The goal of this animation was to provide researchers with a view of a biochemical processes occurring in living cells. Scientists have images of complex biological processes in their imaginations, but those images are very different from one to the next. The feedback from researchers who have viewed the animation has been positive with respect to providing an animated visualization for this particular biological process.</p><p>The resulting animation, we feel, was well worth the individual efforts, as well as the expenditure of computational resources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>Doug Steel and Toto OliveraÕs research group in our Department of Biology provided endless hours of critical discussions and viewing of our work throughout the entire project. They provided our project with the critical scientific input needed for an animation project like this to succeed.</p><p>Zoya Maslak endlessly persisted as a designer-animator over the entire year. Her willingness to respond to the scientific criticism, as well as the criticism of all aspects of the animation, truly tested both her Russian up-bringing and early education.</p><p>Computational support, animation software, digital video and audio editing for this project were provided by the Center for High Performance Computing at the University of Utah.     </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Schematic of G protein coupled receptor activation. The brain is filled with millions of neurons (Figure 2), [2] specialized for sending and receiving electrical signals. They have two types of long finger-like projections which form billions of connections with other cells in the brain, to communicate instructions for the body. The axons are slender extensions which terminate in a flattened bulb called a bouton. It is from the boutons that chemicals are released to communicate with other cells. The second projections are called dendrites, which are dense tree-like networks of nerve endings which make contact with the axons and receive the chemicals released from the axons. It is through a combination of electrical impulses and the release of chemicals that message are relayed throughout the brain. Line drawings of the hypothesized three-dimensional structure of a G protein-coupled receptor (Figures 3 &amp; 4 color plate) have been derived from data [3]</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Image of human neurons.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figures 7, 8, &amp; 9 color plate). To save rendering time, models of the receptors in the background were converted from Meta-Clay models to polygon models(Figure 10 below).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Line drawing of neuron models.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Polygonal (left) &amp; Meta-Clay (right) models.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figures 7 &amp; 8 color plate). Bright, high intensity colors were chosen for the active receptors (Figures 9 &amp; 12 color plate). 3D</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>G-protein receptor data (top view).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>G-protein receptor data (side view).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Neuron models.Figure 7: Synapse models.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Acetylcholine receptor models.Figure 9: G protein receptor &amp; membrane models.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Neuron nucleus model.Figure 12: Adenylate cyclase enzyme model.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Traditional Representation of G Protein-Coupled Receptor Activation from</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kandel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Principles of Neural Science, Third Edition</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page">176</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How Neural Networks Learn from Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific American</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">267</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">144</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A computer animation representing the molecular events of G protein-coupled receptor activation, Molecular Graphics And Modelling Society 17 th International Meeting</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Maslak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Steel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.mgmsoa.org" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-12-10" />
			<pubPlace>San Diego, CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.scripps.edu/pub/goodsell/mgs_art/msg_arts/index.html" />
		<title level="m">Molecular Graphics Art Show, Reuben H. Fleet Space Theatre and Science Center</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Balboa Park, San Diego CA, December 2</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998-01-15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Molecular Graphics Art Show</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Teresa</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Larsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Ju-rorÕs Comments</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
