<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Real-time Visualization of the Clear-up of a Former U.S. Naval Base</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Paul</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Paul M. Chapman, Sonar Research &amp; Development L td</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Unit 1, Grovehill Industrial Estate, Beverley, East Yorkshire</addrLine>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Derek</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Hull</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Paul M. Chapman, Sonar Research &amp; Development L td</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Unit 1, Grovehill Industrial Estate, Beverley, East Yorkshire</addrLine>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Graham</forename><surname>Brookes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Hull</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Paul M. Chapman, Sonar Research &amp; Development L td</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Unit 1, Grovehill Industrial Estate, Beverley, East Yorkshire</addrLine>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sonar</forename><surname>Research</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Development</forename><surname>Ltd</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Real-time Visualization of the Clear-up of a Former U.S. Naval Base</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.7 [Computer Graphics]: Three-Dimensional Graphics and Realism</term>
					<term>I.3.8 [Computer Graphics]: Applications</term>
					<term>I.6.0 [Simulation and Modelling]: General whole field modelling, seabed visualization, sonar technology</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper * describes the effective real-time visualization of the clear-up operation of a former U.S. Nuclear Submarine Base, located in Holy Loch, Scotland. The Whole Field Modelling System has provided an extremely accurate real-time visualization of a large number of varying parameters such as remotely operated vehicles, cranes, barges, grabs, magnets, and detailed seabed topography. The system has improved the field staffs&apos; spatial and temporal awareness of the underwater environment and facilitated decision-making within the c omplex offshore working environment.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Holy Loch lies approximately 50km due West of Glasgow and is 3.9km long and 1km wide. It has been used for military purposes by the British and the US since the First World War. In 1945, the US military returned to the loch to act as peace keepers to the NATO alliance. The US Navy operated a submarine base ( <ref type="figure">Figure  8</ref> -colour plate) in the loch for over 30 years with over 1500 American servicemen stationed at the base. In 1992 the base was finally closed and the American military withdrew leaving behind a large amount of military debris.</p><p>Before the base can be returned to Clyde Port Authority, the loch must be carefully cleared of all debris. In 1996, Sonar Research and Development Ltd. were contracted by the mooring and salvage organization of the Ministry of Defense to assist in the clear-up operation of the loch.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">THE CLEAR-UP PROCESS</head><p>SRD initially surveyed Holy Loch in 1996 using their sonar <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">8]</ref> Seabed Visualization System (SVS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. The resulting highresolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> bathymetric data geographically highlighted the main debris areas. Most of the debris was located directly under the original floating docks. <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref> (colour plate) shows a depth coloured bathymetric plot from the sonar survey showing the <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Typically 5-10 cm positional resolution and 1cm depth resolution. seabed that lay directly under the original floating Naval Base. Note the scour marks <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref> in the loch floor (left of the image) caused by the original heavy anchor chains that secured the docks. The deep circular hole in the centre of the image was originally found to be one of the deepest locations in the loch and consequently used as the main position for the floating docks. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 4</ref> (colour plate) shows an arial photograph of the barge used for the clear-up operation. The barge is approximately 49.5m by 16m wide. Note the cranes at the front of the vessel and the operational control cabins to the rear. The barge is manoeuvred via four long anchor wires running from each corner of the vessel to secure anchors on the loch floor. By slackening or tightening the anchor wires, the barge can be positioned to within metre accuracy over a target area.</p><p>The barge used three over-the-side sub-surface transducer arrays <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and associated motion compensators. A real-time kinematic GPS system was mounted at the top of the crane's jib for positioning purposes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Clear-up Procedure</head><p>The area for debris clearance in Holy Loch has been split into a number of 25m 2 blocks. Each block is broken down into four 12.5m 2 areas (identified A-D). These blocks are composed of 9x9 individual lifting zones (approx 1.3m 2 each). <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> describes a simplified model of the clearance operation. Initially, a working block is pre-surveyed using the SVS subsurface transducer array <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. This survey will identify the exact location of any debris within the 81 lifting zones.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1: Survey procedure</head><p>After the sonar pre-survey, the barge is positioned for grabbing and magnetting. Initially, the grab is fitted to the crane's block <ref type="figure">(Figure 2</ref>-B) and lifting begins. The grab is lowered to the seabed, closed and raised 3m off the loch floor. If the crane's load-cell suggests that there is debris on the grab, the grab will be raised back to the surface. The grab is then continually lowered to the seabed over a particular drop zone until no more debris is recovered. All debris collected from the main crane is carefully lowered onto the wash-down deck and an immediate visual inspection takes place 2 .</p><p>The wash-down crew then clean the silt and mud off the debris using two high-powered water cannons. The debris is subsequently checked for any abnormal levels of radiation to ensure that the gamma radiation does not surpass the background level. The debris is then broken into sections using hydraulic cutters and lifted into skips using a secondary grab. A computer database keeps accurate records of every single lift such as wet weight, dry weight and debris classification. The skips are finally placed into an adjacent barge for later removal from the site and re-cycling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2: WFM Real-time visualization</head><p>When a drop zone is clear, the crane driver moves the grab onto the next adjacent drop zone. When all 81 zones have been cleared, the grab is replaced by a large electro-magnet and the clearance process for all 81 zones is repeated. The magnet collects smaller metallic debris from the loch bed that might slip through the grab. For example gas bottles, spanners and shells.</p><p>After magnetting, a post-survey of the area is performed using the barge-mounted transducers. A Phantom Mark II Remotely Operated Vehicle (ROV) [6] is then deployed from the back of the barge to perform a visual inspection of the block. After the post survey, the ROV will fly over the block in nine runs providing video data of the entire block. The precise position of the ROV is known at all times (Section 3.1) so any debris located can be geographically tagged. After the ROV has finished the video survey, the block will either pass or fail. A failed block will need to be re-magnetted or re-grabbed (depending on the nature of the debris remaining) in the problem areas identified by the ROV video survey. If the block passes, the barge will be moved to the next block (A-D) and the entire process: pre-survey, grab/magnet, post-survey, ROV survey, is repeated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Complexity of Operations</head><p>Section 2.1 has provided a simplified model of the clearance procedure. In reality, the process is more streamlined and not as linear as the model described in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. For example, while the crane is grabbing a particular block, the ROV will be flying over a previously grabbed block and performing a video survey.</p><p>Clearly there is a lot happening here: the ROV flying over the seabed, the movement of the barge, the movement of the crane arm, the position of the grab and magnet and the collection of bathymetric terrain data collected from the sonar surveys. With the existing system it was difficult to conceptualise quickly the location of moving objects in relation to other objects. For example, it is imperative that the ROV pilot knows his vessel's position in relation to the five tonne electro-magnet under the water. Our objective was to provide specific users with a real-time visualization of the clear-up operation to facilitate spatial and temporal awareness of all the components used within the clear-up operation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">REAL-TIME MARINE VISUALIZATION</head><p>The introduction of effective visualization techniques such as GIS within the marine environment has been extremely modest <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[9]</ref>. Real time underwater visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> has been extremely slow to develop and has generally been limited to 2D representations of vessel positions on digital charts <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>The Whole Field Modelling System (WFM), a virtual reality seabed visualization tool developed at SRD <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref> has been extended to allow for real-time visualization of the entire clear-up operation of the former Naval Base. WFM was integrated into the clear-up operation to provide the viewer with an effective realtime visualization of all the operations described in Section 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Implementation</head><p>To build an effective real-time model of operations, a large amount of data was required from a number of different sources. This section describes the data required and explains how we visualized these components within WFM. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows a snapshot from the real-time visualization of the clear-up operation. The image shows the barge in its actual position including a correctly modelled and positioned crane preparing to drop some debris onto the wash-down deck. The 3D models used in the visualization were created using Kinetix's 3DStudio Max from detailed engineering drawings and then imported into WFM and modified for functionality and real-time visualization. We included rolling clouds and mountains to make the virtual environment as 'real' as possible.</p><p>We now consider how to accurately model the barge, crane, grab, magnet, seabed terrain, remotely operated vehicle and debris in real-time.</p><p>The barge's location is calculated using real-time kinematic (RTK) satellite tracking that provides centimetre positional accuracy. The squat and draft of the barge was calculated using a tide monitor located at the front of the vessel. Motion sensors provide rotational information: heave, pitch and roll. Yaw (heading) is taken from the vessel's compass.</p><p>The physical dimensions of the main crane are known including its offset from the centre of the vessel. A GPS receiver on the tip of the crane jib <ref type="figure">(Figure 2-A)</ref> permits the crane's heading and pitch to be calculated 3 . <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> The heading and pitch of the crane arm can be calculated because we know the position of the crane's base as an offset from the centre of the vessel (known via the RTK). Since we know the length of the crane jib, we can calculate the required yaw and pitch angles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B C</head><p>The underwater positioning of the grab and magnet were calculated by placing a responder <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> onto the crane block <ref type="figure">(Figure 2 -B)</ref>. As the crane block travels towards the loch floor, the responder sends out a signal at a known frequency. Two transducer arrays, positioned on the barge at 90 degrees to each other listen in two orthogonally different planes for the responder's return signal. The SVS then provides a bearing and range for each of the planes permitting the exact 3D position of the responder to be calculated to cm accuracy.</p><p>A load-cell on the crane winch provides a metric for lift data in kilograms. The grab and m agnet each weigh approximately 5 tonnes. This weight is 'zeroed' each time the grab/magnet is attached to the crane block improving the accuracy of the lifting sessions. As soon as the weight on the load cell exceeds a predefined threshold, a debris flag is set and WFM renders debris under the grab or magnet <ref type="figure">(Figure 3)</ref>. The exact nature of the debris is not known so an exact visualization is impossible as we only know the weight being lifted. However, to give some indication of the weight from the load-cell, the debris's volume is scaled proportionately to the amount being lifted (assumes homogenous debris).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 3: Grab breaking water level with debris flag set</head><p>The large grab has five hydraulic arms ( <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>) and stands approximately 2m tall with a span of 1.5m 2 . The grab can be open, closed or moving between states. The pressure applied to the grab to open and close the arms is measured using pressure sensors and sent to WFM. Consequently, the visualization system can open and close the grab in real-time.</p><p>The five tonne electro-magnet has a diameter of 1.5 metres and has two states: on and off. The amount of current passing through the magnet is inputted into WFM so that the magnet can be coloured depending on its state: yellow for off, the magnet's 'real' colour, and red for active or 'live'.</p><p>The data read from the SVS sonar transducers fixed on the barge is converted into Digital Terrain Maps (DTMs) in real-time and imported automatically into the WFM model. The terrain is colour texture mapped according to depth. After a sonar survey, WFM receives a network command to import the new terrain into the model. To provide rendering efficiency, WFM used multiple levels of detail for the terrain depending on the viewer's position. Terrain reduction algorithms were not used to reduce the complexity of the terrain datasets due to time constraints. Simplified datasets were created by under-sampling the highresolution DTMs.</p><p>The Phantom ROV was modified to include motion sensors, responders and a specially designed miniature SVS developed at SRD. The position of the ROV is calculated in the same way as the crane's block and detected using a secondary SVS barge mounted transducer system.</p><p>All the above data is streamed into the WFM visualization over a 100 Base-T network. WFM was implemented on a Pentium III 600Mhz PC using Creative G2 graphics technology and developed using Microsoft's Visual C++ Version 6 and OpenGL graphics libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Problems Encountered</head><p>The majority of this visualization system was developed at Sonar Research and Development's headquarters in Beverley, England by simulating operations from captured data recorded in Holy Loch. Actual implementation of the system on the barge highlighted a number of unforeseen problems.</p><p>Debris was originally flagged based on the value returned from the crane's load-cell. However the magnet had a greater surface area than the grab and consequently registered significantly more drag underwater. As a result, more energy was required to pull the magnet through the water column than the grab. We therefore needed to set different load-cell debris thresholds for the grab and the magnet.</p><p>One thing we were not prepared for was that different crane drivers had very different styles of working. For example, one crane driver may pull the grab through the water faster than his workmate. Thresholds therefore needed to be specific to crane drivers. Fortunately there were only two crane drivers so this did not prove to be a problem.</p><p>One small obstacle we had was that the crane block's responder could not be tracked in less than 2m depth of water due to the nature of the sonar equipment. Consequently, when the crane driver lifts the grab or magnet out of the water, the crane's block depth positioning is lost. We therefore introduced a rule that if WFM had not heard from the block's responder within the last four seconds, then the block must be out of the water. The block is then rendered at a fixed height of 6m above water level.</p><p>The heading and pitch of the crane is unaffected by the inability to track the block out of the water because the crane's positioning relies on a DGPS receiver placed on the tip of the crane jib. As a result, we will always have the correct position of the crane so the system can visualize the crane driver depositing the debris on the wash-down deck.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">RESULTS</head><p>WFM rendered to a number of displays within the control cabins on the barge <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref>  <ref type="figure">(Figure 2-C)</ref>: specifically, the ROV, crane, control and party chief cabins. The displays were multiplexed so the viewer could switch between various predefined views (such as under the barge, ROV camera viewpoint and fixed crane grab cameras). No training was required for WFM as the staff did not need to be taught how to read and interpret the natural viewing environment. The visualization system was tested on five different ROV pilots and control staff, two crane drivers and two party chiefs.</p><p>One problem for the crane drivers is that their work can become extremely monotonous, increasing the potential for error. A typical mistake would be forgetting to sensitise the magnet on the loch floor. Supplying the crane driver with the WFM 3D view (rendering the state dependent coloured magnet) eradicated this error completely. The crane drivers also reported that they felt more 'comfortable' knowing the whereabouts of the ROV underwater.</p><p>Control cabin staff no longer need to shout to the adjacent ROV cabin to confirm that the ROV is in a safe position prior to a barge move as they know its exact position in relation to the barge. The cabin staff reported that WFM provided a refreshing change to the large amounts of graphs and sound signals emanating from the PCs within the control cabin.</p><p>The ROV pilots were provided with a WFM 3D display which augmented their 2D ROV displays. On occasions, the silt on the loch floor would be heavily disturbed by the nearby grab lifting operations. This sediment upheaval would reduce the ROV camera visibility to zero. The WFM system is unaffected by poor visibility and continuously provides the pilots with a crystal clear visualization of their ROV underwater.</p><p>The main benefit of WFM reported by the party chief (responsible for all operations offshore) was WFM's ability to provide a more complete picture of the clear-up operation in real-time and in a format that is immediately comprehended. The party chief also had the added luxury of a force feedback joystick to manoeuvre a virtual vessel 'SRD1' <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>, to select any viewpoint or area of interest within the real-time model. This would include the ability to closely examine anomalies on the loch floor generated by the sonar data.</p><p>All parties welcomed the visualization and although the system did not replace the current software tools used for the survey, they did augment, enhance and improve operations. The primary benefit reported from WFM's visualization was a significant improvement in spatial and temporal perception of all components used in the survey. The real-time implementation of WFM offers opportunities for improved effectiveness of the clear-up operation and has provided the field staff with an improved understanding of the underwater environment reducing the potential for error, which in the offshore industry can be extremely costly, both financially and ecologically.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>The real-time visualization used for the clear-up operation of the loch was recently presented to the public at the Oceanology 2000 conference held in Brighton, England, March 2000. This attracted considerable interest from the marine industry due to the real-time interactive nature of the system. We did briefly consider the implementation of a stereo display, for example using liquid crystal shutter glasses, but this was rejected because of the cramped and hazardous nature of offshore working environments. WFM can be easily modified for visualizing different offshore operations. Current research involves investigating effective methods for visualizing the sub-sea pipe laying process in Taiwan including real-time touchdown monitoring. We are also developing a real-time visualization system for deep-sea diamond mining using remotely operated 'crawlers' operating deep on the ocean floor.</p><p>This case study paper has provided another real-world example of how the Whole Field Modelling System can be used to effectively visualize large amounts of data in the offshore marine environment. It is estimated that at the current rate of operations, the clear-up operation of Holy Loch will be completed by March 31, 2000. Animations and photographs from the clear-up operation can be downloaded from: www.hull.ac.uk/php/csspmc  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Arial photograph of the clearance barge</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 5 :Figure 7 :</head><label>57</label><figDesc>WFM visualization of the barge Figure 6: Flying alongside the ROV under the barge Grab dropping debris onto the wash-down deck Figure 8: Photograph of the original Holy Loch Naval Base Figure 9: ROV Control Cabin. Note the WFM display (bottom right) Figure 10: Bathymetric depth coloured view of the seabed (200m 2 ) Figure 11: Grab breaking water with debris flag set Figure 12: Record lift -Dock Super Structure 17028 KG</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">Extreme care was taken when lowering debris to the wash-down deck. Any suspicious or potentially explosive material found was detonated away from the salvage barge by bomb disposal experts.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4">Responder: A transducer that emits a sound pulse after detecting a trigger pulse from a remote secondary device.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5">The WFM system rendered at an average of 25fps and had real-time positional updates to the visual database of between .5 and 1Hz.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>Thanks to the Ministry of Defence and all the staff at Sonar Research and Development Ltd especially Rafe Montgomery, Kevin Brown, Justin Beasley, Mat Duree, Iain Kelwick, John Smith, Andy Smith, Bill Austin, Rosie Stevens and Mark Thomas for their technical support. Thanks to all the Sea Structures crew for their constant assistance offshore and the exceptional crane drivers Wayne and Tom. Special thanks again to Dr Helen Wright, and James 'Wizard' Ward from the University of Hull for their helpful ideas and discussions. Thanks also to the reviewers for providing valuable ideas for improvements to this paper. This work is partially funded by the Teaching Company Directorate.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seabed visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brookes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization&apos;98</title>
		<meeting>Visualization&apos;98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="479" to="481" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing underwater environments using multi-frequency sonar</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brookes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole Field Modelling&apos;: Effective real-time and post-survey visualization of underwater pipelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brookes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization&apos;99</title>
		<meeting>Visualization&apos;99</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="448" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sound underwater images. American Underwater Search and Survey Ltd. Lower Cape</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Carr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time GIS for marine applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hatcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Maher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Marine and Coastal Geographical Information Systems</title>
		<editor>Wright and Bartlett</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="147" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Offshore tidal sands, processes and deposits</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stride</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982" />
			<publisher>Chapman and Hall</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="48" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Principles of underwater sound</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Urick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3 rd Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rumblings on the ocean floor: GIS Supports Deep-Sea Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Geo Info Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="29" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
