<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Geodesics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ingrid</forename><surname>Hotz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kaiserslautern</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 3049</postBox>
									<postCode>D-67653</postCode>
									<settlement>Kaiserslautern</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kaiserslautern</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 3049</postBox>
									<postCode>D-67653</postCode>
									<settlement>Kaiserslautern</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Geodesics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>geodesics, visualization features</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>One of the main research topics in scientific visualization is to &quot;visualize the appropriate features&quot; of a certain structure or data set. Geodesics are very important in geometry and physics, but there is one major problem which prevents scientists from using them as a visualization tool: The differential equations for geodesics are very complicated and in most cases numerical algorithms must be used. There is always a certain approximation error involved. How can you be sure to visualize the features and not only the approximation quality. We present here an algorithm to overcome this problem. This paper consists of two parts. In the first, a geometric method for the construction of geodesics of arbitrary surfaces is introduced. This method is based on the fundamental property that geodesics are a generalization of straight lines on plains. In the second part these geodesics are used to generate local nets on the surfaces.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In this paper we will deal with geodesics, which are in some sense the shortest connections on surfaces. They play an important role in differential geometry for the investigation of surfaces, as in physics. In classical mechanics, the geodesic curves can be interpreted as unaccelerated movements. In the general relativity geodesics are the possible world lines of test particles and therefore give a possibility to gauge the space time.</p><p>The geodesics are given by nonlinear differential equations, which in general are not easy to solve. We are now pursuing a new idea for the construction of the geodesics on smooth surfaces, by a purely geometric method, which makes us independent of the complexity of the description of the surface or the physical problem.</p><p>First, a short introduction to the differential geometry of curves and surfaces, which are the basis when dealing with geodesics, is presented. More details can be found in <ref type="bibr">[?]</ref>. Then the geometric method and the algorithm of constructing geodesics is presented. Finally local nets are build with these geodesics. There are two different approaches being utilized: pseudo orthogonal nets and geodesic polar coordinates. ¿´Ø µµ ¾ Ê ¿ is called the tangent vector or velocity vector of the curve « at Ø. For each Ø ¾ Á where « ¼´Ø µ ¼ , there is a well-defined straight line, which contains the point «´Øµ and the vector « ¼´Ø µ. Therefore we restrict our considerations on curves with « ¼´Ø µ ¼ Ø ¾ Á. Such a curve is called regular. The arc length of a regular parametrized curve from the point Ø¼ to Ø is by definition:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">×´Øµ Ø Ø ¼ « ¼´Û µ dÛ</formula><p>Since the arc length is a geometric invariant of the curve the parametrization by arc length with « ¼´Ø µ ½ ,is also called the natural parametrization. To simplify our exposition, we restrict ourselves on curves parametrized by the arc length. This restriction is not essential, because there exists always a unique parameter transformation, such that the curve is parametrized by arc length.</p><p>The norm « ¼¼´× µ ´×µ of the second derivative measures how rapidly the curve pulls away from the tangent line at ×, in a neighborhood of s. The number ´×µ is called the curvature of « at ×.</p><p>At points where ´×µ ¼ , a unit vector Ò´×µ in the direction « ¼¼´× µ is well defined by the equation « ¼¼´× µ</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>´×µÒ´×µ. The vector</head><p>Ò´×µ is orthogonal to the tangent and is called the normal vector at ×. The unit vector ´×µ Ø´×µ ¢ Ò´×µ normal to the osculating plane is called the binormal vector at ×. It's change measures how rapidly the curve pulls away from the osculating plane at ×. ´×µ ¼´× µ is called the torsion of « at ×. where Ë ¾ means the two sphere.</p><p>We will now have a look on the geometric structures carried by the surface. The natural inner product of ÁÊ ¿ Ë induces on each tangent plane ÌÔË of Ë an inner product, denoted by </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Geodesics</head><p>Geodesics are to a certain extent a generalization of straight lines, shortest connections in the flat Euclidean space. In the case of curved spaces the shortest connections are no longer straight lines. One can think of a surface on which one stretches a cord between two points and the cord cannot leave the surface. On a sphere for example the geodesics are sections of great circles. So geodesics are curves which have only the curvature, being forced upon them by the surface. Here we should mention that the minimality is a local property, globally however this is not true, because there can be more than one geodesic connecting two points. Conversely shortest connections on simply connected surfaces are always geodesics.</p><p>If we interpret a curve as a movement on a surface, the velocity corresponds to the tangent vector ¼ . To give a mathematically exact definition of geodesics, there are still some notions from the differential geometry missing, which we will briefly introduce:</p><p>We start with the definition of covariant derivative of a vector field, which is the analogue for surfaces of the usual differentiation of vectors defined on a plane. Let Û be a vector field on the surface which assigns to each Ô ¾ Í a vector Û´Ôµ ¾ ÌÔË. </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Ù • ¾ ½½ Ú • AE ÙÚ ½ ½¾ Ù • ¾ ½¾ Ú • AE ÚÙ ½ ¾½ Ù • ¾ ¾½ Ú • AE ÚÚ ½ ¾¾ Ù • ¾ ¾¾ Ú • AE</formula><p>The Christoffel symbols can be expressed in terms of the coefficients of the first fundamental form and its derivatives.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">½ ½½ ½ ¾´ ¾ µ Ù • ´ Ú ¾ Ùµ ¾ ½½ ½ ¾´ ¾ µ Ù • ´¾ Ù Úµ ½ ½¾ ½ ¾½ ½ ¾´ ¾ µ´ Ú Ùµ ¾ ½¾ ¾ ¾½ ½ ¾´ ¾ µ´ Ù • Úµ ½ ¾¾ ½ ¾´ ¾ µ Ú • ´¾ Ú Ùµ ¾ ¾¾ ½ ¾´ ¾ µ Ú • ´ Ù ¾ Úµ</formula><p>They quantify the expansion, contraction and torsion of the basis vectors and give therefore the necessary correction for the curved surfaces. For flat surfaces all Christoffel symbols are vanishing, and we have the usual derivatives.</p><p>A vector field Û along a parametrized curve « is said to be parallel if DÛ Ø ¼ for all Ø ¾ Á. In the particular case of the plane, the notion of a parallel field along a curve reduces to that of a constant field along the curve. But on an arbitrary surface parallel fields may look strange to our ÁÊ ¿ intuition. A non constant, parametrized curve Á Ë is said to be a geodesic if the field of its tangent vectors ¼´Ø µ is parallel along for all Ø ¾ Á; that is:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Ø ¼ ¼</formula><p>A parametrized geodesic may admit self intersections. However, its tangent vector is never zero, and thus the parametrization is regular.</p><p>In local coordinates a curve ´Øµ with ¼´Ø µ Ù ¼´Ø µ Ù•Ú ¼´Ø µ Ú, is exactly a geodesic when it fulfills the following differential equations:</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">Ù ¼¼ • ½ ½½´Ù ¼ µ ¾ • ¾ ½ ½¾ Ù ¼ Ú ¼ • ½ ¾¾´Ú ¼ µ ¾ ¼ Ú ¼¼ • ¾ ½½´Ù ¼ µ ¾ • ¾ ¾ ½¾ Ù ¼ Ú ¼ • ¾ ¾¾´Ú ¼ µ ¾ ¼</formula><p>Given a point Ô ¾ Ë and a vector Û ¾ ÌÔË, Û ¼ , there exists always an¯ ¼ and a unique parametrized geodesic ´ ¯ ¯µ Ë such that ´¼µ Ô and ¼´¼ µ Û.</p><p>One can get the same differential equation using the usual variational approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Geometric construction of geodesics:</head><p>Now the question arises on how to compute the geodesics. The differential equations are non linear coupled differential equations. These equations can become arbitrary complicated. of view external to the surface, the absolute value of the geodesic curvature at Ô is the absolute value of the tangential component of the vector « ¼¼´× µ Ò, where is the curvature of « at Ô and Ò is the normal vector of « at Ô. It follows that:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">¾ ¾ • Ò ¾</formula><p>The geodesic curvature is a measure for the change of the angle between the curve and the tangent, by parallel transport along the curve. This means that the normal of a geodetic corresponds to the surface normal. For the curvature of the geodesic we get:</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">¾ ¾ Ò</formula><p>Thus, in a neighborhood of some point, the geodesic to a given direction Û is equal to the normal section in this direction. This allows to construct the geodetic locally by the orthogonal projection relative to the tangent plane ÌÔË on the surface.</p><p>In this way the task of computing geodesics on a surface reduces to projection tangents on the surface. The main point is now how to choose the length of the tangents to project to keep the fault small.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">The Algorithm</head><p>We look at surfaces which are given by a parametrization ´Ù Úµ ´Ü´Ù Úµ ÝÙ Úµ ÞÙ Úµµ. Were Ü Ý Þ are differentiable functions of the parameters Ù and Ú.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Notation:</head><p>We have to deal with points in the parameter space, the corresponding surface points which are the evaluation of the parametrization function at the parameter points. And also with points on the tangent plane, which are the orthogonal projection of the surface points on the tangent. They will be denoted by tangent points. 1. A starting point on the surface, given by a two dimensional point (SP) in the parameter space and a start direction, given by a two dimensional vector (SD) in the parameter space is chosen. 2. Depending on the parameter space (domain) we compute a direction depending maximal step length, by giving a minimal step number. As minimal step length we have a fixed value. As start step length step a nearly arbitrary positive number is fixed. 3. The tangent plane T in the starting point on the surface is specified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">The direction STD of the tangent t to project is computed:</head><p>In the first step, this is the tangent corresponding to the given start direction SD. For the following points this will be the straight line through the starting surface point (SSP) and the projection of the last surface point (LSP) on the tangent plane T (LTP). 5. The next point NP of the geodesic is determined by projection (orthogonal to the tangent plane) of the tangent t on the surface. Simultaneously the step length is adapted to the geometry (the curvature, and change of curvature) of the surface in the point SSP.</p><p>6. If the break conditions aren't fulfilled set SP=NP and continue with point 3. The main point is number five, it will be explained in more detail in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The break conditions</head><p>Depending on the respective task, there are several conditions possible:</p><p>The geodesic reaches the domain border (always active) The geodesic has a given length The number of computed points exceeds a maximal point number The geodesic intersects itself The geodesic intersects another curve of a list of curves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">The Projection</head><p>We start with a parametrized surface given by three functions ´Ù Úµ ´Ü´Ù Úµ ÝÙ Úµ ÞÙ Úµµ, a starting point SP and a starting direction SD or alternatively STD. Further we have a start step length, which is the step length of the last step.</p><p>The projection of the point of the tangent plane corresponds to the solution of a system of non linear equations of three variables (Ù Ú µ:</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">SSP • step £ STD • £ AE ´Ù Úµ</formula><p>Where AE is the surface normal in SSP.</p><p>Here we are faced with the following problems:</p><p>'step ' is not a fixed number, but should be adapted to the geometry of the surface in SSP. If we would fix 'step ' this system might not be solvable. (The orthogonal ray may miss the surface). Even if the system is solvable it is not easy to solve it, because in general we don't have the inverse parametrization functions.</p><p>We can avoid these problems if we use the information of the previous step and the local geometry of the surface. As a first approximation we choose the point FP SP • step £ SD From this point it is easy to compute the surface point FSP and the tangent point FTP. Now we reduce or enlarge the step length until:</p><p>1. the angle between the tangent plane and the connection of FSP and SSP 2. the angle between the tangent and the connection of FTP and SSP 3. the length of the orthogonal part of the difference between the two surface normals: ¡AE ËÌ ¢ AE .</p><p>are lying in some given ranges. The first angle is a measure for the curvature in the starting point, the second angle represents a combination of the curvature of the geodetic parameter curve and the torsion of the geodesic. The last condition directly takes the torsion of the surface curve into account. These condition are also checked by the computation of the next approximation point. If now FTP lies already on the tangent t, we accept FP as new geodesic point.</p><p>If it does not we rotate the direction SD such that the tangent lies between FTP and the next approximation NTP corresponding to the new direction. The rotation of the start direction corresponds to a mapping of a circle with radius step in the parameter space on the tangent plane. The first angle condition guarantees that the image of this mapping is a closed curve which contains the SSP, and we are sure that this curve intersects the tangent. There can be more than one intersection point, but one is as good as the others. Whether it is accepted or not is only dependent on our angle conditions and the distance to the SSP. To find this intersection point we compute the middle point of FP and NP.</p><p>In the parameter space the situation is the following: </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">MP = SP•¼ £(SP,MP) REGION IV ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ REGION II REGION III ´´´´´t angent Ø REGION I ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ ¡ « Ã ØFTP Ø STP ØNTP Ø MTP À À À À À À À Ö Ö</formula><p>In most cases the fourth case does not occur, because in general the step length is small enough that we move in some acceptable field. Surly we can construct a parametrization that this case occurs. But these parameterizations are far away from being natural.</p><p>Because the distance of NP and FP will be halve in every step the iteration converges. In our examples the number of iterations mostly was smaller than six, even though we also tried artificial surfaces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Local error estimation</head><p>What we are computing is exactly the normal section in the point «´¼µ Ô¼ ´Ü¼ Ý ¼ Þ ¼ µ in direction « ¼ Û. To estimate our error we extend a curve around the start point «´¼µ «´d×µ «´¼µ</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">• d× « ¼´¼ µ • ½ ¾ d× ¾ « ¼¼´¼ µ • ½ d× ¿ « ¼¼¼´¼ µ • Ç´d× µ</formula><p>Here × is the arc length. Using the Frenets Formulas we get «´d×µ «´¼µ</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">• d× Ǿ¼µ • ½ ¾ d× ¾ ´¼µÒ´¼µ • ½ d× ¿ ¼ Ò´¼µ ´¼µ ´¼µ ´¼µ ´¼µ ¾ Ø´¼µ ¡ • Ç´d× µ</formula><p>This is valid for the geodesic and for the normal section «Ò. We will now compute the differences between these two curves with the same starting point: «´¼µ and the same start direction Ø´¼µ. Also the normal Ò´¼µ, the binormal ´¼µ and the curvature ´¼µ coincide. However for ´¼µ we get in general different values. For the normal section we have ´¼µ ¼. ´d×µ «Ò´d×µ</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">d× ¿´ ¼ ´¼ µ ¼ «Ò´¼ µµ Ò´¼µ d× ¿ ´¼µ ´¼µ ´¼µ • Ç´d× µ ¡Ò Ò¼µ • ¡ ´¼µ • Ç´d× µ</formula><p>Because both points are lying on the surface the numbers ¡Ò and ¡ aren't independent. We have:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>¡Ò ³ ÓÖØ Ó ¡ ¾</head><p>Were ÓÖØ Ó is the normal curvature in the orthogonal direction. So it is sufficient to look at ¡ .</p><p>Let us now recall the conditions which are controlling the step length: The first angle condition which limits the angle « between the tangent plane and the connection of FSP and SSP, is equivalent to:</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">´¼µ × ¾ × Ò´«µ ³ « «Ñ Ü</formula><p>The third condition limits the length of the projection of the difference between the two surface normals on ´¼µ, what is equivalent to: d×</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">Ò ¼ d× ³ ¡AE STD ¢ AE S</formula><p>o we get for ¡ of our estimation: d× ¿ ´¼µ ´¼µ «Ñ ÜT his means that the maximum error can directly be controlled by the two number «Ñ Ü and¯.</p><p>The second angle condition substantially is a measure of the curvature of the parameter curve, and therefore dependent on the parametrization. But this condition is needed to guarantee that our first approximation lies in some reasonable region. It can surly happen that this condition reduces the step length more than necessary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Computational efficiency</head><p>Let's have a look on the computational effort of one step. The computation of the tangent plane means an evaluation of Ù and Ú.</p><p>To determine the tangent direction one has only to compute a scalar product and a vector addition. The adaptation of the step length means one or two evaluations of the parameter functions. Thus the main time consuming point is the iteration of the projection algorithm.</p><p>The effort of one iteration:</p><p>Computation of the new parameter point a simple vector addition Computation of the corresponding surface point evaluation of the parametrization functions Projecting it on the tangent plane simple scalar product and vector addition. Testing in which region the point lies simple scalar products.</p><p>Finally the computational effort per step is determined by the number of evaluations of the parameter functions which corresponds to the number of iterations plus maximum two evaluations for the step adaptation.</p><p>In general the number of iterations lies between one and ten. In our examples we had an average number of 5.5 iterations per step. This is not much in comparison with the standard fourth order Runge-Kutta method without step adaptation, where one has to compute at least four times the six Christoffel symbols.</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">Ñ Ð ½ ¾ Ñ´ Ð • Ð Ð µ</formula><p>where Ñ Ñ</p><p>and Ñ Ð ¾ Ù Ú Different to usual methods, the computational effort per step depends on the step length, and the local geometry of the surface. If we shorten the step length by requiring a higher accuracy, the first approximation of the next point will become better. Therefore less iterations are necessary. Another advantage is that if we move in an untroubled region of the surface the number of iterations becomes very small.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Geodetic Nets</head><p>What about nets of geodesics?</p><p>Because the geodesics are very sensitive to local variations of the surface, they are not useful for global nets, but for investigation of local behavior they can be used. We followed two different basic approaches:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Pseudo-orthogonal nets</head><p>These nets are constructed in the neighborhood of some point of interest. Two emphasized orthogonal geodesics, starting in this point, are constructed. They were used to determine the starting points and directions of two families of geodesics. The starting points we get by separating the two start geodesics in parts of equal arc length. The start directions are orthogonal to these emphasized geodesics. (In this section orthogonal means always orthogonality on the surface, not in the parameter space.) When the geodesics intersect themselves or another geodesic of the same family the construction is interrupted. In the ideal case we get two bundles of orthogonal geodesics (e.g. on a plane or some isometric surface). In general the intersections of the 'orthogonal' families are not orthogonal and it may even happen that they don't intersect at all. That means that we don't get nets in the classical sense, but this wasn't our aim. With these nets it is easy to classify the starting point, and to find the asymptotic directions (directions with Gaussian curvature zero) if they exist.</p><p>Here we want to cite the Gauss-Bonnet theorem, which gives a remarkable relation between the topology of a compact surface and the integral of its curvature.</p><p>The sum of the interior angles of a geodesic triangle Ì is equal to the integral of the Gaussian curvature Ã over Ì .</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">¿ ½ Ì Ã</formula><p>This is only a special case, but for our intention it is sufficient.</p><p>Important applications for us are:</p><p>On an orientable surface of negative or zero curvature, two geodesics ½ and ¾ starting in one point Ô ¾ Ë cannot meat again in another point Õ ¾ Ë, such that they are the boundary of a simple region Ì Ë.</p><p>On a surface Ë of negative curvature, homeomorph to a cylinder, then Ë has at most one simple closed geodesic.</p><p>This shows that the behavior of geodesics differs very much dependent on the Gaussian curvature, so this method is especially successful in the case of surfaces with negative Gaussian curvature or in the neighborhood of hyperbolic points. On surfaces with strictly positive Gaussian curvature or in the neighborhood of elliptical points, such nets become in cause of self intersections soon chaotic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Geodesic polar coordinates</head><p>The second approach are geodesic polar coordinates. We will briefly illustrate what this means:</p><p>On a curved surface, one cannot find a coordinate system with </p><formula xml:id="formula_16">´ ¢µ ½ ´ ¢µ ¼ ´ ¢µ Ð Ñ ¼ ¼ Ð Ñ ¼´Ô µ ½</formula><p>For the Gaussian curvature one gets:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">Ã ´Ô µ Ô</formula><p>Is the Gaussian curvature negative on the whole surface, so the distance of neighboring radial geodesics is growing with the radius. Since ¼ the family of the geodetic circles is orthogonal to the family of radial geodesics in some neighborhood.</p><p>There exists one well known example where geodetic polar coordinates are used to visualize a surface. This is the sphere where the geodetic polar coordinates correspond exactly to the degrees of longitude and latitude. But also in other cases they provide a very intuitive image of the surface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Results</head><p>We tested the algorithm on a lot of different surfaces. When possible we compared the results with the analytical solution and they were very satisfying. In our examples the point number moved in the range of ten up to some thousands.</p><p>In the first example we take a torus to demonstrate the adaption of the step length. The picture shows a star of geodesics on a torus in the parameter space. To test the parameters of the projection algorithm, we compared the results of different maximum step length by plotting them together in one picture. The pictures are very persuasive. As an example we take again the torus, as a surface with positive, negative and zero curvature. Now we want to show some examples of different nets, which are shown sometimes in the parameter space and sometimes on the surface. All theses lines are linear interpolations of the computed points. The pictures in the parameter space are plotted with gnuplot, the pictures on the surface are generated with Open GL.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I.pseudo orthogonal nets:</head><p>We will start with a surface where the geometrical construction gives an exact result -the sphere parametrization Ü´Ù Úµ Ö ¢ × Ò Ù ¢ Ó× Ú Ý´Ù Úµ Ö ¢ × Ò Ù ¢ × Ò Ú Þ´Ù Úµ Ö ¢ Ó× Ù</p><p>The next example is a hyperbolic paraboloid. It shows how these nets can be used to visualize geometric properties of the surface in the neighborhood of the starting point. In this example we have a hyperbolic point. The asymptotic directions can easily be seen.</p><p>In the first picture we have taken an arbitrary start direction, in the second case an asymptotic start direction is chosen.</p><p>Ü´Ù Úµ × Ò Ù Ú ¢ Ó× Ù Ý´Ù Úµ Ó × Ù • Ú ¢ × Ò Ù Þ´Ù Úµ Ú </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. geodetic polar coordinates</head><p>As first example we take again the sphere, where we get the usual longitude and latitude.</p><p>The second example is a minimal surface with negative curvature, the Enneper's minimal surface</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">Ü´Ù Úµ Ù Ù ¿ ¿ • ÙÚ ¾ Ý´Ù Úµ Ú Ú ¿ ¿ • ÚÙ ¾ Þ´Ù Úµ Ù ¾ Ú ¾</formula><p>As an example with positive Gaussian curvature we show the paraboloid, in the parameter space.</p><p>Ü´Ù Úµ Ù Ý´Ù Úµ Ú Þ´Ù Úµ ½¼¼ Ù ¾ Ú ¾ As last example we take the torus, as a surface with all curvature behavior. "torusPolar.txt"</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>plane is separated in four regions, depending on the locations of FTP and NTP. region I: points on the positive tangent region IV: -points P on the other side of the parallel to the connection of NTP and FTP through STP, that means STP lies in the triangle (FTP,NTP,P) -points with angle between t and (SSP,P) ¾ region II: points on the same side of t as NTP (excluding region I and IV) region III: points on the same side of t as FTP (excluding region I and IV) While MTP lies not in region I do: MTP in region I: MP is good enough and is accepted as new geodetic point. MTP in region II: NP = MT and MP = middle point(NP,FP) MTP in region III: FP = MT and MP = middle point(NP,FP) MTP in region IV: While MTP lies in region IV:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>2 Mathematical basics 2.1 Curves</head><label></label><figDesc>parametrized differentiable curve is a map of class Ö (Ö ½) « ÁÊ Á ÁÊ Ò of an open interval Á of the real line ÁÊ into ÁÊ Ò . In this paper we only consider the case Ò ¿ . The vector Ø´Øµ « ¼´Ø µ</figDesc><table><row><cell>A ´Ü ¼ ½´Ø µ Ü ¼ ¾´Ø µ Ü ¼</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>parametrization of Î Ë. If we require in addition that the two partial derivatives of in Ô Ù Úµ, It is called the tangent plane of in Ô. It coincides with the set of all tangent vectors of Ë at Ô.The choice of the parametrization determines a basis Ù´Ôµ Ú´Ôµ of ÌÔË. this basis the unit normal vector AE´Ôµ of ÌÔË is given by AE´Ôµ</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">The mapping is called a denoted by Ù d dÙ and Ú</cell></row><row><cell>The space ÌÔË</cell><cell>Ô´ÁÊ</cell><cell cols="2">¾ µ ÁÊ ¿ is a vector subspace of di-</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">mension two. In Ù</cell><cell>Ú</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ù</cell><cell>Ú</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">The moving frame consisting of the vectors</cell><cell>Ù Ú AE is</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>equations are valid :</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Frenet formulas:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ø ¼´× µ Ò ¼´× µ ¼´× µ</cell><cell>´×µ ¡ Ò´×µ ´×µ ¡ ´×µ ´×µ ¡ Ø´×µ ´×µ ¡ Ò´×µ</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2.2 Surfaces</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>a map</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ÁÊ ¾ Í Î Ë ÁÊ ¿</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>with the following properties: -is of the class Ö</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-is a homeomorphisms (we have no self intersection)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>-the maps are compatible</cell></row></table><note>The three orthogonal unit vectors Ø´×µ,Ò´×µ, ´×µ form a trihedron called the Frenet trihedron at ×. The derivatives of the vectors can be expressed in the basis Ø Ò . Summarizing the followingA subset Ë ÁÊ ¿ is a parametric surface if, for each Ô ¾ Ë there exists an open neighborhood Î ÁÊ ¿ andd dÚ are linearly inde- pendent for all Ô ¾ Í, the surface is called regular.called Gauss frame. In general it is not an orthogonal frame. The linear map AE Ë Ë ¾ ; Ô AEÔ AE´Ôµ is called Gauss map,</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Then Û½ Û¾ Ô is equal to the inner product of Û½ and Û¾ as vectors in ÁÊ ¿ . This bilinear form on ÌÔË is called the first fundamental form ÁÔ of the surface in Ô. The matrix representation of the first fundamental form ÁÔ with Then the normal section in direction Û is the intersection curve « of the surface with the plane given by the surface normal AE and Û. The normal Ò of « in Ô is equal to the surface normal Ò ¦AE. The curvature of this curve is called the normal curvature Ò in Ô. Then the extreme values of Ò are the principle curvatures in Ô. The corresponding directions of the normal section Û½ and Û¾ are the principal directions. For</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">respect to the basis where Ù Ú: Ù Ú of ÌÔË is given by</cell><cell>´ µ,</cell></row><row><cell>µ</cell><cell>Ù Ù Ú Ù</cell><cell>Ù Ú Ú Ú</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Its matrix representation in the basis by À ´ µ, where Ù Ú: Ù Ú of ÌÔË is denoted</cell></row><row><cell>µ</cell><cell cols="2">AEÙ Ù AEÙ Ú AEÚ Ù AEÚ Ú</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">The matrix of the Weingarten map ÄÔ is symmetric and real, there-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">fore it has two real eigenvalues ½ ¾ the principle curvatures, with</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">corresponding orthogonal eigenvectors. ½ and ¾ The product of the principle curvatures Ã ½ ¾ det´ÄÔµ is called the Gaus-sian curvature, and its mean Å 1 ¾µ´ ½ • ¾µ trace´ÄÔµ is</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">called the mean curvature.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">For an another approach to the principle curvature let Û be a tan-gent vector in ÌÔË with Û ½. Û Û½ Ó× • Û¾ × Ò one gets Euler's formula:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ò</cell><cell>½ Ó× ¾ • ¾ × Ò ¾</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">The curvature can be used to classify the surface points: Points with Ã ¼ are called elliptic points, points with Ã ¼ hyper-bolic points, points with Ã ¼ parabolic points. If both principle</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">curvatures are zero they are flat points.</cell></row></table><note>Ô.Let Û½ Û¾ be two vectors in ÌÔË.The first fundamental form ÁÔ is symmetric, positive definite, and geometric invariant. It allows measurements to be made on the sur- face (e.g. of length of curves, angles of tangent vectors, areas of regions) without referring back to the embedding space ÁÊ ¿ . The tangent map corresponding to the Gauss map ÄÔ AE is called the Weingarten map. The bilinear symmetric form ÁÁÔdefined on ÌÈ Ë by ÁÁÔ´Û½ Û¾µÄÛ½µ Û¾ Û½ Û¾ ¾ ÌÔË is called the second fundamental form of the surface Ë in Ô.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The indices are running about Ù and Ú. The coefficients are called Christoffel symbols. They are a measure for the variation of the Frenet trihedron in the direction Ù and Ú.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Û</cell><cell>Û •</cell><cell>Û</cell></row><row><cell>ÙÙ</cell><cell>½ ½½</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Further let «´Øµ Ù´Øµ ÚØµµ be a surface curve parametrized by arc length,with «´¼µ Ô and « ¼´¼ µ ÖÈ Ö . If one restricts now the vector field to « Û´Ù´Øµ ÚØµµ Û´Øµ Û½´Øµ Ù • Û¾´Øµ Ú then the projection of´ Û Øµ´¼µ on the tangent plane ÌÔË is called the covariant derivative of the vector field Û at Ô relative to the vector Ö. The covariant derivative is denoted by: DÛ dØÖÛ Ö Û It can be shown that this definition does not depend on the choice of « but only on Ö. In local coordinates this means:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The most often used method for solving such systems of differential equation is the classical fourth-order Runge-Kutta formula [?][?]. But it requires at least four evaluations of the six Christoffel symbols per step. If it is combined with an adaptive step size algorithm this will be anymore. Bryson uses in his paper[?]  the Newton Method, with lack of accuracy and Adam's-Bahforth integration, which doesn't allow any step size control. A much better alternative to solving the differential equation is the geometric construction of the geodesics, which uses the property that the geodesics are locally the straight lines This method doesn't need a computation of the Christoffel symbols at all and allows an easy step size adaptation.For an arbitrary curve « on the surface parametrized by its arc length, the algebraic value of the covariant derivative of its tangent vector field « ¼´× µ × is called the geodesic curvature of « at Ô. Geodesics are thus char-</figDesc><table /><note>acterized as curves whose geodesic curvature is zero. From a point</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>« ¬¼ on the whole surface. But for every point Ô there exists such a neighborhood. Special systems with this quality are the normal coordinate-systems:Considering all geodesics passing one given point Ô¼ ¾ Ë, characterized by their tangential vectors Ú ¾ ÌÔË, Ú ¼, the points in the neighborhood of Ô¼ are specified by the geodesics on which they are lying and the arc length of the geodesic to Ô¼. To make the description unique one fixes the arc length and varies the length of the tangent vector Ú. In this way one defines the exponential map:There exists always a¯ ¼, such that the exponential map is defined and differentiable in the interior of a disk Í of radius¯of ÌÔË with center in the origin. is a diffeomorphism in Í of Ô and can therefore be used to introduce coordinates in Î ÜÔÔ´Íµ. Among the coordinate systems thus introduces, the most usual are:1.The normal coordinates which correspond to a system of rectangular coordinates in the tangent plane ÌÔË. The coefficients of the first fundamental form are ´Ôµ ´Ôµ ½ ´Ôµ ¼2. The geodesic polar coordinates, which correspond to polar coordinates in the tangent plane ÌÔË. The images by ÜÔÔ Í Î of circles in Í centered in ¼ are called geodesic circles of Î , and the images of ÜÔÔ of the lines through 0 are called radial geodesics.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>The mapping</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ÌÔË Í Ë Ú</cell><cell>ÜÔ Ô´Ú µ</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">In this coordinate system the coefficients of the first fundamental</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>form are:</cell></row><row><cell>ÜÔ Ô´Ú µ ´½ Ú µ</cell><cell>ÜÔ Ô´¼ µ Ô</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The parametrization of the torus -some circulations:Ü´Ù Úµ Ó× Ú ¢´ • Ö Ó× Ùµ Ý´Ù Úµ × Ò Ú ¢´ • Ö Ó× Ùµ Þ´Ù Úµ Ö ¢ × Ò Ù</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="8">Domain: Starting point:´ Start direction:´¾ ¼ ¿µ ½¾ ¢ ½¼ ¿ µ Translation vector:´ ¼ ¾ ¼ ¾µ</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">The geodetic differential equations:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="9">Ù ¼¼ • ½ × Ò Ù´Ö • Ó× Ùµ´Ú ¼ µ ¾ ¼ Ú ¼¼ ¾ × Ò Ú Ö • Ó× Ú Ú ¼ Ù ¼ ¼</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">minimal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="7">step number number of points</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>93</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">16</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>93</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">64</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>88</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">256</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>226</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1024</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>897</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>v</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">"torusStep.txt"</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>u</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-8</cell><cell>-6</cell><cell>-4</cell><cell>-2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>12</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Virtual Spacetime: An Environment for the Visualization of Curved Spacetimes via Geodesic Flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Steve</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<pubPlace>Visualization</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Do</forename><surname>Manfredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Carmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Differential Geometry of Curves and Surfaces</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1976" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Herbert</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Classical Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley Pub</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Charles</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Misner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kip</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Thorne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">Archibald</forename><surname>Wheeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Gravitation</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Freeman and Company</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Straightest Geodesics on Polyhedral Surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Polthier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schmies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Mathematical Visualization, H.C. Hege and K. Polthier</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="150" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Press</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Teukolsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Vetterling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Flannery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Numerical Recipes in C</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2end edition</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
