<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CohortVA: A Visual Analytic System for Interactive Exploration of Cohorts based on Historical Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jason</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xumeng</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>wangxumeng@nankai.edu.cn.</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Youcheng</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rongchen</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kai</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<email>kai.lk@zju.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zihan</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
							<email>zihanyan@zju.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Siwei</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
							<email>siweitan@zju.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Huamin</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
							<email>huamin@cse.ust.hk.</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Siming</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<email>chenvis@zju.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="middle">Cn Wei</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Lab of CAD&amp;CG</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhejiang University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Ministry of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Art and Archaeology Image (Zhejiang University)</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">CohortVA: A Visual Analytic System for Interactive Exploration of Cohorts based on Historical Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2023-03-27T09:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Historical cohort analysis</term>
					<term>machine learning</term>
					<term>interpretability</term>
					<term>visual analytic</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Fig. 1. CohortVA streamlines the iterative cohort analysis workflow and provides visual interpretation for model results. (A) The Scope Specification Component configures the initial research scope. (B) The Cohort Identification Component visually summarizes recommended cohort and feature candidates. (C) The Cohort Exploration Component provides multi-faceted visualizations to validate the selected cohort from multiple perspectives. (D) The Figure Details Component shows the historical figure's profile.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Cohort analysis is a crucial research area in history studies known as prosopography, which can inspire the interpretation of the historical process. Here, a cohort refers to a group of figures that engage in common activities or have frequent interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>. A prosopographical study typically focuses on one cohort and explores its concept, i.e., the set of supplementary features that describes a cohort (e.g., political identities, relationship networks, and social structure) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref>. For instance, based on cohort analysis, Beard <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> revealed that the United States' founding fathers were closely tied with not only leading the American revolution together, but also personal financial interests. This new concept has provoked widespread discussions throughout the U.S. Federal Constitution from a financial perspective. More importantly, it has inspired subsequent works to adopt cohort analysis in suggesting novel concepts and interpretations of well-known cohorts <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref>.</p><p>Recent advancements in digital humanities have greatly relieved historians from manual data collection and labeling. One remarkable progress is that large-scale historical databases, such as China Biographical DataBase <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref> and China Government Employee Database-Qing <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, have been carefully built and widely used. Leveraging them in cohort analysis poses new challenges because the data sizes and varieties overwhelm analysts' capabilities <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>. Automatic analysis approaches can alleviate these difficulties yet are far from ideal. First, existing tools focus partially on extracting and analyzing features, but merely support correlation analysis in the context of social structure. For example, Netdraw <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> and Worldmap <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> can only construct basic features from relation networks and geographic locations. Second, most tools are inefficient in integrating human intelligence and supporting iterative exploration. Third, the lack of interpretability prevents historians from effectively verifying obtained results. Historians need additional effort to authenticate results by referring to other documents.</p><p>As such, it is highly desirable to integrate domain knowledge and expert hypothesis into the exploration procedure within an intuitive visual interface. For that, we closely worked with historians to observe their behaviors and needs, and identified two challenges: 1) Historians must devote a significant amount of time to synthesizing and crosschecking findings of various figures from a large body of historical literature. It is very time-consuming because figure profiles and features cover various perspectives, such as native place, gender, and changes in official positions. 2) The entire process is repetitive because they may constantly shift the goals. Starting from a familiar targeted group, they might discover interesting patterns and recursively explore and study relevant figures. Considering their exploration process and such obstacles, this is a missed opportunity to provide a visualization-driven solution for efficient analysis and reasoning.</p><p>The kernel of our solution, CohortVA, is a cohort identification model that can automatically identify cohorts and their figures. Specifically, given an initial group of interested figures, our model constructs a knowledge graph of related documentary descriptions. It extracts and fuses the common features as the cohort's concept. Based on weaklysupervised learning, our model identifies new cohorts by proposing different cohort concepts as recommendations. The recommended cohorts and their features are visually investigated within the integrated visual interface from multiple perspectives, e.g., location, time, and relationship. In particular, historians can study feature details, reason relations among figures, and progressively refine features and figures of the targeted cohort. Case studies and expert interviews demonstrate that CohortVA frees historians from their heavy workloads and improves the analysis performance. This study makes the following contributions:</p><p>• We propose a cohort identification model that utilizes weaklysupervised learning to free historians from manual annotation, querying, and cross-checking. • We develop a visual analytic approach, enabling historians to study cohorts and concepts interactively. • We conduct case studies and expert interviews to demonstrate the effectiveness and usefulness of our approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>In this section, we review the relevant works in history-oriented visual analysis and visual analytics for cohort studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">History-Oriented Visual Analysis</head><p>Recently, visual analysis has been widely applied to historical data <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. History-oriented approaches can be categorized as phenomenon-based and theory-based. A phenomenon refers to a recorded historical event, while a theory explains why one or more phenomena occurred.</p><p>Phenomenon-based research analyzes the phenomena of historical entities such as figures <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53]</ref>, events <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref>, and cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>. They focus on a few instances in great detail to find hidden patterns and correlations for the phenomenon. Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref> contextualized poems from the Chinese Song dynasty with the poets' life stories. The Svoboda Diaries Project <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> uses a person's diaries to recreate the personal experience in Ottoman Iraq. However, they fail to provide a holistic overview for interpreting and generalizing similar phenomena.</p><p>Theory-based research deduces coherent explanations from several phenomena. To explore the similarities among social structures, Turchin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> collected and summarized the characteristics (e.g., social scale, economy, and information systems) of 414 societies from 30 regions. Regarding a smaller social unit, GeneaQuilts <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> presents large family trees in an interactive diagonal matrix to study genealogical relationships. Similarly, GenealogyVis <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> explores family structure via correlations between family development and social environment. These works demonstrate the benefits of analyzing social structure from a group perspective. Another popular domain investigates the social mobility aggregated by individual movements. For example, Bol <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> adopted geospatial analysis to study how the Southern Chinese intellectual-social movements spread through the 12 th century. Khulusi et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> used network analysis and a novel visualization design to define groups interactively for musicians' biography. CareerLens <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref> and ACSeeker <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> utilize time-series analysis to explore career trajectories.</p><p>In this work, we mainly follow the theory-based approach to assist historians in developing the concepts behind cohorts. We mine features from large-scale multi-dimensional data and fuse them to propose concept candidates. These concepts characterize the cohort and form the basis for understanding the phenomena. We also borrow ideas from phenomenon-based approaches to let users verify the cohorts and contextualize the concepts with detailed historical events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Visual Analytics for Cohort Studies</head><p>Cohort studies are widely used across various domains, such as medicine <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref> and biology <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. For instance, CoCo <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> integrates statistical and visual analysis for the medical experts to classify and compare cohorts' time series. PhenoStacks <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> simplifies ontological topologies and explores symptom similarities among inter-groups and intra-groups of patients. However, these works focus on analyzing and classifying multiple entities into cohorts with existing and clear definitions. They cannot be directly adopted to historical cohort analysis, which emphasizes the identification of new and vaguely defined cohorts. In addition, they cannot iteratively refine the cohort concepts, which usually only become more evident during the exploratory analysis.</p><p>The development of historical databases has contributed significantly to prosopography <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>. Historians widely adopt data visualization tools to explore cohort characteristics from digital records. For example, Gephi <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, Netdraw <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, and Worldmap <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> leverage basic visualization, such as force-directed graphs and choropleth maps, to help historians organize data intuitively. However, these tools fail to integrate multi-dimensional data and features effectively for cohort analysis. Historians need to spend much time cross-validating discoveries about cohorts in the extensive historical literature.</p><p>Besides visualization, machine learning techniques have significantly empowered cohort visual analysis in terms of efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. For example, Zhao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref> used non-binary hierarchical trees and overlapping clustering to shortlist important clusters, reducing the cost of manual selection. However, historians are often confused about the semantic meaning behind the automatic outputs, i.e., the extracted latent features. For instance, Franke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> pointed out that confidence was the first-class attribute of historians for data adoption. They have thus raised awareness of improving interpretability for wider tool adoption.</p><p>The closest work to ours is PK-clustering <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>. It captures the user's prior knowledge as a set of incomplete clusters, then runs multiple clustering algorithms and visually compares the ensemble results for the user's decisions. It enhances interpretability by keeping humanin-the-loop for each analytical iteration. Although PK-clustering and CohortVA both rely on users' interactions with the interim results, there are still a few key differences compared with our work. First, PKclustering performs typical clustering tasks on medium-sized datasets with 50-500 entities. In contrast, CohortVA identifies a cluster as one cohort from a large-scale relational database having over 500K historical figures. We proposed a weakly-supervised learning model and interlinked views to address the difference in scale. Second, instead of visualizing the results alone, we provide interpretable features that corroborate the cohort and auxiliary domain information to explain the results. These quickly validate the cohort composition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">BACKGROUND</head><p>In this section, we introduce the domain background information and outline the requirements obtained through interviewing domain experts. To characterize domain problems and formulate system requirements, we have worked closely with five experienced historians over the past two years. Three of them (H1-H3) are in charge of the China Biographical DataBase (CBDB) <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>. H1 and H2 are committee members, and H3 is a professor leading cohort analysis research projects based on CBDB. The other two (H4 and H5) are Ph.D. students who use CBDB to study the mobility of historical cohorts and the history of the Chinese Song dynasty, respectively. Our collaboration consists of five phases: data acquisition (Sect. 3.1), task analysis (Sect. 3.2), model design (Sect. 4), system design (Sect. 5), and system evaluation (Sect. 6). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Data Description</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Requirement and Task Analysis</head><p>We interviewed our collaborators about their traditional workflow to guide our system design. The traditional historical cohort research follows a mature paradigm <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref>, including hypothesis formulation, feature summarization, and correlation analysis as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2A</ref>. Our collaborators indicated that the traditional analysis process is energyexhausting and time-consuming. We summarised the system requirements and design tasks that empower historians with enhanced cohort analysis capabilities, geared toward their challenges. Identifying cohorts from a large-scale historical database. The first step of cohort analysis is to define the scope of the study and formulate corresponding hypotheses. To find the targeted scope, historians need to browse and filter the massive data materials. They then need to perform a heuristic search based on their experience and hypotheses. Verifying a hypothesis sometimes costs researchers a few months to read related materials repeatedly. The system should provide efficient cohort identification based on users' interests.</p><p>T1 Specify the initial research scope. Historians' research interests are motivated by different perspectives. For example, supporters of the great man theory would be interested in a few core figures, while those supporting geographical determinism tend to look for location correlations <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. Moreover, the differences in prior knowledge about cohorts lead to different specifications. We should support different research orientations by specifying the initial groups in multiple ways. T2 Generate automatic cohort identification results. Traditional prosopography workflow in identifying groups (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2A</ref>) includes browsing massive historical records within the research scope. Automatic cohort identification can alleviate the burden. Since historians might not know everything about a certain dynasty, the automatic method should also account for reasonable ambiguity. Moreover, historians appreciate various cohort candidates complementing cohort analysis from multiple angles.</p><p>Providing visual interpretation for cohort identification results. Historians need to cross-check the identified cohorts before using them for further research. The system should provide a set of visual interpretations to assist in result verification.</p><p>T3 Validate the concept and features that define a cohort. Historians seek variables of significance to explain a cohort's phenomena.</p><p>The identified cohort includes the list of figures and the cohort concept. Historians need to validate whether the cohort concept adequately covers the associated figures. Moreover, to find the most suitable concept, historians also want to examine alternative features of the identified cohort. T4 Verify the cohort from the organized historical event information. H1-H5 emphasize that they always search for additional evidence to verify the results of automated methods. It is necessary to present historians with rich contexts that historians frequently reference, such as geographic locations and social network relationships. They can cross-check the identified cohorts from the detailed historical event information. T5 Inspect individual figures. Analyzing individual profiles help historians interpret the identified cohort at the most detailed level. All mined features and event evidence can be provided for inspiration. The system should display figure profiles from CBDB with spatial-temporal information and descriptions of social relationships. Directing users to the original sources outside the system should also enhance their trust level in the result.</p><p>Supporting iterative cohort analysis. Cohort analysis processes are naturally iterative, and the system should be able to support them.</p><p>T6 Adapt to the revising research interests. Historians refine their research scopes iteratively during the analytical process. Due to different research interests, they might disagree on how features are fused and cohorts are composed. For example, Sima Guang and Su Shi are famous writers and political rivals in the Song dynasty. When historians decide to focus on one particular political party, cohorts containing both figures should be discarded, and corresponding features should be remodeled. Our system should update the cohort composition and concept recommendations accordingly, to reflect the revised research interests. T7 Track analytic provenance. One of the most mundane tasks in prosopography is the inclusion of newly discovered variables. Upon new discoveries, historians need to trace back to previous steps to test what-if scenarios, accompanied by revisiting the same documents repeatedly. We should support revisiting previous progress to compare different cohort identification results.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>. Explanation and extraction models for the six atomic features. Here, descriptions refer to those about the selected figures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Atomic feature Explanation Extraction approach</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TimeRange</head><p>The time period in which an event happened</p><p>Cluster the years occurred in the descriptions with DBSCAN <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. Then, select the year ranges with more than 30% occurrences as TimeRange features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Location</head><p>The location where an event happened Select the top-three locations in the descriptions as Location features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Affiliation</head><p>The government institution where figures held positions Select the top-three offices in the descriptions as Affiliation features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Relationship</head><p>The relationship (e.g., teacherstudent) associating two figures Construct a strongly connected relationship graph based on the descriptions. Then, select the relationships in communities with over five members as Relationship features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Celebrity</head><p>The person mostly connected by others Link any two figures if they appear in the same description. Then, select the figures linked with over 30% of the selected figures as Celebrity features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Entity</head><p>The entity, like occasions and writing Link a figure with an entity if they appear in at least one description. Then, select the entities linked with over 30% of the selected figures as Entity features. Only those entities not covered by other features are selected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">COHORT IDENTIFICATION MODEL</head><p>The cohort identification model discovers potential cohorts from CBDB based on specified figures and features. As illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3A</ref>, the model contains four steps: 1) generate the knowledge graph and descriptions, 2) extract common features from the initial figures, 3) select the features by their significance, and 4) fuse the selected features as the cohort concept and filter figures by this concept.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Knowledge Graph and Description Generation</head><p>We preprocessed the raw historical data in CBDB by converting them into a knowledge graph (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3A1</ref>), where the information is stored in nodes (i.e., figures and entities) and edges (i.e., relationships). In CBDB, figures and entities are structured as rows, and their relationships are as foreign keys. For instance, in the [POSTED TO OFFICE DATA] table, an [Posting] event is connected to <ref type="bibr">[Zhang Jiuling</ref>] and an office position entity [Prefectural Aide]. The two triplets, (Zhang Jiuling, do, Posting) and (Posting, officeIs, Prefectural Aide), are inferred and inserted into the knowledge graph. We identified 28 node types and 27 edge types, and built a knowledge graph with around 1M nodes and 5M edges. We adopted the meta-path2vec <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> algorithm to generate descriptions around the figure entities. Collaborating with historians, we summarized 15 description templates that express interpretable and descriptive information, such as politics, occupation, and social relationships. Meta-path2vec leverages the templates and the sequential structure of nodes connected by edges in the knowledge graph. Compared with the conventional random walk method <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>, it uniformly generates descriptions regardless of nodes' degrees, avoiding the probability-imbalance issue on different node types. The generated descriptions represent a figure's semantic contexts (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3A2</ref> for an example). Lastly, we obtained about 500K figures and 1M descriptions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Feature Extraction</head><p>We refer to the figure-related characteristics extracted from the descriptions as features. Following the conventional cohort study paradigm <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, we categorized figures' characteristics in CBDB into six types of atomic features, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>. To represent more complicated contexts, a composite feature is generated from multiple atomic features via the and logical combination. For instance, the composite feature [Location(Jingzhou) &amp; TimeRange(737)] indicates that the figures visited the Jingzhou prefecture in 737.</p><p>At the beginning of cohort explorations, users determine a search scope and specify an initial cohort (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3B1</ref>). These initial figures (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3A1</ref>) are the query bases of cohort identification. We generate atomic and composite features from their descriptions. For instance, given the description "Zhang Jiuling served as the prefectural aide in 737 at the Jingzhou prefecture", we use the TimeRange model (see </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Feature Selection</head><p>Historical records contain numerous descriptions for figures, resulting in a large number of extracted features. However, many features are redundant and insignificant. We adopted the Minimum Redundancy Maximum Relevance algorithm (mRMR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> to select appropriate features, which measures statistical dependencies among features.</p><p>Given an initial set of n extracted features</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">F = { f 1 , f 2 , . . . , f n }, where f i refers to the i th feature, mRMR selects k features F * = { f * 1 , f * 2 , . . . , f * k }</formula><p>, which are the least redundant and the most significant. It can be individually formulated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">min R(F * ) = 1 |F * | 2 ∑ f * i , f * j ∈F * f * i ̸ = f * j PMI( f * i ; f * j ) (1) max D(F * , F) = 1 |F * ||F| ∑ f * i ∈F * , f j ∈F f * i ̸ = f j PMI( f * i ; f j )<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where Eq. 1 aims to select independent features, and Eq. 2 aims to select significant features. The point-wise mutual information (PMI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> is applied to measure the redundancy between two features:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">PMI( f i , f j ) = log p( f i , f j ) p( f i )p( f j )<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where p( f i ) refers to the probability that a figure has the feature f i , and p( f i , f j ) denotes the probability that the figure has both f i and f j .</p><p>Statistically, these probabilities can be estimated by the ratio of the figures containing the features. Thus, a higher PMI indicates that the feature pair are more dependent on each other. We optimize both equations by a genetic algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>, which would yield multiple sub-optimal solutions. Each solution contains k features, where k is defaulted at 5 to balance the model complexity and representation capacity. We call each solution a feature group. For every feature f * i in one feature group, the two features with the highest PMIs are provided as the redundant features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Feature Fusion</head><p>The selected k features allow each figure to be represented as a k-dim</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">feature vector v v v = [v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v k ],</formula><p>where v i is the frequency of f i and</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">v i = Nf i</formula><p>Nd , where N fi is the number of the figure's descriptions containing feature f i , and N d is the total number of the figure's descriptions. The concept of a cohort is defined as the fusion of selected features (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">3A6</ref>). It extends the feature group by assigning a fusion weight to each feature. We propose a weakly-supervised classifier to determine whether a figure belongs to the cohort and learn the fusion weights. We calculate the Cohort Score (CS) for each figure v v v, having</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">CS(v v v) = w w w T v v v = k ∑ i=1 w i v i<label>(4)</label></formula><p>where w w w is the fusion weights and w w w = [w 1 , w 2 , . . . , w k ]. The classifier is implemented as a linear regression model for its high interpretability and the continuous outputs for ranking purposes. The initial figures (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3A3</ref>) are the positive training samples. The stochastic gradient descent (SGD) optimizer is adopted in the learning process. A figure's membership in a cohort thus depends on its similarity to the cohort's concept. The higher the cohort score, the more likely the figure belongs to the cohort. To account for a possible mismatch from the extracted features and specified figures, every figure will be reassigned a new label regardless of the initial group specification (T2). A figure with a cohort score over 1.0 is included in the cohort. The one whose cohort score is below 1.0 and over 0.5 is viewed as a candidate, and others are excluded. A new cohort is then identified (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">3A7</ref>) and presented to historians for visual exploration (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3B3</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">VISUAL ANALYTIC SYSTEM</head><p>We propose CohortVA to present the cohort identification results with explanations and to support iterative exploration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Two-stage cohort analysis workflow</head><p>CohortVA, a visual analytics system, follows a two-stage cohort analysis workflow as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2B</ref>. To establish the scope of study (T1), the Scope Specification Component (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3B1</ref>) supports historians in specifying an initial group of figures according to their research interests. The initial group is then piped into the workflow.</p><p>Cohort identification stage. Given a defined group, CohortVA produces a series of cohort candidates using the cohort identification model (T2). The concepts and features of the identified cohort candidates are validated in the Cohort Identification Component (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3B2</ref>) (T3). Historians can compare different concepts and adjust the features' weights in the Cohort Analysis Provenance View. They can also replace certain features with their redundant features in the Cohort Feature Selection View. After validating the concepts, historians select and focus on a cohort candidate for further analysis. Adjustments from either perspective will update the cohort interpretation for the other. Thus, historians can iteratively refine a cohort by piping it back to the Cohort identification stage (T6). The analysis process is recorded in the Cohort Analysis Provenance View for backtracking and testing what-ifs (T7). When the analysis result is satisfactory, historians can export the cohort concept and the list of included figures in CSV format.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Scope Specification Component</head><p>The Scope Specification Component (Fig. <ref type="figure">1A</ref>) provides a control panel for data queries to help historians quickly locate a target figure group.</p><p>Enabling flexible group queries. Four means of figure queries are supported: 1) figures-based query, searching figures by name; 2) ego-network-based query, starting with a core figure and expanding with related figures; 3) condition-based query, picking out figures with common descriptions such as year, location, and identity; and 4) expression-based query, allowing skilled historians to write expressions in the feature representation format (Sect. 4.2) to search for figures, which is most flexible but challenging.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Cohort Identification Component</head><p>The Cohort Identification Component (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>) visualizes the features of the recommended cohorts for historians to select an appropriate cohort and conduct the following exploration. The group features of the search scope and the generated cohort identification schemes are presented in the Cohort Feature Selection view and the Cohort Analysis Provenance view, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.1">Cohort Feature Selection View</head><p>The Cohort Feature Selection View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B1</ref>) interprets all identified features from the initial group as the cohort concept. To facilitate concept understanding, this view depicts each feature's importance, similarity, and overall distribution in feature categories. We encode the features in different channels to make a distinction. Visualizing features in colors, shapes, and thickness. The extracted features could be either atomic or composite (see Sect. 4.2). We use different colors to distinguish the six types of atomic features (i.e., TimeRange, Location, Affiliation, Relationship, Celebrity, and Entity). The composite features combine the colors of their corresponding atomic features. We explicitly encode the number of atomic features by shapes to emphasize the distinction. Specifically, triangles represent atomic features, while squares and circles represent composite features consisting of two and three atomic features, respectively (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>). The border's thickness encodes the feature's weight.</p><p>Justification. We considered three alternative designs. The first one (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>) employs squares to represent atomic features and groups multiple squares to represent composite features. However, composite features with three atomic features occupy too much space and cause visual confusion. We also visualized composite features with gradient colors (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>) and color combinations (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>) of their atomic features. However, the color differences are too small to be perceived and distinguishable. Therefore, we use two visual channels (i.e., shape and color) to enhance the distinction and perception of features.</p><p>Displaying features' similarities. The extracted features are displayed in the force-directed layout. The distance between two features is proportionate to their reciprocal PMI value (see Eq. 3). Therefore, the distance between two features positively correlates with their similarity. If a feature has redundant features, we link them by dashed lines. As well as the graphical representation, a feature list is shown to view features sequentially. In the list, features can be sorted by the count of corresponding figures or the feature's significance (see Eq. 2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.2">Cohort Analysis Provenance View</head><p>The Cohort Analysis Provenance View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B2</ref>) visualizes an overview of multiple identified cohorts and tracks analysis provenance.</p><p>Explaining the cohort concept. The view lists features' descriptions, weights, and the number of related figures). Historians can replace a feature by selecting a redundant feature and clicking the "replace" button in the Cohort Feature Selection View. Each feature's fusion weight can be set via the slider on top of the view.</p><p>Recording exploring iterations. Iterative cohort analysis processes may yield multiple versions of the cohort. For each version, the view summarizes the number of total figures, changed figures, and cohort features for cohort comparisons across iterations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Cohort Exploration Component</head><p>To enhance the interpretability of analysis results, the Cohort Exploration Component (Fig. <ref type="figure">1C</ref>) supports historians in validating cohorts from the model and data perspectives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.1">Cohort Overview</head><p>The Cohort Overview (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5A</ref>) shows the cohort score (see Eq. 4) and the labeling status of all figures in the selected cohort. Considering data scalability issues, historians need to select a sub-group of figures of interest and check their descriptions in the Justification. We tried to encode the figure distribution with colors used in the Cohort Feature Selection (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B1</ref>). However, the multiple colors of composite features did not scale well with the large number of figures, similar to the alternative design in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>. The numerous colors distracted historians from other views, and the limited screen space also poses challenges in distinguishing features. Thus, we unified the features and colored them with different shades of gray. Since the ordering of matrix visualization has an extensive influence on local structure discoveries <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref>, we adopted the Girvan Newman algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, a betweenness-based community detection method, to sort the grids and highlight figures with closer relationships. • Location: The Event Map View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1C3-4</ref>) shows the geographic distribution of all events by circles. The circle size encodes the number of events that happen at a location. Clustered circles highlight the region's importance to the cohort. • Time: The Event Timeline View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1C3-5</ref>) shows the temporal distribution of events. If historians choose a specific year, the detailed information of events happening this year will be displayed for further exploration and validation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Figure Details Component</head><p>The Figure Details Component (Fig. <ref type="figure">1D</ref>) provides historians with detailed descriptions (i.e., background information and hyperlinks to original source) of a selected figure. The figure's identified features are listed in the view for reference. The information helps historians develop an in-depth understanding to make a labeling decision. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">EVALUATION</head><p>We conducted two case studies and eight expert interviews to verify the effectiveness and usefulness of our CohortVA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Case Studies</head><p>We invited the historians mentioned in Sect. 3.2 to explore CohortVA freely according to their research interests and intentions. We encouraged historians to adopt the think-aloud protocol and recorded how they used our system, as described in the following two cases. Cohort identification. To select an appropriate cohort candidate, H4 first observed the cohort feature distribution in the Cohort Feature Selection View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B1</ref>), where several feature clusters appeared. These clusters contained atomic features (e.g., Writings, Neo-Confucian, Zhu Xi) and composite features that are mostly related to Zhu the most famous Neo-Confucianist in the Song dynasty (T2). H4 also noticed an outlier feature Fujian Lu. H4 indicated that this location feature is significant to the Neo-Confucian cohort because 'Zhu Xi' was born and raised in 'Fujian Lu.' Moreover, after 'Zhu Xi' resigned from the government, he ran colleges to preach Neo-Confucianism in 'Fujian Lu' for forty years. Since 'Zhu Xi' was the core figure, H4 further explored the cohort candidate related to Zhu Xi in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B2</ref>. One the five identified features of the cohort candidate is Song Dynasty, which is too coarse to filter effectively. Thus, H4 replaced it with the redundant feature Fujian Lu (T3).</p><p>Cohort exploration. After determining the cohort features, H4 started to validate the features and refine the figures in the Cohort Exploration Component (Fig. <ref type="figure">1C</ref>). In the Cohort Overview (Fig. <ref type="figure">1C1</ref>), H4 re-sorted the figures according to the feature Writings, because authorship was an important characteristic in Neo-Confucianists. Then, H4 screened out the 226 figures with the least cohort scores, and clicked the 'academic' button to observe the writing events that occurred in their lives in the Figure History View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1C3-1</ref>). It turned out that these figures rarely authored writings or participated in academic events, so H4 excluded them from the cohort (T4).</p><p>As shown in the Figure Label View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C2-2</ref>), the figures with the highest cohort scores include several representative Neo-Confucianists, such as 'Zhu Xi,' 'Lu Jiuyuan,' 'Lv Zuqian,' and 'Huang Gan.' However, H4 spotted a few included figures that are not Neo-Confucianists when browsing figure descriptions. For instance, the figure 'Xin Qiji' has not contributed to the spread of Neo-Confucianism theory. 'Xin Qiji' was misidentified due to his close political relationship with 'Zhu Xi,' as shown in the Relationship Matrix View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1C3-3</ref>). H4 manually excluded the figure after validating with the events (T5). To focus on core Neo-Confucianists and reduce cohort size, H4 also excluded 337 less significant figures with less than one hundred events.</p><p>Next, H4 checked the spatio-temporal descriptions of the figures. The Event Map View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1C3-4</ref>) demonstrated that figures in this cohort had recorded events in more than 500 places. Most of the events were clustered in 'Fujian Lu,' which proves the importance of the feature Fujian Lu. In the Event Timeline View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1C3-5</ref>), the time feature 1177,1181 attracted H4's attention due to a sudden surge in events. After hovering over the bar corresponding to the time range, H4 found that all these events involve 'Zhu Xi.' For example, 'Zhu Xi' re-built the Bailudong College <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> (one of the four ancient academies in China) in 1179. H4 considered it a milestone event for the spread of Neo-Confucianism. Iterative exploration. Through the above steps, H4 clicked on the 'update' button in the Cohort Exploration View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1C</ref>), then the system performed the second automatic identification and recommendation in the Cohort Analysis Provenance View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B2</ref>) (T6). New features were selected based on this new cohort. In the Cohort Feature Selection View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B1</ref>), H4 found more interesting features, such as Ritual Texts (the literature embodying Neo-Confucian theories),</p><p>Postface written for book by, and a more precise time feature 1178, 1181 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6A</ref>). H4 added them into the cohort features (T6). H4 checked the recommended figures in the Cohort Exploration View and verified that they align with the cohort concept.</p><p>Lastly, H4 was satisfied with the cohort having 23 core figures and the more precise concept, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6B</ref>. Together with some interesting features in previous iterations (T7), they were exported in CSV format from the Cohort Analysis Provenance View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B2</ref>). H4 would further investigate how these figures spread Neo-Confucianism in the Fujian Province. The exported cohort would be cross-checked with other data sources (e.g., local chronicles in the Intelligent Antiquities Platform <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>) and verified with other research literature.</p><p>This case shows that CohortVA can help historians quickly identify the central figures and important events in the cohort. It provides historians with new perspectives to study the spread of theories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Case2: Explore the Politics in Poetry</head><p>H2 is interested in the history of the Tang Dynasty. In this case, H2 explored the associations around 'Zhang Jiuling,' a famous scholarofficial and poet, and the corresponding social influences.</p><p>Specify the initial cohort of interests. H2 used the figure-based query to choose figures related to 'Zhang Jiuling' in the Scope Specification View (T1). 46 figures were selected from 500K historical figures. Then, in the Cohort Feature Selection View, CohortVA recommended several cohort candidates whose features were mainly political and literary (T2). H2 selected a cohort with the most political and literary features in the Cohort Analysis Provenance View for further exploration (T3). Besides the feature Zhang Jiuling, H2 noticed three identified features of this cohort: 1) Examination indicating that the figures had become bureaucrats through the imperial examinations; 2) Jingzhao reflecting that this group had frequently been active in 'Jingzhao Fu,' the official designation of the Tang's dynastic capital; 3) Presented literary composition as a gift to demonstrating the prevalent literary culture among the cohort (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7A</ref>) (T3).</p><p>Cross-checking and refining the selected cohort. H2 selected the figures with the highest cohort scores and checked their profiles (T5). H2 found that a large proportion of these figures were high-ranking officials. For example, 'Li Longji' and 'Zhang Yue' (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7B1</ref>) were the emperor and the prime minister of the Tang dynasty, respectively. The event distributions in the Figure History View showed that the political and academic events were the most frequent event types (T4). Combined with the relational information in the matrix (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7B3</ref>), H2 concluded that the tight clique of 'Zhang Jiuling' had been deeply associated with academics and politics, especially the political power center of the Tang Dynasty. H2 removed the figures with less than five academic or political events recorded (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7B2</ref>).</p><p>After clicking the 'update' button, the percentage of figures with the feature Examination increased, and a new feature Poet had appeared (T6). In the Relationship Matrix View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7B3</ref>), most of the interactive events about these figures were related to 'Poetry as a gift,' a more precise description than 'literary composition.' From the analysis result, H2 suspected that poets could bond with officials in the Tang Dynasty by presenting poetry. Favored by the officials, these poets could gain an advantage in the imperial examination for selecting state bureaucrats. For example, 'Zhang Jiuling' ingratiated himself with 'Zhang Yue' and 'Li Longji' by writing poems. When he became the prime minister, other poets started writing poems for him as well. Besides, a new feature 710, 712 appeared after the update. Looking at the Event Timeline View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7C</ref>), H2 found that most figures of this cohort gained government positions during this period, where 96 events were recorded. H2 recalled that the Tang Long coup occurred in 710, after which the regime alternation caused significant bureaucratic alternations. After comparing with other cohorts in previous iterations, H2 decided to include this feature (T7).</p><p>Export the exploration results. Finally, H2 exported the exploration results. H2 obtained a refined cohort (consisting of 17 figures) and derived its completed concept as in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7D</ref>. H2 wanted to determine if this cohort was united in their political views. Therefore, he will consult the official documents of the Tang dynasty on The AiRuSheng Platform <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> to further explore the influence of this cohort in politics.</p><p>This case shows that CohortVA enables historians to obtain a more comprehensive understanding of the cohort and discover hidden connections between features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Historian Reviews</head><p>To evaluate the effectiveness of CohortVA, we invited eight historians (i.e., three professors (H1-H3) and five PhDs (H4-H8)) to participate in the interview. We collaborated with H1-H5 for two years, as mentioned in Sect. 3. They participated in multiple design iterations of the CohortVA. Three historians (H6-H8) work on historical research on the Tang, Song, and Ming dynasties, respectively, using CohortVA for the first time. H1-H6 are familiar with the CBDB and digital tools (e.g., Gephi and Netdraw) for historical research. H7 and H8 indicated that they mainly employed paper-based historical documents in their daily research. We interviewed three historians (H1-H3) online. Face-toface interviews were conducted for others (H4-H8). None of the eight participants were co-authors of this manuscript.</p><p>Procedure. Initially, each interviewee was asked to fill out a consent form and a demographic questionnaire about their background. Then, we completed the following steps to collect their comments.</p><p>• Training (20 min). We introduced our motivation, related definitions, the cohort identification model, and visual designs following the visualization introductory description guidelines <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. • Freeform Exploration (45min). We let historians explore our system freely. During the exploration, historians were encouraged to adopt the think-aloud protocol. Their exploration processes were recorded. • Interview (20 min). We asked them to evaluate our system from three aspects, i.e., the effectiveness of the approach, the reliability of the result, and the usability of the system. Effectiveness of the approach. All historians agreed that their research could benefit from the proposed analysis approach. Five historians (H2, H4-H7) pointed out that CohortVA can significantly improve research efficiency. H5 mentioned that they usually missed significant features and made tremendous efforts to re-identify features after initial explorations. Automatic feature extraction can free them from exhausting concept extractions and allow them to focus on other important tasks, like analyzing the causes and effects. H4 said, "CohortVA acts like a reference book that I will refer to at different research stages." Despite the preference for traditional research methodologies, H8 was interested in using CohortVA to explore unfamiliar areas for efficient explorations and inspiration. H3 affirmed the significance of our work and believed that CohortVA is an appropriate teaching tool for history classes. Besides, H2 suggested that our approach should further support comparing multiple cohorts, which would be one of our future works.</p><p>Reliability of the result. Historians must validate the model output before applying the output in historical research. H5 and H7 indicated that the Cohort Exploration Component (Fig. <ref type="figure">1C</ref>) favored them in understanding the extracted cohort features. As mentioned in Sect. 6.1, contextual information helps historians understand why Fujian Lu is included in cohort features. H5 and H6 argued that visual designs and interactions facilitate the connection between interpretation and context. H2 and H4 indicated that adding a hyperlink in the Figure Details Component (Fig. <ref type="figure">1D</ref>) was a great function for checking the original material. H3-H8 pointed out the limitation of a single data source and expressed the wish to introduce more data sources, including user-defined data for cross-checking. Usability of the system. Historians agreed that each view was well-designed. Among all visual forms, historians (H2-H5) considered Event Map View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1C3-4</ref>) to be the easiest to use, believing it has "the most distinct visualization characteristic and the most concise data presentation." H3 suggested providing maps of different historical dynasties to support exploring various research targets. The Event Timeline View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1C3-5</ref>), visualizing events number in each year, was also popular among historians. Although other visualizations, such as the Cohort Feature Selection View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B1</ref>) and the Relationship Matrix View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1C3-3</ref>), require some learning costs for historians unfamiliar with data visualization and analysis, H2 commented on them as being valuable visualization projects, "digital humanities will inevitably be more complex but powerful to support complicated analytical tasks." H4 particularly preferred swift interaction designs, like the filtering and sorting functions in the Cohort Overview View and the tagging function in the Relationship Matrix View. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">DISCUSSION</head><p>This section summarizes the lessons learned from working with historians, as well as the limitations and future work of CohortVA. Through collaborations with historians, we have summarized three design implications for digital humanities (CAD):</p><p>Comprehensibility. Historians prefer easy-to-understand and simple visualizations. Being used to reading a large literature base, they feel more familiar with concrete wordings than abstract visual forms. In our design, we contextualize the generated descriptions with conventional visualizations to simplify the paradigm shifts from reading to perceiving. Moreover, historians are more willing to adopt visualizations that require higher learning costs when presented with clear usage benefits. For example, for the Relationship Matrix View, we used a matrix ordering algorithm to cluster similar groups and encoded relationship types with colors. The efficiency in pattern mining has drawn historians' interest in studying. As H3 indicates, "we can quickly discover the types of social relations between figures through the colors on the matrix, which is very novel." However, visual uncertainty should be used with caution because some historians are conservative about probabilistic inference and favor definite evidence.</p><p>Authenticity. We have identified four ways to enhance historians' trust and confidence in the method, process, result, and data. 1) Reproducing cohorts that agree with existing theories can increase the methods' trustworthiness. It directly verifies functional completeness and correctness. 2) Steering results iteratively give historians more confidence in the process. In CohortVA, historians gradually apply their prior knowledge and expertise to annotate and validate the recommended figures. The smaller gaps between iterations help them infer the different results. H3 highly appreciates the provenance tracking function, "which helps me to trace back and adjust my hypotheses for further research." 3) Providing organized information across various perspectives enhances the result's confidence. Historians emphasize cross-checking the automatic analysis results to reduce biases and misinformation. Displaying and providing access (e.g., hyperlinks) to the original data sources are important features in building trust in the data. Historians value the authenticity of the original textual documents.</p><p>Diversity. Since the ancient documents and historical data span thousands of years, special attention should be paid to the diversity in the underlying spatial and temporal contexts. For spatial contexts, map visualizations should be aware of landscape changes. For example, the Yellow River has undergone six major avulsions (i.e., changes in river's course) in history. Ancient times' regional landscapes and geographical characteristics have notable differences from their modern counterparts. Also, the territorial changes in different dynasties would create trouble recognizing and understanding historical events with modern maps. Therefore, we could provide terrain or historical maps for reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>, as suggested by H2.</p><p>For temporal contexts, besides the missing data and uncertainty issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>, we came across the subtle semantic changes in interpreting entities. For instance, the "Prefectural aide" in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3A2</ref> was represented as "Zhang Shi" in CBDB. From the Qin to Song dynasty, "Zhang Shi" meant the government aide, while it became the administrator from the Yuan dynasty and on <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>. We used composite features to capture these differences implicitly and relied on domain knowledge to spot the difference. H1 suggested that additional knowledge representations could be adopted from existing theories and structured dictionaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> to provide appropriate contexts and reduce ambiguity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Limitations and Future Work</head><p>We outline the current limitations to be addressed in future work.</p><p>Data source. The current system only employs a single data source. Validation with multiple data sources can further strengthen the interpretability of cohort features. In the future, it should combine with other large-scale databases or self-defined knowledge bases. We could define more description templates for knowledge graph completion, but entity alignment is still a challenging problem.</p><p>Cohort comparison. The current system does not provide comprehensive comparisons among cohorts. Analyzing a single cohort limits the research scope and could be biased. Cohort comparison is a complex analysis task we will pursue in our future work.</p><p>Quantitative evaluation. Historians agree that our work can improve their trust in machine learning results, but the claim can benefit from a quantitative evaluation. For example, measuring the decision time and compliance with the recommended results provide viable metrics for comparison with other systems.</p><p>Generalizability. In this work, we mainly cooperated with historians and developed a bespoke tool for them. Due to different requirements, the interface and specific parametric settings cannot be easily applied to other domains. However, the CohortVA workflow is generalizable to domain-specific tasks targeting closely related groups. By properly defining the features, it can process large text corpora and relational databases for many domains, such as medicine <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, finance <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref>, and literature analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref>. For example, social network relationships and social media posts can replace the history corpus in our system for identifying different social groups among users.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this paper, we present CohortVA, an interactive visual analytic system for historians to identify and explore historical cohorts. Given an initial group of figures, the cohort identification model in CohortVA automatically extracts their common features and identifies potential cohorts to improve the efficiency of historians' research. The visual interface of CohortVA provides various supporting information to help historians cross-check these results, fostering trust in the system and a deeper understanding of cohorts. Two case studies and the historian interviews demonstrate the usefulness and effectiveness of our system. We summarized the lessons learned for developing CohortVA and believe that these design implications will guide system designers in dealing with historical data and working with historians.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. A comparison between (A) traditional prosopography workflow and (B) proposed workflow applied in CohortVA.</figDesc><graphic url="image-2.png" coords="3,64.27,516.22,230.73,164.13" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. CohortVA consists of (A) a cohort identification model and (B) a visual interface. We first build (A1) a knowledge graph based on the CBDB and extract (A2) the descriptions. Here, the example from CBDB is translated with [25] to help with the interpretation. Historians specify (A3) the initial figures from (B1) the scope specification component. The figures and extracted descriptions are piped into the model for (A4) feature extraction, (A5) feature selection, and (A6) feature fusion. Then our model automatically identifies (A7) the cohort figures. Generated features and figures are presented in (B2) the cohort identification component, (B3) cohort exploration and figure details component for further interpretation and exploration.</figDesc><graphic url="image-3.png" coords="5,64.23,73.00,472.73,178.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Cohort exploration stage. CohortVA lets historians explore and refine the selected cohort from two perspectives: the cohort concept and included figures. The figures are described by the Cohort Exploration Component and the Figure Details Component (Fig. 3B3). Historians can cross-check the cohort composition according to historical events (T4) and detailed figure descriptions (T5). After validation, CohortVA supports historians in excluding figures from the cohort and including related ones in the Figure Label View.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Cohort Feature Selection View. (A) The encoding scheme for atomic and composite features. (B, C, D) The alternative designs.</figDesc><graphic url="image-4.png" coords="6,64.27,73.00,230.74,114.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure Feature Validation View and the Figure Event Validation View. Summarizing the feature distributions. The view shows the feature distribution of each figure in the selected cohort. The cohort features confirmed by historians in the Cohort Analysis Provenance-View are distinguished in this view by different grayscale values. For a figure, the length of each feature represents the frequency multiplied by the corresponding fusion weight (Sect. 4.4). To focus on a certain feature, historians can sort figures according to the feature's value. Summarizing figure labels. CohortVA employs a multicolored bar to group figures included in the cohort (colored in blue), candidate figures (colored in purple), and excluded figures (colored in pink) on the left of the view. It shows the status of the labeling progress and gives an overview of the labeled figures.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>5. 4 . 2 Figure</head><label>42</label><figDesc>Feature Validation View The Figure Feature Validation View (Fig. 1C2) shows model-related information of the sub-group selected in the Cohort OverviewView in a dual column structure. The Figure Feature View (Fig. 5B) in the left column illustrates a detailed feature distribution. Besides the zoomedin figure distribution, a histogram is employed to reflect the number of figures with each feature. The Figure Label View (Fig. 5C) in the right column lists the labels of each figure. Historians can modify labels and guide the cohort identification model to update the cohort. 5.4.3 Figure Event Validation View The Figure Event Validation View (Fig. 1C3) visualizes the life experience of each figure by demonstrating five categories of events (i.e.., politics, academic, religion, sociality, and military) of concern for historians. We use color encoding to distinguish the five categories. Detailed event descriptions from five perspectives are described below: • Category: Each row in the Figure History View (Fig. 5D) shows the events in a historian-selected category of a figure. The events are visualized by a thin bar, of which the horizontal position encodes the time of the event. A row with dense bars indicates that the corresponding figure was recorded significantly in the category. The time spans of all rows are aligned to support event comparisons. • Frequency: The Event Ranking View (Fig. 5E) shows the total number of events and the top three categories of events ranked by quantity. It provides an overview of the figure's identity characteristics. • Relationships: The Relationship Matrix View (Fig. 5F) employs a 45-degree-rotated matrix to show the relationship among figures. The element in the i th row and j th column represents the events involving the i th and j th figure. The shades of color encode the event quantity.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. The Cohort Exploration component. Historians can shortlist figures from (A) the cohort overview. The (B) figure features, (D) figure history, (E) figure events, and (F) figure relationships views provide supporting information for feature-and event-based validation. After cross-checking from both perspectives, historians can label the figures in the (C) figure label view.</figDesc><graphic url="image-14.png" coords="7,64.28,73.00,472.77,90.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>6. 1 . 1</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Case1: Verify the Neo-Confucianism in Song The research interest of H4 lies primarily in Neo-Confucianism theory in the Song dynasty. To verify the cohort identified by the traditional prosopography workflow, H4 leveraged CohortVA to explore the Neo-Confucian cohort in the Song dynasty. Specify the initial cohort of interests. With clear goals in mind, H4 first initialized the figure group through the conditional queries of 'Song' and 'Neo-Confucianists' in the Scope Specification Component (T1). CohortVA returned 588 figures satisfying the conditions. Then, the cohort identification model (Sect. 4) recommended cohorts in the Cohort Identification Component (Fig. 1B) for further analysis (T2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6. The identified cohort and concept for Case1. (A) An overview of the new features after the first update. (B) The final cohort and concept.</figDesc><graphic url="image-26.png" coords="7,314.16,357.55,230.73,212.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Exploration process. The initial figures and features of Zhang Jiuling (A) were identified. Then H2 explored the political and academical relationships between these figures (B), and noticed an event outburst (C). After an update, H2 obtained the refined cohort concept (D).</figDesc><graphic url="image-38.png" coords="9,64.13,73.00,472.76,111.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic url="image-1.png" coords="1,86.10,166.04,428.97,241.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>to extract the time range feature TimeRange(737) and the Location model for location feature Location(Jingzhou). The two atomic features jointly form the composite feature [TimeRange(737) &amp; Location(Jingzhou)]. In addition, since Zhang Jiuling is a renowned scholar-official (further descriptions in Sect. 6.1.2), he is extracted as the feature Celebrity(Zhang Jiuling). The three atomic features then generate another composite feature [Celebrity(Zhang Jiuling) &amp; TimeRange(737) &amp; Location(Jingzhou)].</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors wish to thank the editors at CBDB for their feedback and contribution to this project. This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 62132017, 61972122), Shanghai Municipal Science and Technology General Program (No. 21ZR1403300) and Sailing Program (No. 21YF1402900).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An economic interpretation of the constitution of the united states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Beard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Historical Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="1913">1913</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="http://dh.ersjk.com/jsp/front/prodlist.jsp" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Beijing Erudition Digital Research Center. Erudition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2022" to="2026" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring lemma interconnections in historical dictionaries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Benito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Therón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Losada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wandl-Vogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</title>
				<meeting>Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Geneaquilts: A system for exploring large genealogies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bezerianos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dragicevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1081" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Gis, prosopography and history</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hartwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">China biographical database project (cbdb)</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Netdraw software for network visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Borgatti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization and the digital humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>El-Assady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Coles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jänicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wrisley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motionrugs: Visualizing collective trends in space and time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Buchmüller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jäckle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cakmak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Brandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glottovis: Visualizing language endangerment and documentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Castermans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hammarström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Speckmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Verbeek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Westenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</title>
				<meeting>Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grounding users in interpretive acts: Lessons learned in the iterative design of a digital collection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Raza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gazula</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mendoza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</title>
				<meeting>Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Big data for the study of qing officialdom: The china government employee database-qing (cged-q)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Chinese History</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="460" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vbridge: Connecting the dots between features and data to explain healthcare models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zytek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Veeramachaneni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114836</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vairoma: A visual analytics system for making sense of places, times, and events in roman history</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sauda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Word association norms, mutual information, and lexicography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Church</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Linguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of overlapping community detection algorithms in social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Devi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Procedia Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chinese smart ancient book platform</title>
		<ptr target="https://csab.zju.edu.cn" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2022" to="2026" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Digital Humanities Research Center, Zhejiang University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">metapath2vec: Scalable representation learning for heterogeneous networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Chawla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Swami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</title>
				<meeting>the ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="144" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ipoet: interactive painting poetry creation with visual multimodal analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confidence as first-class attribute in digital humanities data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Franke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barczok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weltecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</title>
				<meeting>IEEE Workshop on Visualization for the Digital Humanities</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenostacks: Cross-sectional cohort phenotype comparison visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Glueck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gvozdik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chevalier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brudno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wigdor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Gephi: Introduction to network analysis and visualisation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grandjean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Worldmap-a geospatial framework for collaborative research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bertrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Blossom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of GIS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Parsad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O.-S</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Son</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hisva: a visual analytics system for learning history. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A dictionary of official titles in imperial china</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Hucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The &quot;loyalist problem&quot; in the early republic: Naturalization, navigation and the cultural solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Iggulden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1783" to="1850" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of New Hampshire</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jeffreys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Papacostas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Short</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vetch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Prosopography of the byzantine world (pbw). King&apos;s</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>College London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visual profiling of musicians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jänicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Focht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dbscan: Past, present and future</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Rehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Aziz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sarasvady</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of The Fifth International Conference on the Applications of Digital Information and Web Technologies</title>
				<meeting>The Fifth International Conference on the Applications of Digital Information and Web Technologies</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="238" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An interactive chart of biography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Khulusi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kusnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Focht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jänicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</title>
				<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="266" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Random walk: a modern introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lawler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Limic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Taxthemis: Interactive mining and exploration of suspicious tax evasion groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2020.3030370</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="849" to="859" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genealogyvis: A system for visual analysis of multidimensional genealogical data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Human-Machine Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="873" to="885" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community structure in social and biological networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E J N M</forename><surname>Girvan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7821" to="7826" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cohort comparison of event sequences with balanced integration of visual analytics and statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Monroe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Onukwugha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces</title>
				<meeting>the International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="49" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feature selection based on mutual information criteria of max-dependency, max-relevance, and minredundancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1226" to="1238" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating prior knowledge in mixed-initiative social network clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Buono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Valdivia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1775" to="1785" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bladder runner: Visual analytics for the exploration of rt-induced bladder toxicity in a cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Raidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Casares-Magaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Amirkhanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Moiseenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Muren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Einck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vilanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="216" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The cohort as a concept in the study of social change</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ryder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On historical gazetteers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Southall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mostern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Berman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3366/ijhac.2011.0028</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Prosopography. Daedalus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative historical analysis uncovers a single dimension of complexity that structures global variation in human social organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Turchin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Whitehouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Franc ¸ois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Feeney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mullins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hoyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grohmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Savage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="E144" to="E151" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>University</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sinica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>University</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">China biographical database (cbdb)</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019-04">April 2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous matrix orderings for graph collections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Van Beusekom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Meulemans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Speckmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114773</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">If you build it, will we come? large scale digital infrastructures as a dead end for digital humanities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Zundert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Historical Social Research/Historische Sozialforschung</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visual exploration of longitudinal historical career mobility data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2021.3067200</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">01</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1" />
			<date>mar 5555</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seek for success: A visualization approach for understanding the dynamics of academic careers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-Q</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114790</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analyse different characteristics of bailudong college during the north and south song dynasty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Weihan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Journal of Suihua University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A genetic algorithm tutorial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Whitley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Statistics and Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">American political histories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wilentz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>OAH Magazine of History</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="27" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Explaining with examples lessons learned from crowdsourced introductory description of information visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2021.3128157</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual storytelling of song ci and the poets in the social-cultural context of song dynasty</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Visual Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual reasoning for uncertainty in spatio-temporal events of historical figures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new perspective on the study of literature (songci): Text correlation and spatio-temporal visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3724/SP.J.1089.2019.17970</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computer-Aided Design &amp; Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iterative cohort analysis and exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="307" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new clustering method and its application in social networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognition Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2109" to="2118" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
