<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Probablement, Wahrscheinlich, Likely ? A Cross-Language Study of How People Verbalize Probabilities in Icon Array Visualizations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Noëlle</forename><surname>Rakotondravony</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yiren</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lane</forename><surname>Harrison</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Rakotondravony</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Probablement, Wahrscheinlich, Likely ? A Cross-Language Study of How People Verbalize Probabilities in Icon Array Visualizations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2023-03-27T09:20+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Visualization</term>
					<term>Cross-Language Study</term>
					<term>Icon-Arrays</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Visualizations today are used across a wide range of languages and cultures. Yet the extent to which language impacts how we reason about data and visualizations remains unclear. In this paper, we explore the intersection of visualization and language through a cross-language study on estimative probability tasks with icon-array visualizations. Across Arabic, English, French, German, and Mandarin, n = 50 participants per language both chose probability expressionse.g. likely, probable -to describe icon-array visualizations (Vis-to-Expression), and drew icon-array visualizations to match a given expression (Expression-to-Vis). Results suggest that there is no clear one-to-one mapping of probability expressions and associated visual ranges between languages. Several translated expressions fell significantly above or below the range of the corresponding English expressions. Compared to other languages, French and German respondents appear to exhibit high levels of consistency between the visualizations they drew and the words they chose. Participants across languages used similar words when describing scenarios above 80% chance, with more variance in expressions targeting mid-range and lower values. We discuss how these results suggest potential differences in the expressiveness of language as it relates to visualization interpretation and design goals, as well as practical implications for translation efforts and future studies at the intersection of languages, culture, and visualization. Experiment data, source code, and analysis scripts are available at the following repository: https://osf.io/g5d4r/.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We tested a total of 18 probability expressions Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1</ref>: An overview of our cross-language study consisting of two experiments. In (a) Expression-to-Vis, we explore how people draw icon-array visualizations when given particular probability expressions, showing 95% CIs mean responses across Arabic, English, French, German, and Mandarin. In (b) Vis-to-Expression we investigate how people choose probability expressions to describe icon-array visualizations depicting different values. 95% CIs show the icon-array ranges to which each expression was assigned by participants, across the studied languages.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>and citizens on social media share and discuss visualizations in their native languages. Global challenges highlight the importance of better understanding of the interplay of language, culture, and visualization. Climate change, pandemics, and misinformation-all will require a global collective engagement with data to navigate.</p><p>English remains the dominant language in the study and practice of visualization, but the landscape is changing. Creators from diverse languages and cultures are producing more visualizations, in part due to better access to visualization authoring tools and publishing ecosystems.</p><p>International newsrooms are producing visualization-laden journalism, Efforts in Human-Computer Interaction show how effects of language and culture might emerge in visualization. Several HCI studies and design guidelines that focus on WEIRD populations (Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich, and Democratic) have failed to generalize when considering other languages and cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[42]</ref>. Other studies have shown that HCI design processes can successfully integrate language and culture as an influence for interaction mechanisms and interface design <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13]</ref>. More broadly, some research agendas have included multicultural populations and their needs from the outset <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[37]</ref>. These findings raise questions for the visualization community: to what extent do studies centering on WEIRD populations generalize to broader global populations? Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>: Results from Kent's survey of 23 intelligence officers. Each dot is a probability assigned to an expression. The shaded areas indicate scale ranges that Kent proposed for the verbal expressions <ref type="bibr">[2]</ref>. For comparison, we superimpose the shaded areas on our results, see Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>.</p><p>There are comparatively few studies examining language and culture in visualization. A notable exception is Kim et al.'s study of color names across languages <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[24]</ref>, which found that some languages have more distinct names within certain color ranges, potentially influencing visualization color palette design. Related to visualization, studies have found that different languages and culture impact the use of color <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[19]</ref>, and visual forms of how people represent time <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[15]</ref>.</p><p>Studies focusing on language and statistics offer a promising means for exploring visualization across languages. In a widely replicated study, Kent showed that intelligence analysts gave different numerical estimations to the probability expressions used in intelligence reports, such as "likely" or "almost certain" <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref> (see Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Later studies examined probability expressions across languages. Renooij and Witteman elicited numerical values for probability expressions with Dutch speakers <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>. Doupnik et al. studied how German and English-speaking accountants interpret verbal probability expressions in International Accounting Standards, finding significant differences depending on language <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[10]</ref>. Recently, visualization researchers Henkin and Turkay extended similar methodologies to study expressions related to correlation estimation, concluding with an explicit call to examine possible effects across languages <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, we explore the intersection of languages, probability expressions, and visualization. Extending the expression-to-probability methodologies of Kent [23], Renooij and Witteman <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>, and others, we have participants specify values given an expression by drawing icon-array visualizations. We then invert this procedure by having participants choose expressions for a given icon-array visualization, for a two-part randomized within-subjects study. We collect expressions from prior studies, resolving issues like phrase asymmetry, ending with a list of n = 18 base expressions in English. To extend to other languages, specifically French, German, Arabic, and Mandarin, we recruit native speakers in each language for a collaborative translation activity, using inter-coder agreement measures to finalize a set of translations. Using the crowdsourcing platform Prolific, n = 250 participants (n = 50 native speakers for each language) completed both Vis-to-Expression and Expression-to-Vis sections.</p><p>Results suggest that people vary in how they visualize a given probability expression, with differences both within and across languages. Across languages, participants appear to agree more (i.e. the response ranges are tighter) when given expressions that indicate higher and lower probability values, such as very good chance and highly unlikely. Exceptions exist between languages, however, with some expressions producing substantially different value ranges from corresponding expressions in other languages, see Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>. People also vary in how they choose expressions when given an icon-array visualization. In Arabic for example, participants chose 15/18 possible expressions when given an icon-array depicting a 40% chance, compared to 7/18 expressions for Mandarin-speaking participants, see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>. Additional analyses between experiments reveal differences in elicitation method, where people across languages tended to draw values for a given expression that were more extreme, while less extreme values were common when expressions were chosen for a given icon-array, see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">10</ref>.</p><p>Taken together, the experiments and results reveal substantial differences in the expressiveness of translated language as it relates to how people interpret visualizations. We discuss these findings, and how such differences may impact aspects of the visualization design process, particularly as it relates to communication or visualization translation efforts. Among other findings, we contribute:</p><p>• Evidence of no clear mapping between drawn visualizations and probability expressions across languages, suggesting crosslanguage differences, see Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>. • Results suggesting that different languages can exhibit varying degrees of expressiveness for associated icon-array visualizations, see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">9</ref>. • Cross-language experiment materials in 5 languages and datasets reflecting judgments of n = 250 participants, including 4,500 Expression-to-Vis, and 4,750 Vis-to-Expression judgments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">BACKGROUND</head><p>In crafting an experiment targeting estimative probability expressions spanning multiple languages, we draw on methodologies from studies on statistics and language, as well as considerations from cross-cultural studies in the HCI community. For design choices related to the iconarray visualizations, we refer to several visualization studies using icon-arrays in various contexts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Probability Expression Interpretation</head><p>Numerical formats can facilitate probability comparison <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[46]</ref>. Yet because probability is not understood in the same way by everyone, studies have shown that numbers can provide illusory precision <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref>.</p><p>Other studies have shown that people sometimes prefer to communicate uncertainty using verbal expressions in conversation <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[48]</ref>. These verbal expressions of probability, however (e.g. "highly likely, probable"), can be interpreted differently. In a survey of 23 intelligence officers, Kent found variation in the numerical values and ranges that participants assigned to probability expressions that were commonly used in intelligence reports [23]. Kent's work is an early study of the interpretation of probability expressions, and highlighted the uneven relationship between the meaning that a communicator intends and the meaning that the audience may perceive (see Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>). We aim to see if this effect can be found for visualizations of similar values, and whether different patterns are found in languages beyond English. Empirical studies on the numerical estimation of probability expressions have used elicitation methods comprising word-to-number translations <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref>, number-to-word conversion <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[36]</ref>, and rank ordering of expressions <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">38]</ref>. In these studies, probability expressions are generally studied by giving people probabilistic outcomes for specific scenarios. Results from these studies have isolated several potential factors that may impact how people understand, assess, and communicate probabilistic data. For example, the combination of verbal and numerical formats like percentage, frequency or numerical range, have been shown to aid peoples' probabilistic reasoning <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">48]</ref>. Other studies have explored factors related to culture and language. Doupnik and Richter find that German accountants' interpreted probability expressions in international accounting standards as reflecting significantly lower values than that of their American counterparts <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[11]</ref>. Follow up studies have speculated that this may reflect differences in cultural values where German accountants express more conservatism and stronger risk-avoidance <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">9]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Uncertainty Visualization and Icon-Arrays</head><p>Visual depictions of probability are widely considered to be effective in communicating uncertainty, aiding audiences of different backgrounds to improve decisions, trust and judgment <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">41]</ref>. Today, uncertainty visualization is widely studied and applied in both scientific domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[5]</ref> and in communication with general audiences <ref type="bibr">[22]</ref>. One of the most common approaches in uncertainty visualizations implements frequency framing, in which the probabilistic information are displayed in frequency or ratio format <ref type="bibr">[40]</ref>. In a frequency-based representation, the chance of occurrence of an event is shown as a part-to-whole proportion, considered to align better with how people naturally think of probability <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">44]</ref>. Studies have found that uncertainty visualizations using frequency formats tend to be effective in communicating risks, especially for people with low numeracy <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">50]</ref>.</p><p>The icon-array is a common visualization type that implements frequency framing. Icon-arrays typically include one shape (or icon) repeated a number of times, with some of the shapes colored or otherwise marked to represent a proportion (e.g. 35/100). Several studies have shown that icon-arrays are an effective method for communicating risk, such as simple ratio-based probability values <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[33]</ref>. This part-towhole representation of proportion reflects the frequency of events and chances, providing a visual affordances for audiences with different statistical and visualization experience to grasp. Studies have identified potential additional benefits of icon arrays including increased accuracy risk estimation tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[31]</ref>, reduced denominator neglect <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[17]</ref>, and better understanding of medical risk severity <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>.</p><p>In this study, we identify a direct connection between probability expressions from studies that focus on statistics and language, and iconarray visualizations. Building on icon-array designs used in prior work, we use 10x10 icon arrays and similar encoding methods, following studies by Kreuzmair et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[26]</ref>, Bancilhon et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, Garcia-Retamero et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[17]</ref>, and Galesic et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Visualizations, Text, and Language</head><p>While there is little prior work in visualization across languages and culture, topics of visualizations and text or visualizations and natural language provide perspectives that inform the current work. Verbal, text-based answers visualization tasks are a common methodology, from Cleveland and McGill's graphical perception experiment where people specify a text-based answer <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[8]</ref>, to open-ended conversational methodologies such as Peck et al.'s study of visualization perceptions in a local farmer's market <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[35]</ref>. Visualization is also considered in context with the text that surrounds it, for example Ottley et al. combined text and visualizations for Bayesian reasoning tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[32]</ref>. Kong et al. show that the text surrounding a visualization impacts how people engage with the visualization itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[25]</ref>.</p><p>The alignment between the perception of data through visualization and the language used to talk about the data has been sought by researchers who investigate the expressiveness of data visualizations.</p><p>In their study of the "Words of Estimative Correlation", Henkin and Turkay analyzed utterances and verbal descriptions from experiment participants to find how people reason and talk about different levels of correlation seen in scatter-plot visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>. Their study highlights variations between how people use correlation terms to describe a visualizations and how they actually choose to visualize the terms or phrases. Drawing on this and other prior work, we focus on language in the sense of probability expressions, translating them across multiple languages, and determining how people associate these expressions with icon-array visualizations (and vice versa).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Studies Across Languages and Culture in HCI</head><p>Studies in human-computer interaction have investigated the impact of languages and culture on interface design and user behavior. In an online experiment, Baughan et al. found differences in how Japanese and American participants navigate websites, leading to concrete guidelines in which information might be presented across cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[3]</ref>. Similarly, Evers showed that peoples' understanding of a graphical interface can be influenced by their cultural experience and language, with implications for interface metaphor design and interpretation <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13]</ref>. Examining the transferability of primarily Western models of design in African contexts, Winschiers and Bidwell conduct information design activities with indigenous populations in South Africa and Namibia. Their findings surface Afro-centric paradigms which can shape interface design, with themes including cultural values such as interconnectedness, spirituality, and language used through oral and performed communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[47]</ref>. More closely related to visualization, Gibson et al. analyzed the World Color Survey in 110 languages and show that the number of color names are related to how often colors are used within a given culture. They also noted an effect of industrialization, where color becomes an essential part of the identification of objects, impacting how well people identify and name certain colors <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[19]</ref>.</p><p>While it can be argued that computer interfaces are more widely distributed throughout languages and cultures than data visualizations, visualization appears to be on the rise as well. These findings in human-computer interaction suggest that the visualization community could be doing more to question its assumptions about the universality of approaches and guidelines, particularly as data becomes more global. We aim to take another step towards this goal by designing a study-similar in spirit to the internationalized HCI-focused studies of LabintheWild <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[37]</ref>-to examine probability expressions in relation to icon-array visualizations, across multiple languages. Designing a cross-language visualization study requires addressing several challenges, primarily centered around translation, but also typical concerns such as participant scenarios/prompts, visual encoding design, and interaction. We begin with a baseline methodology, extended from probability expression studies including Kent [23], Renooij and Witteman <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>, and Henkin and Turkay's study in the visualization community <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>. These inform two experiments described here that investigate (1) how people visually represent a given expression through icon-arrays, across multiple languages and (2) how people across languages choose expressions to describe a particular icon-array. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> shows an overview of our experiment methodology. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">METHODOLOGY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Participant Prompts/Context</head><p>In general, studies targeting probabilistic reasoning and uncertainty give participants a specific context that defines the nature of the task. Such framings are known to impact peoples' behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[45]</ref>. Visualization studies have explored a range of scenarios, from the relatively neutral "when is my bus coming?" [22] to the charged "what is the chance that someone has cancer?" <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[32]</ref>. Because studies have found that language and culture can impact how people perceive risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[10]</ref>, we adapt a neutral context of a game which we introduce at the beginning of each experiment as follows:</p><p>You are participating in a game which consists of drawing a tile from a set at random. Some of the tiles are orange, and some are gray. The game has two possible outcomes:</p><p>-You draw an orange tile and you win a prize -You draw a gray tile and you do not win a prize </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Selecting and Translating Probability Expressions</head><p>Inèstudiesètargetingèlanguageèandèstatistics,èvariousèrangesèofèprobabilityèexpressionsèhaveèbeenèused.èForèexample,èKentèbeganèwithèfiveè andèexpandedètoè16è[23],èwhileèRenooijèandèWittemanèuseètheèsevenè expressionsèmostèsuggestedèbyètheèstudyèparticipantsè <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>.èMethodsè forècollectingèexpressionsèincludeèscanningèpriorèliterature,èelicitingè expressionsèfromèstudyèparticipantsè <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>,èandèborrowingèfromèspecificè documentsè <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">11]</ref>.èWhileèstudiesèhaveèexaminedèaspectsèofèestimativeè probabilityèexpressionsèinèotherèlanguages,èsuchèasèDutchè <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>èandèGermanè <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[10]</ref>,èweèdidènotèidentifyècomprehensiveèexpressionèlistsèforèallèourè targetèlanguages.èWeèbeganèwithèKent'sèoriginalèlistèofè16èexpressions,è asètheyèhaveèbeenèadaptedèacrossèseveralèstudies,è(e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">36]</ref>).è Throughèpilotèstudies,èweèidentifiedètwoèambiguitiesèthatèimpactedètheè symmetryèofètheèlist.èWeèaddè"chancesèlessèthanèeven"èaècomplementè toè"chancesèbetterèthanèeven"èandè"implausible"ètoèmatchè"plausible".è Asèaèresult,èforèthisèstudy,èweèuseèaèlistèofè18èexpressions,èandèprovideè optionsèforèparticipantsètoèspecifyètheirèownèifènoneèfitèwhatètheyèwouldè preferètoèchooseèduringètheèVis-to-Expression experiment.è OurègoalèwasètoèconductètheèstudyèinèEnglish,èFrench,èGerman,èMandarin,èandèArabic.èForèeachèlanguage,èweèrecruitedèthreeèindependentè translatorsèwhoèwereènativeèspeakersè(US,èFrance,èGermany,èChina,è SaudièArabia,èandèTunisia),èandèalsoèfluentèinèEnglish.èToèmitigateètheè potentialèforèliteralè(word-by-word)ètranslation,èweèremindedètranslatorsè toèconsiderètheèstudyèscenarioèduringètranslation,èandètoèprovideètermsè theyèwouldèuseèinètheirènativeèlanguageèwithinètheègivenècontext.è Toèmeasureèagreement,èweèuseèinter-raterèreliabilityèmetricsè(e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[29]</ref>)èandècalculateètheèFleiss'èKappaèκ valuesè <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[14]</ref>èforètheètranslations.è Whileèκ French = 0.55,èandèκ German = 0.585èareèsimilar,èκ Mandarin = 0.187èandèκ Arabic = 0.341èareèlowerèinèagreement.èInètermsèofècounts,è theènumberèofèexpressionsèforèwhichèallè3ètranslatorsèdisagreeèincludeè disag f rench = 3,èdisag german = 1,èdisag mandarin = 8,èandèdisag arabic = 4.è Theènumbersèofèexpressionsèforèwhichèallètranslatorsèagreedèareè ag f rench = 8,èag german = 8,èag mandarin = 1,èandèag arabic = 3.è GivenètheèhighèlevelsèofèdisagreementèinèMandarinè(i.e. onlyè9/18è expressionsèhadètwoèpeopleèagreeing),èweèengagedènativeèspeakersèforè possibleèexplanations.èOneèpotentialèreasonèthatèaroseèfromèthisèdiscussionèisèthatèaègroupèofèexpressionsèinètheèsourceèlanguageè(English)ècanè mapètoèaègroupèofèexpressionsèinèMandarinèinèanèinterchangeableèway.è Forèinstance,è{"probable",è"likely"}èandè{"improbable",è"unlikely",è "probablyènot"}èwereètranslatedètoèMandarinèasè{可能, 很可能, 大 概,也许}èandè{不太可能, 可能不会, 未必}.èInèsuchècases,èpersonalè preferencesèmightèplayèaèroleèinèword/phraseèselection.è Nextèweèresolveèdisagreementsèinètheètranslation.èInècasesèwhereè twoèagree,èweètakeètheèmajorityèasètheèfinalèexpression.è Whenèallè translatorsèdisagree,èweèuseèaèmediationèprocedureèuntilèagreementsè areèreachedèaboutètheèexpressionsè <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[29]</ref>.èHowever,èprovidingèaèsingleè translationètoèeachèEnglishèexpressionèwasènotèalwaysèfeasible.èForèexample,è"unlikely"èandè"improbable"èwereèbothèrepeatedlyètranslatedèasè "unwahrscheinlich"èinèGerman,èandè"probablyènot"èandè"improbable"è wereèbothètranslatedèasè inèArabic.èInètheseècases,èweè reduceètheènumberèofèexpressionsèinètheètargetèlanguage,èandèmarkèthemè accordinglyèinèresults.èOverall,èweèexpectèthatèsomeèofètheseèdifferencesè andèsimilaritiesèinèlanguagesèwillèbeèreflectedèinètheèexperimentèresults.è Tableè1èshowsètheèfinalèlistèofèprobabilityèexpressionsèusedèinèthisèstudyè withètheirètranslationsèinèFrench,èGerman,èArabic,èandèMandarin.è</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Visual Encodings for the Icon-Arrays</head><p>Visualizationèstudiesèhaveèsuggestedèthatètheètypeèandèarrangementè ofèanèicon-arrayècanèimpactèreaderèperceptionèandèengagementèwithè theèunderlyingèdataè <ref type="bibr">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">50]</ref>.èToèalignèwithètheèscenarioèdescribedèinè ourèstudy,èweèuseèaè10èxè10ègridèofèsquareèicons,èaètypicalèratioèinè theèliteratureèforèproblemsèwithèaèpopulationèofè100èitemsè(usedèinè e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[32]</ref>èandè <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[49]</ref>)è.èColorèisèusedètoèdenoteèiconsèrepresentingèdifferentè outcomesèinètheèeventèofèinterest:è Drawing an orange square and winning a prize,èandèiconsèwereèarrangedèconsecutively.è</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Participants and Procedure</head><p>StudyèparticipantsèwereèrecruitedèusingètheèonlineèplatformèProlific.è Participantsèmustèhaveètheètargetèlanguageèofètheèexperimentèdefinedè asètheirènativeèlanguageèinètheirèProlificèprofile,èandècouldèonlyètakeè theèexperimentèonce.èInèeachèstudy,èVis-to-ExpressionèandèExpressionto-Visèwereèassignedèinèrandomèorder,èwhereèhalfèofètheèparticipantsè seeèExperimentè1èfirstèwhileètheèotherèhalfèseeèExperimentè2èfirst.è50è participantsèwereèrecruitedèforèeachèversionèofètheèstudy,èmakingèaè totalèofè250èparticipantsèforèallèlanguages.èParticipantsèwereèpaidè$1.90è basedèonèpilotèstudiesèestimatingèaè10-15èminuteècompletionètime,èandè followingèProlificèplatformèguidelines.èPayèwasèfixed,èi.e. itèwasènotè impactedèbyèparticipantèchoicesèorèperformanceèinètheèexperiment.è</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">EXPERIMENT 1: EXPRESSION-TO-VIS, FROM PROBABILITY EXPRESSIONS TO ICON-ARRAYS</head><p>Inèthisèexperiment,èweèaimètoèunderstandèhowèpeopleèvisualizeèprobabilityèexpressionsèthroughèiconèarrays,èandèhowèthatèvariesèacrossèEnglish,è French,èGerman,èMandarin,èandèArabic.èUnlikeèexistingèstudiesèaboutè numericalèestimationèofèprobabilityèexpressions,èweèaskèparticipantsètoè representètheirèestimationsègraphically.è </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Results</head><p>Inètotal,èweècollectedè4,400èanswersèfromèparticipantsèacrossèEnglish,è French,èGerman,èMandarin,èandèArabic.è Becauseèthereèwereètwoè instancesèwhereètranslatorsèagreedèaboutèaè2-to-1èmappingèfromèanè Englishèexpressionètoètheètargetèlanguages,èweèduplicateètheseèconfidenceèintervalsèandèperformèstatisticalècomparisonsèseparatelyèforè each.èTheseèincludeètheèentriesèforèunwahrscheinlichèforètheèEnglishè expressionsè"unlikely"èandè"improbable",èandè forètheè Englishèexpressionsè"probablyènot"èandè"improbable".è Figureè5èshowsèbootstrappedè95%èconfidenceèintervalsèofètheèmeansè forèallèexpressionsèacrossètheèfiveèlanguages.è Thereèappearsètoèbeè generalèalignmentèwithèKent'sèsuggestedèranges,èthoughèsomeèsuchè asèhighlyèlikelyèandèimprobableèdeviateèsomewhat.èThisèmayèbeèdueè toèsampleèdifferences,èi.e. Kentèstudiedè23èintelligenceèanalystsèinè theè1960s.èMoreègenerally,èweènoticeèseveralèdifferencesèforèaègivenè expressionèacrossèlanguages.èForèexample,èvisualizationsèdrawnèforèexpressionsèaligningèwithè"likely",è"probable"èandè"probably"èinèFrench,è German,èMandarinèandèArabicèdeviateèlowerèthanèEnglish,èinèsomeè casesèbelowètheè50%èmark.è Whileèweègenerallyèalignèourèanalysesèwithèrecommendationsèinètheè VISèandèHCIècommunitiesètoèmoveèbeyondèdichotomousèstatisticsè <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12]</ref>,è weèprovideèstatisticalècomparisonsèhereètoègoèalongèwithèanalysisèshownè inèFigureè6.èOurèaimèisètoèidentifyèexpressionsèthatèareèsubstantiallyè aboveèorèbelowètheèassociatedèEnglishètranslations.èWhileècomparisonsè betweenèotherèlanguagesèareèpossible,èweèfocusèonèEnglishèsinceètheè expressionsèwereèoriginallyètranslatedèfromèEnglish.è Analyzingètheèbetween-languageèvarianceèofèparticipant-drawnèvisualizationsèwithèaèone-wayèANOVA,èweèfindèthatèonlyèfiveèexpressionsè doènotèshowèatèleastèoneèsignificantèdifferenceèacrossètheèfiveèlanguages.è Theseèstableèexpressionsèincludeè"plausible"è(andèitsètranslations:è"plausible",è"plausibel",è" ",è"貌似可信"),è"almostècertain"è(presqueè certain,èziemlichèsicher, , 几乎确定 ),è"chancesèaboutèeven"è (chancesèàèpeuèprèsèégales,èungefährègleicheèChancen,è ,è 大约一半),è"probablyènot"è(probablementèpas,èwahrscheinlichènicht, , 可能不会),èandè"almostènoèchance"è(presqueèaucuneè chance,èfastèChancenlos,è , 几乎没概率).è </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>‫املحتمل‬ ‫من‬</head><p>Examples where the interpretations of the proposed translations are significantly lower than the English expression "likely"</p><p>Comparison centered around the mean value for English</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Expression-to-vis</head><p>‫املحتمل‬ ‫غري‬ ‫من‬ ‫املحتمل‬ ‫غري‬ ‫من‬ Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>: 95% confidence intervals for differences in mean of English expressions and their translations. Values are centered on the mean value in English. Intervals on the left indicate that the mean value for an expression is lower than its associate in English. We label translations that are significantly misaligned with the English expressions. In German, entries for "unlikely" and "improbable" are duplicated (they repeatedly translated as the same German unwahrscheinlich); similarly in Arabic , entries for "improbable" and "probably not" are duplicated (they are translated in the same Arabic expression ).</p><p>To further analyze differences between languages, we use Tukey posthoc tests to identify pairs where the expressions significantly differ from English. All reported confidence intervals are bootstrapped 95% CIs. In French, we find two deviating expressions: possible (mean: -20.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[43]</ref>.öTheseöincludeö51%öofötotalöanswersöforöEnglish,ö54%öforöFrench,ö 52%öforöGerman,ö45%öforöArabic,ö48%öforöMandarin.öThisöpatternö alsoöalignsöwithöpreviousöresultsöwhereöpeopleötendöprovideönumericalö estimationsöthatöareömultiplesöofö10öforöverbalöprobabilitiesö <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">39]</ref>ö(seeö Figureö7)ö Weöcanöalsoöviewöeachöbaseöexpressionöfromötheöperspectiveöoföitsö rangeöacrossölanguages,öseeöFigureö7.öForöexample,öalthoughöthereöisö noöparticularöpatternöacrossötheöfiveölanguagesöforötheöexpressions,ötheö Mandarinötranslationöofö"implausible"öshowsötheölargestöIQRöwithö91%,ö asöwellöasöaöbimodalödistributionöoföresponses.öExpressionsöwithönarrowö rangesösuggestöthat,öacrossöassociatedöexpressionsöinöotherölanguages,ö participantsöwillödrawösimilarörangesöinöicon-arrays.öAnotheröpatternö isöthatöexpressionsönearöextremeölow/highöandöcenterövaluesöappearö toöhaveösmalleröinterquartileöranges.öExpressionsöatötheöextremesöareö consistentlyöevaluated,öwhileömid-rangeöexpressionsö(butönotöcentral)ö mayöconveyölessöpreciseöestimatesöoföprobability.ö</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">EXPERIMENT 2: VIS-TO-EXPRESSION, FROM ICON-ARRAYS TO PROBABILITY EXPRESSIONS</head><p>ThisöexperimentöisöessentiallyöanöinversionöoföExperimentö1.öHere,ö weöaimötoöunderstandöhowöpeopleöchooseöprobabilityöexpressionsötoö describeöaögivenöicon-arrayövisualization.ö</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Procedure</head><p>Usingötheösameöneutralöscenario,öparticipantsöareögivenöanöicon-arrayö oföaöspecificövalue,öalongöwithöaölistöoföprobabilityöexpressionsö(seeö Figureö8.ö Participantsöareöaskedötoöselectötheöexpressionöthatötheyö believeöbestödescribesötheöicon-arrayöshown.öExpressionölistsöconsistö ofö18öexpressionsöinöEnglish,öFrench,öandöMandarin,ö17öexpressionsöinö German,öandöArabic.öParticipantsöareöalsoöencourageötoöprovideötheirö ownöanswer,öifödesired.öToöcoverötheöprobabilityöspace,öweöencodeö19ö valuesöbetweenö5%ötoö95%öwithöaöstepöofö5%.öForöeachötrial,öweöcollectö theöpairö{icon-arrayövalue,öselectedöprobabilityöexpression}.ö </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Results</head><p>Inötotal,öweöcollectö4,750öicon-arrayötoöexpressionöpairsöfromöparticipantsöacrossötheöfiveölanguagesö(50öparticipantsöperölanguage).öIconö arraysöacrossöstepsöofö5%öareödescribedöfiftyötimesöbyöparticipants,öeitheröbyöselectingöanöexpressionöfromötheösuggestedölist,öoröbyötypingö theiröanswers.öSimilarötoöExpression-to-Vis,öweöduplicateöentriesöforö expressionsöthatömapötoötwoöexpressionsöinöEnglish.öTheseöincludeö inöArabicöandöunwahrscheinlichöinöGerman.öResultsöforö Vis-to-ExpressionöareöshownöinöFigureö9.ö TheöupperöbarögraphöinöFigureö9öshowsötheöcountöoföuniqueöexpressionsöforöeachöicon-arrayövalue.öAcrossölanguages,öthereöappearsötoö beöconsistencyöinöthatöhigherövaluesö(90%,öandö95%)öareödescribedö usingöfeweröuniqueöexpressions.öThisömayöreflectöaömoreöconsistentö expressivenessöofölanguagesöoföprobabilityöexpressionsöinöhigheröranges.ö However,ögivenötheöaverageöcountsöacrossöallövalueöpossibilities,öitöisö clearöthatöfew,öiföanyöperfectömatchesöoföprobabilityöexpressionsöandö visualizationöexists.ö Arabicöhasötheöhighestöaverageönumberöoföuniqueöexpressions.öOnö average,ö10.89öexpressionsö(stdvö=ö2)öwereöusedötoödescribeöeachöprobabilityövalue.ö Foröexample,öforöicon-arraysöofö40%,öparticipantsöinö Arabicöchoseö15öoutöofö17öpossibleöexpressions.ö10öofötheseöexpressionsö wereöselectedöatöleastötwice.öLookingöbacköatötheöExpression-to-Visö resultsöinöFigureö5,öthereöappearsötoöbeöaögapöaboveö25%öandöbelowö 45%,öalthoughö orö"chancesölessöthanöeven"ödidöendöupö beingötheömostöselectedöexpressionöforöthisövalueö(19ötimes).ö Inöcontrast,öMandarinöhasötheölowestöaverageöcountöoföuniqueöexpres-sionsöperöiconöarrayö8.10ö(stdvö=ö1.73)öthanötheöotheröversionsöofötheö experiment.öImplausibleöisöaönotableöexception,öwhichöwasörarelyöusedö andöhadöaöwideörangeöassociatedöwithöit.öToöaölesserödegree,öGerman,ö French,öandöEnglishöshowötheöcentralövaluesöaroundö50%öwithöaölowö numberöoföuniqueöexpressionsö(belowötheiröaverages),öwhileömid-rangeö valuesöaboveöandöbelowö50%öshowömoreövariance.ö Figureö9öalsoöshowsötheöintersectionöoföicon-arrayövaluesöandöexpressionöcounts.öTheösizeöofötheöcirclesöindicateötheöratioöatöwhichöanö expressionsöhasöbeenöusedötoödescribeöaögivenövalue.ö Lookingövertically,öthereöappearsötoöbeövarianceöinöhowöicon-arraysö depictingöparticularövaluesöareödescribed,öwithösomeöexpressionsöpreferredöoveröother.öForöexample,övaluesöaroundö30-40%öandö60-80%ö occasionallyöshowömultipleöpossibleöpreferredöexpressions.ö Acrossö allövaluesöandöexpressions,ölargeröcirclesöappearötoöexistöforöcentralö andöhighöprobabilityövalues,öreflectingösomeöofötheöconsistencyöseenö inötheöfirstöexperiment.öPeopleöacrossölanguagesöseemötoöhaveöclearö preferencesöforötranslationsöofö"chancesöaboutöeven"öforöanöicon-arrayöatö 50%.öOtheröpatternsöshowövarianceöandödisagreement.öTheötranslationsö forö"probable",ö"likely"öappearötoöbeöusedötoöspecifyöaölargeörangeöofö probabilityövaluesöinöaöhighörange.öNotably,öhowever,ösimilaröpatternsö doönotöappearötoöexistöacrossölanguagesöforöwideörangesöofölowöprobabilityövalues.öForöinstance,öwhileö"implausible"ötranslationsöpotentiallyö fitsöthisölow-and-wideörangeöroleöisöGerman,öFrench,öandöArabic,öitöisö scarcelyöchosenöatöallöinöEnglishöandöMandarin.ö Duringötheöexperiment,öparticipantsöhadötheöoptionötoösuggestöadditionalöprobabilityöexpressionsöwheneveröneeded.öParticipantsöprovidedö theiröownöexpressionsö55ötimesöforöArabic,ö99öforöEnglish,ö145öforö French,ö65öforöGerman,öandö14öforöMandarin.öExampleötrendsöinötheseö includeöpeopleöusingötheölistedöexpressionsöinöaöfullösentencesö(e.g. Ilö estöimprobable deögagnerö("itöisöimprobableö toöwin")),öoröwithövaryingö qualifiersö(e.g.</p><p>("highöchance,överyöhighö chance")).öAmongötheönewöexpressionsöandöphrasesöthatöwereösuggested,öweönoticeösomeöreferringödirectlyötoötheöproportionöshownöinö theöiconöarrayöarrangementö(e.g. EtwaöjederöVierteögewinntöforöaö25%ö iconöarray).öWeöprovideötheseödataöinötheösupplement,öasöanöextendedö analysisöoföwrittenöanswersöbyöparticipantsömayögiveöanöopportunityö toöexploreöadditionalölanguageöoröculturalöfactorsöthatöpeopleöreferötoö whenömakingöjudgmentsöaboutöicon-arrayövisualizations.ö</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">COMPARING EXPRESSION USAGE ACROSS EXPERIMENTS</head><p>Givenötheöwithin-subjectsödesignöoföbothöexperiments,öitöisöpossibleö toömakeöcomparisonsöacrossöthem.ö Inöexperimentö1öExpression-to-Vis,öpeopleöwereögivenöeachöexpressionöandödrewöaöspecificöicon-arrayö designö(storedöasöaöpercentageövalue).öSimilarly,öInöexperimentö2öVis-to-  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">DISCUSSION</head><p>The results of the Expression-to-Vis and Vis-To-Expression experiments suggest that language plays an important role in the specification and interpretation of icon-array visualizations. Differences are found within languages. For example, in Mandarin, there was no overlap in Kent's suggested scale range of 55%-85% for the expressions likely, probable, and probably and the visualizations participants drew when given translations of these expressions.</p><p>There are other differences across languages. Using English as a source translation, we identified instances in every tested language that deviated significantly above or below the ranges for the associated English expression (Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>). These and other reported findings raise questions about the interplay between language expressiveness, visualization, and translation efforts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Implications for Visualization Translation</head><p>The observed differences across languages may hold implications for visualization translation efforts. Consider a case where a climate change visualization originally crafted in English, but is intended to be translated into other languages for broader distribution. Translation may use a similar visualization technique, but requires substantial changes to the accompanying textual elements to facilitate target audiences' understanding of the communicated data in the specific context of the visualization. Results here suggest that estimative probability expressions, which may be used both in visualizations themselves and in texts referencing the visualization, should be carefully translated so as to preserve the intended numerical range. Difficulties in translation may persist across both translators and automatic translation tools, such as Google Translate. Future studies might build on these results and others examining the impact of text on visualization interpretation, e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[25]</ref>, to investigate the extent to which alignments and misalignments between expressions and visualizations impact peoples' judgments.</p><p>The translation process itself is another factor that may play a role in the observed differences. Although multiple native speakers were consulted and mediation procedures were used to reach agreement, it is possible that other speakers would have generated somewhat different expressions. Even with other translators, however, there is no guarantee that the chosen expressions would have matched the ranges participants chose for the source expression. A different resulting expression list would also not necessarily cover equal spans of the probability value ranges in the target language.</p><p>These translation challenges raise one possible application of the methodology and the results here. It may be possible to align expressions based on the resulting participant-driven probability ranges. For example, while the expression plausible in French differs significantly from the English plausible, another expression in French, plus d'une chance sur deux (originally translating chances better than even), does align better with this range in the observed data. Computational methods could be designed to construct these translations for the tested languages and others. As an initial exploration, we iteratively paired up expressions across two languages until we found pairs that do not significantly differ following a Tukey test comparison. The results of this approach showing multiple possible "aligned" translations are available in supplemental material. Computational approaches to language-expression alignment could address challenges in cross-language statistical reporting scenarios. The IPCC (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change) report, for example, specifies guidelines for its writers to use certain probability expressions for certain ranges <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6]</ref>. As medical tests and associated symptom displays also rely on an intersection of icon-arrays and language (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">32]</ref>), these efforts may also aid medical or pandemic risk communication. Our results provide a possible path towards further refining these standards, helping ensure the intended meaning of statistics and charts is communicated faithfully across languages.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Towards Better Elicitation for Cross-Language Visualization</head><p>Methodology was a key challenge in the study. While we aimed to carefully adapt and extend prior studies to begin exploring the intersection of visualization and languages, possibilities emerged through the design and resulting analysis. In the Vis-to-Expression experiment, participants offered 86 (out of 4750) additional expressions. While some of these overlap with existing expressions in the study, it is likely that there are other expressions or phrases that the studied languages and associated cultures use in talking about probabilistic events. Finding ways to elicit these could be a challenging but rewarding effort for visualization. For instance, a participant in the Mandarin version commented:</p><p>"貌似可信"在汉语中不是一个好的表达，我作为母语 者都不能完全理解你们用这个词想表达什么" (It seems "plausible" is not a good expression in Chinese. As a native speaker, I can't fully understand what you are trying to express with this word)</p><p>In English, "plausible" is common, but might there be other translations or similar expressions in other languages that fill a similar role?</p><p>One possibility is to move beyond English as a source, and instead develop in-language elicitation methodologies. These might be graphically based, using interaction and visualization with input capability to allow participants to specify ranges and expressions. Alternately, they may be large crowdsourced studies, following similar scenario and trial-based methods. In either case, the goal would be to elicit a wider range of expressions and visualization descriptions from participants. Such efforts could reveal additional ranges and expressive capabilities within languages, beyond those studied here.</p><p>Beyond the results presented here, there are other useful starting points for exploring possibilities in cross-language elicitation for visualization. One source would be to consider the history of large-scale color elicitation studies such as the World Color Survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[28]</ref>. Other language and statistics studies such as Renooij and Witteman <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[38]</ref>, and the NLP-driven analysis of Henkin and Turkay <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref> might inform approaches to scale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Limitations and Future Work</head><p>One limitation of the current work is the restriction to five languages. While these were chosen as an initial step in the space, and intended to cover several major language families, there are thousands of languages in the world and various language groups that could be explored. In the context of a global pandemic, for example, it is important to support effective data-focused communication as broadly as possible. Another limitation is the use of English as a source language. While the intended focus of this study is to highlight difficulties surrounding translation, the use of English still somewhat centers findings on WEIRD populations. Other possible study designs are within reach, however. Future work might design expression elicitation methods directly for native speakers, or using both visualization and numerical probabilities, which might reveal additional expressive features between languages. Elicitation methods might also examine the language people use when describing visualizations of probability distributions, instead of individual probabilities. The neutral scenario / context given to participants and sole use of icon-array visualizations are other practical limitations to explore in future work. Cultural differences such as risk avoidance (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">10]</ref>) may be less pronounced in neutral scenarios, but become more pronounced with carefully designed contexts. We might refer to studies targeting medical reasoning (e.g. Ottley et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[32]</ref>) or natural disaster risk (e.g. Padilla et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[34]</ref>) for promising scenarios and visualizations to explore in future work. Finally, to more directly target implications for visual representations, future studies might explore the extent to which different visual representations elicit responses from native speakers, which might uncover effects of language and culture between visualizations. available in supplementary material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">CONCLUSION</head><p>With the changing global landscape of data and visualization practice, it is important that the research community explores the intersection of language and visualization. We present two experiments with the goal of understanding how people across five languages draw icon-array visualizations given probability expressions and assign probability expressions given icon-array visualizations. Results of these experiments show several differences both across and within languages, with no clear mapping across languages, and several instances of possible "gaps" between expressions in a given language. We discuss implications of these results for ongoing efforts such as data and visualization translation, targeting areas such as climate change and pandemic communication. Taken together, these studies and results are intended to offer a limited yet useful step in broadening the focus of the visualization community beyond traditional WEIRD populations.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Participants visually represent icon arrays to match a probability expressionParticipants choose a probability expression to describe an icon translations, the values drawn in icon arrays led to significant differences as opposed to other languagesValue drawn in icon arraysValue shown in icon arrays ... ... The range of probability values in icon arrays for which "likely" was selected vary across the five languages Arabic English French German Mandarin</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3: The methodology that we follow in our studies. After signing the consent form and viewing an introduction, participants start the study with either Expression-to-Vis or Vis-to-Expression. (a) and (b) point respectively to sample data sets collected from the two experiments.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4: A screenshot of the instructions for experiment 1 Expression-to-Vis in English. The orange-colored icon array indicates a sample answer by the participant, which we evaluate numerically as 46%. Participants can access the instructions at anytime during the experiment.</figDesc><graphic url="image-26.png" coords="4,63.46,427.65,232.38,145.67" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>4. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig.è5:èBootstrappedè95%èconfidenceèintervalsèofèmeanèresponsesèinè Expression-to-Vis.èTheèrangeèofèresponsesèacrossètheèfiveèlanguagesèareè tighterèforèexpressionsèindicatingèhighèandèlowèvalues.èShadedèareasè indicateètheèscaleèrangeèofèprobabilitiesèproposedèbyèKentè[23].è</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig.ö7:öRangeöplotsöoföexampleöexpressionsöandövaluesödrawnöonötheöicon-arraysö(Expression-to-Vis).öThereöseemsötoöbeöroundingöbehavioröaroundö multiplesöofö0öandö5.öValueörangesöforösomeöexpressionsöalsoövaryöacrossötranslationsö(e.g. "likely"ödiffersöbetweenöEnglishöandöotherölanguages).ö</figDesc><graphic url="image-27.png" coords="7,60.69,173.19,236.91,116.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig.9: Results from experiment 2 Expression-to-Vis. Barcharts represent the number of unique expressions participants selected for a given icon-array. Bubbles indicate count of each probability expression and value pair. Results show similarities and differences across languages.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>moins d'une chance sur deux possible plausible des chances à peu près égales plus d'une chance sur deux -Vis vs. People tend to draw values smaller than the ones they describe using the same expressions People tend to describe values smaller than the ones they draw for the same expressions</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10: Comparing the two experiments, results show differences in elicitation methodology that hold across languages. People appear to draw visualizations with more extreme values when given an expression. But when given a visualization of similar value, people tend to choose different expressions. Charts for all five languages and for individual participants are</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>List of all expressions used in the studies and their translations. The supplemental materials include this table augmented with results from the experiments, including mean assigned values and bootstrapped 95% CIs for the Expression-to-Vis experiment, and the ratio of usage of the expressions for each icon-array for the Vis-to-Expression experiment.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>English</cell><cell>French</cell><cell>German</cell><cell>Mandarin</cell><cell>Arabic</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>plausible</cell><cell>plausible</cell><cell>plausibel</cell><cell>貌似可信</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>almost certain</cell><cell>presque certain</cell><cell>ziemlich sicher</cell><cell>几乎确定</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>highly likely</cell><cell>fort probable</cell><cell>sehr wahrscheinlich</cell><cell>极有可能</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>very good chance</cell><cell>deètrèsègrandesèchancesè</cell><cell>sehrèguteèChance</cell><cell>很有可能</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">5è probableè</cell><cell>probableè</cell><cell>wahrscheinlich</cell><cell>可能</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">6è likelyè</cell><cell>possibleè</cell><cell>möglich</cell><cell>或许</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">7è probablyè</cell><cell>probablementè</cell><cell>vermutlich</cell><cell>也许</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">8è chancesèbetterèthanèevenè plusèd'uneèchanceèsurèdeuxè</cell><cell>überdurchschnittlicheèChancen</cell><cell>超过一半概率</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">9è chancesèaboutèevenè</cell><cell>chancesèàèpeuèprèsèégalesè</cell><cell>ungefährègleicheèChancen</cell><cell>大约一半</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">10è chancesèlessèthanèevenè</cell><cell cols="2">moinsèd'uneèchancesèsurèdeuxè unterdurchschnittlicheèChancen</cell><cell>不到一半</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">11è probablyènotè</cell><cell>probablementèpasè</cell><cell>wahrscheinlichènicht</cell><cell>可能不会</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">12è improbableè 13è unlikelyè</cell><cell>improbable invraisemblableè</cell><cell>unwahrscheinlich</cell><cell>不太可能 未必</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">14è littleèchanceè</cell><cell>peuèdeèchanceè</cell><cell>kleineèChance</cell><cell>没什么几率</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">15è almostènoèchanceè</cell><cell>presqueèaucuneèchanceè</cell><cell>fastèchancenlos</cell><cell>几乎没概率</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">16è highlyèunlikelyè</cell><cell>trèsèpeuèprobableè</cell><cell>sehrèunwahrscheinlich</cell><cell>极不可能</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">17è chancesèareèslightè</cell><cell>lesèchancesèsontèfaiblesè</cell><cell>dieèChancenèsindègering</cell><cell>机会渺茫</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">18è implausibleè</cell><cell>peuèplausibleè</cell><cell>nichtèplausibel</cell><cell>难以置信</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors wish to thank Alvitta Ottley and Melanie Bancilhon, as well as Cagatay Turkay and Rafael Henkin for their input on early versions of this work. The authors also wish to thank the translators, and the many participants on the Prolific.co platform who participated in the study.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ûbancilhon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2019.û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûZ.ûLiu,ûandûA.ûOttley.ûLet&apos;sûGamble:ûUncoveringûtheûImpactû ofûVisualizationûonûRiskûPerceptionûandûDecision-Making.ûComputing Research Repository (CoRR)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ûbaughan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1145/3411764.3445519û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûN.ûOliveira,ûT.ûAugust,ûN.ûYamashita,ûandûK.ûReinecke.ûDoû Cross-CulturalûDifferencesûinûVisualûAttentionûPatternsûAffectûSearchû EfficiencyûonûWebsites?ûInûCHI &apos;21: CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, Virtual Event / Yokohama</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Japan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">May 8-13, 2021. û2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ûbocklisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="ûvol.û35.ûcognitivesciencesociety.org,û2013.û" />
		<title level="m">ûA.ûGeorg,ûS.ûBocklisch,ûandûJ.ûKrems.ûDoûYouûMeanûWhatû YouûSay?û TheûEffectûofûUncertaintyûAvoidanceûonûtheûInterpretationû ofûProbabilityûExpressions-AûComparativeûStudyûbetweenûSpanishûandû German.ûInûProceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ûBrust-Renck,ûC.ûE.ûRoyer,ûandûV.ûF.ûReyna.ûCommunicatingûNu-mericalûRisk:ûHumanûFactorsûThatûAidûUnderstandingûinûHealthûCare.û Reviews of Human Factors and Ergonomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ûg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2013.ûdoi:û10.û 1177/1557234X13492980û</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="276" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1038/nclimate2194û</idno>
		<ptr target="D.ûV.ûBudescu,ûH.ûH.ûPor,ûS.ûB.ûBroomell,ûandûM.ûSmithson.ûTheûInterpre-tationûofûIPCCûProbabilisticûStatementsûaroundûtheûWorld.ûNatureClimateChange" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">û2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="508" to="512" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ûConsistencyûinûInterpretationûofûProba-bilisticûPhrases.ûOrganizational behavior and human decision processes</title>
		<idno>û1985.û</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="391" to="405" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ûClevelandûandûR.ûMcGill.ûGraphicalûPerception:ûTheory,ûExperimentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ûs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û1984.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûandûApplicationûtoûtheûDevelopmentûofûGraphicalûMethods.û Journal of the American statistical association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">387</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="554" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2006.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûS.ûDoupnikûandûE.ûL.ûRiccio.û TheûInfluenceûofûConservatismûandû SecrecyûonûtheûInterpretationûofûVerbalûProbabilityûExpressionsûinûtheû AngloûandûLatinûCulturalûAreas.ûThe International Journal of Accounting,û</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="261" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1016/S0361-3682(02)00010-7û</idno>
		<ptr target="T.ûS.ûDoupnikûandûM.ûRichter.ûInterpretationûofûUncertaintyûExpressions:ûaûCross-nationalûStudy.ûAccounting" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organizations and Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">û2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Ûs</forename><surname>Ofû</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.2308/jiar.2004.3.1.1û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">InûContext&quot;ûVerbalûProbabilityûExpressions.ûJournal of International Accounting Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">û2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ûDragicevic.ûFairûStatisticalûCommunicationûinûHCI.ûInûModern statistical methods for HCI,ûpp.û291-330.ûSpringer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2016.û</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ûevers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û1998.û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûCross-CulturalûUnderstandingûofûMetaphorsûinûInterfaceûDesign.ûProceedings CATAC&apos;98, Cultural Attitudes towards Technology and Communication,ûpp</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>û1971.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J.ûL.ûFleiss.ûMeasuringûNominalûScaleûAgreementûamongûManyûRaters.û Psychological bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">378</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<idno>û2010.û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûBoroditsky.û Cross-CulturalûDifferencesûinûMentalû RepresentationsûofûTime:ûEvidenceûfromûanûImplicitûNonlinguisticûTask.û Cognitive science</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1430" to="1451" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ûgalesic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ûgarcia-Retamero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1037/a0014474û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûandûG.ûGigerenzer.ûUsingûIconûArraysû toûCommunicateûMedicalûRisks:ûOvercomingûLowûNumeracy.ûHealth Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="210" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">û2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CommunicatingûTreatmentûRiskû ReductionûtoûPeopleûwithûLowûNumeracyûSkills:ûAûCross-CulturalûComparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ûgarcia-Retameroûandûm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.2105/AJPH.2009.160234û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2196" to="2202" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">û2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ûgarcia-Retameroûandûm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1016/j.socscimed.2009.11û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûGalesic.ûWhoûProfitsûfromûVisualûAids:ûOver-comingûChallengesûinûPeople&apos;sûUnderstandingûofûRisks.ûSocial Science and Medicine</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">û2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1019" to="1025" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ûJara-Ettinger,ûK.ûMahowald,ûL.ûBergen,ûS.ûRatnasingam,ûM.ûGibson,ûS.ûT.ûPiantadosi,ûandûB.ûR.ûConway.ûColorûNam-ingûAcrossûLanguagesûReflectsûColorûUse.ûProceedings of the National Academy of</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ûgibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2017.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10785" to="10790" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Ûgigerenzerûandûu</forename><surname>Ûhoffrage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û1995.ûdoi:û10.1037/0033-295X.102.4.684û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûHowûtoûImproveûBayesianûReasoningûwith-outûInstruction:ûFrequencyûFormats.ûPsychological Review</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="684" to="704" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Ûhenkinûandûc</forename><surname>Ûturkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>ûWordsûofûEstimativeûCorrelation:ûStudyingû VerbalizationsûofûScatterplots.ûCoRR,ûabs/1911.12793,û2019.û</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">(ish)ûisûmyû Bus?ûUser-CenteredûVisualizationsûofûUncertaintyûinûEveryday,ûMobileû PredictiveûSystems.ûConference on Human Factors in Computing Systems -Proceedings,ûpp</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ûkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û1964.û</idno>
		<ptr target="ûT.ûKola,ûJ.ûR.ûHullman,ûandûS.ûA.ûMunson.ûWhenû" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">WordsûofûEstimativeûProbability.û Journal of the American Intelligence Professional</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="65" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>û5092-5103,û2016.ûdoi:û10.1145/2858036.2858558û [23]û S.ûKent.û</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ûKim,ûK.ûThayer,ûG.ûS.ûGorsky,ûandûJ.ûHeer.û ColorûNamesûAcrossû Languages:ûSalientûColorsûandûTermûTranslationûinûMultilingualûColorû NamingûModels.ûInûEuroVis (Short Papers)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2019.û</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-K</forename><surname>Ûkong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ûZ.ûLiu,ûandûK.ûKarahalios.ûFramesûandûslantsûinûtitlesûofû visualizationsûonûcontroversialûtopics.ûInûProceedings of the 2018 CHI conference on human factors in computing systems,ûpp</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">û2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ûkreuzmair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="û2016.ûdoi:û10.û1111/risa.12531û" />
		<title level="m">ûM.ûSiegrist,ûandûC.ûKeller.ûHighûNumeratesûCountûIconsû andûLowûNumeratesûProcessûLargeûAreasûinûPictographs:ûResultsûofûanû Eye-TrackingûStudy.û Risk Analysis</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1599" to="1614" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Journal international de Recherche en Education et Formation Evaluer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pourcentageûdeûchances</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2016.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal international de Recherche en Education et Formation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="125" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">WorldûColorûSurveyûColorûNamingû RevealsûUniversalûMotifsûandûtheirûWithin-LanguageûDiversity.ûProceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1073/pnas.0910981106û</idno>
		<ptr target="D.ûT.ûLindseyûandûA.ûM.ûBrown.û" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">19785-19790,û2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">û2019.ûdoi:û10.1145/3359174û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûProceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1214/ss/1177012242û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">F.ûMostellerûandûC.ûYoutz.ûQuantifyingûProbabilisticûExpressions.ûStatistical Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">û1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ûGarcia-Retamero,ûE.ûT.ûCokely,ûandûA.ûMaldonado.ûImprovingû RiskûUnderstandingûacrossûAbilityûLevels:ûEncouragingûActiveûProcessingû withûDynamicûIconûArrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ûokan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1037/xap0000045û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûJournal of Experimental Psychology: Applied,û</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="194" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">û2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">:ûTheû EffectsûofûPhrasing,ûVisualization,ûandûSpatialûAbility.ûIEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ûottley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2016.ûdoi:û10.û 1109/TVCG.2015.2467758û</idno>
		<ptr target="ûE.ûM.ûPeck,ûL.ûT.ûHarrison,ûD.ûAfergan,ûC.ûZiemkiewicz,ûH.ûA.ûTaylor,ûP.ûK.ûHan,ûandûR.ûChang.ûImprovingûBayesianûReasoning" />
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="538" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ûpadilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">ûS.ûC.ûCastrob,ûandûH.ûHosseinpoura.ûAûReviewûofûUncertaintyû VisualizationûErrors:ûWorkingûMemoryûasûanûExplanatoryûTheory.ûThe Psychology of Learning and Motivation</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>ûp.û275,û2021.û</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ûpadilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2020.û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûM.ûKay,ûandûJ.ûHullman.ûUncertaintyûVisualization.ûHandbook of Computational Statistics and Data Science</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ûPeck,ûS.ûE.ûAyuso,ûandûO.ûEl-Etr.ûDataûisûPersonal:ûAttitudesûandû PerceptionsûofûDataûVisualizationûinûRuralûPennsylvania.ûarXiv,ûpp.û1-12</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ûm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Ût</forename><surname>Ûreagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1037/0021-9010.74.3.433û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">ûF.ûMosteller,ûandûC.ûYoutz.ûQuantitativeûMeaningsûofûVerbalû ProbabilityûExpressions.ûJournal of Applied Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ûreineckeûandûk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1145/2675133.2675246û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûZ.ûGajos.ûLabintheWild:ûConductingûLarge-Scaleû OnlineûExperimentsûWithûUncompensatedûSamples.ûInûProceedings of the 18th ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work &amp; Social Computing, CSCW 2015</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Vancouver, BC, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1364">March 14 -18, 2015,ûpp.û1364-1378.ûACM,û2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Talkingûprobabilities:ûCommunicatingû probabilisticûinformationûwithûwordsûandûnumbers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Ûrenooijûandûc</forename><surname>Ûwitteman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û1999.ûdoi:û10.1016/S0888û-613X(99)00027-4û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Approximate Reasoning</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="194" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ûA.ûSanneûWillemsûandûI.ûS.ûVerbal.ûVariabilityûinûtheûInterpretationûofû ProbabilityûPhrasesûUsedûinûDutchûNewsûArticlesû-ûaûRiskûforûMiscommunication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2020.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûOrphanet Journal of Rare Diseases</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Probability?ûAûQualitativeûStudyûofûRiskûCommunicationûFormatsûUsedû inûHealthûCare.ûMedical Decision Making</title>
		<idno>û2001.û</idno>
		<ptr target="M.ûM.ûSchapira,ûA.ûB.ûNattinger,ûandûC.ûA.ûMcHorney.ûFrequencyûorû" />
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="467" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ûspiegelhalter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1126/science.û1191181û</idno>
		<ptr target="ûM.ûPearson,ûandûI.ûShort.ûVisualizingûUncertaintyûaboutûtheûFuture.ûScience" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">û2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">333</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1400" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ûsturm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ûoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1145/2702613.2702656û</idno>
		<title level="m">ûS.ûLinxen,ûJ.ûAbdelnourûNocera,ûS.ûDray,ûandûK.ûReinecke.ûHowûWEIRDûisûHCI?ûExtendingûHCIûPrinciplesûtoûOtherûCountriesû andûCultures.ûInûProceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems,ûvol.û18,ûpp</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2425-2428,û2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ûTalbot,ûV.ûSetlur,ûandûA.ûAnand.ûFourûExperimentsûonûtheûPerceptionûofû BarûCharts.ûIEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2014.û .031û</idno>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2152" to="2160" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>û2014.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">C.ûTill.û FosteringûRiskûLiteracyûinûElementaryûSchool.û International Electronic Journal of Mathematics Education</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="98" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ProbabilityûInformationûinûRiskûCommunication:ûAûReviewûofûtheûRe-searchûLiterature</title>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1111/j.û1539-6924.2008.01137.xû</idno>
		<ptr target="V.ûH.ûVisschers,ûR.ûM.ûMeertens,ûW.ûW.ûPasschier,ûandûN.ûN.ûDeûVries.û" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">û2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1037/0096-3445.û115.4.348û</idno>
		<ptr target="T.ûS.ûWallsten,ûD.ûV.ûBudescu,ûA.ûRapoport,ûR.ûZwick,ûandûB.ûForsyth.ûMea-suringûtheûVagueûMeaningsûofûProbabilityûTerms" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûJournal of Experimental Psychology: General</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="365" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">û1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ûwinschiers-Theophilusûandûn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>û2013.û</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ûJ.ûBidwell.ûTowardûanûAfro-Centricû IndigenousûHCIûParadigm.ûInternational Journal of Human-Computer Interaction</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="255" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1371/journal.pone.0213522û</idno>
		<ptr target="B.ûC.ûWintle,ûH.ûFraser,ûB.ûC.ûWills,ûA.ûE.ûNicholson,ûandûF.ûFidler.ûVerbalûProbabilities:ûVeryûLikelyûtoûbeûSomewhatûMoreûConfusingûthanûNumbers.û" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">û2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<idno>û2022.û</idno>
		<ptr target="ûC.ûXiong,ûA.ûSarvghad,ûD.ûG.ûGoldstein,ûJ.ûM.ûHofman,ûandûÇ.ûDemiralp.û" />
		<title level="m">Investigatingûperceptualûbiasesûinûiconûarrays.û InûCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems,ûpp</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Ûj</forename><surname>Ûzikmund-Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">û10.1177/0272989X13511706û</idno>
		<ptr target="ûH.ûO.ûWitteman,ûM.ûDickson,ûA.ûFuhrel-Forbis,ûV.ûC.ûKahn,ûN.ûL.ûExe,ûM.ûValerio,ûL.ûG.ûHoltzman,ûL.ûD.ûScherer" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="453" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ûandû A.ûFagerlin.ûBlocks,ûOvals,ûorûPeople?ûIconûTypeûaffectsûRiskûperceptionsû andûRecallûofûPictographs.ûMedical Decision Making</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
