<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">VACSEN: A Visualization Approach for Noise Awareness in Quantum Computing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shaolun</forename><surname>Ruan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yong</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Weiwen</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ying</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Qiang</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">VACSEN: A Visualization Approach for Noise Awareness in Quantum Computing</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2023-03-27T09:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Data visualization</term>
					<term>quantum computing</term>
					<term>noise awareness</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A1 C1 Circuit Comparison View Fig. 1: The interface of VACSEN makes users aware of the quantum noise via three linked views (A-C). Computer Evolution View (A) allows the assessment for all quantum computers based on a temporal analysis for multiple performance metrics. Circuit Filtering View (B) supports the filtering for the potential optimal compiled circuits. Circuit Comparison View (C) supports the in-depth comparison regarding the performance of qubits or quantum gates and corresponding usages. The control panel (D) allows users to interactively configure the settings of VACSEN. Fidelity Comparison View (E) shows the fidelity distribution of each compiled circuit. Probability Distribution View (F) visualizes the results of state distribution of a quantum circuit execution.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Along with the evolution of actual quantum computers from industry, like IBM, IonQ, Rigetti, and D-Wave, quantum computing research has been rapidly growing in the past few years. An increasing number of quantum algorithms have been developed and shown a significant speedup over their best-known classical counterparts <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">49]</ref>. On top of the breakthroughs in quantum algorithms, quantum computing has become a promising method in many important applications such as chemistry simulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref> and machine learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">58]</ref>.</p><p>Despite the promising impacts on speeding up algorithms, the high noise level in quantum devices is one of the key challenges to achieve the real quantum advantage in today's quantum computers, which are well known as Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) computers.</p><p>The noise originates from a quantum computer's fundamental components <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, including (1) qubits, which are the basic units to store the quantum states; and (2) quantum gates, which are the basic operators to manipulate qubits' states. For example, due to the volatility and limited coherence time, flip errors can occur at qubits <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</p><p>The quantum noise issue becomes more severe due to the variation of the topology (i.e., connection) on physical qubits. Specifically, quantum algorithms are synthesized as quantum circuits (also called logical circuits <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[48]</ref>). The quantum circuits will finally be deployed to the physical qubits for execution. It will go through the process of mapping logical circuits to physical qubits to obtain the physical quantum circuits (also called compiled circuits <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">56]</ref>). The compiled circuit, however, is specified to the actual quantum computer since the topology of qubits is different. Thus, even for the same quantum algorithm, the effects of quantum noise on the algorithm can be significantly different.</p><p>In NISQ era, it is crucial to improve the fidelity of quantum computing, enabling the correctness of quantum algorithms (or at least approximate to the desired results). To this end, designers of quantum algorithms need to have a clear understanding of the hidden noise of different quantum computers as well as the noise inside different compiled circuits on the same quantum computer for a specific quantum algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[47]</ref>. However, this is not a trivial task. On the one hand, the access to most of today's quantum computers has been provided by IT companies, like IBM, Amazon, and Microsoft, as a cloud service. To the best of our knowledge, no uniform tool revealing the noise exists to assist the designers. On the other hand, due to the rapid increase of quantum computing users <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, we face the increasing queuing time for accessing cloud quantum computers without noise awareness. Thus, the evaluation and mitigation of noise before execution has become even more urgent to avoid the waste of queuing time for unsatisfied results. Currently, the common practice to obtain less-noisy execution results is still a trial-and-error process.</p><p>To address the above problems, it is essential to have a tool to effectively inform users of the noise in quantum computing for a better selection of quantum computers and compiled circuits. Given that visualization has shown great power in various applications <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, we aim to develop a novel visualization approach to enhance users' noise awareness in quantum computing and make quantum computing more transparent and reliable. However, there exist many challenges that mainly come from two perspectives: complex and dynamically-evolving quality of quantum computers and significant variations of the compiled circuits. First, the performance of quantum computers relies on multiple factors of qubits and quantum gates <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">45]</ref>, such as quantum decoherence, gate error, and qubit readout error. These factors are dynamically changing over time <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. It is challenging to visualize these complex factors as well as the qubit topological connections along a timeline. Second, a quantum algorithm can be compiled to various compiled circuits with significantly-different noise on the same quantum computer. For a large-scale quantum algorithm, the compiled circuits can be several hundreds <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">44]</ref>. The noise of compiled physical circuit needs to be evaluated from different perspectives, e.g., the circuit depths and the noise of involved qubits or quantum gates <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. But it is difficult to visually summarize a large number of the compiled circuits regarding the various noises, and enable users to select the most appropriate one shortly.</p><p>To fill the research gap, we propose VACSEN 1 , a Visualization ApproaCh for noiSe awarenEss in quaNtum computing. VACSEN can inform quantum computing users of the noise in quantum computers and compiled physical circuits, leading to a better execution result with higher fidelity. We follow a user-centered design process <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> by working closely with five domain experts in quantum computing for over five months. A pilot study is conducted to derive the design requirements. These design requirements guide our subsequent visual 1 VACSEN is pronounced as "vaccine". We envision VACSEN can provide insights for designers to vaccinate their quantum algorithms against noise. designs for VACSEN. VACSEN mainly consists of three novel visualization views: Computer Evolution View, Circuit Filtering View, and Circuit Comparison View. Specifically, Computer Evolution View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 A</ref> ) facilitates the temporal noise assessment of quantum computers by a novel circuit-like design that reveals the qubit connectivity. Circuit Filtering View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 B</ref> ) supports the filtering of the compiled circuits, allowing users to pick the compiled circuits of interest. Circuit Comparison View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 C</ref> ) further enables a more detailed comparison of selected compiled circuits with a novel coupled bar chart design, facilitating the selection of an optimal compiled circuit for the final execution. To the best of our knowledge, VACSEN is the first visualization approach for real-time noise awareness in quantum computing.</p><p>To evaluate the usefulness and effectiveness of VACSEN, we present two case studies on both small-scale and large-scale quantum algorithms and conduct in-depth interviews with 12 target quantum computing users. The results show that VACSEN can provide users with an intuitive way to be aware of quantum noise. The major contributions of this paper can be summarized as follows:</p><p>• We formulate the design requirements for interactive visual analysis of the noise in quantum computers and compiled circuits, together with quantum computing experts.</p><p>• We present an interactive visual analytics approach, VACSEN, to help quantum computing users assess the noise in quantum computing. Two novel visual designs are proposed: a circuitlike design facilitates the temporal analysis of quantum computer noise, and a coupled bar chart design enables the in-depth comparison of compiled circuits.</p><p>• We conduct two case studies and in-depth user interviews with expert users to demonstrate the effectiveness and usability of VACSEN.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>Our work is relevant to prior research on visualization for quantum computing and the reliability improvement in quantum computing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Visualization for Quantum Computing</head><p>Researchers have attempted to explain quantum computing via visualization. Miller et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> proposed a node-link approach to present quantum circuits. Lin et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> introduced a method to reveal the parameters' dynamic change by the sequence of quantum gates. Tao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[53]</ref> introduced an interactive platform for users to better understand Shor's algorithm. Also, there are online platforms that support an interactive implementation of circuits. For example, Quirk [39] provides a graphical tool to make users aware of quantum circuit's behaviors and state changes. Some commercial vendors also provide cloud platforms that allow users to build quantum circuits interactively, e.g., IBM Quantum<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">2</ref> and Amazon Rigetti<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">3</ref> . All of the above studies focused on visualizing qubit states for a better understanding of the quantum workflow. The existing quantum computing platforms (e.g., IBM Quantum) often provide users with some quality indicators of each qubit. However, these platforms can not make users aware of the noise in the compiled circuit, making the circuit execution less reliable. Our system aims to enable multi-level noise awareness in quantum computing through a novel visualization approach and then help enhance the fidelity of the execution of a quantum algorithm with noise awareness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Reliability Improvement in Quantum Computing</head><p>Reliability improvement studies different methods to enhance the probability of correct results of quantum circuit execution, and has become a prominent research topic in quantum computing <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">54]</ref>. There are three major ways to enhance the reliability in quantum computing <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, i.e., building better qubits, quantum error correction, and qubit re-mapping. To build better qubits, the decoherence time of qubits has been improved significantly in the last two decades <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>. However, qubits and gate operations can be made more robust and accurate from a fabrication and control perspective, and there are still some bottlenecks. Quantum error correction <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> requires significant qubit overhead (e.g., 18X extra qubits in the surface code <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>). Furthermore, quantum computing researchers have studied methods of optimizing the mapping from logical qubits to more reliable physical qubits by considering the noise of physical qubits <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36]</ref>. Ash-Saki et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> provided an approach where high-quality qubits are prioritized for mapping. Bhattacharjee et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> proposed a mapping approach considering the nearest neighbor compliance. Alam et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> studied a qubit mapping algorithm to optimize circuits by exploiting gate re-ordering.</p><p>However, existing quantum computers still suffer from noises and the above approaches cannot achieve error-free quantum computing. Thus, it is still crucial to provide users with an intuitive way to understand and compare the noise of both quantum computers and compiled circuits, which is the focus of this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">BACKGROUND</head><p>This section introduces the overall background of quantum computing which is relevant to our study, including quantum computer architecture, quantum computing workflow, fidelity and noise in quantum computing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Quantum Computer Architecture</head><p>Qubit, or quantum bit, is the basic unit of quantum information in quantum computing. For classical computing, a bit always has two deterministic states, i.e., "0" or "1". For quantum computing, there are two orthonormal basis states for a qubit, i.e., |0 and |1 . The actual quantum state of a qubit can be represented by a linear superposition of the two basis states <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">|Ψ = α |0 + β |1 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where α, β are complex numbers subject to |α| 2 + |β | 2 = 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. Also, multiple qubits can be entangled to support the qubit interactions, which is called quantum entanglement <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. An entangled state of the two qubits can be made via a gate on the control qubit, followed by the so-called CNOT gate <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><p>Quantum Gate, or quantum logical gate, is a basic quantum circuit operating on qubits to modify the qubit states. For example, Pauli gate is for a single qubit, and CNOT (Control-NOT) gate is a commonlyused quantum operation applied on two qubits simultaneously. Like classical logic gates, where the conventional digital circuits are the basic building blocks, quantum gates are also the building blocks of quantum circuits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Quantum Computing Workflow</head><p>The general quantum workflow includes quantum circuit implementation, quantum computer selection, and qubit mapping &amp; execution <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[57]</ref>.</p><p>Quantum Circuit Implementation. Quantum circuit implementation is the first step of the quantum workflow where users implement a quantum circuit to realize a quantum algorithm. A logical quantum circuit is ready to be compiled and executed by connecting multiple qubits with quantum gates. There are many ways to implement a quantum circuit. For example, the IBM Quantum platform supports circuit implementation by an online graphical interface, and the implementation by programming with Qiskit 4 is also supported.</p><p>Quantum Computer Selection. After implementing a usable logical quantum circuit, users are required to select a preferred quantum computer for further execution. This step is totally up to users to decide which quantum computer is appropriate. A constraint for quantum computer selection is the required number of qubits for a given circuit. For example, the quantum computer ibmq armonk in IBM Q platform with only one qubit is not appropriate to host a circuit with five qubits required. A quantum computer with a better performance of qubits and quantum gates would be more reliable to execute a quantum circuit <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p><p>In addition, the job queuing number determines the waiting time for a circuit execution. Thus, quantum computer selection is a complex task. Qubit Mapping &amp; Execution. As mentioned in Section 1, the logical circuit will be mapped to a "physical quantum circuit" <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[55]</ref> to fit the connectivity of the selected computer. The qubit mapping procedure depends on the mapping algorithms and cannot be modified by users. The mapped physical circuit can be different even for the same logical circuit <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[55]</ref>. Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> B shows four different mapped physical circuit options for the same logical circuit (Fig. <ref type="figure">2 A</ref> ). Since the mapping is a blind mapping without any noise awareness, the probability of the correct results would be different due to the performance variation of qubits and quantum gates <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure">2 C</ref> ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Fidelity &amp; Noise in Quantum Computing</head><p>VACSEN uses the fidelity of the execution results to assess the qubit error and gate error in quantum computers and compiled circuits.</p><p>Fidelity. Fidelity is a metric for measuring the difference between ideal execution results (noise-free) and actual results. For today's NISQ computer, the execution of a quantum algorithm is error-prone, leading to biased results of measurements compared with a noise-free result. The higher the fidelity is, the more accurate and valid an execution is.</p><p>Qubit Error. A qubit can retain the state for only a limited period of time, and this duration is called decoherence time. There are two metrics to measure the decoherence error, i.e., relaxation time T1 and dephasing time T2. T1 affects the quantum state |1 (i.e., |1 → |0 ), leaving state |0 invariant. However, it is also possible that qubit may interact with the environment and encounter a phase error, and the time constant associated with this decay is called dephasing time T2. Besides the decoherence error, errors can also exist in the readout of the qubit state, which is called the readout error <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">52]</ref>.</p><p>Gate Error. Gates are operations controlling multiple qubits. They can also affect qubit states due to the noise. Gate error rate is defined as the probability of introducing an error while performing operations <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Different types of gates may have different impacts on fidelity. For example, a recent study reveals the error rate of a 2-qubit gate (e.g., CNOT gate) can cause the maximum loss of fidelity <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">INFORMING THE DESIGN</head><p>We conducted a pilot study to identify the general workflow and derive design requirements for noise awareness in quantum computing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Pilot Study</head><p>We designed a pilot study following the methodology introduced by Sedlmair et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[46]</ref>. Specifically, we invited five quantum computing experts (P1-5) to participate in the pilot study. P1 is a research scientist from Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, P2-4 are professors or post-doc researchers from three different universities, and P5 is a Ph.D. student majoring in quantum computing. Among them, P1 and P2 are doing research on quantum chemistry. P3 is working on quantum machine learning, and is one of the co-authors of this work. P4 and P5 study the temporal patterns of quantum hardware's quality. All the domain experts have an average of 4.9 years of research and development experience in quantum computing.</p><p>We began the pilot study by performing one-on-one, semi-structured, hour-long interviews with all participants. We categorized all participants into two groups. First, Group 1 (P1-3) were asked several questions about their understandings and solutions to noise awareness in quantum computing. Based on their feedback, we formulated the initial design requirements and proposed a low-fidelity demo system. Next, we presented the demo system to Group 2 (P4-5), who can provide in-depth suggestions for the noise analysis based on their calibration data analysis experiences of quantum computers. We discussed the demo system with Group 2 iteratively. They were asked several questions about their suggestions and concerns; we tuned the demo system accordingly. We observed and took notes during the meetings to ensure that our early system meets the basic requirements for the quantum computing scenario. Second, we presented the early system and held weekly meetings with Group 2 over the next two months. They were asked to explore the prototype system freely and complete the analysis tasks for noise-aware quantum circuit execution. We recorded each meeting and then held open discussions separately. The suggestions collected in this round were used to polish our system further.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Design Requirements</head><p>According to the feedback from all the experts, there are two major steps for executing a quantum algorithm on a quantum computer: quantum computer selection and compiled circuit selection. Even on the same quantum computing platform, different quantum computers can have significantly different hardware properties such as gate-count, qubitcount, performance data, and qubit connectivity. Also, selecting a better compiled circuit can improve the fidelity and reliability of execution due to the noise variation of the compiled circuits. We summarized six design requirements for the evaluation and mitigation of noise.</p><p>For the quantum computer selection, users need to select the optimal quantum computer to host the quantum algorithm, which requires users to be aware of quantum noise from the following aspects: R1 Facilitate the temporal analysis of qubit and gate noise. All participants (P1-5) confirmed that it is crucial to enable the temporal exploration of the qubit and quantum gate noise. Specifically, the temporal analysis of quantum computers' status will be more accurate than the reflection under a single timestamp. P1 also commented that it will be intuitive to reveal the periodical patterns of qubits' performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> via a visualization approach. R2 Make users aware of the latest quantum computing noise.</p><p>P1 and P5 confirmed that besides tracing the historical noise of quantum computers, it is also important to be informed of the latest noise status, since the time-varying quantum hardware properties can change quickly when the calibration launches.</p><p>P4 also reported that the real-time reflection of the queuing job number will also be helpful for quantum computer selection.</p><p>For the compiled circuit selection, the following requirements are crucial for informing the quantum noise users of different noise:</p><p>R3 Provide an overview of all compiled circuits. According to the suggestions from four participants (P2-5), more compilation results can increase the likelihood of selecting an optimal compiled circuit. Thus, it will be helpful to allow users to select multiple compiled circuits of their interest for an in-depth comparison. R4 Enable a detailed comparison of the usages of implemented qubits and gates. All participants (P1-5) emphasized the need for a drilling-down comparison of selected compiled circuits. In addition, P4 also pointed out that it is necessary to provide the reference value of the performance for a better noise comparison.</p><p>R5 Support a real-time compilation and fidelity validation of quantum algorithms. All participants (P1-5) confirmed that the system should support real-time compilation of quantum algorithms on real quantum computers to generate the latest compiled circuits. Also, the preferred compiled circuit needs to be further executed on the selected quantum computer, which can help users validate the performance of the selected quantum computer and compiled circuits for running the selected algorithm.</p><p>For the overall visual designs, experts also requested flexible interactions and intuitive visualizations: R6 Provide flexible user interactions and intuitive visual designs.</p><p>Three participants (P1, P3-4) commented that the system needs to support on-demand analysis for quantum computing noise assessment. For example, some casual users will focus on the quantum gate error rate to handle simple quantum circuits, while other users may be interested in the qubit decoherence time when executing a complex quantum circuit like a quantum machine learning model. Flexible user interactions can support such requirements. Also, concise design is preferred, as quantum computing users often do not have a background in data visualization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Dataset</head><p>Guided by the above design requirements, we collected the following data from the cloud quantum platform (i.e., IBM Quantum), which indicates quantum noise and will be visualized in VACSEN:</p><p>• Calibration data of quantum computers. We collected the latest relaxation time T1, dephasing time T2, qubit readout error, and gate error rate. We also collected the queuing number of the quantum computer from the remote quantum cloud computing platform.</p><p>• Properties of compiled physical circuits. Such properties need to be extracted from real-time compilation, which includes the usage of each qubit and quantum gate, and the execution results of a quantum algorithm from the cloud quantum computing platform. Following the prior studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">59]</ref>, we further calculate the fidelity of each compiled physical circuit by using the Hellinger distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">VACSEN</head><p>We propose VACSEN, an interactive visualization approach to inform users of the noise in quantum computing when trying to execute their quantum algorithms on quantum computers. VACSEN can be accessed via the URL: https://vacsen.github.io/. Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the architecture of VACSEN. VACSEN is designed to work with quantum computing cloud platforms (e.g., IBM Quantum), and inform users of the quantum noise in the quantum circuit compilation and execution. VACSEN consists of three modules: storage module, processing module and visualization module. The storage module stores all the available latest calibration data, including qubit properties and gate properties. The processing module handles the quantum algorithm's implementation and the compiled circuit's extraction from the cloud quantum computing platform. The visualization module reveals the noise of quantum computers and compiled circuits.</p><p>After selecting the optimal compiled circuit, VACSEN also supports a post-execution analysis for a quantum algorithm. Fidelity Comparison View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 E</ref> ) supports the validation of the compiled circuits' fidelity. The vertical coordinate of the dot indicates the fidelity value. The dot highlighted in black in Fidelity Comparison View denotes the fidelity value of the compiled circuit selected by the user. Also, users can further check their detailed state distributions by clicking the dot. The corresponding execution result will be visualized on Probability Distribution View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 F</ref> ), where the x-axis indicates the state distribution and the y-axis represents the corresponding shot numbers. Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>: The system architecture of VACSEN contains three modules (a storage module, a processing module, and an visualization module) and the remote quantum computing platform.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Computer Evolution View</head><p>We propose a circuit-like design to visualize the quantum computer noise in each timestamp. Following the prior studies [6, 7, 10], we encode qubit T1 time, qubit T2 time, qubit readout error rate, and quantum gate error rate to portray the noise in quantum computers. We utilize a sequence of circuit-like designs to visualize the time-varying performance of a quantum computer. Also, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> A 6 , the latest queuing number of the quantum computer is encoded by the horizontal bar chart.</p><p>Circuit-like Design. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref> A , the colored circles represent the value of one of the qubit noise attributes (i.e., T1 time, T2 time, and readout error), which can be switched by the user. According to the feedback of domain experts, the relative noise across different qubits and gates is even more effective than their absolute noise values for quantum computers and compiled circuit selection. Thus, we first calculate the average of the noise attributes among all qubits as the reference value and further compute the difference between a noise attribute and the reference value. Specifically, the circle radius represents the absolute value of the difference between the readout error and the reference value. A circle will be colored in blue if the readout error is lower than the reference value. Otherwise, it will be colored in red . The larger the radius of the blue circle, the better the performance of the qubit; conversely, the larger the radius of the red circle, the worse the performance of the qubit; if the radius of the circle is close to 0, it means that the performance of the qubit is close to the average performance. Meanwhile, the quantum gate topology is encoded by the line segments in grey. The horizontal coordinate of each line segment indicates its gate error rate, while the vertical position of two endpoints denotes the two qubits that the quantum gate operates on. We adjust the opacity of line segments to mitigate the possible visual clutter issues due to overlapped line segments.</p><p>During the iterative weekly meetings with domain experts, they mentioned that it is difficult to understand the overall noise level of quantum gates. To this end, we visually summarized the overall distribution for quantum gates' noise using the Kernel Density Estimation (KDE) method. Given all quantum gates' error rate distribution list (x 1 , x 2 ,...,x n ), the KDE can be calculated as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">fh (x) = 1 nh n ∑ i=1 K( x − x i h ),<label>(2)</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Timestamp of the current</head><p>Error rate of a quantum gate ,which visualizes the error rate and gate connectivity via horizontal and vertical coordinates respectiely.</p><p>Distribution of gate error rates.</p><p>The color represents the error rate from low to high.</p><p>Metrics (T1, T2, or Readout error) of a qubit. Blue circle represents the metric is better than the reference value, while red circle means a worse one. where K is the kernel -a non-negative function -and h is a smoothing bandwidth. We utilize the Gaussian function <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> as the kernel of the KDE distribution. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref> 1 , we visualize the KDE distribution at the bottom of each circuit-like design. Furthermore, we fill the density area chart with a gradient color (i.e., from blue to red) to intuitively show the quantum gate noise distribution.</p><p>Design Alternatives. Before finalizing the current visual design, we also considered four design alternatives for the temporal analysis of the quantum computer noise (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4 B</ref> ). Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref> 2 is the initial design that is a general design for temporal analysis. However, it is not appropriate to visualize a number of qubits' noise trends simultaneously in a narrow space, making it difficult to observe the temporal patterns. To address the problem, we abstracted the anomalous periods and highlighted them with red line segments (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref> 3 ). During our weekly meeting with domain experts, all the experts (P1-5) commented that it would be better to embed the quantum gates' noise and their connectivity into the design. The design in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref> 4 addressed this problem, but the curve lines denoting the gate connectivity will introduce a severe visual clutter when the qubit number is over five. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">4</ref> 5 addressed the challenge by using a timeslice approach. However, as mentioned above, the quantum gate noise distribution is not intuitive for this design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Circuit Filtering View</head><p>The Circuit Filtering View aims to help users filter several compiled circuits of their interest. To portray the overall performance of qubits and gates, we define a metric overall performance scores, including qubit scores and gate scores, for each compiled circuit. We then calculate the average of all scores as the reference value. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1 B</ref> , each row denotes a compiled circuit. The horizontal coordinate of the circle depicts the depth of the circuit, which indicates the number of instructions for a compiled circuit. The circle will be colored blue if the overall performance scores are higher than the reference value. Otherwise, it would be rendered in red. The user can configure in the control panel and indicate either gate scores or qubit scores to be visualized by the circles. The circle radius indicates the absolute value of the difference between the overall performance scores and the reference value. The larger the radius of the blue circle, the less noisy the circuit; conversely, the larger the radius of the red circle, the noisier the circuit; if the circle radius is closer to 0, it means that the circuit noise is closer to the average level.</p><p>For a compiled circuit, a physical quantum gate or qubit is often be used for multiple times. After discussing with the domain experts, we followed the idea of Linearly Weighted Moving Average and proposed Reference values.</p><p>indicates the usage count is higher than the reference value，while depicts a lower usage count. the overall score (S), which represents the weighted error rate across different qubits or gates to indicate the overall error rate of a compiled circuit. We choose the reciprocal of the overall error rate to represent its overall performance. Thus, given a compiled circuit with N quantum gates (or qubits), we define the overall score S as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">S = ( ∑ N i=1 C i • E i ∑ N i=1 C i ) −1 ,<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where E i denotes the error rate of a quantum gate (or qubit), and C i is the usage times of a quantum gate (or qubit).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Circuit Comparison View</head><p>Circuit Comparison View supports the in-depth comparison of multiple compiled circuits. We propose a novel coupled bar chart to enable users to drill down to the previously selected compiled circuits. The design summarizes the instructions of the compiled circuits. It portrays the noise based on the performance metrics (i.e., qubit T1 time, qubit T2 time, qubit readout error, and quantum gate error rate) and the usage times of the hosted qubits and quantum gates.</p><p>Coupled Bar Charts. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">5</ref> A , each coupled bar chart indicates the noise for a compiled circuit. The upper group of bars denotes the usage times of quantum gates of a compiled circuit, while the bottom group of bars represents the usage times of the qubits. The color of the upper bars represents the error rate of the gates, while the color of the lower bars denotes one of the three noise attributes for qubits (i.e., T1, T2, and readout error). The darker the blue of the bar, the less the noise of the qubit or gate; the darker the red of the bar, the more noise of the qubit or gate. The height of the black rectangle indicates the average usage times of the gate or qubit among all compiled circuits. Meanwhile, the curved lines between the upper and lower groups of bars visualize the connectivity of quantum gates. Specifically, the upper endpoint of the curved line represents a quantum gate, while the corresponding two lower endpoints denote the two qubits operated on the quantum gate.</p><p>Design Alternatives. We considered other two design alternatives for the detailed comparison of compiled circuits regarding the noise. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">5</ref> B shows the compiled circuit's noise by the original topology of the selected quantum computers. The usage times of qubits and quantum gates are encoded by the circle radius and line segment width, respectively. The noise level is indicated by the same color encoding as the coupled bar chart. However, it is difficult to compare the line segment width between multiple compiled circuits. The second design alternative is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">5</ref> C , which encodes the gate usage times by the bar height and qubit usage times by the horizontal position of the glyph (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">5 C 1</ref> ). However, we found that the comparison between multiple compiled circuits from horizontal and vertical directions simultaneously is confusing for the users. To address all these challenges, we further propose coupled bar chart (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">5 A</ref> ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">User Interactions</head><p>VACSEN enables rich interactions to help users smoothly explore and analyze the noise of different quantum computers and compiled circuits.</p><p>Hierarchical noise analysis. The Computer Evolution View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 A</ref> ) provides an overview of quantum computer noise. By clicking a quantum computer, users can view the noise of all the compiled circuits in the Circuit Filtering View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 B</ref> ), which can be further explored and compared in detail in the Circuit Comparison View (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 C</ref> ).</p><p>Time configurations. Users can adjust the time range of the noise to be shown in the Computer Evolution View by specifying the latest "time range" value in the control panel (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 D</ref> ) and the time "interval" (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 D</ref> ) can also be adjusted to show quantum computer noise with different granularity.</p><p>Quantum algorithm specifications. Users can specify the quantum algorithm to be run and the number of compilations in the control panel (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 D</ref> ). Once the quantum algorithm is determined, users can launch the compilation of the quantum algorithm on the cloud platform by simply clicking the button "Compile" (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 D</ref> ).</p><p>Interactive filtering and sorting of compiled circuits. Users can switch between "Gate" and "Qubit" to visualize the compiled circuits according to either gate scores or qubit scores. Also, VACSEN allows users to sort all compiled circuits in the Circuit Filtering View by the quality scores or circuit depth via the switch "Sort by scores" and "Sort by depth" in the control panel (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 D</ref> ). Furthermore, users can filter circuits by their quality scores via the "Score Filter" range slider.</p><p>Remote execution controlling. After selecting the preferred compiled circuit for execution, the user can launch the execution via the button "Run" in the control panel (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 D</ref> ). The remote cloud quantum computer would host and execute the selected compiled circuit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CASE STUDY</head><p>In this section, we conducted two case studies on both small-scale and large-scale quantum circuits to demonstrate the effectiveness of VACSEN. The users involved in the case studies are two quantum computing experts (U1 and U6) who also attended the user interviews in Section 7. IBM Quantum platform was used to compile and execute the quantum circuits on March 5, 2022<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">5</ref> .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Case Study I -Two-qubit Circuit</head><p>U1 employed VACSEN to explore the noise of different quantum computers and select an appropriate compiled circuit for the two-qubit circuit introduced by Ash-Saki et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. This circuit is often used for demonstrating the different probabilities of correct results.</p><p>Striking a trade-off between quantum computer noise and queuing time. Both quantum computer noise assessment and queuing number awareness are crucial for quantum computer selection, which can make the execution more reliable and time-saving. Given that the quantum circuit needs two qubits, eight potential quantum computers can be used, except ibmq armonk with only one qubit. U1 first compared the noises of different quantum computers in the past week (R1) and set the time interval as one day in the control panel. U1 then set the "Qubit Noise" as the readout error (R6). By simply glancing at all the available quantum computers, U1 immediately noticed that ibm perth has the least qubit noise (i.e., the best qubit performance) from 2022-2-27 to 2022-3-5, as indicated by the consistently large blue circles (Fig. 6 A 1 ). The gate error rate of ibm perth was rather low on the current day (i.e., 2022-3-5), though it fluctuated from 2022-2-28 to 2022-3-3 as indicated by the density area charts (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6</ref> A 2 ). He then noticed the quantum computer ibmq manila, whose gate error rates have been stable in the past week, staying below 1% (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6 A 4</ref> ). Meanwhile, the qubit noise of ibmq manila is quite low via inspecting the blue circles. Thus, U1 concluded that the noise of quantum computers ibm perth and ibmq manila is the least among all quantum computers. U1 evaluated ibm perth and ibmq manila to the same noise level regarding the qubit and gate errors. Furthermore, U1 noticed that the queuing numbers for ibm perth (i.e., 430 in total) were much larger than other computers, as indicated by the bar charts below the computer names. Given that the waiting time of ibm perth is a bit long, U1 finally selected ibmq manila for the subsequent quantum circuit execution.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">A B A5 [3,4] 3 4 [0,1] 0 1 [2,3] 2 3 [1,2] 1 2 [1,2] 1 2 [0,1] 0 1 [1,3]</formula><p>Unveiling the mask of low-fidelity compiled circuits. After selecting the appropriate quantum computer (i.e., ibmq manila), U1 then moved on to the next step (i.e., quantum circuit compilation). U1 further used VACSEN to filter the suitable compiled circuits on ibmq manila. U1 first changed the number of compilation times to 60 in the control panel. After a few seconds of compilation, all the compiled circuits were displayed in the Circuit Filtering View. Then, U1 sorted all the compiled circuits according to the gate scores (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6 B 1</ref> ). U1 noticed that the 60 compiled circuits have the same depth of 24, as indicated by the circles' horizontal coordinates. Meanwhile, from the radii of all the circles, U1 speculated that the two-qubit logical circuit can be compiled into four different physical circuits based on the qubit mapping algorithm. U1 randomly selected one compiled circuit from each category and switched to the Circuit Comparison View for a detailed comparison. U1 immediately noticed that the four circuits are assigned on different physical quantum gates on ibmq manila, as indicated by the four coupled bar charts in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6 B</ref> . For example, Circuit trans 24 with the highest gate scores assigned the CNOT gate on Gate cx3 4 and Qubits q3 and q4, whose gate error is minimal as indicated by the blue bar on the top. Also, U1 found that the two bars in Circuit trans 18 were in dark red, indicating that trans 18 utilized Gate cx1 2 and Qubit q2 with the highest error rate for the quantum circuit implementation. Thus, U1 decided to select Circuit trans 24 for the final execution. To test the effectiveness of VACSEN and make sure Circuit trans 24 was the circuit with the least noise, U1 also executed the other three compiled circuits. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6</ref> B 2 shows the fidelity distribution for the four compiled circuits. It was apparent that the preferred compiled circuit trans 24 represented by the black rectangle had the highest fidelity (89.4%). In contrast, the fidelity of the other three compiled circuits was 87.5%, 83% and 82.1%, respectively. U1 finally got the best execution results with the least noise with the help of VACSEN.</p><p>Selecting the best of a bad bunch. U1 planned to execute the two-qubit circuit on another quantum computer with small queuing numbers to see if it is possible to generate a high-fidelity result with little queuing time. As shown in the Computer Evolution View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6 A5</ref> ), the performance of ibmq lima's qubits was below average as indicated by the red circles, and several gates (Gate cx1 3 and Gate cx3 4) also performed badly in the past week according to their line segments' horizontal coordinates. However, due to the small queuing number of the quantum computer ibmq lima, as indicated by the bar chart below the computer name, U1 planned to execute on the noisy quantum computer ibmq lima to get a relatively reliable result in a short waiting time. After the circuit compilation and sorting of all the compiled circuits in the control panel, U1 found four types of compiled circuits from Circuit Filtering View (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6 B 3</ref> ). U1 found that Circuit trans 0 had the least noise due to the color of bars for the implemented Gate cx1 2 and Qubits q1 and q2. Thus, U1 selected the Circuit trans 0 for the final circuit execution. To convince himself, U1 then executes other three compiled circuits. The fidelity of the execution is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">6 B 4</ref> . Circuit trans 0 showed a much better fidelity (83.1%) than the other circuits (77.5%, 74.4% and 58.5%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Case Study II -Shor's Algorithm</head><p>U6 used VACSEN to assess the quantum noise when trying to execute a large-scale quantum circuit, i.e., Shor's algorithm. Shor's algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[49]</ref> is a famous and widely-used quantum algorithm for integer factorization. Meanwhile, it is usually used for the evaluation of noise optimization algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">43]</ref>. The experiment was conducted on the IBM Quantum platform on March 5, 2022.</p><p>Balancing different noises of a quantum computer. Since the Shor's algorithm requires seven qubits, the potential quantum computers are those with no less than seven qubits, i.e., ibm lagos, ibm perth and ibmq jakarta. U6 changed the time range and interval to 30 and 7 respectively in the control panel, to explore their status in the past month. U6 first set the qubit noise to "readout error" in the control panel. U6 quickly found that ibmq jakarta (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> A 3 ) has the most stable gate noise from the density area charts (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1 A7</ref> ), while ibm perth's gate error rate was much higher than the other two computers due to the three red areas from 2022-1-19 to 2022-2-12. Particularly, the error rate of Gate cx4 5 (3.64%) on 2022-2-12 was significantly higher than that of the other gates (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1 A5</ref> ). Since the decoherence time matters for large-scale quantum algorithms <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Thus, U6 changed the qubit noise to "T1" to assess quantum computers regarding the decoherence time. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 A 4</ref> , U6 noticed that Computer ibm perth, whose gates are most noisy among all the three computers as illustrated above, has the best performance for T1 time as indicated by the large blue circles. Meanwhile, Computer ibm lagos's T1 time is the shortest among the three computers, though ibm lagos has the best performance in terms of gate error rate as indicated by the consistently blue circles in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> A 1 . Thus, U6 concluded that the three quantum computers have diverse noise patterns. Taking into account all the factors, i.e., the qubit noise, gate noise, and queuing number (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1 A 6</ref> ), U6 decided to select Computer ibmq jakarta for the final execution.</p><p>Breaking the tie: "similar" compiled circuits can be different. After selecting ibmq jakarta as the preferred quantum computer, U6 launched the compilation to map Shor's algorithm on this computer. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> B , the depths of all the compiled circuits were from 706 to 817, which were larger compared with the previous twoqubit quantum circuit. Meanwhile, U6 found that every circle has a different radius, indicating that a new compiled circuit was generated at every time of the compilation. Since minimizing the depth of the T1 Find the best-quality quantum computer regarding qubit's relaxation time T1. T2 Find the best-quality quantum computer regarding qubits' dephasing time T2. T3 Find the best-quality quantum computer regarding qubits' readout error. T4 Find the best-quality quantum computer regarding gates' error rate. T5 According to the tasks above, find the most suitable computer for the further execution. T6 Find the circuits of interest regarding the quality of building blocks. T7 Find the circuits of interest regarding the circuit depth. T8 Compare and highlight the compiled circuits with good gate-quality for the final execution. T9 Compare and highlight the compiled circuits with good qubit-quality for the final execution. circuit can minimize the decoherence noise for a large-scale circuit <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">60]</ref>, U6 regarded circuit depth as the major factor for the compiled circuit selection and sorted all the 60 compiled circuits by depth in an ascending order via the switch "Sort by depth" in the control panel (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 D</ref> ). U6 then clicked the top five circuits with a minor depth (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> B 1 ) for the comparison. Then, the five corresponding coupled bar charts were shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> C . For the gate error rates, U6 noticed that Gate cx1 2, which is highlighted by the purple dotted box in all the five circuits, has the highest error rate as indicated by the dark red bar. U6 then found that trans 19, trans 40, and trans 5 used Gate cx1 2 much less frequently than the other two compiled circuits (i.e., trans 6 and trans 56) as indicated by the small height of the three bars. Meanwhile, the usage times of the high-performance Gate cx3 5 in the above three circuits were much larger than those in the other two circuits, as indicated by the light blue bar's height. U6 commented, "Because the extra usage numbers of the high-nois gate cx1 2 were transferred to the low-noise gate cx3 5, making it more reliable." For the qubit noise comparison, U6 noticed that Qubit q6, highlighted by the purple box, has the highest noise among all qubits as indicated by the dark red bars. Also, it was apparent Circuit trans 5 used Qubit q6 most often as indicated by the bar heights, which was far above the reference value as highlighted by the black box. Thus, U6 decided to execute Circuit trans 19 due to its smaller depth than trans 40, though they have a similar noise level. After waiting for a while, the system displayed the fidelity distribution (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 E</ref> ), showing that the fidelity of Circuit trans 19 (73.6%) was the highest among the five circuits, as U6 expected. Meanwhile, U6 found that the result fidelities of trans 19 and trans 40 were at the first tier of less-noise circuits (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> C 1 ) due to the similar visual evidence of the corresponding coupled bar charts, while the average fidelity for the other three circuits was 58%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">USER INTERVIEWS</head><p>To further evaluate the effectiveness of VACSEN, we conducted in-depth user interviews with the target users working on quantum computing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Study Design</head><p>Participants and Apparatus. We invited 12 participants (2 females) from six different educational institutions and a national research laboratory to join our in-depth user interviews. The participants are different from the experts participated in the pilot study. Specifically, U1-5 are postgraduate students working on quantum computing. U6 is a research staff from a research laboratory for quantum machine learning. U7-12 are professors with an average of over five years of research experience in the quantum computing-related research fields. Among them, U8-9 's current research direction is the qubit mapping algorithm. To guarantee that the findings from the interviews are general for common users,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q1</head><p>The system provides enough evidence to inform the noise in quantum computer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q2</head><p>The system enables the exploration and comparison of the noise in different compiled circuits.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q3</head><p>The system can facilitate noise mitigation for the quantum circuit execution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q4</head><p>The overall visual design is easy to understand. Q5</p><p>The visual designs of circuit-like design are helpful for assessing the noise in quantum computers Q6</p><p>The design of the coupled bar charts for compiled circuit comparison is effective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q7</head><p>The user interaction of the visualization is smooth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Q8</head><p>The interaction to support the communication between the remote quantum computing platform is robust Q9</p><p>The visual analytics system is easy to use Q10 The visual analytics system is easy to learn Q11 I would like to use the visual analytics system to mitigate the noise in quantum computing in the future. Q12 I will recommend the visual analytics system to my colleagues working on quantum computing.</p><p>Table <ref type="table">2</ref>: The questionnaire consists of four parts: the effectiveness for quantum noise awareness (Q1-3), the visual design (Q4-6), the user interactions (Q7-8) and the usability (Q9-12).</p><p>none of the participants has a background in visualization or HCI. The user interviews were conducted through the online zoom meetings due to the COVID-19 pandemic. In addition, the participants were asked to use a monitor with a resolution of 1920 × 1080 in advance.</p><p>Quantum Algorithms and Tasks. We provided three common quantum algorithms for quantum circuit implementation, i.e., Quantum Fourier Transform (QFT) algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> and Bernstein-Vazirani (BV) algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> (both with the depth of up to 50) and Shor's algorithm (with the depth of over 700). We asked participants to select the quantum algorithm of interest. Also, we asked participants to fulfill nine carefully-designed tasks to assess VACSEN, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">1</ref>.</p><p>Procedures. The user interview for each participant was conducted using the online VACSEN system. We recorded and took notes for each interview and their interaction processes. We first introduced the analysis workflow and the corresponding visual designs of VACSEN to the participant. After that, we showcased an example (i.e., the two-qubit circuit) to better illustrate the usage of VACSEN. The above tutorial lasted for about 25 minutes. After that, the participants were asked to accomplish the pre-defined tasks of selecting an appropriate quantum computer and an optimal compiled circuit for execution. Upon the exploration, participants were encouraged to describe the reasons for the selection in a think-aloud manner. The aforementioned tasks lasted about 40 minutes. We also invited every participants to rate the VACSEN system based on a 7-point Likert scale from four aspects shown in Table <ref type="table">2</ref>. Finally, we further conducted a post-study interview with each participants, which lasted about 25 minutes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Result</head><p>We summarized all participants' detailed feedback as follows:</p><p>The Effectiveness for Noise Awareness. Most participants (rating mean = 5.83, rating sd = 1.03) agreed that VACSEN can facilitate noise awareness and mitigation in quantum computing. Four participants (U1-3, U11) highly appreciate the temporal noise analysis for quantum computers. U11 commented, "It is beneficial that I can visually analyze the time-series pattern of various noises. For example, I find that the qubit readout error of ibmq jakarta 's q5 and q6 is always worse than that of other qubits, which is really intuitive" Also, three participants (U5-6, U10) commented that the proposed workflow to support the quantum computer and compiled circuit selection is quite helpful. U10 said, "In my daily work, I need to wait for even hours for my quantum machine learning circuit execution. Now, VACSEN can save me a great number of time to get a similar high-fidelity result from other quantum computers with much less queuing time." In addition,  all participants (U1-12) were very interested in the communication between VACSEN and the remote quantum computing platform IBM Q. U8 reported that the real-time execution makes VACSEN even more valuable and practical compared with other theoretical approaches.</p><p>Usability. Most participants are in favor of the usability of VACSEN (rating mean = 5.88, rating sd = 1.37). U1-5 mentioned that VACSEN is really user-friendly and easy to use for quantum computing researchers and developers. U4 commented that the interface is really what quantum computing users want to use due to the intuitive designs. U6 also praised VACSEN, "For quantum machine learning, the model training device's noise state significantly impacts the model performance, and the prediction process also requires to be run on the quantum computer which has the same noise state as the one for model training. To this end, I believe the interface is the one we are looking for to complete the noise assessments." Meanwhile, U8-9, who are doing research on qubit mapping algorithm, commented, "I believe VACSEN will be helpful for our current research topic of quantum network routing. We can utilize VACSEN to host our different routing algorithm as it can reflect various noises in real-time." U5 mentioned he will utilize VACSEN for his daily circuit execution rather than a blind execution in the past. Meanwhile, he expressed the desire to recommend VACSEN to his colleagues in his research lab.</p><p>Visual Design and Interactions. The majority of the participants like the effective and user-friendly visual design (rating mean = 6.02, rating sd = 0.81) and flexible user interactions (rating mean = 6.04, rating sd = 1.12) of VACSEN. Four participants (U5-8) mentioned that the circuit-like design is amazing, which encodes the topology and metrics simultaneously for each timestamp. Meanwhile, U6 and U7 commented that the density area chart within each block of Computer Evolution View is very informative. U6 mentioned, "To my surprise, the design can visualize the distribution of all quantum gates' error rates. I can glance at the gates' density area charts and individual line segments and compare them between different quantum computers." For the user interactions, U1-12 confirmed that the system's interactions are really smooth and easy to use. U9 commented, "I found it is easy to switch between different noise attributes, which meets the needs to fit different quantum algorithm scenarios."</p><p>Suggestions. Despite the positive feedback, several participants also gave suggestions to improve VACSEN. U2 suggested that synchronous circuit execution should be more time-saving. U11 pointed out the selection of quantum computers can consider the correlations between various noises. U10 commented that he would be happy if the VAC-SEN system could support his research domain, i.e., quantum machine learning.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">DISCUSSION</head><p>In this section, we first summarize the lessons we learned during the development of VACSEN. Then, we discuss the limitations of VACSEN.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1">Lessons</head><p>We learned many lessons from the system design and implementation.</p><p>Critical importance of visualization for quantum computing. As shown in the above evaluations, VACSEN received highly positive feedback from the target users. Among all the feedback, they emphasize the strong needs and critical importance of visualization approaches. As various noises originates from the inherent noise in current quantum computers, they really need an interactive way to investigate the reasons behind the errors of running a quantum algorithm. VACSEN is only the first step to address such kinds of needs in both visualization and quantum computing field, which can play an even more important role in reliable, accessible, and transparent quantum computing.</p><p>Intuitive visual designs matter much for quantum computing users. While designing the prototype of VACSEN, we attempted to visualize all the noise attributes of qubits and gates simultaneously, which resulted in a sophisticated visual design. However, during our regular meeting with the five domain experts (Section 4.1), they pointed out that it is really confusing for them to explore the system because learning the complex visual designs has a steep learning curve for target users. Therefore, we simplified the visual designs, and further proposed intuitive and novel designs, such as the circuit style design and coupled bar chart to ensure that each quantum computing user can easily use it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2">Limitations</head><p>Our evaluations have shown that VACSEN can effectively enable noise awareness for the execution of quantum algorithms. However, the proposed approach still has limitations.</p><p>Calibration Data Resolution. VACSEN can extract the latest calibration data to portray the performance of a quantum computer. However, according to our analysis of the calibration data, we found that the actual resolution of the data is sometimes larger than one day. In addition, we found that the updating of the calibration data may suspend for a few days (e.g., ibmq bogota).</p><p>Visual Scalability. According to the feedback of domain experts, general users will often access and use only quantum computers with a relatively small number of qubits (e.g., up to 16) in most situations. Our case studies and user interviews have confirmed that VACSEN can work well for these situations. However, VACSEN may suffer from scalability issues when it is used to explore quantum computers with an extreme number of qubits (e.g., 127).</p><p>Generalizability. VACSEN is mainly tested using the data collected from IBM Quantum. However, it can be easily extended to other cloud quantum computing platforms (e.g., Rigetti), as the workflow and performance data of quantum computers are similar across different quantum computing platforms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">CONCLUSION</head><p>We present VACSEN, an interactive visual analytics approach to support noise awareness in quantum computing. To inform the visual design, we identified six design requirements for visually analyzing a quantum computing-specific problem. We proposed two novel quantum computing-specific designs, i.e., the circuit-like design and coupled bar chart, to facilitate the temporal analysis of noise in quantum computers and in-depth comparison of compiled circuits. We conducted case studies and in-depth user interviews with 12 target users to demonstrate the effectiveness of VACSEN. The results show that VACSEN can effectively make the users aware of various noises and further improve the reliability of the execution result for a given quantum circuit.</p><p>In future work, we will enhance the scalability of VACSEN in terms of facilitating noise evaluation on quantum computers with a larger number of qubits. Also, it will be interesting to enable automated recommendation of desirable quantum computers and compiled circuits in VACSEN and further enhance its usability and effectiveness in helping users select the optimal quantum computer and compiled circuit.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4: Computer Evolution View. (A) The time-varying quality of all usable quantum computers are visualized using the uniform timeslicing approach. (B) Design alternatives of the Computer Evolution View. The alternative designs (2) and (3) cannot visualize the connections among qubits. While the other alternative designs either suffer from visual clutters (4) in visualizing qubit connections or cannot clearly indicate gate errors (5).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5: Circuit Comparison View. (A) The Circuit Comparison View supports the in-depth comparison of multiple compiled circuits. (B)(C) Design alternatives of Circuit Comparison View. Both alternative designs cannot support an effective comparison of the usage times of qubits and quantum gates.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6: The case for two-qubit circuit. (A) Computer Evolution View for temporal analysis of ibm perth, ibmq manila, ibmq lima. (B) Comparison of compiled circuits for ibmq manila. Comparison of compiled circuits for ibmq lima.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7: The summary of the user feedback.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Property Matching Calculate Ref. Value Calibration Data ibm_lagos ibm_santiago ibmq_quito Compilation Quantum Computing Platform Visualization Storage</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Qubit Property</cell><cell>Gate Type</cell></row><row><cell>Connectivity</cell><cell>Gate Property</cell></row><row><cell>Reference Values</cell><cell>Reference Values</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Processing Data Cleaning Data Data Formatting Quantum Job Circuit Extraction Circuit Implementation Computer Evolution View Circuit Filtering View Circuit Conparison View VACSEN Execution Quantum Computer</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>All tasks are grouped by the analysis workflow, i.e., quantum computer selection and compiled circuit selection.</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_0">IBM Quantum: https://www.ibm.com/quantum-computing/</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_1">Rigetti: https://www.rigetti.com/</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_2">Only nine out of 10 quantum computers are in service on March 5, 2022 (the date of our case studies), while the unavailable quantum computer ibmq santiago is under maintenance</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>This research was supported by the Lee Kong Chian Fellowship awarded to Yong Wang by Singapore Management University. Qiang Guan was supported by US National Science Foundation CCF-2217021 and IBM quantum hub at NC State. We would like to thank the participants in our user interviews and anonymous reviewers for their feedback.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum machine intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Acampora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circuit compilation methodologies for quantum approximate optimization algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ash-Saki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 2020 53rd Annual IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)</title>
				<meeting>2020 53rd Annual IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="228" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experimental test of mermin inequalities on a five-qubit quantum computer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Alsina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Latorre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12314</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decoherence in adiabatic quantum computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Amin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Averin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nesteroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">22107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum supremacy using a programmable superconducting processor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Arute</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Arya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Babbush</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bacon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bardin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barends</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Biswas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boixo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Brandao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">574</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7779</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="510" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qure: Qubit re-allocation in noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ash-Saki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 56th Annual Design Automation Conference</title>
				<meeting>the 56th Annual Design Automation Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019. 2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Temporal analysis of quantum errors in nisq computers: an empirical study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Baheri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21227/bjfa-hs39</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">IEEE Dataport</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Domain-specific compilers for dynamic simulations of quantum materials on quantum computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bassman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gulania</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Powers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Linker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kalia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nakano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vashishta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quantum Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14007</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum complexity theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Vazirani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM Journal on computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1411" to="1473" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Muqut: Multi-constraint quantum circuit mapping on noisy intermediatescale quantum computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Saki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1911.08559</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Biamonte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wittek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Pancotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rebentrost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wiebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7671</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Brassard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Monroe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11032" to="11033" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum computers, factoring, and decoherence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Laflamme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zurek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">270</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5242</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1633" to="1635" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum computing simulation through reduction and decomposition optimizations with a case study of shor&apos;s algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>De Avila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Reiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e3961</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Codar: A contextual duration-aware qubit mapping for various nisq devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2020 57th ACM/IEEE Design Automation Conference (DAC)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimized quantum compilation for near-term algorithms with openpulse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gokhale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Javadi-Abhari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Earnest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Chong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 2020 53rd Annual IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)</title>
				<meeting>2020 53rd Annual IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="200" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to probability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Grinstead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Snell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<publisher>American Mathematical Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum entanglement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Horodecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Horodecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Horodecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Horodecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Reviews of Modern Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">865</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface code quantum computing by lattice surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Horsman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fowler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Devitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Van Meter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Journal of Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">123011</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suppressing decoherence and improving entanglement by quantum-jump-based feedback control in two-level systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12336</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">the-quantum-computing-era-is-herewhy -it -mattersand -how -it -may -change -our -world / ?sh = c6eb35a5c2b1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.forbes.com/sites/ibm/2020/01/16/" />
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2022" to="2023" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The quantum computing era is here: Why it matters, and how it may change our world</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A co-design framework of neural networks and quantum circuits towards quantum advantage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The emergence of classical properties through interaction with the environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Joos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zeitschrift für Physik B Condensed Matter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="243" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized benchmarking of quantum gates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Knill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Leibfried</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Reichle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Britton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Blakestad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Langer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ozeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seidelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wineland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12307</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grover&apos;s search algorithm: an optical approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kwiat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schwindt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Modern Optics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2-3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tackling the qubit mapping problem for nisqera quantum devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twenty-Fourth International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems</title>
				<meeting>the Twenty-Fourth International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1001" to="1014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum error correction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lidar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quflow: Visualizing parameter flow in quantum circuits for understanding quantum computation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2018 Proceedings of IEEE Scientific Visualization Conference</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Qucloud: A new qubit mapping mechanism for multiprogramming quantum computing in cloud environment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2021 IEEE International Symposium on High-Performance Computer Architecture (HPCA)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="178" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Informational distance on quantum-state space</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphstatevis: Interactive visual analysis of qubit graph states and their stabilizer groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 2021 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE)</title>
				<meeting>2021 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="384" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the impact of quantum computing technology on future developments in high-performance scientific computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vuik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ethics and Information Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A nested model for visualization design and validation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Munzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="921" to="928" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Visualization analysis and design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Munzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>CRC press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum computation and quantum information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design space exploration in the mapping of reversible circuits to ibm quantum computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Niemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>De Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dueck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Drechsler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2020 23rd Euromicro Conference on Digital System Design (DSD)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="407" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A variational eigenvalue solver on a photonic quantum processor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peruzzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Shadbolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-H</forename><surname>Yung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-Q</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Love</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aspuru-Guzik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>O'brien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum computing in the nisq era and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Preskill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">79</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Demonstration of universal parametric entangling gates on a multi-qubit lattice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reagor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Osborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tezak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Staley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Prawiroatmodjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scheer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Alidoust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Didier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Da Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3603</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A day in the life of a quantum error</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Resch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tannu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Karpuzcu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Qureshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Architecture Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey and tutorial on security and resilience of quantum computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Saki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Phalak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Suresh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Topaloglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE European Test Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021. 2021</date>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The nisq analyzer: Automating the selection of quantum computers for quantum algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Breitenbücher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Leymann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Weder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Symposium and Summer School on Service-Oriented Computing</title>
				<meeting>Symposium and Summer School on Service-Oriented Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="85" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automating the comparison of quantum compilers for quantum circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Leymann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Weder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Symposium and Summer School on Service-Oriented Computing</title>
				<meeting>Symposium and Summer School on Service-Oriented Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum decoherence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schlosshauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">831</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Design study methodology: Reflections from the trenches and the stacks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sedlmair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Munzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2431" to="2440" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network community detection on small quantum computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shaydulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ushijima-Mwesigwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Safro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mniszewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Alexeev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advanced Quantum Technologies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1900029</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing efficient qca logical circuits with power dissipation analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sheikhfaal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Angizi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sarmadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moaiyeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sayedsalehi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microelectronics Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polynomial-time algorithms for prime factorization and discrete logarithms on a quantum computer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantum computing platforms: assessing the impact on quality attributes and sdlc activities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sodhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kapur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2021 IEEE 18th International Conference on Software Architecture (ICSA)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="91" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimality study of existing quantum computing layout synthesis tools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1363" to="1373" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Not all qubits are created equal: a case for variability-aware policies for nisq-era quantum computers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tannu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Qureshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twenty-Fourth International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems</title>
				<meeting>the Twenty-Fourth International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="987" to="999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shorvis: A comprehensive case study of quantum computing visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 2017 International Conference on Virtual Reality and Visualization</title>
				<meeting>2017 International Conference on Virtual Reality and Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="365" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to quantum computation reliability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Thornton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2020 IEEE International Test Conference (ITC)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quantum circuit compilation: An emerging application for automated reasoning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Venturelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rieffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Booth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Narayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nanda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compiling quantum circuits to realistic hardware architectures using temporal planners</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Venturelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rieffel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quantum Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25004</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automated quantum hardware selection for quantum workflows</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Weder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Leymann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electronics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">984</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wiebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kapoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Svore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1412.3489</idno>
		<title level="m">Quantum deep learning</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mapping quantum circuits to ibm qx architectures using the minimal number of swap and h operations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Burgholzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zulehner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 2019 56th ACM/IEEE Design Automation Conference (DAC)</title>
				<meeting>2019 56th ACM/IEEE Design Automation Conference (DAC)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient methodology for mapping quantum circuits to the ibm qx architectures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zulehner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Paler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wille</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1226" to="1236" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
