<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Mapping Color to Meaning in Colormap Data Visualizations</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Karen</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schloss</surname></persName>
							<email>kschloss@wisc.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Connor</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gramazio</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Allison</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Silverman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Madeline</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
							<email>madeline@wheatoncollege.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Audrey</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<email>aswang@alumni.caltech.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><surname>Connor</surname></persName>
							<email>connor@cs.brown.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Taylor</forename><forename type="middle">• A</forename><surname>Silverman</surname></persName>
							<email>taylorsilverman@alumni.brown.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology and Wisconsin Institute for Discovery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Wisconsin-Madison</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Brown University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Brown University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology and Wisconsin Institute for Discovery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Wisconsin-Madison</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied and Computational Mathematics, California Institute of Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Mapping Color to Meaning in Colormap Data Visualizations</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Visual Reasoning</term>
					<term>Visual Communication</term>
					<term>Colormaps</term>
					<term>Color Perception</term>
					<term>Visual Encoding</term>
					<term>Visual Design</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Fig. 1. Example trial in which participants reported whether there were more alien animal sightings early or late in the day (left) and colormaps constructed from four color scales tested on black and white backgrounds in Experiment 1 (right). In the example trial, the right side of the colormap is darker, the color scale is oriented so dark is high in the legend, and the legend text is positioned so &quot;greater&quot; is high in the legend. However, the side of the colormap that was darker, the orientation of the color scale in the legend (dark-high or light-high), and the position of the text in the legend (&quot;greater&quot;-high or &quot;fewer&quot;-high) were independently varied in the experiment. Thus, participants had to interpret the legend on every trial to know the correct answer. The datasets used to generate the colormaps also varied across trials (see Experiment 1 Methods for details).</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>When people interpret colormap data visualizations, they are faced with a task of visual reasoning-forming conceptual inferences from visual input. For instance, to interpret weather maps, neuroimages, and gene expression matrices, people make conceptual inferences about weather patterns, neural activity, and gene co-expression from perceived variations in color.</p><p>Both perceptual and cognitive factors influence people's ability to complete this visual reasoning task. Perceptually, they must be able to discriminate perceptual features that correspond to different quantities (e.g., perceive a difference between two shades of blue that represent different amounts of neural activity in neuroimages). Cognitively, they must be able to comprehend concepts underlying the depicted data (e.g., understand implications of observing greater neural activity in one brain region than another). At the interface between perception and cognition, people must interpret how perceptual features map onto concepts that are represented by the data (e.g., determine which shades of blue map onto which amounts of neural activity).</p><p>During this process, people construct inferences about how visual features map onto concepts, based on the visual input they perceive and the relevant concepts in the particular context <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. It is easier for people to interpret visualizations when their inferred mapping matches the encoded mapping in the visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>, even when a legend clearly specifies the encoded mapping <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. The question is, what factors determine people's inferred mappings? To address this question, we studied how inferred color-quantity mappings for colormap data visualizations were influenced by relations between colors within colormaps and colors of the background.</p><p>From previous literature, it is unclear how varying the background influences people's inferred mappings for colormap data visualizations (see Section 2.3.1). There are three types of biases that could determine inferred mappings, which have different implications for the role of the background. A dark-is-more bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref> implies people infer that darker colors map to larger quantities, regardless of the background color. A contrast-is-more bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> implies people infer that higher-contrast colors map to larger quantities, which depends on the background (i.e., dark is more on light backgrounds; light is more on dark backgrounds). An opaque-is-more bias implies people infer that more opaque colors map to larger quantities, which depends on the background in the same manner as the contrast-is-more bias, but only when the colormap appears to vary in opacity.</p><p>We tested for these biases by presenting participants with colormaps of fictitious alien animal sightings ( <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>), and evaluating their response time to report whether there were more sightings early or late in the day. We varied the encoded color-quantity mapping in the legend ("dark-more" or "light-more" encoding), as well as the color scale used to construct the colormap and the color of the background. By determining which encoded mappings resulted in faster response times for different colormap and background combinations, we learned about the conditions under which inferred mappings were affected by the background. Our results demonstrate:</p><p>• The role of the background differs depending on the kind of color scale used to construct the colormap and its relation with the background. The background only matters if the colormap appears to vary in opacity.</p><p>• When colormaps do not appear to vary in opacity, inferred mappings are dominated by a dark-is-more bias with no effect of the background. This finding challenges a pure version of the contrast-is-more bias.</p><p>• When colormaps do appear to vary in opacity, inferred mappings contain an opaque-is-more bias. The strength of the opaque-ismore bias depends on the strength of apparent opacity variation. The opaque-is-more bias is a nuanced version of the contrastis-more bias because contrast with the background only matters when there is apparent variation in opacity.</p><p>By distinguishing between dark-is-more, contrast-is-more, and opaque-is-more biases, our results unite prior results and illustrations in the literature, and resolve seemingly conflicting claims.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>In this section, we first discuss related work on colormaps, followed by the motivation for our current approach.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Colormap Data Visualizations</head><p>Previous work on colormap data visualizations can be grouped into three main types: (1) designing color scales for colormaps, (2) selecting color scales according to data and task, and (3) encoding semantics in colormap visualizations. We briefly touch on the first two types and then go into greater depth on encoding semantics, given that is the topic of the present study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1">Designing color scales for colormaps</head><p>Extensive research has focused on defining the properties of color scales that result in effective colormaps. In a comprehensive review, Bujack et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> organized these properties into distinct categories, highlighting three categories for which they defined mathematical formulations: discriminative power, uniformity, and order.</p><p>Discriminative power relates to the amount of distinct colors observers can perceive in a color scale. Bujack et al.'s mathematical formulation of discriminative power focused on distance in color space, A C B D <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>. The top row shows value-by-alpha maps from Roth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> on (A) white and (B) black backgrounds. The colormaps are different on the two backgrounds. The most saturated color is interpolated with the background color, consistent with apparent variation in opacity. The bottom row shows approximations of the colormaps from McGranaghan <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, based on the color coordinates reported in the paper. The colormaps are the same on the (C) white and (D) black background. The most saturated color is in the middle of the color scale with lighter and darker colors that are less saturated, inconsistent with apparent opacity variation.</p><p>but perceptual discriminability also depends on additional factors, including trajectory in color space <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p><p>Uniformity relates to the consistency in perceived differences between pairs of equidistant points that are sampled from different parts of a color scale. In a uniform scale, pairs of points that are equidistant should appear equally different.</p><p>Order relates to the appearance that colors in the color scale follow a natural progression. For some color scales, the order is easy to perceive when viewed in scale format (e.g., in a legend), but the order is difficult to perceive when viewed in colormap format, especially when the positions of the colors are scrambled. Rainbow colormaps are notorious for this problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>, but it has been argued that this issue should not preclude their use <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28]</ref>.</p><p>For thorough discussions on factors involved in designing color scales, see Bujack et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, as well as <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49]</ref>, and references therein.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2">Selecting color scales according to data and task</head><p>Different color scales are more or less effective, depending on the properties of data they represent and the tasks needed to interpret the data (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49]</ref> for reviews).</p><p>One important property of the data to consider is the format of the underlying numeric scale (e.g., sequential or diverging) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. It is widely held that sequential data-varying from low to high-should be represented by sequential color scales-varying from light to dark or dark to light. In contrast, diverging data with a meaningful midpoint (e.g., neutral or average), should be represented by diverging color scales with a clear perceptual midpoint (e.g., gradations of saturation with an achromatic midpoint) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33]</ref>.</p><p>Another relevant property of the data is its spatial frequency composition. Rogowitz and Treinish <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> suggested using color scales that vary in lightness to reveal high spatial frequency patterns (fine details) and using color scales that vary in hue and saturation to reveal low spatial frequency patterns (courser changes). However, recent evidence suggests that hue variation helps observers perceive gradients when there are high spatial frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</p><p>People perform different kinds of tasks when interpreting colormaps, which include detecting surface structure and identifying specific quantities. Researchers have suggested that people are better at detecting surface structure of scalar field colormaps when color scales vary monotonically in lightness, compared to when color scales vary in hue <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47]</ref>. In contrast, people are better at identifying specific quantities when color scales vary in hue than when they vary only in light-ness. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref>. Based on these findings, some suggested that "redundant" color scales that vary in hue while also varying monotonically in lightness are robust for different kinds of tasks <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47]</ref>. Indeed, Liu and Heer reported that these kinds of scales were better for judging relative distances between colors sampled from the scale, compared with single-hue color scales varying monotonically in lightness and multi-hue color scales varying non-monotonically in lightness <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>. However, Reda, Nalawade, and Ansah-Koi reported that for perceiving spatial patterns in scalar field colormaps, multi-hue, divergent scales with non-monotonic lightness variation might be best <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3">Encoding semantics in colormap visualizations</head><p>Once one selects a well-designed scale that is appropriate for the task and data, one must decide how to map perceptual dimensions from the color scale onto conceptual dimensions represented by the data. Should larger quantities in the data be mapped to darker colors? To higher contrast colors? To more opaque colors?</p><p>Dark-is-more bias Early empirical work in cartography reported a dark-is-more bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. When presented with choropleth colormaps with no legend, participants inferred that darker regions represented larger quantities.</p><p>A subsequent eye-tracking study found that participants fixated on the legend less often and were more accurate at answering questions for 'conventional' lightness-based choropleth maps with dark-more encoding, compared with 'unconventional' hue-based colormaps <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. These results suggest 'conventional' lightness-based choropleth maps were easier to interpret. However, the authors did not test colormaps with light-more encoding, so it is unclear if these differences were because of a dark-is-more bias, or because it was easier to interpret the ordering among colors in the lightness-based scale than in the hue-based scale.</p><p>Contrast-is-more bias McGranaghan <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> suggested the dark-ismore bias is a special case of a contrast-is-more bias, in which people infer that darker colors map to larger quantities on light backgrounds, but lighter colors map to larger quantities on dark backgrounds. Mc-Granaghan <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> tested this hypothesis by asking participants to interpret choropleth colormaps presented on white, gray, and black backgrounds when there was no legend to specify the encoded mapping. Participants inferred that darker colors represented larger quantities for all three background conditions, but this effect was significantly reduced on the black background. These results challenged the hypothesis that there is a contrast-is-more bias, but also challenged the notion that there is only a dark-is-more bias that is unaffected by the background. To this point, Brewer <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> suggested that although higher values are usually represented by darker colors, this mapping can be reversed on dark backgrounds, as long as there is clear legend specifying the mapping.</p><p>The role of opacity variation? Roth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> proposed using 'value-by-alpha' maps, in which larger quantities map onto the highest contrast colors <ref type="figure">(Figure 2A and B)</ref>. Given McGranaghan's <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> empirical evidence challenging the contrast-is-more bias, one might think that the light-more encodings in value-by-alpha maps on dark backgrounds contradict people's inferred mappings. However, that might not be the case if the key factor is actually apparent opacity given the background, rather than color contrast (or distance in color space) from the background. If so, people may have an opaque-is-more bias, which to our knowledge, has not yet been empirically tested.</p><p>A colormap should appear to vary in opacity when the color scale is constructed by linearly interpolating between a reference color and a perceptually distinct background color. In the resulting color scale, the reference color is the highest contrast, or most distinct color from the background. Parts of the image containing the reference color appear as opaque foregrounds, and parts containing intermediate colors appear as foregrounds with varying amount of opacity, overlaid on the background. This is the basic principle for producing apparent variation in opacity in graphics software by adjusting sliders that control opacity or transparency <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</p><p>In Roth et al.'s <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> value-by alpha maps shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2A</ref> and B, there are two reference colors, saturated red and saturated blue.  <ref type="figure">Figure   Fig. 3</ref>. Illustrations of the conditions that produce apparent opacity variation in value-by-alpha maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, in which the figural region is a heterogeneous translucent surface (varying amounts of opacity) on a homogenous ground (left) and traditional perceptual transparency, in which the figural region is a homogeneous surface (constant amount of opacity) on a heterogeneous ground (right)</p><p>These colors are interpolated with the background color, which produces intermediate colors that appear to vary in opacity. This can be interpreted as a divergent color scale with maximally opaque endpoints and a minimally opaque midpoint.</p><p>In contrast, the color scale used in McGranaghan's <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> study (approximated in <ref type="figure">Figure 2C</ref> and D) curved in color space in a manner that would impede apparent variation in opacity on black or white backgrounds. That is, the lightest and darkest colors were low in saturation and the mid-level lightness colors were high in saturation, which would not occur if either endpoint was a reference color that varied in opacity. This color scale is similar to ColorBrewer Blue <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, which we studied in Experiment 1. This key difference could explain why light-more encoding on dark backgrounds may match people's inferred mappings for value-by-alpha maps, but not for the colormaps tested in McGranaghan's study. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> (left) illustrates conditions in the natural world that could produce the kind of apparent variation in opacity that is relevant to colormaps. Here, a surface with heterogeneous levels of opacity is superimposed on a homogeneous background. A similar percept might occur if discrete figural elements vary in density on a given background (e.g., variation in density of chocolate powder on whipped cream or density of snow on asphalt). The percept of opacity variation in these displays depends on the way colors vary with respect to each other and the background, regardless of their spatial arrangement. As Roth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> discuss, apparent opacity variation in colormaps must not depend on colors appearing in specific spatial relations because spatial arrangements of colored regions will vary depending on the dataset.</p><p>Research in perception has begun to work on understanding apparent variations in opacity on homogenous backgrounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, but these conditions differ from classic demonstrations of perceived opacity (more typically referred to as perceptual transparency) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40]</ref>. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> (right) illustrates the classic version, in which a homogenous surface of a constant level of opacity appears to be superimposed on a heterogeneous background. Here, the percept of opacity variation depends on spatial relations between the colored regions in the configuration (i.e., x-junctions).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Motivating Our Approach</head><p>We discuss three factors that motivated our approach for designing the experiments in this study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1">Measuring inferred mappings</head><p>Inferred mappings between perceptual features and concepts are typically measured in one of two ways. In the direct report method, participants are asked to interpret the meaning of perceptual features in visualizations that do not have legends or labels to specify the correct answer <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>. Without objectively correct answers, participants' reported interpretations reveal their inferred mappings. In the response time method, participants are asked to accurately interpret the meaning of perceptual features in visualizations that do have legends or labels to specify the correct answer <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. The response time method relies on the assumptions that (a) it is easier to interpret visualizations in which the encoding mapping matches the inferred mapping <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>, and (b) ease of interpretation can be operationalized as faster RTs. It follows that we can learn about inferred mappings by evaluating which encoded mappings facilitate faster RTs.</p><p>We chose the response time method, and compared RTs for colormaps with legends that encoded different mappings. One reason for this choice was our concern that if we explicitly asked participants to interpret unlabeled colormaps, they might try to be consistent across trials, even when we varied the background. Response time is an implicit measure that should be less subject to this sort of participant demand characteristic. We considered that McGranaghan <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> might have found that the dark-is-more bias weakened, but did not reverse on the black background because participants were trying to respond consistently across background conditions. However, given the results of our present study, we no longer have this concern about McGranaghan's findings (see General Discussion).</p><p>Another reason for choosing this method is that colormaps typically (though not always <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>) have legends or labels that specify the encoded mapping, and we sought to study colormaps under conditions in which they are typically observed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2">Using synthetic data to construct visualizations</head><p>Following prior literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>, we used synthetic data to construct the data visualizations used as test stimuli, enabling tight control over the stimulus parameters. We also used a fictitious cover story, explaining that the data were about alien animal sightings on Planet Sparl, to prevent participants from having preconceived notions about colors associated with the subject matter that 'produced' the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3">Specifying colors to produce colormaps</head><p>In laboratory experiments where the goal is to display colors that other researchers can perfectly reproduce in their own labs, it is critical to use careful monitor calibration procedures and specify colors in a device-independent color space. Here, we aimed to study colormaps that people use for real data visualizations, which are specified in device-dependent coordinates (e.g. RGB), and are typically viewed on personal computers or printed documents. Therefore, we chose to use pre-made color scales from MATLAB and ColorBrewer <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> for Experiment 1, and we generated color scales based on Roth et al.'s <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> value-by-alpha maps in Experiment 2. When we converted the RGB values of these color scales to CIELAB coordinates, we made standard assumptions about the white point and monitor characteristics, using MATLAB's rgb2lab function. The approach we used here is typical in the visualization literature, where the goal is to study visualizations that are robust to variations in viewing conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>. However, we note that these are only approximations of CIELAB coordinates, and to render true CIELAB coordinates it is necessary to carefully calibrate the display screen and verify that color presentation is accurate using a color measurement device.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">EXPERIMENT 1</head><p>In Experiment 1, we evaluated how the background color influenced inferred mappings when colormaps were constructed using various color scales that are standard for visualization ( <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>). In the experiment, participants saw colormaps of alien animal sightings and reported whether there were more sightings early or late in the day. We varied the encoded mapping such that the legend specified that darker colors meant greater amounts of sightings ('dark-more' encoding) on half of the trials and lighter colors meant greater amounts of sightings ('light-more' encoding) on the other half. By identifying which encoding conditions resulted in faster RTs, we learned about people's inferred mappings. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Participants</head><p>There were 30 participants (mean age = 22), who were undergraduates or members of the community at Brown University. They received either partial course credit or $10 for their participation. All had normal color vision (screened using the HRR Pseudoisochromatic Plates <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>) and gave informed consent. The Brown University Institutional Review Board approved the experimental protocol. Data from three additional participants were excluded (not analyzed), due to experimenter error in giving the instructions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Design and displays</head><p>The display for each trial contained a colormap data visualization with a legend specifying the encoded mapping (dark-more or light-more) <ref type="figure">(Figure 1</ref>; left). The colormap visualization was an 8 × 8 grid (6.5 cm × 6.5 cm) centered on the screen. The rows represented fictitious alien animal species, the columns represented time of day, and the color of each cell corresponded to frequency of sightings of each animal at each time point. To help participants categorize the sightings as early vs. late in the day, the left four columns were labeled "early" and the right four columns were labeled "late." A legend (5.5 cm tall × 0.5 cm wide) was displayed 2.25 cm to the right of the colormap. The colormap and legend appeared on either a white or black background (16.25 cm × 16.25 cm) centered on the screen. The surrounding monitor color was gray (RGB = [128, 128, 128]). The displays were presented on a ProArt PA246Q monitor (1920 × 1200 resolution, 67 cm diagonal). We generated the colormaps using four different color scales that varied monotonically in lightness: MATLAB Autumn, Hot, and Gray, and ColorBrewer Blue <ref type="figure">(Figure 1</ref>; right). We also included the MATLAB Jet color scale, which does not vary monotonically in lightness-both endpoints are dark. Given that our focus is on inferred mappings for color scales that vary monotonically in lightness, we reserved discussion of the Jet colormap for the Supplementary Material ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure S4</ref>). The colormap images and summary data from the experiments can be found on our website (https://schlosslab.discovery.wisc.edu/resources).</p><p>The data used to generate the colormaps were sampled from an arctangent curve with added normally-sampled noise <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 4</ref>). To generate the data for each row of the colormap, we discretized the arc tangent curve into eight bins, corresponding to the eight columns in the colormap display. We centered the arctangent curve between the fourth and fifth bins, such that half of the display was biased to have larger values than the other half. We then perturbed each arctangent value by sampling from a normal distribution with the mean equal to the arctangent value and the standard deviation equal to 0.25. When the values fell outside the [0,1] interval, we re-sampled until they were all within the correct range. For half of the datasets, the arctangent curve was oriented as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 4</ref>, and for the other half, it was left/right reversed. This enabled a left/right balance of the darker region (i.e., half of the colormaps contained the darker region on the left and the other half contained the darker region on the right).</p><p>There were 20 colormap conditions (5 color scales × 2 background colors × 2 left/right balances). For each colormap condition, we created 20 different colormaps with unique datasets generated using the sampling procedure described above. This enabled us to repeat the same conditions 20 times without having participants see the same images, which helped prevent them from memorizing the patterns. Participants saw 400 unique colormap images.</p><p>During the experiment, participants saw each of these 400 colormap images four times to accommodate four different legend conditions: 2 encoded lightness mappings (dark-more, light-more) × 2 legend text positions ("greater"-high, "fewer"-high). This was achieved by independently varying the orientation of the color scale in the legend (dark-high or light-high), and the position of the text in the legend ("greater"-high or "fewer"-high) (see <ref type="figure">Figure S1</ref> in the <ref type="figure">Supplementary  Material)</ref>. This design ensured that participants read the legend on every trial and could not merely look at which color or label was at the top or bottom of the legend to make a correct response. By showing each colormap image four times, one for each legend condition, we ensured that any differences in response times due to the legend conditions were not due to variations in the underlying data used to construct the colormaps. The combination of these 4 legend conditions x 400 unique colormaps described above produced 1600 trials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Procedure</head><p>Participants were told that they would see colormaps representing the amount of animal sightings on a distant planet, Sparl. The x-axis would represent time of day and the y-axis would represent type of animal. Each map would have a legend, and sometimes the larger numbers would be on the top of the legend and other times larger numbers would be at the bottom (no numbers were explicitly shown, only the labels "greater" and "fewer"). Their task would be to indicate whether there were more animals early (left) or late (right) in the day by pressing the left or right arrow key. They were asked to respond as quickly as possible while maintaining their accuracy. They were told that a tone would play each time they made an error, and that they would be notified of their accuracy periodically.</p><p>To help participants account for why they would see many colormaps of the same kind of data during the experiment, they were told that each map showed data measured from different locations on the planet, where different animals were visible different amounts at different times of day. On the instructions screen, there were eight different grayscale colormap data visualizations without legends so participants could see how the datasets could vary.</p><p>Prior to beginning the experiment, there were 20 practice trials, which were randomly selected from the set of all possible conditions. Each trial began with a 500 ms blank gray screen, followed by an experimental display containing the colormap and legend. This experimental display remained on the screen until participants made their response.</p><p>During the experiment, the colormaps were presented using a blocked randomized design: all 80 possible conditions (5 color scales × 2 backgrounds × 2 left/right balances × 2 encoded lightness mappings × 2 legend text positioning) were displayed once in a random order within each block before beginning the next block. Participants were given short breaks after each set of 20 trials. We recorded RT and accuracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Results and Discussion</head><p>To prepare the RTs for analysis, we first eliminated trials with errors (mean accuracy was 97%; range of accuracy across participants was 91%-99%). We then calculated the mean and standard deviation across all remaining trials for each participant, and pruned any trials that were +/-2 standard deviations from that participant's mean. Next, we calculated the mean across the remaining trials (out of 20) within each of the 80 experiment conditions and averaged over the left/right positioning of the darker region in the colormap. Given that legend text position was not central to our research question, and we only varied it to ensure participants read the legend on each trial, we present results involving legend text position in the Supplementary Material ( <ref type="figure">Figure  S2</ref>). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5A</ref> shows the mean RTs for dark-more and light-more encoded mappings, separated by color scale and background, but averaged over legend text position. Overall, the RTs were faster for dark-more encoding than light-more encoding and faster for the white background than the black background. RTs also varied across color scales (fastest for Autumn, slowest for Gray, with Hot and Blue in between).</p><p>These observations were supported by a repeated-measures ANOVA with 2 encoded lightness mappings (dark-more, light-more) x 2 backgrounds (white, black) x 4 color scales (Autumn, Hot, Blue, and Gray) x 2 legend text positions ("greater"-high, "fewer"-high). There were main effects of encoded lightness mapping (F(1,29) = 32.50, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .528), background (F(1,29) = 23.60, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .449), and color scale (F(3,87) = 20.49, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .414). We compared RTs for each pair of color scales using the Bonferroni correction (adjusted alpha = .008). RTs were faster for Autumn than Hot, Blue, and Gray (F(1,29) = 9.48, 20.23, 34.01 ps &lt;.008, η 2 p = .246, .411, .540, respectively). RTs for Hot and Blue did not differ (F &lt;1), but were faster for Hot than Gray and Blue than Gray (F(1,29) = 18.06, 19.43 ps &lt;.008, η 2 p = .384, .401). Critical for our question of how inferred mappings depend on the background, there was a 3-way interaction between encoded lightness mapping, background, and color scale (F(3,87) = 13.94, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .325). As evident in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5A</ref>, participants showed a dark-is-more bias for the Autumn, Hot, and Blue color scales, although it was reduced for the Blue color scale on the black background. The pattern was different for the Gray color scale, with faster RTs for dark-more encoding on the white background but no difference on the black background.</p><p>These observations were supported by ANOVAs within each color scale (2 encoded lightness mappings × 2 backgrounds). For Autumn, Hot, and Blue, there were main effects of encoded lightness mapping, with dark-more encoding resulting in faster RTs (F(1,29) = 28.19, 41.62, 17.85, ps &lt;.001, η 2 p = .493, .589, .381, respectively). This effect did not interact with the background for Autumn or Hot (Fs &lt;1), but did interact with the background for Blue (F(1,29) = 7.58, p = .010, η 2 p = .207). Despite this interaction, RTs for Blue were faster for dark-more encoding on both white backgrounds (F(1,29) = 19.74, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .405) and black backgrounds (F(1,29) = 9.72, p = .004, η 2 p = .251). For Gray, RTs were overall faster for dark-more encoding (F(1,29) = 9.82, p = .004,η 2 p = .253), but that was driven by the difference within the white background condition (F(1,29) = 30.98, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .516). Encoded lightness mapping interacted with background (F(1,29) = 21.05, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .421), with faster RTs for dark-more encoding on the white background as stated above, but a trend toward faster RTs for light-more encoding on the black background (F(1,29) = 3.31, p = .079, η 2 p = .102). Why did the background have different effects depending on the color scale? A possibility is that the color scales differed in their degree of apparent opacity variation. By viewing the colormaps along the x-axis in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5A</ref>, it may be observed that the Gray colormaps appear to vary in opacity, the Blue colormaps somewhat appear to vary in opacity, and the Autumn and Hot colormaps do not appear to vary in opacity. As discussed in Section 2.1.3, apparent opacity variation arises when a reference color is linearly interpolated with the background color. This suggests that we can estimate the degree of apparent opacity variation based on the degree to which the colors in the color scale deviate from the linear interpolation. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5B</ref>-C illustrates the differences in the trajectories of each color scale (squares and thick gray line) and the linear interpolation between the color scale's highest contrast color with the white background ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5B</ref>) and black background ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 5C</ref>) (circles and thin dashed line). Here, the color scales are plotted on the L* b* plane in CIELAB space. A version of this figure containing the L* a* plane of CIELAB space can be found in the Supplementary Material ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  S5</ref>). Notice that the Gray color scale falls along this interpolated line, Blue follows a curve that deviates slightly from the line, and Autumn and Hot deviate substantially from the line (the deviation for Autumn on the white background is more apparent on the L* a* plane).  We quantified these deviations in what we call an Opacity Variation Index defined as, log(z+1), where z is the root mean squared error (RMS) between each point in the color scale and the line between the highest-contrast color and the background. We used log RMS because we reasoned that small deviations from the line would strongly affect apparent variation in opacity, but the effect of further increasing the deviation should level off as apparent variation in opacity is broken. The Opacity Variation Index for each color scale on each background is displayed above each plot in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 5B and 5C</ref>. Smaller Opacity Variation Index values-less deviance from the line-indicate greater perceptual evidence for opacity variation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blue</head><p>We examined whether the Opacity Variation Index could account for the relative difference in RTs for dark-more and light-more encodings across color scales. <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref> illustrates the mean RT difference (darkmore encoding -light-more encoding) for each color scale as a function of the Opacity Variation Index for the white and black backgrounds. Generally, the points are below zero, which reflects the dark-is-more bias reported above. However, if the only effect present was the darkis-more bias, the points for each color scale would have the same shift below zero. Instead, the points fall along a line predicted by the Opacity Variation Index (white background: r = 0.969, p = .031; black background: r = -.999, p = .001). On the white background, RTs were especially faster for dark-more encoding when there was greater evidence for opacity variation (smaller Opacity Variation Indexes), which can be explained as cooperating dark-is-more and opaque-is-more biases. The opposite was true for the black background, which can be explained as conflicting dark-is-more and opaque-is-more biases.</p><p>The Gray color scale was an anomaly in this experiment as the only condition in which RTs were not faster for dark-more encodings than light-more encodings when the background was black. However, we predicted that it should be possible to replicate and extend this effect for other color scales that follow linear interpolations between the highest contrast color and the background. We test this prediction in Experiment 2.</p><p>In summary, Experiment 1 demonstrated that when color scales did not appear to vary in opacity, inferred mappings were dominated by a dark-is-more bias, regardless of the background. However, as evidence for opacity variation increased, inferred mappings became increasingly more influenced by an opaque-is-more bias. When the background was white, the opaque-is-more bias reinforced the dark-is-more bias (i.e., faster RTs for dark-more encoding). When the background was black, the opaque-is-more bias contradicted, and thereby dampened the dark-is-more bias.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">EXPERIMENT 2</head><p>Experiment 2 directly tested our hypothesis that there is an opaque-ismore bias. Participants saw colormaps that were generated from three different color scales, which were linear interpolations between blackwhite (analogous to Gray in Experiment 1), black-blue, and blue-white. These colormaps were presented on three possible background colors: black, blue, and white. Therefore, for each color scale, there were two backgrounds on which the color scales appeared to vary in opacity, one dark and one light, and one color scale in which the color did not appear to vary in opacity (see <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.1">Participants</head><p>There were 36 participants (mean age = 18.9), who were undergraduates at the University of Wisconsin-Madison and received partial course credit for their participation. All had normal color vision (screened using the HRR Pseudoisochromatic Plates <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>) and gave informed consent. The University of Wisconsin-Madison Institutional Review Board approved the experimental protocol. Unlike Experiment 1, where all participants were highly accurate (range from 91%-99%), we noticed early on that some participants in Experiment 2 were far less accurate (75%-77%). To approximate the accuracy levels from Experiment 1, we set a criterion for Experiment 2 that to be included in further analysis, participants had to have an overall accuracy of greater than 90%. This criterion excluded 6 participants, and our final sample size was n = 30 to match Experiment 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.2">Design and displays</head><p>The design and displays in Experiment 2 were similar to Experiment 1, except we tested three different color scales (black-white, blackblue, and blue-white) presented on three possible backgrounds (black, white, and blue). The coordinates for blue were the same as in Roth et al.'s blue value-by-alpha map <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, derived from ColorBrewer.org <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> [RGB = <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(56, 126, 185)</ref>]. The coordinates for black were [RGB = (0, 0, 0)] and for white were [RGB = (255, 255, 255)]. We created each color scale by linearly interpolating in RGB color space between the two endpoints, which is analogous to varying the alpha level of the a reference color on a given background (see Section 2.1.3).</p><p>The full design included 72 experimental conditions, from the orthogonal combinations of 3 color scales × 3 background colors × 2 encoded lightness mappings × 2 legend text positions × 2 left/right balances. As in Experiment 1, there were 20 replications of each condition, with different underlying datasets used to generate the colormaps in each replication, resulting in 1440 trials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.3">Procedure</head><p>The procedure was the same as in Experiment 1, except there were 72 trials per block in the blocked randomized design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Results and Discussion</head><p>As in Experiment 1, we prepared the RTs for analysis by first eliminating trials with errors (mean accuracy was 97%; range of accuracy across participants was 92%-99% after excluding participants with mean accuracy that was not greater than 90%; see Participants section). We then calculated the mean and standard deviation across all remaining trials for each participant, and pruned any trials that were +/-2 standard deviations from that participant's mean. Next, we calculated the mean across the remaining trials (out of 20) within each of the 72 experiment conditions and averaged over the left/right positioning of the darker region in the colormap. The results regarding legend text position are in the <ref type="figure">Supplementary Material (Figure S3)</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref> shows the mean RTs for dark-more and light-more encoded lightness mapping, separated by color scale and background and averaged over legend text position. For each color scale, the backgrounds are ordered along the x-axis such that the two pairs of bars to the left of the vertical divider are for color scales that should appear to vary in opacity-dark is more opaque on the light background (left) and light is more opaque on the dark background (right). These conditions are analogous to Gray in Experiment 1. Both the dark-is-more and opaque-is-more biases should be in effect for these conditions, so we expected faster RTs for dark-more encoded mappings on light background and equal or faster RTs for light-more encoded mappings on dark backgrounds. The pair of bars to the right of the vertical divider is for color scales that should not appear to vary in opacity. Only the dark-is-more bias should be in effect, so we expected faster RTs for dark-more encoded mappings.</p><p>RTs were overall faster for dark-more encoding than light-more encoding, but this effect varied depending on the background. This observation was supported by a repeated measures ANOVA with 2 encoded lightness mappings (dark-more, light-more) × 3 background/color scale relations (opacity variation light-background, opacity variation darkbackground, no opacity variation) × 2 legend text positions ("greater"high, "fewer"-high) × 3 color scales (black-white, black-blue, whiteblue). There was a main effect of lightness mapping (F(1,29) = 6.43, p = .017, η 2 p = .182) and a lightness mapping × background interaction (F(2,58) = 50.47, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .635). There was no 3-way interaction between lightness mapping, background, and color scale (F(4,116) = 1.73, p = .149, η 2 p = .056), which suggests that the general pattern in the lightness mapping × background interaction was comparable across color scales. Therefore, for further tests to understand the lightness mapping × background interaction, we averaged over color scale.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A B</head><p>-100 100 0 100 L* b* <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>. (A) CIELAB coordinates of the three color scales and three backgrounds tested in Experiment 2. The color scales are interpolations between the white and black, white and blue, and black and blue background colors. (B) Example colormaps for generated from the three color scales and 3 backgrounds in A. Here, the same colormap is presented on each background for direct comparison, but in the experiment participants saw different colormaps generated from the same color scales on different backgrounds. Each color scale appears on a background that matches its lightest endpoint (darker should appear more opaque), darkest endpoint (lighter should appear more opaque), or neither end point (positive diagonal; should not appear to vary in opacity).  For color scales that appeared to vary in opacity on light backgrounds (left pairs of bars in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref>), RTs were faster for dark-more encoding (F(1,29) = 41.13, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .586). For color scales that appeared to vary in opacity on dark backgrounds (center pairs of bars in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure  8</ref>), RTs were faster for light-more encoding (F(1,29) = 21.25, p &lt;.001, η 2 p = .423). For colors that did not appear to vary in opacity given their background (right pairs of bars in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref>), RTs were faster for dark-more encoding (F(1,29) = 15.00, p = .001, η 2 p = .341). Upon inspecting the data in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref>, there was one result that appeared to violate our predictions described above. There seemed to be no dark-is-more bias for the blue-white color scale on the black background, even though the blue-white color scale should not appear to vary in opacity on the black background. We believe this result may be due to carryover effects from the other trials with the black background. On those other trials, the color scales did appear to vary in opacity, with lighter colors appearing more opaque. This led to competing opaque-is-more and dark-is-more biases, which mitigated the dark-is-more bias on the black background. We suspect this suppressed dark-is-more bias on black backgrounds carried over to the blue-white color scale, even though it did not appear to vary in opacity. Further investigation is necessary to understand how such contextual influences might bias inferred mappings.</p><p>In summary, the results of Experiment 2 supported the existence of an opaque is more bias. When color scales appeared to vary in opacity, RTs were faster for dark-more encoding on light backgrounds and light-more encoding on dark backgrounds. When color scales did not appear to vary in opacity, RTs were generally faster for dark-more encoding, consistent with the dark-is-more bias.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">GENERAL DISCUSSION</head><p>The goal of this study was to understand the conditions under which people's inferred color-quantity mappings for colormap data visualizations were influenced by the background color.</p><p>The existing literature paints a confusing, and sometimes conflicting, picture regarding the role of the background. For example, Cuff <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> provided evidence for a dark-is-more bias without considering the background color. McGranaghan <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> suggested there is a contrastis-more bias, but when he varied the background color, the dark-ismore biased persisted, though was reduced on dark backgrounds. This result challenged the pure form of the contrast-is-more bias, but also suggested there is more to inferred color-quantity mappings than just a dark-is-more bias. Roth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> proposed the use of value-by-alpha maps, which encode larger quantities in higher contrast, more opaque colors. This includes encoding larger quantities in lighter colors on dark backgrounds. Based on McGranaghan's findings one might believe this light-more encoding on dark backgrounds would contradict people's inferred mappings. Despite this, Roth et al.'s illustrations encoding larger quantities in lighter, more opaque colors on dark backgrounds appear compelling, though this was not empirically tested.</p><p>The present results clarify this confusion. The degree to which the background color influenced people's inferred color-quantity mappings depended on apparent variation in opacity. When color scales did not appear to vary in opacity, inferred mappings were dominated by a dark-is-more bias. As apparent opacity variation increased, inferred mappings became more influenced by an opaque-is-more bias. These results are relevant to interpreting choropleth maps typically used in cartography <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>, as well as heat maps commonly used in a variety of disciplines including genetics <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and neuroscience <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</p><p>The results from Experiment 1 explain why McGranaghan <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> found that the dark-is-more bias was reduced, but not reversed, on a black background. Similar to the ColorBrewer Blue scale tested in our study, McGranaghan's color scale only weakly appeared to vary in opacity (see <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>) so the opaque-is-more bias did not supersede the dark-is-more bias. We were initially concerned that McGranaghan's results were influenced by participants' trying to maintain consistent responses on different backgrounds. However, we essentially replicated his result with a different, more implicit measure, which mitigated this concern.</p><p>The results from Experiment 2 provide behavioral evidence supporting the effectiveness of the value-by-alpha maps that were previously illustrated by Roth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> but not empirically tested. In general, when there was strong evidence that the color scales varied in opacity, participants inferred that higher-contrast/more-opaque colors mapped to larger quantities.</p><p>From a practical perspective, our results suggest that it is easiest for people to interpret colormaps that are designed such that the dark-ismore and opaque-is-more bias result in congruent inferred mappings. This occurs when darker, more opaque colors map to larger quantities on a light background. However, there might be cases in which designers want to present the same colormap on different backgrounds (e.g., slides with a white or black background). In such cases, our results suggest using dark-more encoding and avoiding colormaps that appear to vary in opacity on any background. Colormaps that curve substantially through color space, such as Hot, should not appear to vary in opacity on any background because no background color would enable linear interpolation between all colors in the color scale and the background color.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Open questions</head><p>We now consider open questions to be addressed in future research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1">Explanation for dark-is-more and opaque-is-more biases</head><p>A fundamental question is why there are dark-is-more and opaque-ismore biases. It has been suggested that the dark-is-more bias arises from changes in appearance as more ink is added to a page <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and that contrast effects might arise from percepts of varying density of dark elements on light backgrounds or light elements on dark backgrounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. The relation between opacity and quantity can be observed in the way pigmented chemicals appear to vary as their concentration increases in a clear solution (Beer-Lambert Law <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref>). It is also possible that these biases are related to exposure to conventions in data visualization and map making, especially given that dark-is-more mappings became a standard for visualizing statistics in the early 1900s <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>.</p><p>These exposure accounts are consistent with the Color Inference Framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>, which proposes that people continually form colorconcept associations based on their experiences of co-occurrences between colors and concepts in the world. To interpret the meanings of colors in color-coding systems, people draw on these associations to infer color-concept mappings in the particular context.</p><p>To evaluate whether these biases are learned from visualization conventions, as opposed to experiences of how colors vary as element density varies in the natural world, it would be helpful to study a population that has not been exposed to abstract representations of data. It would also be interesting to study experts in fields that conventionally use light-more encodings in their data visualizations, such as neuroscientists <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> and radiologists <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. It is possible they would infer light-more mappings for visualizations in their area of expertise, but would infer dark-more mappings for visualizations outside of that domain. Alternatively, they might have learned light-more inferred mappings that generalize across domains. If so, they might not show the dark-is-more bias observed in the present study, and dark-more encodings would contract their inferred mappings, making visualizations harder for them to interpret.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2">Opacity Variation Index</head><p>We defined the Opacity Variation Index for a given color scale and background as the deviation between each point in the color scale and the line between the highest-contrast endpoint of the color scale and the background. This is a simple way to operationalize apparent variation in opacity, but there are conditions under which it could be problematic. For the present color scales and background, it was straightforward to specify which endpoint contrasted most with the background (i.e., furthest distance in CIELAB space). However, it would be possible to have a color scale and background for which both endpoints equally contrasted with the background. Understanding how best to quantify apparent variation in opacity is an open question.</p><p>Further, we defined the Opacity Variation Index with respect to metric properties in CIELAB color space, but empirical experiments are necessary to test whether this, or any other metric, corresponds to people's perceived variation in opacity. If it turns out that people are not sensitive to these kinds of metrics, but the metrics still predict inferred mappings for visualizations, such information would still be a useful construct for anticipating conditions under which interpretations of colormaps are influenced by the background.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.3">Spatial configuration</head><p>Another question concerns how inferred mappings are influenced by the spatial organization of the colored regions. In this study we used grids in which one side was biased to be light and the other side dark, but the spatial arrangement of the colors was otherwise random. Our goal was to avoid configural cues that indicated which region represent 'more.' This kind of spatial layout is similar to those found in colormaps visualizations of correlation matrices and gene expression co-occurrences.</p><p>However, colormaps are often used to visualize data that produce more concentric 'hot spot' configurations (e.g., EEG scalp topographies, fMRI bold signal images, and weather maps). Schott <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> suggested in that in such cases, the concentric layout might be a cue to the encoded mappings-the center of the configuration represents 'more.' He further suggested that in such cases, people's interpretations of colormaps may be dominated by the spatial distribution of colors rather than the colors themselves. It is unknown whether the dark-is-more and opaque-ismore biases observed in the present study would influence inferred mappings for such 'hot spot' visualizations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.4">Semantic context</head><p>In the present study, we explicitly used fictitious data about alien animals to prevent participants from using prior associations between colors and the subject matter (i.e., alien animals) to inform their judgments. However, people do have strong color-concept associations for particular objects, which influence their inferences about the meanings of colors in information visualizations <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref>. Based on this logic, Samsel et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> created color scales with intuitive color coding for environmental sciences (e.g., blue color scales for water, green color scales for vegetation, and brown/yellow/red color scales for earth).</p><p>This point raises the question of whether the dark-is-more and opaque-is-more biases would hold if they directly conflict with colorconcept association for the subject matter. For example, if a data visualization illustrates amount of snow accumulation or sunshine, which are associated with light colors, would people infer light-more mappings? If so, would that only hold when the lighter color is associated with the concept (e.g., white for snow, and white/yellow for sunshine), or would it to generalize to any light colors?</p><p>In Cuff's <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> study on temperature maps he reported that the dark-ismore bias prevailed over color associations with temperature. However, to fully address these questions, it would be necessary to (a) obtain judgments about color-concept associations for the subject matter to ensure that the researchers know what those associations are, and (b) test a variety of subject matter (not just temperature).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.5">Dark-is-more beyond colormaps</head><p>The present work contributes to a body of evidence that there is a darkis-more bias when interpreting colormap data visualizations. However, when participants were asked to map different lightnesses to different mouse sizes, Smith and Sera <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> reported that young children have a dark-is-more bias but adults have no systematic lightness-magnitude mappings. Therefore, the question remains of whether the dark-is-more bias in adults is confined to colormaps, or might generalize to some other aspects of cognition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSION</head><p>We investigated how visual features in colormap data visualization influence people's inferred color-quantity mappings. We report evidence supporting two distinct types of inferred mappings: dark-is-more and opaque-is-more biases. The dark-is-more bias was established in the literature long ago, but when and how inferred mappings are modulated by the background color has remained mysterious. We found that the role of the background increases as apparent variation in opacity increases. When colormaps do not appear to vary in opacity, inferred mappings are dominated by the dark-is-more bias and are unaffected by the background. When there is strong apparent variation in opacity, an opaque-is-more bias emerges and can limit, or even override, the darkis-more bias when colormaps are presented on dark backgrounds. Our results suggest that to understand how people interpret visualizations, it is necessary to understand both lower-level perceptual processing (e.g., conditions that support apparent variations in opacity), and how those percepts map onto cognitive constructs that are represented in visualizations.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Distribution used to sample values at each time point to generate the data used to construct the colormap images (see text for details).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>(A) Mean RTs for light-more encoding (light bars) and dark-more encoding (dark bars), separated by background color (x-axis) and color scale (separate plots). The icons along x-axis represent example colormaps with each condition (note: the darker region is on the right in these examples, but the dark region was left/right balanced in the experiment). Error bars represent +/-standard errors of the means. (B) Plots of each color scale (squares) and interpolations between the highest contrast color and the white background (circles) in CIELAB space. (C) The corresponding plots from B for the black background. In B and C, the number above each plot is the Opacity Variation Index (see text for details).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>(A) Mean RTs for light-more encoding (light bars) and dark-more encoding (dark bars), separated by background color (x-axis) and color scale (separate plots). The icons along x-axis represent example colormaps with each condition (note: the darker region is on the left in these examples, but the dark region was left/right balanced in the experiment). The order of the icons along the x-axis is: opacity variation-light background (left), opacity variation-dark background (center), no opacity variation (right). Error bars represent +/-standard errors of the means.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors thank Laurent Lessard, Morton Gersbacher, Stephen Palmer, Bas Rokers, David Laidlaw, Chris Racey, and anonymous reviewers for their valuable feedback on this work. The authors also thank Isobel Heck, Methma Udawatta, Charlotte Walmsley, Alexandra Lawton, Caroline Turner, Katie Foley, Shannon Sibrel, Charlie Goldring, Amanda Hoyer, Zachary Leggon, David Nelson, and Jacob Shaw for their help with data collection. Support for this research was provided by the Office of the Vice Chancellor for Research and Graduate Education at the University of Wisconsin-Madison with funding from the Wisconsin Alumni Research Foundation. It was also supported in part by a grant from the Brown University Center for Vision Research in the Brown Institute for Brain Research.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An empirical analysis of the design principles for quantitative and qualitative area symbols. Cartography and Geographic Information Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Antes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-T</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="277" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lowered h3k27me3 and dna hypomethylation define poorly prognostic pediatric posterior fossa ependymomas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bayliss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mukherjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Jain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sabari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Margol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Panwalkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Parolia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science translational medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="366" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The perception of transparency with achromatic colors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Prazdny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ivry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perception &amp; psychophysics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rainbow color map (still) considered harmful</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Borland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M T</forename><surname>Ii</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE computer graphics and applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Color use guidelines for mapping and visualization. Visualization in modern cartography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="148" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Spectral schemes: Controversial color use on maps. Cartography and Geographic Information Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="220" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The good, the bad, and the ugly: A theoretical framework for the assessment of continuous colormaps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bujack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Samsel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ahrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="923" to="933" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colorful brains: 14 years of display practice in functional neuroimaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Christen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Vitacco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Harboe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Fabrikant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Brugger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colour on temperature maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cuff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Cartographic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="1973" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impending conflict in color guidelines for maps of statistical surfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cuff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cartographica: The International Journal for Geographic Information and Geovisualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The peculiar nature of simultaneous colour contrast in uniform surrounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ekroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Faul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Niederée</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vision Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1765" to="1786" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colorgorical: Creating discriminable and preferable color palettes for information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gramazio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Laidlaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schloss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rittler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Neitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">HRR pseudoisochromatic plates. Richmond Products</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colorbrewer. org: an online tool for selecting colour schemes for maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harrower</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brewer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Cartographic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sizing the horizon: the effects of chart size and layering on the graphical perception of time series visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Agrawala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1303" to="1312" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual representations are dominated by intrinsic fluctuations correlated between areas</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Henriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S.-M</forename><surname>Khaligh-Razavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kriegeskorte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical perception of multiple time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Javed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mcdonnel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Elmqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="927" to="934" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Naked to the bone: Medical imaging in the twentieth century</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kevles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Rutgers University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overview use in multiple visual information resolution interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Munzner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kincaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1278" to="1285" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selecting semantically-resonant colors for data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fortuna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="410" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Somewhere over the rainbow: An empirical assessment of quantitative colormaps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
			<biblScope unit="page">598</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ordering choropleth map symbols: The effect of background</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcgranaghan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Cartographer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The perception of transparency</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Metelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific American</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">230</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diverging color maps for scientific visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moreland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Symposium on Visual Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="103" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The design of everyday things: Revised and expanded edition</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Basic Books (AZ)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The debate on the standardization of statistical maps and diagrams (1857-1901). elements of the history of graphical semiotics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Palsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cybergeo: European Journal of Geography</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compositing digital images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Duff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In ACM Siggraph Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical perception of continuous quantitative maps: the effects of spatial frequency and colormap design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Reda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nalawade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ansah-Koi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
			<biblScope unit="page">272</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Task-based color scale design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rheingans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">28th AIPR Workshop: 3D Visualization for Data Exploration and Decision Making</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3905</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="44" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Look of Maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1952" />
			<publisher>University of Wisconsin Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Madison</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Atomic spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data visualization: the end of the rainbow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rogowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE spectrum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How not to lie with visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rogowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bryson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Value-by-alpha maps: An alternative technique to the cartogram</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Woodruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Cartographic Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Intuitive colormaps for environmental visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Samsel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Turton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wolfram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bujack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A color inference framework</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schloss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color inference in visual communication: the meaning of colors in recycling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schloss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lessard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Walmsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cognitive research: principles and implications</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colored illustrations of the brain: some conceptual and contextual issues</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Neuroscientist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="508" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using color in visualization: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Madeira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers &amp; Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="333" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a perceptual theory of transparency</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychological review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">492</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A developmental analysis of the polar structure of dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cognitive Psychology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using color to code quantity in spatial displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Spence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kutlesa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Experimental Psychology: Applied</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">393</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An engineering model for color difference as a function of size</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Szafir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Setlur</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Color and Imaging Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2014</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="258" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling color difference for visualization design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Szafir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="392" to="401" />
			<date type="published" when="2018" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing thought</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Topics in Cognitive Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="535" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Animation: can it facilitate?</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Morrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Betrancourt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of human-computer studies</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color sequences for univariate maps: Theory, experiments and principles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bars and lines: A study of graphic communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zacks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Tversky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Memory &amp; Cognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1079" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of colormaps in visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2051" to="2069" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
