<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">NetLens: Iterative Exploration of Content-Actor Network Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hyunmo</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bongshin</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Advanced Computer Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bederson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Advanced Computer Studies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Maryland</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Human-Computer Interaction Laboratory Computer Science Department</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">NetLens: Iterative Exploration of Content-Actor Network Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>CR categories: H.5.2 [Information Interfaces and Presentations]: User Interfaces -graphical user interfaces (GUI)</term>
					<term>interaction styles</term>
					<term>prototyping Human-Computer Interaction</term>
					<term>information visualization</term>
					<term>network visualization</term>
					<term>content-actor network data</term>
					<term>iterative query refinement</term>
					<term>incremental data exploration</term>
					<term>user interfaces</term>
					<term>digital library</term>
					<term>piccolo</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Networks have remained a challenge for information retrieval and visualization because of the rich set of tasks that users want to accomplish. This paper offers an abstract Content-Actor network data model, a classification of tasks, and a tool to support them. The NetLens interface was designed around the abstract Content-Actor network data model to allow users to pose a series of elementary queries and iteratively refine visual overviews and sorted lists. This enables the support of complex queries that are traditionally hard to specify. NetLens is general and scalable in that it applies to any dataset that can be represented with our abstract data model. This paper describes NetLens applying a subset of the ACM Digital Library consisting of about 4,000 papers from the CHI conference written by about 6,000 authors. In addition, we are now working on a collection of half a million emails, and a dataset of legal cases.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Most visualization research on understanding relationships in large datasets implicitly assumes that a node link diagram is appropriate. In fact, nearly all the submissions to the InfoVis 2004 contest -that required solutions to the analysis of 10 years of InfoVis publications and their authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[13]</ref> -used displays of node-link diagrams. We have designed many such visual displays ourselves and we believe that node-link diagrams are very useful in supporting topology-based tasks such as finding clusters or connected components, detecting patterns or outliers, determining the shortest path between the nodes, etc. However, node-link diagrams also have limitations in accomplishing attribute-based tasks in network dataset. In addition, they don't scale up well and too often produce cluttered overviews with few readable labels. For example, let's consider a scientific publication network dataset that is composed of several thousand papers (represented as nodes) that are linked by directed edges representing the citation relationship. If this network is paired with the author network which consists of another several thousand researcher nodes that are linked by co-authorship, the node-link diagram would not easily support even a simple task such as reviewing the papers referenced by a selected author.</p><p>In this paper, we describe a different approach with the design of NetLens, which was inspired by our submission to that contest (PaperLens <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[16]</ref>), by using multiple simple coordinated views of ordered lists and histogram overviews. NetLens represents a general and scalable design that uses a "Content-Actor" model of information. Examples of Content-Actor pairs of interest to the visual analytics community include scientific publications and authors, emails and people, legal cases and courts, intelligence reports and countries or groups, products and companies, etc. In all these examples, both the content and actors consist of networked data such as reports citing other reports, authors having co-authors, products replacing or integrating other products. NetLens shows paired networks of content and actors in coordinated views. It supports complex queries that are traditionally difficult to specify by allowing users to pose a series of elementary queries and iteratively refine them with visual overviews and sorted lists.</p><p>After reviewing the related work, this paper first describes the NetLens interface using a subset of the ACM Digital Library. We show how users can easily determine which sub-fields are trendy and which are on the decline, find appropriate experts to review a paper or serve as an expert witness in patent litigation, or even determine relationships between groups based on an analysis of their publications. We then describe NetLens in more general terms and show how the Content-Actor data model is defined with its related tasks, and finally review the most important usability challenges of this novel approach and how we addressed them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">RELATED WORK</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Network Data Visualization</head><p>Many interactive visualization systems have been developed to help users explore and analyze collections of networked documents or communities of people <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[9]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12]</ref>. Several websites (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[2]</ref>[28]) show a rich variety of network visualization examples. However, most network visualization efforts have focused on layout strategies that can be classified into node-link diagrams or matrix representations <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[8]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[11]</ref>.</p><p>Visual interfaces to digital libraries show an alternative way of network visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[6]</ref>. For example, Butterfly <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[18]</ref> combines search and browsing to visualize citation graphs. Envision <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[20]</ref>, a digital library augmented with a flexible user interface, facilitates examination of very large datasets and helps users discover patterns in results of queries. GRIDL <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[24]</ref> visualizes thousands of search results at once on a twodimensional display that use hierarchical, categorical axes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Multiple Coordinated Views</head><p>Multiple coordinated views often improve user performance, enable discovery of unforeseen relationships, and offer unification of the desktop <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[3]</ref> <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[19]</ref>. For example, Spotfire <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[26]</ref> displays a *: {kang ,plaisant, bongshin, bederson}@cs.umd.edu single table in different types of views, such as scatter plots and bar charts. All the views are coordinated by brushing <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[4]</ref> to allow users to relate data points across views. Visage <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref> provides richer data manipulation operations such as drill-down, drag, paint, and roll-up to enable users to compose a complex query, but all the views are coordinated based on a single centralized table so it can not represent the relationships across multiple tables. Snap-Together <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[19]</ref> enables users to create different types of coordinations such as brushing, drill down, overview and detail view, and synchronized scrolling. Although some types of coordinations can represent joined tables, their relationships are limited only to one-to-one or one-to-many and thus are not appropriate for representing network relationships.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Iterative Query Refinement</head><p>Conventional search interfaces to online resources allow users to specify several query fields and initiate the query by pressing a button. While these systems are easy to manipulate, it is often difficult to formulate or express queries effectively. Furthermore, users often learn what they need to ask and how to do it through the query process. Thus, iterative query refinement has been used in many information retrieval systems. For example, SIS <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[9]</ref> commits queries whenever users change any of the filtering widgets. VQuery <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[14]</ref> enables users to interactively refine query results, using Venn diagrams to provide dynamic query previews. PESTO <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref> provides a query history mechanism enables users to reuse old queries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">NETLENS INTERFACE</head><p>While NetLens supports any dataset that can be represented with our abstract Content-Actor data model (see Section 4), we first illustrate the interface using a specific dataset and describe simple scenarios of use in this context. The dataset consists of a subset of the ACM digital library and contains 4,073 papers from the CHI conference from 1982 to 2004 authored by 6,358 people. The NetLens display <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1</ref>) is divided into two symmetric sections. On the left is the content (i.e. the papers) for this dataset, and on the right are the actors (i.e. the authors) of the papers. Each section includes several panels: overviews at the top (showing histograms which can show distributions of items over all the available attributes), filters on the right side, and lists of items in the lower area. In each section the different panels are tightly-coupled <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[19]</ref> so that any changes such as selection in one panel is immediately reflected in the other panels. All elements of the display are used to specify queries and to display results: for example, selecting a histogram bar filters the list of papers, and hiding certain papers from the list (e.g. the less cited ones) is reflected in the histogram.</p><p>Initially the two sections for papers and authors are not linked and are explored individually. The red oval at the center of the display indicates that nothing will flow in between, and users can change this and set the direction of the flow by right clicking on the red oval. When flow is allowed the oval is replaced by a directional arrow <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2c</ref>).  Let's imagine that John needs to learn more about a group of scientists from Canada that is knowledgeable in HCI. He thinks of several questions such as: "What group is it?", "How active are they?", "What topics are they working on?", "Who leads with many influential papers?", and so on. He asks to see an overview of the authors by Nationality by changing the attribute mapped to the X axis to "Country". He clicks on the Canada bar and scans the list of names and affiliations <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2a</ref>). It looks like Universities are dominating, so he sets the overview to show a distribution by institution and selects "Universities" which filters the list of authors to 140 authors. He sorts and visually scans the affiliations. He can see many variants of the name University of Toronto so that must be the place he should be studying more closely. He removes other institutions from the list and narrows down authors to 38 ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2b</ref>). Now he wonders what they worked on, so he sends the list of authors to the paper side by changing the red oval to a left arrow ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2c)</ref>. He sees that they have 82 papers. By scrolling the paper overview he sees lots of papers in Target Acquisition and Multimodal User Interfaces. Papers are sorted by number of citations so the top of the list now shows the most influential papers. Double-clicking on a paper brings it up in the ACM Digital Library <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2d)</ref>. When a paper is selected, its citations are also highlighted and brought to the top of the list of citations. He can switch to references instead of citations.</p><p>Next, John wonders who wrote the most influential papers. He selects the 11 most influential papers (i.e., those cited more than or equal to 20 times), then changes the direction of the arrow. Only 7 authors are left <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2e)</ref>. He can order them by the number of influential papers. On the top is I. Scott Mackenzie who was an author on 4 influential papers.</p><p>Finally, John decides to look at who was influenced by the work of University of Toronto. He selects all the citations of the 11 most cited papers and saves those citations in "My List" and asks to have that shown in the histograms. It updates the list of authors accordingly, showing the distribution of who cited the influential papers. John resets the author filters to see them all (instead of only the University of Toronto authors). He then switches to an overview by country, to see which countries have been following this work <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 2f)</ref>.</p><p>Now that we have introduced the interface of NetLens with this scenario, we will describe the underlying data model and explain how and why we chose it in Section 4. In Section 5 we will come back to the some of design challenges we encountered and how we addressed them in designing the NetLens interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">NETLENS DATA MODEL</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Data Analysis</head><p>Entity-Relationship models <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[25]</ref> of several common network data domains such as email archives, personal photo collections, and digital libraries ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3)</ref> show that network data sets are frequently composed of a small number of independent entities and their relationships. The relationships can be further divided 1 Video demo is available at http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/netlens into intra-relationship (relationship within the same entities) and inter-relationship (relationship between the different entities). It is interesting to note that Entity-Relationship models have two properties that are useful to define an abstract network data model. First, the structure of the data model can be manipulated to suit the tasks and tools. An entity's attributes can be separated from the entity to become a new independent entity. For example, one of the paper's attributes, "Category", can be separated from the paper entity and converted to a new entity so that they can have a "HAS" relationship. On the contrary, an independent entity can be merged into the related entity to represent an attribute. For example, the author entity could become an attribute of the paper entity. Second, many network tasks can be described by following a path (an alternating sequence of entities and relationships) in the model. Suppose that you want to find out how many citations of the papers a person has written are not selfcitations. You would have to search for papers written by the author, find all citations of those papers, find the authors of those citations, remove the original author, and filter the original set of citations to see only the papers written by the remaining authors. Finally, counting the papers in the resulting set yields the answer. The path for this search is People (a researcher) → Paper (written by the researcher) → Paper (citations of that paper) → People (authors of the citations) → Paper (written by those authors) → Paper (intersect two lists of papers). Based on these two properties of Entity-Relationship models, we designed an abstract data model as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>. The data model is composed of two symmetric entities, which we describe as Content and Actors respectively, and their inter-and intrarelationships. We use the terms content and actors to help in understanding and simplifying network data. While we understand that there will be some kinds of network data that are hard to map to this simple model, we are confident that this basic model can be extended to represent more complex network data model as well as it can be used as is for many practical datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Task Analysis</head><p>Using the abstract Content-Actor data model as a basis, we examined the tasks that were collected from group interviews and discussions with our stakeholders as well as graph visualization user studies. It was interesting to note that most of the collected network analytic tasks were based on the attributes of the two entities and their intra-and inter-relationship while there were a few topology-based tasks that were more suitable for the nodelink diagram approach.</p><p>The network tasks we identified can be classified into two groups based on our abstract data model: Single-step and multistep tasks. Single-step tasks can be defined as a query regarding the entity itself and its attributes, or one step intra-or interrelationships. The following are examples of single-step tasks for a digital library dataset with paper and author entities:</p><p>• How many papers on "User Study" were published in 1998?</p><p>• Who are the authors of the papers on "Virtual Reality", which were published at the CHI 99 conference?</p><p>• Which paper is most frequently cited by the papers published at the CHI 2004 conference?</p><p>• Which author is most frequently cited in the "InfoVis" topic?</p><p>• How many papers were published by UMD HCIL people?</p><p>• Who are the authors whose nationality is Korea? <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> shows the classification of single-step tasks, which is based on our abstract Content-Actor data model. It shows that each entity can be used either for a search query or for a search result. In other words, papers can be searched either by papers or by people, just as authors can be searched by papers or by people. Due to the symmetric structure of the entities in our data model, the search results of a single-step task can be recursively used as an input to other single-step tasks, which enables users to achieve more complex multi-step tasks by iterating over the table.</p><p>Single-step tasks can be linked together to form multi-step solutions to more complicated and high level network tasks. The following examples show some interesting high level tasks that people might ask about digital libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Evaluate individuals:</head><p>how many papers were self-referenced? -how frequently was each paper referenced by other papers?</p><p>• Identify communities:</p><p>what are the major paper topics published by UMD HCIL and who in this group has the most papers in that topic? -how do UMD HCIL's research interests change over time and who in this group made that change? • Find experts (to review papers or attend a workshop):</p><p>who wrote the most papers in the InfoVis topic and how many papers cited that author's papers? -whose paper in the InfoVis area is most frequently referenced by other papers? • Learning about a new topic (to find a good PhD topic):</p><p>which topic has growing publications and who contributed most to this topic in the last 3 years? -what are the other topics that the authors in the InfoVis area also are interested in? • Where should I go on a sabbatical?</p><p>which country (or research group)'s authors most frequently reference my papers?</p><p>The above example tasks can be answered by iterating through Table 1 multiple times.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">A GENERAL AND SCALABLE INTERFACE DESIGN</head><p>NetLens uses a general interface design that can be applied to any dataset represented with our abstract Content-Actors data model. This means that there must be just two entity types, each with attributes and relationships within and between those entities. For example, in conference publications, the two entity types are papers and people. Papers have attributes such as titles, abstracts and keywords. They cite and are cited by other papers and are authored by people. Those people have attributes such as institutions and fields of interest, and can be connected to papers through authorship relationships and possibly to other people through advising or committee memberships. This basic structure applies equally to collections of photos (with the primary entities being photos and objects within those photos), email collections and even legal cases. An example of intra-relationship is reflected in the two lower panels of the Papers side, with the list of papers on the left and their references or citations on the right <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">(Figure 1</ref>). NetLens uses whatever metadata (i.e., attributes) is available, creates filters and displays the results. The quality of the interface depends heavily on the richness and value of the metadata.</p><p>NetLens is also scalable because it uses a standard relational database and the interface is built of common simple components such as histograms and lists. Together, they offer surprisingly rich support for real complex tasks. By avoiding visual overviews of the entire dataset that display a visual element for each entity instance, we avoid immediate problems of scalability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">INTERFACE CHALLENGES AND PROPOSED SOLUTIONS</head><p>In this section, some of the design challenges that were uncovered from our early usability testing are discussed along with the proposed solutions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Dataflow Control</head><p>One of the most important issues in designing the NetLens interface was about how to control dataflow between and within the entity windows (between-entity and within-entity dataflow hereafter). The initial between-entity dataflow model was simple. We designed the entity windows to be tightly-coupled so that any data changes in one entity window were automatically transferred to the other. However, the tightly-coupled entity windows often resulted in a cyclic dataflow, and moreover, the automatic between-entity dataflow often caused unintended and unnecessary query refinement as well as performance problems. Therefore, the between-entity dataflow model was revised to let users manually select the direction of dataflow (if any) by using an additional interface widget (red arrow) as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2c</ref>. On the other hand, all the sub-panels in the entity windows are tightly-coupled. For example, if some papers are filtered out from the overview panel in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref>, then the list of papers in the detail-on-demand panel will be updated (1→2), and the list of references in the intra-relationship panel will also be updated accordingly (2→3). However, NetLens stops the within-entity dataflow and does not allow it to be propagated to the overview panel (3→1) in order to avoid cycles. Although the direct dataflow between 1 and 3 is not allowed in NetLens, users can make use of the "My List" feature for indirect dataflow between 1 and 3. Users can collect any entity instances and save them to "My List" while exploring data, and use this collection as a filter in the overview panel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">History and Integrated Help</head><p>Because users generally perform a sequence of interactions to accomplish a task, they sometimes get lost during the data exploration and ask themselves questions such as, "How did I get here?" or "What does the current filtered dataset mean?" To avoid such problems, we added two support mechanisms in NetLens: query history management, and integrated guidance.</p><p>The query history management system records every interaction users make in NetLens and automatically annotates each interaction to help users remember the interactions they have made before. By using the list of annotated interactions ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 6</ref>), users can go back and forth to confirm or correct their previous interactions. The annotations can be manually edited later if any interaction needs to be described more precisely. The history of interactions can be saved to a file and retrieved later for reuse.</p><p>The integrated guidance system helps users understand the meaning of the current dataset in each panel. Each panel has a "?" button located at the top right corner. Upon clicking that button, a yellow sticky-note-like window appears over the window to show what queries have been applied so far to the dataset in the panel. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Multi-layered Interface</head><p>Although the NetLens interface is composed of two entity windows and six sub-panels (three panels per entity) to represent the whole abstract Content-Actor data model, users do not always need all the panels and may find the interface overwhelming, therefore we implemented a multi-layered interface <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[15]</ref>[23] with 3 levels: a) overview only b) overview + lists, and c) overview + detail-on-demand + intra-relationship (e.g. references/citations). Users can also see a single entity to start.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.4">Data Export and Integration</head><p>NetLens provides a rapid way to sift thru a lot of data and identify areas of interest. It can transfer any filtered or selected set of data to other applications through the windows clipboard (using copy and paste), internal graph class object, or even xml documents. To illustrate this capability we connected a graph browsing tool we developed called TreePlus <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[17]</ref> to allow users to study the co-  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">SYSTEM ARCHITECTURE</head><p>NetLens was written in C# using the University of Maryland's open source Piccolo toolkit <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[5]</ref> for histogram visualization.</p><p>Piccolo is a layer built on top of low level graphics API, which facilitated the implementation of 2D structured histogram component by providing many useful features such as screen repainting, bounds management, event handling and dispatch, picking, layout, and so on.</p><p>NetLens uses an MS Access database, but it can be connected to any relational databases as long as they fit the basic data schema that is composed of two tables representing two individual entities, one table for their inter-relationship, and finally two optional tables to represent the intra-relationship for each entity. One of the major benefits of using a relational database system in implementing NetLens was that it is relatively easy to construct a real data schema from our abstract Content-Actor data model. Good performance and relatively small data storage size are two additional benefits we can get from the current relational database technologies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">FURTHER EVALUATION</head><p>Evaluating complex interfaces is a challenge, especially in the field of exploratory search <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[29]</ref> and Information Visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>. In the case of NetLens three approaches can be taken: 1) Usability: evaluation could measure how usable the interface is, using classic usability measures such as speed of performance or error rates on simple imposed representative tasks.</p><p>2) Power: evaluating NetLens could consist of evaluating the range and complexity of queries that can be answered, and characterizing the queries that cannot be answered, then comparing the complexity of the user task compared to let's say SQL queries, either theoretically or empirically.</p><p>3) Generality: The evaluation can focus on the generality claim of the system by evaluating how easy it is to create new applications for new domains and data models.</p><p>We have not focused extensively on evaluation yet as we are finishing our first mature prototype but some progress has been made in all three approaches. The ACM Digital Library turns out to be a wonderful application domain to investigate because we found ourselves surrounded by potential users who are familiar with the data (and its limitations), have queries of their own, and often are mentioned in the data itself, titillating their interest and increasing their motivation to participate and provide feedback. Overall we have collected feedback from dozens of users who saw or interacted with our interface in the lab or at large government sponsored project meetings (intelligence analysts, researchers from industry and academia, software developers). They made us aware of many low level usability problems such as readability of the histogram labels, color choices, or needed improvements to the table displays. On the other hand, NetLens has always been well received. Users seem to show a sense of relief from avoiding the traditional node link diagram displays, and greatly appreciated the simplicity of the interfaces while always acknowledging that the complex queries executed by NetLens would be very difficult if not impossible for them to specify with SQL.</p><p>An independent heuristic evaluation has been conducted at the National Institute of Standard and Technology (NIST) in the context of the NIMD program. After video training the reviewers conducted six tasks using NetLens. The reviewers used both general HCI heuristics and visualization specific heuristics to categorize problems and issues. A report that collates the 5 individual reports as well as the individual reviews and video recordings of all the interactions shows that the overall interaction metaphor was understandable and the navigation was easy and required little training even though it indicated several low level usability problems in the NetLens interface.</p><p>To explore the generality of the NetLens design, we connected NetLens to two other datasets. Our first attempt was to explore the Enron email collection <ref type="bibr">[27]</ref>. In about 3 days the first author and main developer of NetLens was able to design the new data model, produce data converters and customize NetLens to create the prototype. An estimated 200 lines of code was needed to modify the software. Most of the effort was focused on designing the data model and manipulating data. Our prototype shows emails on the left, and people on the right. An example iteration of queries is: Find the emails with a certain characteristics (e.g. rated as confidential), then find who received those emails, are there people who received significantly more emails like this, for those people, what were the characteristics of the emails they received (e.g. topic distribution), read the emails that concerned pricing issues.</p><p>A second application was developed to explore legal precedents. The database of legal cases collected by a team of researchers from the Dept of Government and Politics at the University of Maryland contains 2,780 federal judicial decisions from the period 1978 to 2005 concerning the legal issue known as "regulatory takings." Within a day, we designed the new data model, produced data converters and customized NetLens. An estimated less than a hundred of lines of code was needed. Again, most of the effort was focused on designing the data model and processing the data. The prototype shows on the left the cases, and on the right the courts that managed them. We are also planning to apply NetLens to two additional datasets, student life judicial data and personal photo library data, to further verify the generality of our design.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">CONCLUSION</head><p>Our analysis of Entity-Relationship models of common network datasets enables us to describe an abstract Content-Actor data model which we used in the design of NetLens. The NetLens interface allows users to explore network data incrementally and refine their queries iteratively so that they can accomplish complex network tasks that are usually composed of a sequence of low level tasks. NetLens is general in that it applies to any dataset that can be represented as a Content-Actor data model. Also, the NetLens interface design is scalable because the interface is built from common simple components such as histograms and lists so that it can avoid visual overviews of the entire dataset that display a visual element for each entity instance. This is just a beginning, but the utility of NetLens seems promising. Generalizing and simplifying common network datasets to the abstract Content-Actor data model and connecting them to NetLens might facilitate completion of required tasks more rapidly and reliably while offering rich support for real analytic tasks. We believe that there are great benefits in using a consistent and simple user interface to explore a variety of Content-Actor datasets. Finally NetLens demonstrates that there exist powerful alternative and complementary techniques to the classic node-link diagrams to explore network data.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>NetLens has two symmetric windows. The left is for Content (papers), the right for Actors (authors). Each side is further divided into panels; overview at the top, filters on the right, and lists at the bottom. Here the Content side has two lists to reflect the citation or reference relationship between papers. The paper overview panel shows the distribution of papers (in logarithmic scale) over time, grouped by topics.Users can see which topics have seen their number of papers increase or decrease over 22 years. On the right side the overview of the authors shows the distribution of countries of origin in logarithmic scale.(a) In the overview of authors per country, Canada was selected (b) The overview is changed to show distribution by institution and the list filtered accordingly. and university is chosen, and some institutions removed. (c) The University of Toronto authors are sent to the paper side (d) Sorting by number of citations reveals influential papers. revealing the topic and time distribution of their papers. Double click opens a paper (or a an author page) at ACM. (e) Most influential papers were selected and sent to author side. (f) All citations of the influential papers are saved in "My list" The list of influential UT authors is sorted by number of papers.and shown. Right side shows country distribution of their authors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Selected steps of the interaction of the scenario "Learn about a group of researchers" Scenario: "Learn about a group of researchers" 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Entity-Relationship diagrams of three networks (email collections, photo collections, and scientific publications).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Abstract Content-Actors network data model</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The within-entity dataflow among three sub-panels. Note that red numbered circles and arrows are not part of the actual interface.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>History management system shows the list of steps users have performed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the citation network in more detail(Figure 7).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>TreePlus shows the network of co-authorship network between Ben Bederson and Canadian authors who cite him.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Sample single-step tasks (on digital libraries) classified by the combination of two entities and the way the entities are used (either search-by entities or result entities)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Search By</cell><cell cols="2">Entity 1 (Paper)</cell><cell cols="2">Entity 2 (People)</cell></row><row><cell>Search Result</cell><cell>Entity 1's Attributes</cell><cell>Entity 1 (Paper)</cell><cell>Entity 2's Attributes</cell><cell>Entity 2 (People)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Search for papers by paper</cell><cell>Search for papers that</cell><cell>Search for papers by people</cell><cell>Search for papers written by</cell></row><row><cell>Entity 1</cell><cell>attributes such as year,</cell><cell>"cite" or "are cited by" the</cell><cell>attributes such as author's</cell><cell>the specified authors (either</cell></row><row><cell>(Paper)</cell><cell>keywords, title,</cell><cell>specified papers.</cell><cell>affiliation, institution,</cell><cell>conjunctive or disjunctive).</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>conference, topics, etc.</cell><cell></cell><cell>nationality, etc.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Search for authors by</cell><cell>Search for authors of the</cell><cell>Search for authors by people</cell><cell>Search for academic advisors</cell></row><row><cell>Entity 2</cell><cell>paper attributes such as</cell><cell>selected papers.</cell><cell>attributes such as author's</cell><cell>of the specified authors</cell></row><row><cell>(People)</cell><cell>year, keywords, title,</cell><cell></cell><cell>affiliation, institution,</cell><cell>(either conjunctive or</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>conference, topics, etc.</cell><cell></cell><cell>nationality, etc.</cell><cell>disjunctive).</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>We appreciate the efforts of Mary Czerwinski and George Robertson from Microsoft Research for their work on PaperLens, the motivating work for this project, and their topic analysis of CHI papers that we used in the current prototype. We also thank Doug Oard for suggesting the Content-Actor terminology. This work was supported by ARDA/Booz-Allen Hamilton #MDA-904-03-c-0408 Novel Intelligence from Massive Data Program.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REFERENCES.</head><p>[ </p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">An</forename><surname>Atlas Of Cyberspace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cybergeography.org/atlas" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines for using multiple views in information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Q W</forename><surname>Baldonado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Woodruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kuchinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Advanced Visual Interfaces Conference (AVI &apos;00)</title>
		<meeting>Advanced Visual Interfaces Conference (AVI &apos;00)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="119" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brushing Scatter Plots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cleveland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toolkit Design for Interactive Structured Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bederson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grosjean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/piccolo" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Software Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual interfaces to digital libraries: Motivation, utilization, and socio-technical challenges</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Börner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visual Interfaces to Digital Libraries</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PESTO: An Integrated Query/Browser for Object Databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Maganty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Williams</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (VLDB &apos;96)</title>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (VLDB &apos;96)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="214" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graph Drawing: algorithms for the visualization of graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Battista</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Eades</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tamassia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tollis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stuff I&apos;ve Seen: A System for Personal Information Retrieval and Re-use</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dumais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cutrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cadiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jancke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sarin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Robbins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceeding of the 26th ACM SIGIR Conference</title>
		<meeting>eeding of the 26th ACM SIGIR Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="79" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizating Social Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Freeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Social Structure</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Comparison of the Readability of Graphs using Node-Link and Matrix-Based Representations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ghoniem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Castagliola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceeding of IEEE Symposium of Information Visualization 2004 (InfoVis04)</title>
		<meeting>eeding of IEEE Symposium of Information Visualization 2004 (InfoVis04)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graph Visualization and Navigation in Information Visualization: a Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Melançon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<ptr target="http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/iv04contest" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The History of InfoVis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphical Query Specification and Dynamic Result Previews for a Digital Library</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST &apos;98)</title>
		<meeting>the Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology (UIST &apos;98)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="151" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New Approaches to Help Users Get Started with Visual Interfaces: Multi-Layered Interfaces and Integrated Initial Guidance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceeding of the Digital Government Research Conference</title>
		<meeting>eeding of the Digital Government Research Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="146" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding Research Trends in Conferences Using PaperLens</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Czerwinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bederson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-04" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1969" to="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Graphs as Trees: Plant a Seed and Watch it Grow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Parr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bederson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of GD 2005</title>
		<meeting>GD 2005</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer -Verlag</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An Organic User Interface for Searching Citation Links</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="73" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Component-Based, User-Constructed, Multiple View Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>North</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI&apos;01)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-04" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="202" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Search Results with Envision</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Nowell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>France</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hix</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extend Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human factors in Computing Systems (CHI &apos;97)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Challenge of Information Visualization Evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces</title>
		<meeting>the Working Conference on Advanced Visual Interfaces</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="116" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visage: A User Interface Environment for Exploring Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Senn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gomberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Burks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stroffolino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kolojejchick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dunmire</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Symposium on Information Visualization</title>
		<meeting>the Symposium on Information Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Promoting Universal Usability with Multi-Layer Interface Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ACM Conference on Universal Usability</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Digital Library Search Results with Categorical and Hierarchical Axes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Grau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the fifth ACM Conference on Digital Libraries</title>
		<meeting>the fifth ACM Conference on Digital Libraries</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Database System Concepts</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Silberschatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Korth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sudarshan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>McGraw Hill</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://www.spotfire.com" />
		<title level="m">Spotfire</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supporting Exploratory Search, Special Issues of the</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kules</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Drucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schraefel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="39" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-04" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
