<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Christmas Tree Case Study: Computed Tomography as a Tool for Mastering Complex Real World Objects with Applications in Computer Graphics</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Armin</forename><surname>Kanitsar</surname></persName>
							<email>kanitsar@cg.tuwien.ac.at</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Theußl</surname></persName>
							<email>theussl@cg.tuwien.ac.at</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lukas</forename><surname>Mroz</surname></persName>
							<email>mroz@tiani.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Miloššrámek</surname></persName>
							<email>milos.sramek@oeaw.ac.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology Vienna</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Austrian Academy of Sciences † Tiani Medgraph ‡ VRVis Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Austria Austria Vienna, Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Vilanova Bartrolí</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Balázs</forename><surname>Csébfalvi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jiří</forename><surname>Hladůvka</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dominik</forename><surname>Fleischmann</surname></persName>
							<email>dominik.fleischmann@univie.ac.at</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Knapp</surname></persName>
							<email>knapp@cg.tuwien.ac.at</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rainer</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
							<email>wegenkittl@tiani.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Petr</forename><surname>Felkel</surname></persName>
							<email>felkel@vrvis.at</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Röttger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology Vienna</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Austrian Academy of Sciences † Tiani Medgraph ‡ VRVis Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Austria Austria Vienna, Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Guthe</surname></persName>
							<email>guthe@gris.uni-tuebingen.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology Vienna</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Austrian Academy of Sciences † Tiani Medgraph ‡ VRVis Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Austria Austria Vienna, Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Werner</forename><surname>Purgathofer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Meister</forename><forename type="middle">Eduard</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
							<email>meister@cg.tuwien.ac.at</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">WSI/GRIS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Vienna ¶ VIS Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms *</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Stuttgart Vienna University of Technology University of Tübingen</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Christmas Tree Case Study: Computed Tomography as a Tool for Mastering Complex Real World Objects with Applications in Computer Graphics</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.3 [Computing Methodologies]: Computer Graphics-Picture/Image Generation I.6.5 [Computing Methodologies]: Simulation and Modeling-Model Development modeling</term>
					<term>computed tomography</term>
					<term>volume visualization</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Figure 1: A short story: Before Christmas-the 25 th-left for holidays-the sad end-Christmas tree in heaven.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>In computer art, one is often faced with the task to digitize real world objects for further processing with various computer graphics tools. The commonly used methods like range scanning suffer from certain limitations since only information of the visible surfaces of objects is provided. Non-convex surfaces, an inherent property of complex objects, often cause difficulties or even cannot be handled at all. Similar arguments hold for taking a set of photographs from different viewpoints to be used for image based rendering.</p><p>With procedural modeling of existing physical objects it is difficult to come up with an accurate description of the real world object. Furthermore it requires special effort to get a physically correct model and the more complex the model is the more difficult the modeling task becomes.</p><p>Generating data sets (i.e., modeling the objects) by scanning real world objects using CT modalities is independent of model complexity and physical correctness is automatically achieved. Different structures within the data set can be segmented and the interior can be examined as CT provides volumetric descriptions. On the other hand, CT scanners are rather expensive and not easily accessible. In this paper we describe our experiences of using CT to model a decorated Christmas tree, a very complex object with many different structures and small details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>Computed tomography has been used for non-destructive investigations of trees <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. In order to do this, mobile CTs have been built which extract single slices. This way diseases of trees are detected with adequate precision. State-of-the-art interactive modeling tools today are either polygon or patch oriented (Maya, Truespace). However, manipulation of the underlying data structures (polygonal meshes, NURBS) is often not versatile enough to fulfill the artist's demands. Therefore, in the early stages of the design often clay models are created, which are subsequently digitized by means of range scanners <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>There is of course a lot of literature on laser range scanning objects. Particularly interesting for the visualization community is the work by Levoy et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, who describe their efforts to digitize large objects at high resolution with mobile laser range scanning hardware. However, for objects with a high degree of complexity this approach is not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DATASET ACQUISITION</head><p>To obtain a realistic model of a Christmas tree, we decided to use CT. The following section describes the generation process and preprocessing of the data set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model Preparation:</head><p>Firstly, special care had to be taken in the preparation of the real model to assume a high data set quality. Especially, no metal was allowed to be used, as this would result in artifacts. Therefore the sweets were unwrapped and metal hooks replaced (see <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>). Due to the limited diameter of the CT gantry, the size of the tree must not exceed 50 cm. Furthermore the proportions of the Christmas tree decoration and the small conifer should match those of a real Christmas tree. Therefore special items, as small candles for birthday cakes, were used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scanning Process:</head><p>The CT acquisition protocoll had to be specifically designed as neither presets nor protocols are available for small trees. The Christmas-tree model was scanned with a Siemens Somatom Plus 4 Volume Zoom Multislice-CT scanner at the general hospital in Vienna. A tube voltage of 140kV and a tube current of 100mAs was used during the 40s scan. The collimation was 4 x 1mm, the table increment was 3mm/360 • gantry rotation. Transverse sections with a nominal slice width of 1.25mm were reconstructed at 0.5mm intervals using a medium/sharp (B40) reconstruction kernel. A dataset of 512 x 512 x 998 voxels was reconstructed from a field of view of 476mm x 476mm x 499mm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preprocessing:</head><p>Due to low noise and good spatial resolution of the data set no further preprocessing and enhancement was necessary. Limitations of some rendering tools required seperate 8 bit voxel-valued data sets.</p><p>The resulting data were originally stored in DICOM format, which is the standard format in medical imaging. For scientific and experimental purposes more handy file formats are desirable. Therefore, the data set was converted (and is publicly available therein) to the .dat and f3d formats <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. The first six bytes of the .dat format represent the data set dimension. Each following pair of bytes represent one voxel. The f3d format is more general and stores all the necessary data attributes in an easy to read header, followed by a preview image and the compressed 3D data itself.</p><p>Segmentation of tomographic data sets is traditionally depending on the goals, either very simple or very complicated. The simple task in our case was classification of the foreground voxels (the tree itself with decorations) with respect to the background. This task was accomplished easily by thresholding. The hard segmentation task was to separate various tissues of the tree (trunk and needles) and decorations. For this purpose we used two segmentation tools, ISEG <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and the segmentation functionality of JVision (a medical 3D workstation from TIANI MedGraph <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>). ISEG is a general purpose interactive system for segmentation of 3D data sets based on the assumption of spatial object homogeneity. Such <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>: A picture of the Christmas tree.</p><p>objects can be identified by thresholding. Several objects can be selected even if their density ranges overlap. Therefore, tools are provided (connected component labeling, morphological-erosion, dilation and smoothing-and logical-voxel-wise AND, OR, XORoperations) to separate such objects. 15 different objects were labeled, some of them representing several instances of similar but spatially disconnected decorations (e.g., candles or balls). A similar functionality was available for segmentation using JVision. Separating objects with similar value ranges and close spatial locations is often difficult to handle with just threshold based and morphological methods. Therefore, a local water-shed method <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> was applied to split and divide masks containing multiple objects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">VISUALIZATION ALGORITHMS</head><p>In the following the results of different volume visualization methods are presented. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref> (left) shows polygon rendering using OpenGL hardware acceleration. The iso-surfaces at a value of -944 HU (Hounsfield Units) were extracted from the data set using an extended marching cubes algorithm. The internal structure of the decoration is represented with opaque surfaces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shaded Surface Display:</head><p>Object labels and masks, which were the result of the segmentation step were further used for high quality rendering by means of ray tracing. Smooth object surfaces were obtained directly from the label volume by a first-order interpolation and thresholding <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, while the normals, necessary for realistic surface shading, were estimated directly from the original CT data by central differences and trilinear interpolation <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Figure 3, middle)</ref>. The Chessboard distance ray traversal technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> was used to speed up the rendering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Direct Volume Rendering:</head><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref> (right) software raycasting is presented using a sharp transfer function showing an iso-surface at -954 HU.</p><p>Interactive direct volume rendering running at 5 to 10 frames per second, on a Pentium 4 based system using a GeForce4 Ti4600 graphics card is used in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> to the left. This approach is based on real-time decompression of a wavelet encoded multiresolution hierarchy and multiresolution volume rendering <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The images are rendered using lossless compression at a ratio of about 3.9:1. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 6</ref> demonstrates volume rendering using a view-dependent hierarchical octree representation and a screen space error of less than one pixel. Pre-integration was used to render the data with exactly projected cells. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows images of the Christmas tree rendered using the RTVR library <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, at about 3-4 frames per second on a PIII/1.2GHz machine (full spatial resolution of the dataset, 512x512 image). RTVR allows to combine different compositing modes for different objects like surface rendering for the angels and summation (X-ray) for the remaining objects in image 5 of <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. As RTVR is a pure Java solution the tree can be viewed interactively using an RTVR applet at this paper's web-page <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> (middle) shows non-photorealistic direct volume rendering using the "Bubble Model" <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Iso-surfaces are rendered as thin semi-transparent membranes similarly to blown soap bubbles. The approach is a fast previewing technique for volumetric data which does not require a time consuming transfer function specification to visualize internal structures. Originally developed for medical data the method also works for the scanned data set in quickly illustrating the most important features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Arboroscopy:</head><p>Virtual endoscopy is used to inspect tubular objects of volumetric data sets. Applied to our data set, the term arboroscopy most illustratively describes this technique. A seven-fold branching is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> (right). As branches of such high degree rarely exist in common endoscopic applications, this dataset provides an interesting worst-case test scenario.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Curved Planar Reformation (CPR):</head><p>Curved Planar Reformation is a visualization technique used to inspect vascular structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The re-sampled plane in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 5</ref> is generated from the central axis of a branch of the tree. Thus the stability and correctness of the CPR algorithm could be investigated exemplarily on this special data set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>We have presented a straightforward technique for modeling of complex shapes by means of tomographic scanning. The limits of its applicability are given by the scanner properties, which define the outer and inner scale of the representable object: one can scan objects with dimensions up to about 500 mm with small details at about 1 mm or even less. Some materials (i.e., metal) cause artifacts and therefore should be, if possible, avoided. Color information is lost during the scan process. Up to now CT modalities are expensive and restricted in accessibility.</p><p>On the other hand this model acquisition method provides important properties. The data acquisition is independent from the object complexity and both surfaces and object interiors are represented. Different types of material are distinguishable according to the material dependent attenuation. Computed Tomography produces high resolution data sets. Even small features, as the needles of the presented data set, are still properly sampled.</p><p>Finally, a contribution of this work is to provide the visualization community with a high resolution data set with some interesting properties. It includes rather large and smooth objects like the figure on top of the tree as well as a lot of fine details like the needles. It is usable as a test data set for several applications which we showed by applying various visualization algorithms. The Christmas tree data set is publicly available from our web site <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.    </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>IEEE</head><label></label><figDesc>Visualization 2002 Oct. 27 -Nov. 1, 2002, Boston, MA, USA 0-7803-7498-3/02/$17.00 © 2002 IEEE</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>From left to right: OpenGL polygon rendering based on marching cubes surface extraction. Ray tracing of the segmented tree. Direct volume rendering: ray casting.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>From left to right: Interactive wavelet encoded multiresolution volume rendering. Non-photorealistic rendering using the "Bubble Model". View of a seven-fold branch in a virtual arboroscopy.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>A Curved Planar Reformation of the XMas-Tree dataset.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Viewdependent simplification with error threshold of 1 pixel. The tetrahedral mesh was rendered with pre-integrated cell projection.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The work presented in this publication has been partly funded by: AngioVis -Visualization Tools for Peripheral CT-Angiography project (FWF-P15217-INF), supported by the Fonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung, Austria; ADAPT project (FFF-804544), supported by Tiani Medgraph and the Forschungsförderungsfonds für die gewerbliche Wirtschaft, Austria; the VRVis research center, Vienna supported by the K plus Programm. Special thanks to Martin Kampel and Robert Sablatnig from the Pattern Recognition and Image Processing Group, Vienna University of Technology, for laser range scanning the Christmas tree (and telling us in advance it would not work). Thanks to Theresia Fasser for involuntarily donating the tree that started it all.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive volume rendering based on a &quot;bubble model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Csébfalvi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">GI 2001</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="216" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Implementation and complexity of the watershed-from-markers algorithm computed as a minimal cost forest</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Felkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bruckwschwaiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eurographics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Manchester, United Kingdom</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="26" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time decompression and visualization of animated volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guthe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Strasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="356" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applications of computerized tomography in forest and tree sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Habermehl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Ridder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Symposium on Computerized Tomography for Industrial Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computed Tomography Angiography: A Case Study of Peripheral Vessel Investigation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kanitsar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Felkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fleischmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sandner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="480" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The digital Michelangelo project: 3D scanning of large statues</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pulli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Curless</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rusinkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Koller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ginzton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ginsberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fulk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Siggraph</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="144" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RTVR -a flexible Java library for interactive volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mroz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="279" to="286" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kizamu: A system for sculpting digital images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Perry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Frisken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Annual Conference Series</title>
		<editor>Eugene Fiume</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="56" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive segmentation of tissues for medical imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Šrámek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Czech Pattern Recognition Workshop &apos;93</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Czech Republic</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="164" to="171" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Václav Hlaváč and Tomáš Pajdla. Temešvár u Písku</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast surface rendering from raster data by voxel traversal using chessboard distance</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Šrámek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization&apos;94</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="195" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">f3d -a file format and tools for storage and manipulation of volumetric data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Šrámek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dimitrov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">1 st International Symposium on 3D Data Processing, Visualization and Transmission</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Padova, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE CS</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="368" to="371" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast ray-tracing of rectilinear volume data using distance transforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Šrámek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="252" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">JVision/Spacevision diagnostic workstation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tiani</forename><surname>Medgraph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.tiani.com/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Tree Web Page</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Xmt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Christmas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://ringlotte.cg.tuwien.ac.at/datasets/XMasTree/XMasTree.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
