<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Hardware-Accelerated Selective LIC Volume Rendering</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yasuko</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
							<email>yasuko-s@isl.melco.co.jp</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Issei</forename><surname>Fujishiro</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chen</forename><forename type="middle">‡</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hiroko</forename><surname>Rist</surname></persName>
							<email>hiroko@imv.is.ocha.ac.jp</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Mitsubishi Electric Corp</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Ochanomizu University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Ochanomizu University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Hardware-Accelerated Selective LIC Volume Rendering</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.3 [Computer Graphics]: Picture/Image Generation; I.6.6 [Simulation and Modeling]: Simulation Output Analysis Flow visualization</term>
					<term>flow topology</term>
					<term>significance map</term>
					<term>illumination model</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Line Integral Convolution (LIC) is a promising method for visualizing 2D dense flow fields. Direct extensions of the LIC method to 3D have not been considered very effective, because optical integration in viewing directions tends to spoil the coherent structures along 3D local streamlines. In our previous reports, we have proposed a selective approach to volume rendering of LIC solid texture using 3D significance map (S-map), derived from the characteristics of flow structures, and a specific illumination model for 3D streamlines. In this paper, we take full advantage of scalar volume rendering hardware, such as VolumePro, to realize a realtime 3D flow field visualization environment with the LIC volume rendering method.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Intuitive and effective visualization of flow fields is a very incentive topic in scientific visualization. Traditionally, flow fields are usually displayed by inserting geometrical primitives such as arrows, particles, or other kinds of stream objects. Due to inadequate sampling, these primitive insertion methods often either generate cluttered images, or fail to capture significant features of flow fields. In order to solve this sampling problem, Line Integral Convolution (LIC), proposed by Carbral and Leedom in 1993 <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, has been attracting much attention as a high-potential texture-based visualization method.</p><p>Much work has been done to increase the usefulness, quality and efficiency of the LIC method on a 2D surface <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>. Forssell and Cohen <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> extended the LIC method for visualizing a flow field on a 3D curvilinear surface. Their method unfortunately involves the defect of texture distortions caused by the two-way nonlinear mappings between the computational and physical spaces. Mao, et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> presented another 3D LIC method, which performs the convolution operation directly in the physical space so that resultant textures do not suffer from any artifacts due to misaligned local texture grids and image interpolation during rendering. However, both 3D LIC methods are limited to the delineation of LIC texture on 3D surfaces, and cannot grasp the whole interior structures of flow fields.</p><p>The true 3D counterpart of LIC can transform a given 3D flow field easily into a corresponding 3D scalar (gray-value) field. It has been generally considered, however, that direct volume rendering of LIC solid textures does not work well because such textures are too dense and intricate, and optical integration along viewing directions countervails the coherent structure of the textures. Nevertheless, by taking into account the fact that unavoidable-to-see flow features are not uniformly distributed throughout the 3D space, it seems to become a promising solution to this problem to highlight LIC texels within significant regions. Indeed, Shen, et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> utilized the advection of colored dye to highlight local flow features in LIC volume-rendered images. In order to reveal global flow features with the technique, the dyed LIC images need to be animated. Interrante and Grosch <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref> presented several strategies for visualizing 3D flow fields effectively with the volume LIC method. These strategies include defining an appropriate input texture; discriminating texels with different depths; and highlighting regions of interest (ROIs) in both input and output volumes. As for how to find ROIs, they provided only a single way to find the depth discontinuities. Rezk-Salama, et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> suggested interactive functionalities such as transfer function (TF) control and region clipping in order to ensure comprehensive and convenient exploration of 3D flow fields. It is still very time-consuming and troublesome for the user to find appropriate TFs and regions to be clipped for a given unknown 3D flow dataset.</p><p>In our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, we derived a significance map (S-map) semi-automatically based on the flow field topology analysis in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, and utilized it to adjust the length of convolution kernel and the granularity of noise textures, resulting in not only highlighting the significant structures of a 2D flow field but also in accelerating the texture image generation. In our recent report <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, we extended the approach to 3D, and relied on a 3D streamline illumination model <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> to produce comprehensible volume LIC images.</p><p>In this paper, we take full advantage of scalar volume rendering hardware, such as VolumePro <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, to realize a realtime 3D flow field visualization environment with the selective LIC volume rendering method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">SELECTIVE LIC VOLUME RENDERING</head><p>This section is devoted to a brief description of our selective LIC volume rendering method. The pipeline of the method consists of the following three main steps <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>:</p><p>Step1: LIC solid texture generation;</p><p>Step2: 3D S-map derivation; and Step3: Vector volume rendering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">LIC Solid Texture Generation</head><p>A procedure, called 3D LIC herein, is the direct 3D extension of the original 2D LIC <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, and smears a given 3D white noise texture along paths that are dictated by a given 3D flow field. The 3D LIC algorithm takes as input, a 3D white noise texture of the same size as the vector field, and convolutes the input at each texel with a 1D filter kernel defined along the local streamline in the 3D flow field. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>, for a texel P´x y zµ, the corresponding local streamline is generated in both forward and backward directions. Then, the output texture value F out´x y zµ at the texel P´x y zµ can be computed as follows: </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">F out´x y zµ n ∑ i 0 F in´ P i µh i • m ∑ i 0 F in´ P ¼ i µh ¼ i n ∑ i 0 h i • m ∑ i 0 h ¼ i h i s i •∆s i s i k´wµdw s i s i 1 • ∆s i s 0 0</formula><p>where k´wµ: Convolution kernel; P i : Integer texel index at which grid point P i is located; F in´ P i µ: Input texture value at texel´</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">P x i P y i P z i µ;</formula><p>n, m: The number of texels through which the streamline passes in the forward and backward directions, respectively. Dashattached variables are defined in the backward direction. ∆s i : The length of arc connecting the points s i to s i•1 on texel boundaries along the streamline.</p><p>This formula is repeatedly evaluated for all the texels to generate an LIC solid texture. Note that the above computation uses the original 3D streamlines whereas 2D streamlines projected onto arbitrary surfaces are used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">3D S-Map Derivation</head><p>The 3D LIC contracts a given 3D vector field into a corresponding 3D scalar field. As stated in Section 1, however, a naive direct volume rendering of LIC solid textures cannot produce useful projected images, since optical integration along viewing directions tends to spoil the coherent structures along 3D local streamlines. Therefore, we decided to adopt a selective approach to LIC volume rendering <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>. We first rely on the intrinsic properties of a given 3D flow field to create a significance map (S-map), where regions containing interesting structures, such as vortices, are assigned higher significance values, whereas regions with little interesting detail are assigned lower significance values. Then, we can set the opacity of each texel to be proportional to its significance value. The resultant volume rendered images are expected to highlight the ROIs by minimizing the occlusion artifacts caused by insignificant regions.</p><p>S-map can be viewed to provide spatially-dependent opacity transfer function (TF) for classifying 3D LIC texels effectively. In order to determine the significance value at each point in a given flow field, we can employ the flow field topology analysis technique described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Local features of a flow field can be characterized with critical points, which are points where the velocity of flow equals zero. Each critical point can be classified into six cases by the eigenvalue analysis of the Jacobian at the point <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig. 2)</ref>. R1, R2 and I1, I2 are real and imaginary parts of eigenvalues of the Jacobian at the point, respectively. This technique is extendable to 3D, though the 3D version sometimes cannot locate all the flow features. For example, center points of swirling vortices cannot be detected because they have base velocities in the principle direction of the swirling flow field. In practical, we can take advantage of various flow analysis methods in combination with the technique according to the nature of a given 3D flow field. Needless to say, the user is allowed to specify or modify S-map interactively. Actual examples will be described in Section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Vector Volume Rendering</head><p>LIC volume rendering is different from scalar volume rendering.</p><p>In the traditional method, the sharp variation in intensity suggests the existence of virtual surfaces among different adjacent materials in a volume. This kind of boundary plays a very important role in revealing the structural features of the volume. Therefore, the firstorder central difference is usually adopted as the surface normal in evaluating the volume shading model. On the other hand, no physical meaning can be generally found in the intensity variation between adjacent texels in LIC solid textures, and thus, we cannot adopt the central difference as the normal of the virtual surface. In order to take as full advantage as possible of shading techniques for revealing 3D flow structures, we decided to adopt the illumination model for 3D streamlines <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> although streamlines themselves do not really exist in the LIC solid texture space. For line primitives, there are 2D manifolds containing an infinite number of possible normals and reflection vectors. All possible reflection vectors R lie on a cone around the tangential direction T at the point on the streamline. For the actual lighting computation, only the one contained in the L T plane should be chosen. So the light intensity at a texel can be given by the following Phong shading model: L¡Nµ and´V ¡Rµ used in Eq. (1) can be computed using the following formulae (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 3</ref>): </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">I k a I a • k d´L ¡NµI l • k s´V ¡Rµ n I l<label>(1)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">L R V T L N L T N</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>L¡Nµ</head><formula xml:id="formula_4">L N Õ 1 L T 2 Õ 1 ´L¡T µ 2 ´V ¡Rµ ´V ¡´L T L N µµ (2) ´L¡T µ´V ¡T µ Õ 1 ´L¡T µ 2 Õ 1 ´V ¡T µ 2</formula><p>Since N and R do not appear on the right sides of Eq. (2), Eq. (1) can be rewritten simply in terms of L, T , and V .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">ACCELERATION USING VolumePro</head><p>In this section, we attempt to accelerate the LIC volume rendering method described in Section 2 with a commertially-available PCI board, called VolumePro TM 500 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The method cannot be executed on VolumePro as it is because the board renders a loaded volume with only scalar field-dependent TFs, and relies on the traditional volume illumination model. Therefore, we decided to adopt a lookup table-based approach.</p><p>Our algorithm consists of the following three steps:</p><p>Step 1: Constructing a shaded LIC volume Shading a given LIC volume using the 3D streamline illumination model in Section 2.3 into what we call index volume hereafter, whose intensity levels are normalized into 8 bit unsigned integers (0 255).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 2: Making LUT</head><p>Making an LUT which relates 4,096 index values to the 256 intensity levels, and 16 opacity levels determined by a given S-map. The order of entries should be determined so as to minimize the smearing artifacts caused by interpolation of intensity between adjacent indices.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Step 3: Volume rendering index volume with LUT</head><p>Loading the index volume generated in Step 1 into Volume-Pro, and performing real-time, non-shading volume rendering on VolumePro using the LUT generated in Step 2 as the default intensity TF table. Although the user is still allowed to adjust the opacity TF table on the fly, the flatness or linearity is expected to be maintained so that the discipline of S-map construction is not disturbed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">APPLICATIONS</head><p>We attempted to apply the present method to visualizing two kinds of datasets. One is a program-generated tornado dataset having 128 3 voxels. The other is a more complicated flow field within porous media, which was simulated by the Lattice Boltzmann method with 64¢64¢256 voxels. For all experiments, 2D LIC textures were visualized by AVS/Express Ver5.1 2 running on an SGI O2 system (CPU: R10000; Clock: 195MHz; RAM: 256MB), and LIC solid textures were visualized interactively by VolumePro 500 installed in a Dell Dimension XPS T550 system (OS: WindowsNT 4.0; CPU: PentiumIII; Clock: 550MHz; RAM: 512MB). <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> VolumePro is a trademark of TeraRecon, Inc. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> AVS/Express is a trademark of Advanced Visual Systems, Inc. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Tornado</head><p>For visualizing the tornado dataset effectively, the field topology analysis method in Section 2.2 was applied to each of horizontal cross-sections (x y planes) to locate its vortex center (repelling node). All the centers were connected mutually along the z axis to form a twisted vortex centerline of the tornado. Then, an S-map used here was generated by computing the inverse of the horizontal distance from each texel to the vortex centerline. <ref type="figure">Fig.4(a)</ref> shows a 2D LIC texture on a horizontal cross-section, whereas <ref type="figure">Fig.4(b)</ref> shows an LIC volume rendered image. It is seen from the figures that global features of the dataset are visualized more clearly by the LIC volume rendering. Especially, highlights give an effective depth cue to understand the coherent structure of the flow field. We generated an animation from the LIC volume rendered images using a sequence of phase-shifted filters <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Next, we attempted to prove that S-map modification is available for imitating various visual effects of existing 3D flow visualization methods. Three different ways to modify S-maps are:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Setting 1: Cross-section effect</head><p>Re-assigning a higher importance value to all the texels located over a cross-section; Setting 2: Isosurface effect Re-assigning a higher importance value to all the texels located on an iso-velocity surface; Setting 3: Streamtube effect Re-assigning a higher importance value to all the texels with an identical intensity value.</p><p>It is seen from Figs. 5(a) and (b) that the thoughtful design of S-maps allows the LIC volume rendering to include the mapping of LIC textures onto arbitrary surfaces. Note that the accentuated LIC textures do not represent the 2D flow directions projected onto the surfaces, but represent the original 3D flow directions. More interesting result is obtained in <ref type="figure">Fig. 5(c)</ref>, where Setting 3 produces a visual cue just as if a dense set of streamtubes was extracted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Inner-Porous Media Flow</head><p>Second, we attempted to explore how effectively the present method can visualize a more complicated dataset for 3D flow field  within porous media, which was taken from a contemporary stratum disposal research.</p><p>It has been considered that coherent flow fields like tornado described in Section 4.1 can be characterized sufficiently with a reasonable number of critical points, whereas it is difficult for us to analyze complex flow fields containing critical points almost everywhere. Therefore, in order to design an effective S-map for the inner-porous media flow dataset, we herein introduce a different approach.</p><p>In order to determine the significance value at each point, we derived the velocity and flux volumes <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6</ref> comparatively shows the two visualization results. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Fig. 6(a)</ref>, the wall of holes, where a number of critical points are concentrated, was assigned relatively higher significance values, to make difficult for us to see the inner flow structures within the holes. On the other hand, in Figs. 6(b), main streams with higher velocity and flux volumes are visualized in an accentuated manner.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>In this paper, we have presented a selective LIC volume rendering method based on 3D S-map construction and a specific volume illumination model for vector fields. In addition, we succeeded in realtime animation of LIC solid textures using a scalar volume rendering hardware device. The effectiveness of the present 3D flow exploration environment was proven empirically with application to visualizing two kinds of 3D simulated flow datasets.</p><p>Verma, et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> use a template texture to integrate LIC and streamlines, whereas judicious choice of S-maps enables the present LIC volume rendering technique to unify 2D LIC mapping to cross-sections or isosurfaces as well as extracting streamtubes.</p><p>At present we are utilizing a VG-cluster system (a commodity PC cluster with multiple VolumePro boards) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> to realize further acceleration of the LIC volume rendering method for larger flow volume datasets.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>IEEEFigure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Visualization 2002 Oct. 27 -Nov. 1, 2002, Boston, MA, USA 0-7803-7498-3/02/$17.00 © 2002 IEEE Definition of local 3D streamline for generating LIC solid texture.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Classification of critical points (2D).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Illumination model for streamline (3D).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :Figure 5 :</head><label>45</label><figDesc>Comparison of 2D and 3D LIC texture rendering methods for visualizing tornado dataset. Visual effects of S-map modification (tornado).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Visual effects of S-map modification (inner-porous media flow).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors would like to express their sincere gratitude to Roger Crawfis at Ohio State University for giving a chance to use his program to generate the tornado dataset visualized in Section 4.1. This work has been partially supported by the Japan Society for Promotion of Science under Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (C) 13680401.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illumination in Diverse Codimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Banks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIG-GRAPH 94</title>
		<meeting>SIG-GRAPH 94<address><addrLine>Florida</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="334" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging Vector Fields Using Line Integral Convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cabral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Leedom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH 93</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH 93<address><addrLine>Anaheim</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="270" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast LIC Image Generation Based on Significance Map</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fujishiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">High Performance Computing -Third International Symposium, ISHPC 2000</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Tokyo</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1940" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="546" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings, Lecture Notes in Computer Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensible Volume LIC Rendering Based on 3D Significance Map</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fujishiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceeding of SPIE VDA &apos;02</title>
		<meeting>eeding of SPIE VDA &apos;02<address><addrLine>San Jose</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-01" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="153" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Line Integral Convolution for Flow Visualization: Curvilinear Grids, Variable-Speed Animation and Unsteady Flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Forssell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">TVCG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Helman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hesselink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualizing Vector Field Topology in Fluid Flows</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991-05" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Interrante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Grosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Strategies for Effectively Visualizing 3D Flow with Volume LIC</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Phoenix</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="421" to="424" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings of Visualization &apos;97</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing 3D flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Interrante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Grosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CG&amp;A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="1998-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Texture Synthesis with Line Integral Convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIG-GRAPH 97 Course Notes</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Los Angeles</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Line Integral Convolution for Arbitrary 3D Surface Through Solid Texturing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kikukawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fujita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Imamiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 8th Eurographics Workshop on Visualization in Scientific Computing</title>
		<meeting>8th Eurographics Workshop on Visualization in Scientific Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="69" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Next-Generation Visual Supercomputing Using PC Clusters with Volume Graphics Hardware Devices</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Muraki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ogata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koshizuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kajihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nagano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shimokawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">CD-ROM Proceedings of IEEE SC2001</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The VolumePro Real-Time Ray-Casting System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hardenbergh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knittle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Seiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of SIGGRAPH 99, Los Angeles</title>
		<meeting>SIGGRAPH 99, Los Angeles</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="260" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Exploration of Line Integral Convolution Based on 3D-Texture Mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rezk-Salama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hastreiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Teitzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization&apos;99</title>
		<meeting>Visualization&apos;99<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="240" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization Vector Fields Using Line Integral Convolution and Dye Advection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization</title>
		<meeting>the 1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="70" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PLIC: Bridging the Gap Between Streamlines and LIC</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Verma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization&apos;99</title>
		<meeting>Visualization&apos;99<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="348" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Visualization of 3D-Vector Fields Using Illuminated Stream Lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zöckler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stalling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-C</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;96<address><addrLine>San Francisco</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="113" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
