<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Full Body Virtual Autopsies using a State-of-the-art Volume Rendering Pipeline</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Patric</forename><surname>Ljung</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division for Visual Information Technology and Applications (VITA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Calle</forename><surname>Winskog</surname></persName>
							<email>calle.winskog@rmv.se.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division for Visual Information Technology and Applications (VITA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anders</forename><surname>Persson</surname></persName>
							<email>anders.persson@cmiv.liu.se.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division for Visual Information Technology and Applications (VITA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>Student Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Claes</forename><surname>Lundström</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division for Visual Information Technology and Applications (VITA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Anders</forename><surname>Ynnerman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division for Visual Information Technology and Applications (VITA)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Winskog</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Board of Forensic Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Forensic Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Linköping</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Persson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Medical Image Science and Visualization (CMIV)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">•</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lundström</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Center for Medical Image Science and Visualization (CMIV)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Sectra-Imtec AB</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Linköping University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Full Body Virtual Autopsies using a State-of-the-art Volume Rendering Pipeline</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">received 31 March 2006; accepted 1 August 2006; posted online 6 November 2006.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-20T19:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Forensics</term>
					<term>autopsies</term>
					<term>medical visualization</term>
					<term>volume rendering</term>
					<term>large scale data</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper presents a procedure for virtual autopsies based on interactive 3D visualizations of large scale, high resolution data from CT-scans of human cadavers. The procedure is described using examples from forensic medicine and the added value and future potential of virtual autopsies is shown from a medical and forensic perspective. Based on the technical demands of the procedure state-of-the-art volume rendering techniques are applied and refined to enable real-time, full body virtual autopsies involving gigabyte sized data on standard GPUs. The techniques applied include transfer function based data reduction using levelof-detail selection and multi-resolution rendering techniques. The paper also describes a data management component for large, out-of-core data sets and an extension to the GPU-based raycaster for efficient dual TF rendering. Detailed benchmarks of the pipeline are presented using data sets from forensic cases.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The importance of autopsy procedures leading to the establishment of the cause of death is well known. In forensic cases, which are the focus of this paper, the autopsy can provide key information and guide the criminal investigation. A recent addition to the autopsy work flow is the possibility of conducting postmortem imaging, in its 3D version also called Virtual Autopsy (VA), using Computed Tomography (CT) data from scans of the cadavers <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Direct Volume Rendering (DVR) techniques. There are several reasons for the rising interest in VA. First, the VA can be a complement to standard autopsies enabling broad, systematic examinations of the whole body which are normally difficult and time consuming, for example, examination of the entire bone structure or searching for the presence of air in the body. Several studies have also shown the great potential of postmortem imaging in forensic investigations <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>.</p><p>There is also a decreasing trend in the frequency of full autopsies for reasons such as cost, availability of pathologists, and improved premortem diagnosis. Furthermore, the VA has, for certain cases, the potential to replace standard autopsies. In the multicultural society of today autopsies are frequently rejected by family members due to religious beliefs. Replacement will, however, require significant medical research leading to the establishment of procedures and protocols for virtual autopsies.</p><p>A striking feature of the data sets from the virtual autopsy is the overwhelming amount of information. In a typical full body virtual autopsy using Multi Detector Computed Tomography (MDCT), up to 8000 images can routinely be reconstructed. This leads to data set sizes of several gigabytes. In addition, the lighting models essential for high-quality images require precise gradient data which increases the total amount of data even further. Specific demands on the DVR pipeline are thus put in terms of: fast handling of large scale data, seamless navigation and zooming, interactive adjustment of transfer function settings, support for shading and lighting models. Furthermore the DVR system should preferably run on commodity desktop systems and graphics hardware. Existing DVR systems for commodity PCs have not yet reached a level where all these requirements can be met.</p><p>The application presented in this paper is enabled by research results such as our work on transfer function based level-of-detail scheme for volume data reduction <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> and rendering of the resulting volumes <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>. This paper thus presents a DVR pipeline integrating these methods and, in addition, also presents features specifically targeting the VA procedure. The contributions of this paper can be summarized as:</p><p>• A detailed description of the forensic virtual autopsy procedure based on real cases showing the potentially large impact and wide deployment of the application.</p><p>• A presentation of the data management subsystem for ondemand loading of out-of-core, multiresolution volume data.</p><p>• An extension to the GPU-based raycaster for efficient rendering of dual TFs, enabling fast visual localization of, for example, metal fragments.</p><p>• A performance analysis of the DVR pipeline is given in the context of virtual autopsy data sets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">THE VIRTUAL AUTOPSY PROCEDURE</head><p>The presented autopsy procedure has been developed through a collaboration between the Center for Medical Image Science and Visualization and the Swedish National Board of Forensic Medicine. The procedure is now routinely used for forensic examinations and has been applied to over 100 cases so far. Our experience with VA has shown that full body high resolution DVR visualizations are of great value in crime investigations. We will limit the presentation and the cases shown in this paper to the forensic context, even though similar VA procedures are feasible for other types of autopsy. The pipeline presented in this paper focuses on the full-body data sets that previously could only be viewed in separate parts and with limited interactivity. These shortcomings are the main motivation behind the development of the visualization pipeline described in this paper. The work flow of the forensic procedure is summarized in figure 2. The traditional physical autopsy is extended by adding the VA activities shown in red. In most cases the forensic pathologist comes to the <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>. From full body view to detailed close-ups at high resolution in a single session. From left to right: Fractures on the right middle foot, left tibia and fibula, right knee and left femoral shaft. Fractured jaw and a broken vertebra -the cause of death. A transfer function based level-of-detail selection and cropping allows us to inspect any part at original full resolution which fits into the allocated memory of the GPU. This data set is 5.7 GB on disk and rendered on a PC equipped with an ATI X1800XT using 192 MB of texture memory. crime scene and oversees the handling of the human cadaver, which is placed in a sealed body bag before being transported to the forensic department, and put in cold storage. The following morning, a full body MDCT scan is performed. In preparation for the physical autopsy a collaborative DVR session between the pathologist and the radiologist is conducted. The radiologist and forensic pathologist quickly receive a clear overview of the entire body and can use transfer functions to select aspects of the body, such as the skeleton to localize fractures, or the distribution of air in the body (see figures 1, 8 and 3). The full body procedure, together with the dual TF rendering feature presented below, also allows for fast localization of foreign objects such as metal fragments or bullets, see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">figure 5</ref>. This can provide essential information in the early part of the police investigation. Another important aspect is the high resolution of the data which, in a seamless visualization, allows for extraction of details such as dental information for identification purposes, see figure <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref>.</p><p>An important added value of the VA procedure is that the captured MDCT data is stored which gives the possibility to iterate the procedure. Often findings during the physical autopsy lead to new questions that the VA can answer. The pathologist can also, at any point during the investigation, re-examine the cadaver, and search for additional information. Also, in crime scene investigations new findings may require that other hypotheses need to be scrutinized by VA.</p><p>VA is currently used as a complement to the autopsy procedure. It should, however, be noted that the work flow overhead introduced is minimal as the time needed for the MDCT scan and visualization session is short in comparison to the physical autopsy and can, in fact, make the autopsy more efficient since the pathologist has prior knowledge of the case before conducting the autopsy. The fact that the cadaver remains in a sealed body bag throughout the VA procedure also secures the technical evidence, for example fibres and body fluids, which in forensic cases are of great importance.</p><p>Below we give detailed descriptions of the most important kinds of forensic cases we have worked with.</p><p>Shootings Knowing the bullet location beforehand saves the pathologist much time, especially if the bullet has left the body and so no search is needed. Bullets will frequently lodge in a position far from their entry points, particularly if they are deflected by curved bone such as the ribs or the skull. In line with the results from other research <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25]</ref>, we have found that 3D MDCT data can minimize the location uncertainty of bullets, entry and exit wounds, as well as wound channels. The full-body overview is particularly useful when it comes to determining bullet paths. To further ease the detection of metal fragments we have added a dual TF rendering feature. With the help of this tool, sub-millimeter metal fragments can be visualized which otherwise are hard to discover since they are buried in the streaks around high intensity materials, see figure 5b,c. These fragments can indicate a bullet's path and reveal information about the angle and direction of fire. Streaking artefacts from metal are a significant problem in MDCT. With DVR these streaking artefacts can be reduced and give information about the type of bullet <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>Drowning In the traditional autopsy there are no unambiguous indications of drowning. The diagnosis relies primarily on the examination of the subject's individual characteristics, circumstances and postmortem changes both macro-and micro-pathologically. Above all, the lungs are studied and the lung volume is estimated. MDCT constitutes an additional method of determining the cause of death in these cases. With postmortem MDCT a number of important attributes can be studied: the lung volume, the mean attenuation, the anterior-posterior attenuation difference, the lung density profile and the amount of water within the lungs <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. This is one of the areas of postmortem imaging that holds great promise for the future.</p><p>Polytrauma and traffic accidents Fractures can be clearly visualized with DVR including shading. Minor fractures can often only be seen at specific angles, hence the freedom of rotation, or light positioning, in DVR is essential. In general, the rendered image can quickly give the viewer a good understanding of the underlying 3D postmortem anatomy and the cause of death. A striking example of a) A three week old infant that died during a laryngoscopy procedure. The CT scan findings suggested that air was admitted around the heart. b) A close up view of the lungs and throat with an emphasis on the air-tissue interface reveals air in the soft tissue of the chest cavity, to the right of the trachea. c) Virtual autopsy conclusion: A ventilation needle had penetrated the pericardium leading to air flowing into the space between the heart and the pericardium, causing the heart to stop.  . The dental fillings are easily accessible and CT scans have been used for identification in two cases. (Not the actual cases shown.) These images were made by zooming in and cropping to the visible section from the full data sets together with preset transfer functions for dental identification.</p><p>the benefit of DVR is dental identification. Conventional postmortem radiography produces 2D images, 'shadows' of three-dimensional objects. Fillings on the cheek side of a tooth cannot be distinguished from those on the tongue side <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. By using MDCT with small voxel size in combination with DVR, this can be overcome and the dental identification of a body made possible, see figure 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">TECHNICAL BACKGROUND</head><p>This section reviews key technical components for the DVR pipeline. In medical applications it is important that no data is irreversibly distorted and lossy compression is consequently prohibited.</p><p>Block based management of large volumes is a common concept. Hierarchical techniques for DVR have been presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. Flat blocking techniques have also been used and are presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>. The are several trade-offs between these two approaches. Hierarchical blocking increases the blocks' spatial extent but keeps the amount of data constant per block. Flat blocking works the opposite way, keeping spatial extents constant while varying the amount of data per block.</p><p>An inherent problem with block based methods is the interpolation of samples over block boundaries. Sample replication and padding, resulting in block overlaps, have been proposed to solve this issue in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. This solution counteracts the data reduction achieved through a level-of-detail scheme, specifically for flat blocking schemes. The resolution difference between neighboring blocks is also restricted to one level. In addition, the positioning and alignment of samples within the blocks are limited. Ljung et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> propose an interblock interpolation technique which supports direct interpolation across boundaries between blocks of arbitrary resolutions. Block resolutions are not restricted to powers of two, as applied to inter-tile interpolation in 2D <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</p><p>Several methods for level-of-detail selection have been proposed. View-dependent methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33]</ref> use lower resolution for blocks at greater distance from viewer. Data errors, as introduced by subsampling in lower resolution blocks, has also been used <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>. Improved prediction of screen-space error, and thus a more optimized LOD selection, is achieved by incorporating the TF used for voxel classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. The maximum voxel value deviation is used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> to compute errors per channel in RGB-space. An adaptive, simplified voxel value distribution representation per block is used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> to compute a perceptual color error, ∆E, in CIEL * u * v * color-space.</p><p>Interactive volume rendering using graphics hardware has been accomplished by object-or view-plane aligned texture slicing <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> in most of the papers referenced above. Methods for empty space skipping and occlusion culling were presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> for octree volumes. Krüger et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> presented a multi-pass raycasting technique, employing empty space skipping and early ray termination. Stegmaier et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> introduced single-pass raycasting on the GPU. This technique was extended by Klein et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> using frame-to-frame coherence for initial empty space leaping. Ljung <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> presents a single-pass raycaster using adaptive sampling density for flat-blocked multiresolution volumes. a) Alien objects are readily visible and the 3D mode makes it easy to determine their exact location.</p><p>b) The location of a bullet and small fragments can be buried in context tissues and streaking artefacts. c) Using dual TF rendering, metal fragments can be located faster, without excessive use of clip planes and cropping. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">VISUALIZATION PIPELINE</head><p>This paper presents a complete DVR pipeline that has been assembled with components from previous work by the authors, including TFbased adaptive level-of-detail <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, interblock interpolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and single-pass raycasting of multiresolution volumes <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. To be able to deal with data sets larger than available host memory a data management component for large, out-of-core multiresolution volumes has been developed. This enables the a user of the Virtual Autopsy application to seamlessly explore uncompressed, large, full body CT scans. Furthermore, an extension to the GPU-based raycaster has been developed that enables efficient dual TF rendering for fast localization of, for example, metal fragments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Pre-processing and data structures</head><p>In the pre-processing stage the data is scaled from 12 bit precision to fill the range in 16 bits which ensures better interpolation accuracy on the GPU. Gradients are also pre-computed, permitting the use of more expensive gradient operators such as the Sobel operator. On-the-fly computation of gradients are furthermore costly, specifically for multiresolution volumes due to the required interblock sample lookup. To achieve high accuracy of gradient directions, these are normalized and stored in three bytes, storing the magnitude in a fourth byte. This ensures high precision gradient directions even for gradients with small magnitudes. The gradients thus result in a 200% increase in the total data set size. This enables better gradient operators and continuity over block boundaries can be exploited, which compensates for the overhead cost of the increased data size.</p><p>A volume is divided into equally sized blocks, in this paper 16 3 voxel blocks are used. All resolution levels, from full resolution (L 16 ) down to a single average value (L 1 ), are computed separately for each block by average downsampling. In a flat blocking scheme, lower resolution blocks are not combined into larger blocks, as in hierarchical schemes. Since each block can be processed separately, including gradient computation using an additional one voxel layer around each block, this scheme is extremely well suited for parallel execution.</p><p>The challenge of using this scheme for access to out-of-core data, stored on disk, is the poor I/O request throughput of commodity disk systems. While I/O bandwidth has increased and algorithms for optimizing block reads are used, the throughput of read requests has not improved significantly over the years. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 6</ref> shows this problem by plotting read performance as a function of block size, the amount of data per read request. The average time per block read, 7 ms for 1 kbyte, is slightly increased to 10 ms for 128 kbyte. These results clearly indicate that a lossless compression, rarely above a 3:1 ratio, would yield little performance gain for block reads. Furthermore, it also means that reading precomputed gradient data will have little impact on read performance as well.</p><p>The graph in figure 6 also indicates that reading low resolution blocks separately is not efficient. First, the lowest resolution level, L 1 , is stored in a separate thumbnail volume. Second, the concept of Groups Of Blocks (GOBs) is introduced. A GOB stores multiple blocks at the same resolution level, L λ , together. A GOB size specifies the number of blocks to be stored together at the second lowest resolution level. For each consecutively higher resolution level the GOB size is halved in each dimension since the block data size is increased, keeping the disk size of a GOB constant. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 7</ref> illustrates the GOB concept in 2D for a GOB size of 4 × 4.</p><p>The data loader then loads an entire GOB whenever a block is requested in that GOB. Additional blocks requested at the same resolution within that GOB will thus not generate a disk read request. This scheme supports efficient loads in the case where neighbors are assigned the same level-of-detail. Finally, the data loader uses multithreading and runs in the background such that rendering is not impacted by disk I/O.</p><p>In the pre-processing stage, a sample value distribution, h(s), is collected for each block, including the additional one voxel layer around the block to ensure that the value range between blocks are accounted for. The block specific distributions are each simplified into piecewise constant segments. Raw storage of this data consists of only 0.5% of the block data size, using a resolution of 256 value entries and 10 segments. This simplified value distribution representation is used in the LOD selection scheme during run-time, as described in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">LOD selection</head><p>The LOD selection scheme is based on the methods presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. A short summary is provided here for the clarity of this presentation.</p><p>For a given target memory budget, such as the amount of available texture memory on the GPU, an optimal LOD selection is sought where the resulting screen-space error is minimal, compared to a full resolution volume rendering. Since a full resolution rendering is not available an error prediction has to be made, preferably before loading any volume data. To this end, the simplified voxel value distribution, h(s), and the average value, s, is used to compute a block-wise maximum post TF error, τ(1), in the CIEL * u * v * color-space. The color error, ∆E, in CIEL * u * v * is a perceptually adapted color difference.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">τ(1) = ∑ s ∆E T * (s), T * (s) h(s),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where T * is the current TF expressed in the CIEL * u * v * domain. This measure, τ(1), represents a block's significance and also expresses the TF content of a block. When τ(1) = 0 the block can be left at the lowest resolution, L 1 , without introducing errors. The higher the significance, the higher the block resolution desired, L 2 , L 4 , . . .. The block significance for intermediate levels, τ(λ ), is linearly distributed over all resolution levels, with τ(16) = 0 naturally. Before the final LOD optimization step, all blocks having τ(1) &lt; ε are discarded and assigned the lowest resolution level, L 1 . In the last step of the LOD selection a priority queue is populated with the remaining blocks, initially assigned a minimum resolution level, λ min . The block with the highest significance difference between two consecutive levels, with respect to the increase of block size, is then picked and assigned the next higher resolution. A block is re-inserted into the queue, unless the maximum resolution level, λ max , has been reached. The procedure is repeated until the given memory budget is reached or the queue is empty. By having the maximum resolution defined per block, efficient culling of blocks is enabled, for example cropping of the volume.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Rendering</head><p>The data loader packs the retrieved blocks into a single volume texture and creates an index texture, specifying block location and resolution level in the packed volume texture. Since sample replication is not needed and average downsampling has been used, the placement of voxel samples within a block differs from schemes used for Adaptive Texture Maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> and in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>.</p><p>For rendering of the multiresolution volumes both texture slicing and single-pass raycasting have been implemented. The use of interblock interpolation in texture slicing based rendering is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and single-pass, GPU-based rendering of multiresolution volumes, using adaptive object-space sampling is presented in <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. Adaptive sampling density provides a form of empty space leaping, both in front of and behind an embedded object, as well as for empty space inside objects. Early Ray Termination (ERT) is also incorporated as an additional loop condition. Optionally, the phase of the initial ray start position can be jittered to minimize perceived aliasing artefacts, as suggested in <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>. In our case, this is achieved through a mirrored-repeat texture lookup of a small texture (64×64), which holds a uniform distribution of random values between 0 and 1.</p><p>The raycaster employs adaptive sampling density along the rays, as dictated by the resolution level of the block that is being sampled. A naive stepping scheme would be to advance the ray in steps of the inverse of the block scale. This could however result in undersampling of high resolution blocks when advancing the ray by multiple steps. Close to the boundary of a high resolution block, the ray would penetrate deep into that block, potentially missing visible parts. In <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> this is solved by limiting ray stepping such that the ray can only advance to the first position outside the block. The current implementation can relax this block boundary constraint since the interblock interpolation scheme provides the resolution levels for neighboring blocks. Ray advancement is here derived from the maximum resolution level of the blocks in each eight block neighborhood.</p><p>The dual TF rendering feature constitutes a straightforward addition to the raycaster. A secondary TF is defined and, for each ray, two rayintegration vectors are used instead of one. Upon termination of the ray, the secondary ray integral is composited, using a blending factor, over the ordinary ray integral.</p><p>An issue introduced by the dual TF raycasting is that early ray termination is in effect disabled, since both integrals are required to be sufficiently saturated before the ray can be terminated. This problem is minimized by the introduction of a pixel priority pass. A volume of block significance values is generated for the secondary TF. This block significance volume is first rendered into a low resolution viewport. A modified raycaster is used that only produces one sample per block and accumulates the significance of blocks along the ray. If this value is above some small threshold, the pixel is set to white, otherwise black. The resulting framebuffer is copied to a texture and used in the following dual TF raycasting pass. If the lookup in the generated priority texture yields a value below a specific threshold (0.3), the ERT alpha threshold for the secondary TF is set to zero. This ensures that rays that do not intersect any block with content in the secondary TF are terminated as usual and the performance impact of dual TF raycasting is kept to a minimum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">RESULTS</head><p>In this section we describe the capturing and representation of the forensic data sets, which have also been used to benchmark the performance of the presented DVR pipeline. The data management and rendering performance is also reported.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Data Capture and Representation</head><p>When capturing MDCT data for high-quality DVR renderings it is essential to use the thinnest collimation possible, in this case 0.7 mm. Moreover, the data set should, ideally, be reconstructed from raw data as isotropic voxels requiring an inter-slice spacing of 0.3-0.5 mm. This makes it possible to reconstruct images in any plane with submillimeter spatial resolution and good discrimination of tissues (detecting attenuation differences less than 1%) can be achieved <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. Four different data sets are used in this paper. The largest is a full body that has been constructed by combination of two separate scans reconstructed with different field-of-view. There is, therefore, a discontinuity at the hip. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> shows details of the data sets. Next generation CT scanners will, however, support full body scans. The voxel sizes for the data sets are of sub-millimeter scale, ranging from <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>. Data set details. The source column denotes the 12 bit precision input data size and the size column denotes the data set size, including pre-computed gradients, 6 bytes per voxel. the disk column denotes the size of the data set on disk including all MIPMAP levels and the GOB size overhead. 0.3 mm for the infant child and 0.5 mm for the full body data set along the length axis, Z. The X/Y sizes are between 0.4 and 0.9 mm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Set</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Data Management</head><p>All results in this paper have been produced using a desktop PC with 4 GB of host memory, an AMD Athlon64 CPU and an ATI X1800XT with 512 MB of memory. The target data size was set to either 96 MB or 192 MB of texture memory for the scalar and gradient textures. The data reduction for the volumes varied between 7:1 and 30:1 and has been indicated in table 3. Pre-processing takes about 0.8 ms per block, and the full body data set is being constructed in less than 4 minutes. Guthe et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> reported 1 hour of preprocessing for a volume of one third in size. Both the pre-processing and the run-time data loader support concurrent execution, specifically the pre-processing benefits from multi-CPU/core architectures.</p><p>On the system used, the disk read performance is reported to be 66 MB/s according to the tool hdparm in Linux, 1200 MB/s for cached reads. The read-ahead parameter is 128 kbytes. In order to determine the optimal GOB size we tested three different sizes, 4 3 , 8 3 and 16 <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> , the last of which means that 8 full resolution blocks will be read as minimum. Our application performed best with the largest GOB size, in agreement with the reported disk performance (figure 6). When a data set is loaded we first load a limited resolution set to provide a quick overview. The numbers in the columns Load 1 and Update 1 of table 2 are the results of initial load and an update after a reboot, to make sure no data is in OS file buffers. The loading times otherwise vary depending on the amount of change in the TF, cropping, whether GOBs are already loaded, etc. For interactive use, the loading times do not disturb the work flow interaction.</p><p>Computing the TF significance required for LOD selection takes 1.6 µs per block, or 350 ms for the full body data set. The optimization of level-of-detail then takes between 200 and 250 ms but decreases as the number of culled blocks increases, i.e. when cropping the volume. This processing is also done in a separate loader thread to minimize the impact on the interactivity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Rendering Performance</head><p>While there are many factors that affect the rendering performance, two major factors are the sampling density along the rays and the rendered image size. All images presented in this paper have been rendered in a viewport of 1024 × 1024 and the sampling density has been about 1.5 samples/voxel. Single-Pass (SP) raycasting has been used and is compared with Texture Slicing (TS) in some cases, see table <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref>. The performance is also compared between Nearest Block (NB) sampling and Interblock Interpolation (II) sampling. When using texture slicing and interblock interpolation each slice is rendered in two passes. The first pass renders intrablock samples and the second fills in the pixels using interblock interpolation, except for L 1 blocks. Early Z termination is thus exploited on the ATI GPU and usually improves the performance by a factor of three, compared to rendering all pixels with interblock interpolation. In the texture slicing scheme, full interblock interpolation is roughly 10 times slower than nearest block sampling only. In its single-pass raycasting version, full interblock interpolation is 4-5 times slower. All images shown in this paper are rendered using single-pass raycasting with adaptive stepping and interblock interpolation. Rendering without interblock interpolation is significantly faster but may result in blocking artefacts, specifically in close-up views as in figures 8d-f. The images in this paper are however not large enough to clearly show these artefacts. When interacting with the system, intrablock sampling is used. For rendering of static images interblock interpolation is used.</p><p>The dual TF rendering feature causes only a minor reduction of the rendering performance, as can be seen in table 3 for the bullet data set. The image in figure 5c is rendered at 1.8 FPS (NB yields 7.5 FPS), compared to 2.0 FPS (9.2 FPS) for the standard rendering in figure 5b. Without the use of the additional pixel priority rendering pass, the dual TF performance usually drops by a factor of 2-3. The use of the blending factor, typically set to 0.7, reduces the effect of appearing on top of the ordinary object.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE CHALLENGES</head><p>In this paper we have presented a DVR pipeline that supports full body VA and the added value of the full body procedure in forensic cases has been described. The presented load-on-demand data management subsystem, together with the TF-based data reduction scheme, provides a platform for interactive work with gigabyte sized volumes on commodity PC systems, using only a few hundreds of megabytes of graphics memory. Furthermore, the ability to interactively zoom in, and out, with updated level-of-detail, optimized for best quality in the region of interest, makes this DVR pipeline an efficient tool for the VA procedure. The dual TF rendering feature also provides a simple and efficient visual detection scheme, highlighting specific materials, such as bullet fragments and dental fillings. Single pass, GPU-based raycasting with adaptive sampling is also found to be significantly faster than traditional texture slicing based rendering.</p><p>From the medical perspective there are a number of research and development issues that need to be addressed to enable the further deployment of VA, both as a complement to and as a substitute for standard autopsy procedures. First, more thorough investigations establishing the potential and limitations of VA for a range of cases and scenarios need to be conducted. After considering the findings of these investigations, clinical validation can then be performed leading to the establishment of protocols for virtual autopsies. From a technical perspective there are several interesting areas of research and development. One area of special interest is to enable automated detection of alien objects through classification and inclusion of domain knowledge in the DVR pipeline. The vision for deployment is also to have a rich tool set with features suitable for VA and a collaborative workstation platform, including large back projected displays and tracked interaction devices as well as making use of augmented reality guidance for the pathologist during the autopsy procedure.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Overview of the forensic autopsy procedure. Virtual autopsy activities, shown in red, are added to the traditional work flow and enable an iterative approach. The procedure is based on a continuous interaction between the forensic pathologist, the radiologist, and the police.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Forensic use of DVR visualizations: detecting pockets of air in unnatural locations or the lack of air can reveal the cause of death. a) A zoom in on the jaw and teeth of the bullet data set. b) A zoom in on the jaw and teeth of the knife data set.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The dental fillings are easily accessible and CT scans have been used for identification in two cases. (Not the actual cases shown.) These images were made by zooming in and cropping to the visible section from the full data sets together with preset transfer functions for dental identification.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Examples of forensic use of DVR visualizations: detecting embedded alien objects. Image b shows that small metal fragments can be hard to detect. The dual TF rendering feature significantly improves localization of the fragments, image c.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Raw disk performance for random access reads as a function of the block size, average time per block. This test uses 32 threads and direct I/O to bypass the file buffers of the OS. This graph clearly indicate the need to request large blocks per read requests, or conversely, the number of read requests (access density) is the limiting factor.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>2D illustration of Group-Of-Block structure. Data is organized into chunks of GOBs. The smallest unit accessed from disk is one GOB which ensures sufficiently large transfers in order to minimize the number of read requests.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>d) Close-up view of bones (11.1/2.7 fps) e) Close-up view of skin (28.4/6.1 fps) a) Body bag (23.3/5.0 fps) b) Skin (38.0/8.8 fps) c) Bones (20.4/4.3 fps) f) Close-up view of body bag (11.6/2.3 fps) From body bag to bones. Data reduction provided by the TF-based LOD selection is 30:1 for a target of 192 MB of texture memory. Initial loading of the optimized LOD for the body bag TF (a,f) takes 34 seconds. Changing to the skin TF (b,e) takes 10 seconds and another second for the bones TF (c,d). Zooming to the section in (d-f) takes less than 5 seconds for any TF. The images are rendered in a 1024×1024 viewport using adaptive volume sampling and interblock interpolation. Framerates are shown for nearest block and interblock interpolation sampling (NB/II), see also table 3.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Performance results for various data sets and views (frames per second). Results for Texture Slicing (TS) and Single-Pass raycasting (SP), using Nearest Block (NB) and Interblock Interpolation (II). Rendered to a 1024×1024 viewport, sample density about 1.5 samples/voxel.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Dataset (figure)</cell><cell>SP/NB</cell><cell>SP/II</cell><cell>TS/NB</cell><cell>TS/II</cell></row><row><cell>Full body 30:1 (8b)</cell><cell>38.0</cell><cell>8.8</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Full body 30:1 (8e)</cell><cell>28.4</cell><cell>6.1</cell><cell>7.7</cell><cell>3.1</cell></row><row><cell>Full body 30:1 (8c)</cell><cell>20.4</cell><cell>4.3</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Full body 30:1 (8d)</cell><cell>11.1</cell><cell>2.7</cell><cell>7.7</cell><cell>3.2</cell></row><row><cell>Bullet 7:1 (5b), Single TF</cell><cell>9.2</cell><cell>2.0</cell><cell>4.3</cell><cell>1.9</cell></row><row><cell>Bullet 7:1 (5c), Dual TF</cell><cell>7.5</cell><cell>1.8</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Infant 16:1 (3a)</cell><cell>26.1</cell><cell>5.6</cell><cell>7.5</cell><cell>2.0</cell></row><row><cell>Infant 16:1 (3c)</cell><cell>9.3</cell><cell>1.9</cell><cell>4.1</cell><cell>1.2</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors wish to thank Petter Quick at CMIV for conducting the CT scans. The study has been approved by the local ethics committee. This work has been funded by the Swedish Research Council, grant 621-2001-2778 and 621-2003-6582, and the Swedish Foundation for Strategic Research, grant A3 02:116.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3D RGB image compression for interactive applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bajaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ihm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiresolution volume visualization with a texture-based octree</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Boada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Navazo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scopigno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerated volume rendering and tomographic reconstruction using texture mapping hardware</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cabral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Foran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">VVS &apos;94: Proceedings of the 1994 symposium on Volume visualization</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="98" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Utility of postmortem computed tomography in trauma victims</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Donchin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Rivkind</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bar-Ziv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Almog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Drescher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of trauma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="552" to="555" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional volume rendering imaging in detection of bone fractures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ö</forename><surname>Etlik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Temizöz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kayan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Arslan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of General Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of medical and dental radiographic identification of unknown human remains</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fischman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Forensic Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">New technical developments in multislice ct, part 1: approaching isotropic resolution with sub-millimeter 16-slice scanning. Fortschritte auf dem Gebiete der Röntgenstrahlen und der Nuklearmedizin</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Flohr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stierstorfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bruder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schaller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="845" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distributed data management for large volume visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Atchley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization 2005</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 2005</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="189" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visibility culling using plenoptic opacity functions for large volume visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="348" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advanced techniques for high quality multiresolution volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guthe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Strasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Computers &amp; Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Elsevier Science</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive rendering of large volume data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guthe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gonser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Straßer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postmortem magnetic resonance images of the injured brain: effective evidence in the courtroom</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Forensic Science International</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet-based 3d compression scheme for interactive visualization of very large volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Ihm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interleaved sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Heidrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 12th Eurographics Workshop on Rendering Techniques</title>
		<meeting>the 12th Eurographics Workshop on Rendering Techniques</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="276" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting frameto-frame coherence for accelerating high-quality volume raycasting on graphics hardware</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Strengert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stegmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization 2005</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 2005</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="230" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive texture maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kraus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eurographics/SIGGRAPH Workshop on Graphics Hardware</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="15" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acceleration techniques for gpu-based volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization 2003</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 2003</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="292" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiresolution techniques for interactive texture-based volume visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lamar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Joy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization 1999</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization 1999</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="362" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient error calculation for multiresolution texture-based volume visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lamar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Joy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Hierachical and Geometrical Methods in Scientific Visualization</title>
		<editor>G. Farin, B. Hamann, and H. Hagen</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive sampling in single pass, GPU-based raycasting of multiresolution volumes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ljung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Eurographics/IEEE Workshop on Volume Graphics</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics/IEEE Workshop on Volume Graphics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiresolution interblock interpolation in direct volume rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ljung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lundström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ynnerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Eurographics/IEEE Symposium on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics/IEEE Symposium on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="266" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transfer function based adaptive decompression for volume rendering of large medical data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ljung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lundström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ynnerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Museth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Volume Visualization and Graphics Symposium 2004</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Volume Visualization and Graphics Symposium 2004</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="32" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Search for isotropic resolution in CT from conventional through multiple-row detector</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mahesh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiographics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="962" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid high quality compression of volume data for visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Saupe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional reconstruction of a bullet path: validation by computed radiography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chancellor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Soitys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Symon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cullip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rosenman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hellman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boxwala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gormley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Forensic Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preautopsy magnitic resonance imaging: initial experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Baer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Staab</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic Resonance Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advanced GPU raycasting</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Scharsach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 9th Central European Seminar on Computer Graphics</title>
		<meeting>the 9th Central European Seminar on Computer Graphics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple and flexible volume rendering framework for graphics-hardware-based raycasting</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stegmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Strengert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eurographics/IEEE Volume Graphics Symposium. Eurographics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CT-based measurement of lung volume and attentuation of deceased</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sylvan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Linköping University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Master&apos;s thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New horizons in forensic radiology: the 60-second digital autopsy-full-body examination of a gunshot victim by multislice computed tomography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Thali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schweitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ozdoba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Spielfogel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dirnhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American journal of forensic medicine and pathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Forensic microradiology: microcomputed tomography (Micro-CT) and analysis of patterned injuries inside of bone</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Thali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Taubenreuther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Karolczak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Brueschweiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kalender</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dirnhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Forensic Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1336" to="1342" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtopsy, a new imaging horizon in forensic pathology: virtual autopsy by postmortem multislice computed tomography (MSCT) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) -a feasibility study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Thali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schweitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Boesch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ozdoba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schroth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sonnenschein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Doernhoefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Scheurer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Plattner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dirnhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Forensic Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="386" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Level-of-detail volume rendering via 3d textures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Volume Visualization and Graphics Symposium</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Volume Visualization and Graphics Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
