<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">I/O Optimal Isosurface Extraction</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yi-Jen</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Cláudio</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
							<email>csilva@ams.sunysb.edu.partially</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics and Statistics, SUNY Stony Brook</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>11794-3600</postCode>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">State University of New York at Stony Brook</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Applied Mathematics and Statistics, SUNY Stony Brook</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>11794-3600</postCode>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">I/O Optimal Isosurface Extraction</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>In this paper we give I/O-optimal techniques for the extraction of isosurfaces from volumetric data, by a novel application of the I/Ooptimal interval tree of Arge and Vitter. The main idea is to preprocess the dataset once and for all to build an efficient search structure in disk, and then each time we want to extract an isosurface, we perform an output-sensitive query on the search structure to retrieve only those active cells that are intersected by the isosurface. During the query operation, only two blocks of main memory space are needed, and only those active cells are brought into the main memory, plus some negligible overhead of disk accesses. This implies that we can efficiently visualize very large datasets on workstations with just enough main memory to hold the isosurfaces themselves. The implementation is delicate but not complicated. We give the first implementation of the I/O-optimal interval tree, and also implement our methods as an I/O filter for Vtk&apos;s isosurface extraction for the case of unstructured grids. We show that, in practice, our algorithms improve the performance of isosurface extraction by speeding up the active-cell searching process so that it is no longer a bottleneck. Moreover, this search time is independent of the main memory available. The practical efficiency of our techniques reflects their theoretical optimality. scanning of all cells in the search phase is found to be inefficient,</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Isosurface extraction represents one of the most effective and powerful techniques for the investigation of volume datasets. In fact, nearly all visualization packages include an isosurface extraction component. Its widespread use makes efficient isosurface extraction a very important problem.</p><p>The problem of isosurface extraction can be stated as follows.</p><p>A scalar volume dataset consists of tuples x; Fx, where x is a 3D point and F is a scalar function defined over 3D points. Given an isovalue (a scalar value) q, the extraction of the isosurface of q is to compute and display isosurface Cq = fxjFx = qg.</p><p>The computational process of isosurface extraction can be viewed as consisting of two phases. First, in the search phase, one finds all cells of the dataset that are intersected by the isosurface; such cells are called active cells. Next, in the generation phase, depending on the type of cells, one can apply an algorithm to actually generate the isosurface from those active cells. Let N be the total number of cells in the dataset, and K the number of active cells. It is estimated that the average value of K is ON 2=3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, therefore an exhaustive spending a large portion of time traversing cells that are not active. A lot of research efforts have thus focused on developing outputsensitive algorithms to speed up the search phase by avoiding such exhaustive scanning. Most algorithms developed so far (except for the inefficient exhaustive scanning), however, require the time and main memory space to read and keep the entire dataset in the main memory, plus some additional preprocessing time and main memory space if some structures are built to speed up the search phase. Unfortunately, for really large volume datasets, these methods often suffer the problem of not having enough main memory, which can cause a major slow-down of the algorithms due to a large number of page faults. On the other hand, when visualizing isosurfaces, as opposed to volume rendering, only a small portion (K = ON 2=3 active cells) of the dataset is ever needed. This seems to indicate that it is not necessary to use time and main memory to load and store the whole volume. If users never had to load a dataset completely but rather only had to store the triangles that defined the isosurface, effective visualization could be performed on low to middle range workstations, or even on PCs in some cases.</p><p>In this paper, we present I/O-efficient techniques to resolve the memory issue and to speed up the search phase of isosurface extraction, by a novel use of the I/O-optimal interval tree of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. After preprocessing, we can query for active cells using only two blocks of main memory space, and only Olog B N + K=B disk reads, where B is the number of cells that can fit into a disk block (and thus dK=Be disk reads are necessary to report all K active cells).</p><p>The technique hence acts as an I/O-filter, performing only those disk accesses to the dataset that are needed, plus a negligible overhead. The search structure is in fact I/O-optimal in space, query, and preprocessing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Previous Related Work</head><p>As mentioned before, isosurface extraction has been the focus of much research. Here we briefly review the results that focus on speeding up the search phase of isosurface extraction by acting as a filter, avoiding traversals of cells that are not active. (Please see <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for an excellent and thorough review.)</p><p>In Marching Cubes <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, all cells in the volume dataset are searched for isosurface intersection. Essentially, each time a user runs Marching Cubes, ON time is needed. Concerning the main memory issue, this technique does not require the entire dataset to fit into the main memory, but dN=Bedisk reads are necessary. Wilhems and Van Gelder <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> propose a method of using an octree to optimize isosurface extraction. This algorithm has worst-case time of OK + K logN=K (this analysis is presented by Livnat et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>) for isosurface queries, once the octree has been built.</p><p>Itoh and Kayamada <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> propose a method based on identifying a collection of seed cells from which isosurfaces can be propagated by performing local search. Basically, once the seed cells have been identified, they claim to have a nearly ON 2=3 expected performance. (Livnat et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> estimate the worst-case running time to be ON, and the memory overhead to be quite high.) More re-cently, Bajaj et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> propose another contour propagation scheme, with expected performance of OK. Livnat et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> propose NOISE, an O p N + K-time algorithm. Shen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> also propose nearly optimal isosurface extraction methods.</p><p>The first optimal isosurface extraction algorithm was given by Cignoni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, based on the use of an interval tree to store the intervals induced by the dataset cells. After an ON log N-time preprocessing, queries can be performed in optimal Olog N + K time. This achieves tight theoretical bounds.</p><p>All the techniques mentioned above are main-memory algorithms, requiring the entire dataset to fit in the main memory (except for Marching Cubes). There is also a class of external-memory algorithms (not particularly for isosurface extraction; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> for references). For large-scale applications in which the problem is too large to fit in the main memory, Input/Output (I/O) communication between fast main memory and slower external memory (disk) becomes a major bottleneck. Algorithms specifically designed to reduce the I/O bottleneck are called external-memory algorithms. Although most of the results in this area of research are theoretical, the experiments of Chiang <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> and of Vengroff and Vitter <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> on some of these techniques show that they result in significant improvements over traditional algorithms in practice. Also, Teller et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> describe a system to compute radiosity solutions for polygonal environments larger than main memory, and Funkhouser et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> present prefetching techniques for interactive walk-throughs in architectural virtual environments whose models are larger than main memory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Our Results</head><p>We give I/O-optimal techniques for isosurface extraction, by a novel use of the external-memory interval tree of Arge and Vitter <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>Following the ideas of Cignoni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, we produce for each cell an interval min; max , where min and max are the minimum and maximum values among the scalar values of the vertices of the cell. Then given an isovalue q, the active cells are exactly those cells whose intervals contain q (i.e., min q max). This reduces the searching of active cells to the following problem called stabbing queries: given a set of intervals and a query point q in 1D, find all intervals containing q. We then use the external-memory interval tree of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> to solve the stabbing queries in an I/O-optimal way. We propose a new preprocessing algorithm for the interval tree which is I/O-optimal. We give the first implementation of the I/O-optimal interval tree, and also implement our methods as an I/O filter for Vtk's isosurface extraction routine <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> for the case of unstructured grids. Our experiments show that the search phase, originally the bottleneck of isosurface extraction, now needs less time than the generation phase, i.e., the search phase is not a bottleneck any more! The advantages of our techniques can be summarized as follows.</p><p>Our query algorithm is output-sensitive and improves the performance of isosurface extraction by speeding up the search phase so that it is no longer a bottleneck, and yet by building the search structure in disk, our preprocessing is performed once and for all, as opposed to other output-sensitive techniques which require preprocessing each time the process starts to run. Our search structure can be duplicated by just copying files, without ever running the preprocessing again.</p><p>Our query algorithm only needs two blocks of main memory, and only brings to main memory those K active cells, where K is usually ON 2=3 . Other techniques either have to visit the whole dataset during queries, or have to use a large amount of main memory to keep the entire dataset plus some additional search structure.</p><p>Our preprocessing algorithm needs only a fixed amount of main memory space, which can be parameterized. For datasets much larger than can fit into main memory, the running time is the same as performing a few external sortings, and is linear in the size of the datasets. Thus our preprocessing method is both efficient and predictable.</p><p>Our techniques have a wide range of applications. In addition to improving the performance of isosurface extraction, there are some other implications:</p><p>Datasets can be visualized very efficiently on workstations with just enough main memory to hold the isosurfaces themselves.</p><p>Datasets can be kept in remote file servers. Only the necessary parts are fetched during visualization, thus even at ethernet speeds, interactive isosurface extraction can be achieved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organization of the Paper</head><p>The rest of the paper is organized as follows. In Section 2, we present the I/O-optimal interval tree of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, and our novel preprocessing algorithm. Next we present in Section 3 the implementation details of our I/O filter for Vtk's isosurface extraction routine. In Section 4, we present the overall experimental performance of our methods, followed by conclusions in Section 5.</p><p>Because of limited space, our presentation is sometimes sketchy. We refer to the full paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> for full details and more complete references.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">I/O Optimal Interval Tree</head><p>As described in the previous section, we produce an interval I = min; max for each cell of the dataset, and use the I/O-optimal interval tree of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> to find the active cells of an isosurface by performing stabbing queries.</p><p>Since pointer references are very inefficient for disk accesses, we store the direct cell information together with the corresponding interval whenever that interval has to be stored in the interval tree. Thus each record of an interval includes the cell ID, the 3D coordinates and the scalar values of the vertices of the cell, and the left and right endpoints of the interval.</p><p>If the input dataset is given in the format providing direct cell information, then we can build the interval tree directly. Unfortunately, the datasets are often given in the format that contains indices to vertices. Thus we have to de-reference the indices before actually building the interval tree. We call this de-referencing process normalization. Using the technique of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, we can efficiently perform normalization as follows. We make one file (the vertex file) containing the direct information of the vertices (3D coordinates and scalar values), and another file (the cell file) of cell records with vertex indices. In the first pass, we externally sort the cell file by the indices (pointers) to the first vertex, so that the first group in the file contains cells whose first vertices are vertex 1, the second group contains cells whose first vertices are vertex 2, and so on. Then by scanning through the vertex file and the cell file simultaneously, we fill in the direct information of the first vertex of each cell in the cell file. In the next pass, we sort the cell file by the indices to the second vertices, and fill in the direct information of the second vertex of each cell in the same way. By repeating the process for each vertex of the cells, we obtain the direct information for each cell; this completes the normalization process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data Structure</head><p>We first review the data structure of the I/O-optimal interval tree <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Each node of the tree (for readers not acquainted with interval trees, see <ref type="bibr">[13, pages 360-361]</ref>) is one block in disk, capable of holding OB items. The branching factor, b, is the maximum number of children an internal node can have. We let b = O p B; the reason will be clear later. Let S be the set of all N intervals, and E be the set of 2N endpoints of the intervals in S. We denote by n = djEj=Be the number of blocks in E. First, we sort E from left to right in the order of increasing values, assuming that all endpoints have distinct values (we use cell ID to break ties). Set E is now fixed and will be used to define slab boundaries for each internal node of the tree. The interval tree on E and S is defined recursively as follows. The root u is associated with the entire range of E and with all intervals S. If S has no more than B intervals, then node u is a leaf storing all intervals of S. Otherwise u is an internal node. We then evenly divide E into b slabs E0; E 1 ; ; E b , 1 , each containing the same number dn=be blocks of endpoints in E. The b,1 slab boundaries are the first endpoints of slabs E1; ; E b , 1 . We store the endpoint values of the slab boundaries in node u as keys. We use these keys to consider each interval I 2 S (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). If both endpoints of I lie inside the same slab, say the i-th slab Ei, then I belongs to the i-th child ui of node u, and is put into the interval set Si S (e.g., in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>, interval I0 is put in S0). Otherwise (the two endpoints of I belong to different slabs, i.e., I crosses one or more slab boundaries), I belongs to node u. The intervals belonging to node u will be stored in the secondary lists of u pointed by pointers in u. We adopt the convention that if an endpoint of I is exactly the slab boundary separating slabs Ei,1 and Ei, that endpoint is considered as lying in slab Ei; this is consistent with our choice of slab boundaries. We associate each child ui of node u with the range of slab Ei and with the interval set Si, and define the subtree rooted at ui recursively as the interval tree on range Ei and intervals Si. Notice that slab Ei is pre-defined when E is given (dn=be blocks of endpoints in the first level, dn=b 2 e blocks of endpoints in the next level, and so on), but set Si has to be decided by scanning through the intervals in S and distribute them appropriately according to the slab boundaries. Observe that Si may be empty, in which case child ui of u is null (it is also possible that all children of u are null).</p><p>For each internal node u, we use three kinds of secondary structures to store the intervals belonging to u: the left, right and multi lists, described as follows.</p><p>There are b left lists, each corresponding to a slab of u. For each i, the i-th left list stores the intervals belonging to u whose left endpoints lie in the i-th slab Ei. Each list is sorted by increasing left endpoint values of the intervals (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>).</p><p>There are also b right lists, each corresponding to a slab of u. For each i, the i-th right list stores the intervals belonging to u whose right endpoints lie in the i-th slab Ei. Each list is sorted by decreasing right endpoint values of the intervals (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>).</p><p>There are b , 1b , 2=2 multi lists, each corresponding to a multi-slab of u. A multi-slab i; j , 0 i j b , 1, is defined to be the union of slabs Ei; ; E j . The multi list for multi-slab i; j stores all intervals of u that completely span Ei E j , i.e., all intervals of u whose left endpoints lie in slab Ei,1 and whose right endpoints lie in slab Ej+1. Since the multi lists 0; k for any k and the multi lists `; b,1 for any l are always empty by the definition, we only care about multi-slabs 1; 1 ; ; 1; b , 2 ; 2; 2 ; ; 2; b , 2 ; ; i; i ; ; i; b , 2 ; ; b , 2 ; b , 2 . Thus there are b , 1b , 2=2 such multi-slabs and the associated multi lists (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 1</ref>). boundary is an interval endpoint, and each slab Ei has same blocks of endpoints). Consider only the intervals shown here and node u.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">E 0 E 1 E 2 E 3 E 4 S 0 S 1 S 2 S 3 S 4 I 4 I 5 I 0 I 1 I 2 I 3 I 6 I 7 u 0 u 1 u 2 u 3 u 4 u slabs: multi-slabs: [1, 1] [1, 2] [1, 3] [2, 2] [2, 3] [3, 3] E 0 ~E 4</formula><p>The interval sets for its children are: S0 = fI0g, and S1 = S2 = S3 = S4 = ;. Its left lists are: left0 = fI2; I 7 g , left1 = fI1; I 3 g , left2 = fI4; I 5 ; I 6 g , and left3 = left4 = ; (the intervals in each list are sorted in the order as they appear Now let us analyze some properties of the interval tree. First, the height of the tree is Olog b N = O log B N, because each time we go down one level of the tree, the range of slab E associated with a node is reduced by a factor of b. Secondly, each interval belongs to exactly one node, and is stored at most three times: if it belongs to a leaf node, then it is stored only once; if it belongs to an internal node, then it is stored once in some left list, once in some right list, and possibly one more time in some multi list. Therefore we need roughly ON=Bdisk blocks to store the entire data structure. In theory, more blocks may be needed, and the optimal space of ON=Bblocks is achieved by using the corner structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>; see <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> for more details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Query Algorithm</head><p>We now review the query algorithm given in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Given query value q, we perform the following recursive process starting from the root of the interval tree. For the current node u that we want to visit, we read it from disk (recall that u is a disk block). If u is a leaf, we just check the OB intervals stored in u, report those intervals containing q and stop. If u is an internal node, we perform a binary search for q on the keys (slab boundaries) stored in u to identify the slab Ei containing q. Now we want to report all intervals belonging to u that contain q. We check the i-th left list lefti of u, scan through the list from beginning and report intervals, until we reach some interval whose left endpoint value is larger than q.</p><p>Recall that each left list is sorted by increasing left endpoint values of the intervals. Similarly, we check the right list rightiof u, scan through the list from beginning and report intervals, until we reach some interval whose right endpoint value is smaller than q.</p><p>Again, recall that each right list is sorted by decreasing right endpoint values of the intervals. Also, all intervals that span slab Ei must contain q and thus must be reported. We carry out this task by reporting all intervals in multi lists multi `; r , where 1 ` i and i r b,2. Finally, we visit the i-th child ui of node u, and recursively perform the same process on ui (if child ui is null then we stop).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Preprocessing Algorithm</head><p>We give a new preprocessing algorithm achieving nearly optimal</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">O N B log B N I/O's.</formula><p>It is based on a paradigm we call scan and distribute, inspired by the distribution sweep I/O technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</p><p>The algorithm can also be made I/O-optimal <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>The algorithm follows the definition of the interval tree given in Section 2.1. We start by duplicating each interval record, one with the left endpoint as the key and the other with the right endpoint as the key. We then sort (using external sorting) all these endpoints by the keys from left to right in increasing order (breaking ties by cell ID's). This gives the sorted set of endpoints E. This set is used to decide the range and the slab boundaries of the current node throughout the process. Again, we use n to denote the number of blocks in E. The set S of intervals sorted by increasing left endpoint values is initially created by copying and filtering out the right endpoints from E. Now we use a recursive procedure to build the tree, as follows. The root u of the tree is associated with the entire range of E and the entire interval set S. If S has no more than B intervals, then we make node u a leaf, store those intervals in u, and stop. Otherwise, we make u an internal node. We extract the b , 1</p><p>endpoints from E as slab boundaries which evenly divide E into b slabs E0; ; E b , 1 of dn=be blocks each. We then scan through the set S; for each interval I being examined, we perform a binary search for each of the two endpoints on the slab boundaries, and decide whether I lies entirely inside some slab Ei (in which case we have to put I into set Si), or crosses some slab boundary (in which case I belongs to node u and we want to put I into appropriate left, right and/or multi lists). We use a temporary list for each Si, and similarly for each list lefti, righti, and multi `; r of node u. Each temporary list is kept in consecutive blocks in disk, and is also associated with one buffer, which is of one disk block size, in the main memory. Notice that we only need OB blocks in the main memory for the buffers. In our actual implementation, we only need 4b buffers instead; see Section 3. Each time we want to put the current interval I into some set Si or some left/right/multi list, we just insert I into the buffer of the corresponding temporary list. When the buffer is full, we write the buffer out to the corresponding temporary list in disk, and the buffer is again available for use. After scanning through the entire interval set S, each interval in S is distributed to its appropriate temporary lists. Observe that originally S is sorted by increasing left endpoint values of the intervals, thus after this scan and distribute process is done, each temporary list is automatically sorted by increasing left endpoint values as well. We then sort (using external sorting) each right list by decreasing right endpoint values of the intervals, so that all temporary lists are in the desired sorted orders. After this, we copy each temporary list back to its corresponding list in disk, set up appropriate information (e.g., the number of intervals and a pointer to the starting position in disk of each list, etc) in node u. Finally, we write node u to the disk, and recursively perform the same procedure on each child ui (of node u) with the range of slab Ei and interval set Si (if Si is empty then node ui is null).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Implementation</head><p>We implemented our methods as an I/O filter for Vtk's isosurface extraction for the case of unstructured grids. First, ioBuild is used to preprocess the dataset to build the interval tree, and then ioQuery is used to report the active cells of a given isosurface. We first describe how to implement the interval tree, and then describe the interface with Vtk.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">External Memory Interval Tree</head><p>We describe the organization of the data structure. We use files dataset.intTree, dataset.left, dataset.right, and dataset.multi to hold the interval tree nodes, all left lists, all right lists, and all multi lists, respectively. Every time we create a new tree node, we allocate the next available block from file dataset.intTree and store the node there. <ref type="figure">(</ref> to speed up the query: when we need to check the query point q against this left list, if q is smaller than the value stored here, then no interval in the list will contain q and thus we can avoid reading any block of the list. The information about each right list are similar. The information about each multi list are also similar, but do not contain item (c) since during queries a multi list is reported as a whole with no checking necessary. From the size of each data type of each field and the fact that a node holds at most 4,096 bytes, we can compute the branching factor b of the tree, which in our case is 29 (observe that b p B here). For the simplicity of the coding, we currently do not implement the corner structure.</p><p>There are some interesting issues involved in the implementation of the preprocessing algorithm. Recall from Section 2.3 that during the scan and distribute process for the current node u (associated with endpoint set E and interval set S), we use a temporary list for each of the b left lists, b right lists, b , 1b , 2=2 multi lists, and b interval sets Si. A first attempt would be to use a file for each temporary list. This would require us to open 3b+ b , 1b,2=2</p><p>files at the same time, since no temporary list is completed until one pass of the scan and distribute process is done. Unfortunately, there is a hard limit imposed by the operating system on the number of files a process can open simultaneously (given by the system parameter OPEN MAX; older version of Unix allowed up to 20 open files and this was increased to 64 by many systems).</p><p>Our solution to this problem is to use a scratch file as a collection of the temporary lists of the same type. For example, we use file dataset.left temp to collect all temporary lists for the b left lists. Observe that all intervals belonging to lefti (and thus belonging to the temporary list of lefti) must have their left endpoints lying in slab Ei, but there are no more than dn=be blocks of endpoints in slab Ei, where n is the number of blocks in E. Therefore, each temporary list has at most dn=be blocks of intervals, and thus we let the i-th temporary list start from block i d n=be of file dataset.left temp, for i = 0 ; ; b , 1 . Notice that the size of file dataset.left temp is no more than the size of E. After the construction of all temporary left lists is complete, we copy them to the file dataset.left, and the scratch file dataset.left temp is again available for use in the next recursion. We handle the temporary lists for the right lists in the same way, except that before copying to file dataset.right, each temporary right list has to be sorted first (in the order of decreasing right endpoint values). In the same way, each interval set</p><p>Si for child ui of node u has at most dn=be blocks. We scan the entire file for S (file dataset.intvls) and distribute the intervals to the appropriate temporary lists for each Si The number of buffers in main memory needed for constructing the multi lists is also reduced from b , 1b , 2=2 to b. In summary, to construct the left, right, and multi lists and the interval sets Si for children, we use four scratch files, each with size n blocks, and also 4b blocks of main memory as buffers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Handling Degeneracies</head><p>The issue of degenerate cases arises when the endpoint values of the intervals are not distinct. We use cell ID's to break ties. We also adopt the convention that if an endpoint is exactly the slab boundary separating slabs Ei,1 and Ei, then this endpoint is considered as lying in slab Ei; this is consistent with our choice of slab boundaries (see Section 2.1). In the internal node of the interval tree, we only store the endpoint values as slab boundaries (keys), without storing the corresponding cell ID's. During query operations, if the query value q has the same value as some slab boundary, we consider all slabs that can possibly contain the value of q, and perform the query operation on all such slabs accordingly. This ensures that all answers are correctly reported. Notice that if several slab boundaries have the same value as that of q, we only need to go to the two children respectively to the left of the leftmost such slab boundary and to the right of the rightmost such boundary. This is because </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Interfacing with Vtk</head><p>Extracting isosurfaces with ioBuild and ioQuery is relatively simple. The input to ioBuild is a Toff file , which unfortunately contains indices to vertices. Therefore, the first part of ioBuild is to normalize the Toff file, de-referencing these indices as described in the beginning of Section 2, before the actual construction of the interval tree can begin. Since there are four vertices in each cell (tetrahedron), four passes over the input are necessary. If the files are already given in de-referenced form, the first part of ioBuild would not be necessary.</p><p>A full isosurface extraction pipeline should include several steps in addition to finding active cells. In particular, (1) intersection points and triangles have to be computed; (2) triangles need to be decimated <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>; and (3) triangle strips have to be generated. Steps (1)-(3) can be carried out by the existing code in Vtk <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, which makes it a perfect match for a proof-of-concept implementation of our I/O techniques. Our current code only implements the actual triangle generation. Using Vtk's simple pipeline scheme, it is a simple programming exercise to further process the triangulation, decimate it and create the strips.</p><p>The ioQuery code is implemented by linking our I/O querying code with Vtk's isosurface generation, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2</ref>. Given an isovalue, (1) all the active cells are collected from disk; (2) a vtkUnstructuredGrid is generated; (3) the isosurface is extracted with vtkContourFilter; and (4) the isosurface is saved in a file with vtkPolyMapper. At this point, memory is deallocated. If multiple isosurfaces are needed, this process is repeated. Note that this approach requires double buffering of the active cells during the creation of the vtkUnstructuredGrid data structure. A more sophisticated implementation would be to incorporate the functionality of ioQuery inside the Vtk data structures and make the methods I/O aware. This should be possible due to Vtk's pipeline evaluation scheme (see Chapter 4 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Experimental Results</head><p>In this section we present experimental results of actively using our I/O filtering techniques on real datasets. We have run our experiments on four different datasets shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 2</ref>. All of these datasets are tetrahedralized versions of well-known datasets. Our primary interest in this initial implementation was to quantify the A Toff file is analogous to the Geomview "off" file. It has the number of vertices and tetrahedra, followed by a list of the vertices and a list of the tetrahedra, each of which is specified using the vertex locations in the file as an index. I/O overhead, if any, both in terms of memory and time, and to compare with Vtk's native isosurface implementation.</p><p>Our benchmark machine was an off-the-shelf PC: a Pentium Pro, 200MHz with 128M of RAM, and two EIDE Western Digital 2.5Gb hard disk (5400 RPM, 128Kb cache, 12ms seek time). Each disk block size is 4,096 bytes. We ran Linux (kernel 2.0.27) on this machine. One interesting property of Linux is that it allows during booting the specification of the exact amount of main memory to use. This allows us to fake for the isosurface code a given amount of main memory to use (after this memory is completely used, the system will start to use disk swap space and have page faults).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preprocessing with ioBuild</head><p>Using ioBuild is a fully automatic process. The only argument is the name of the input file containing tetrahedral cells. During its execution, ioBuild creates and writes multiple files, but in the end only the four files are kept. In analyzing the behavior of external memory algorithms, it is very important to take into account the amount of main memory used by the algorithm. In general, the more memory it is given, the less I/O operations it needs. For instance, when sorting a file that can be kept entirely in main memory, we just need to touch the file twice, once for reading, and once for writing. As the available main memory is smaller, we need to perform more I/O operations. The scalability of an external memory algorithm is best seen when the main memory is smaller than the dataset. In order to simulate this, we only allow ioBuild to allocate a 1024K blocks (4 Mb) of RAM. This is a parameter in the program.</p><p>The first time we ran ioBuild, it just seemed to be too fast for the number of I/O reads and writes ioBuild was issuing. It turned out that the operating system was able to optimize (by caching) a lot of those I/O requests, and the CPU was running at nearly 95% of usage. In order to avoid these side effects of the operating system, we lowered the amount of main memory of our system by starting Linux with a "linux mem=16M" command line at kernel boot time. Basically, about 14M of main memory can actually be used by applications, and during the time of our benchmarks, our system was fully functional (i.e., it was not in single user mode; all system-related daemons were active). That is, we ran our experiments in a "normal" environment on the datasets with size equal to or larger than the main memory. (Remember that only 4M of RAM were actually used by ioBuild.) The actual CPU usage percentage during this preprocessing was in the range of low teens.</p><p>In <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> we show all relevant experimental data obtained from running ioBuild with a 16M/4M configuration. Recall from Section 3.2 that the first part of ioBuild is to normalize (i.e., dereference) the input Toff file (which in turn amounts to several external sorting operations), and the second part is to actually construct the interval tree. The basic operations of ioBuild are hence external sorting and scanning (the scan and distribute process described in Section 2.3). It should be clear from <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> that the overall running time of ioBuild is the same as performing external sorting several times, and is linear in the size of the datasets. Therefore ioBuild is both efficient and predictable -for a given system configuration, one can estimate (or extrapolate) the overall running time based on a linear behavior. This preprocessing can be made much faster by using faster disks, and optimized to use more memory. For instance, in an SGI Power Challenge, it only takes 10 minutes to preprocess the Delta Wing dataset.</p><p>The interval tree data structure requires more disk space than the normalized tetrahedron file, which is also larger than the original Toff file. The average increase in disk space is about 7.7 times, and the maximum increase is 8.5 times (see <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>). During the preprocessing time, scratch files used for computation are necessary. In general, one needs about 16 times the amount of disk space of  <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>: Statistics for the running of ioBuild in a machine with 16M of main memory and 4M of buffer memory, for the datasets in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 2</ref>. The first four values are the sizes of the four files kept after the preprocessing. "Total size" is the total amount of disk space used after preprocessing. "Normalization" is the time used to convert the input Toff file to a normalized (i.e., de-referenced) file. "Tree Construction" is the actual time used to create the interval tree data files from the normalized file. "Total Time" is the overall running time of the whole preprocessing. "Page Ins" and "Outs" are the numbers of disk block reads and writes requested to the operating system.</p><p>the original Toff file to generate the interval tree. Notice, however, that this extra disk space for scratch files is needed once and for all, since after running ioBuild once to build the interval tree files, these tree files can be duplicated by just copying, without ever running ioBuild again. Because it might be necessary to use as much as 16 times the original disk space for preprocessing a given dataset, we believe that in large production environments, large scratch areas should be available for preprocessing. We see this as a minor cost for the overall savings in both time and space later on. One should also note, that disk prices are on the order of 35-40 times lower than main memory prices. So the overall cost of a four to eight factor increase in disk space overhead is negligible when compared to a twofold increase in main memory costs. (In <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, a twofold main memory overhead is reported for improved, although not optimal, isosurface generation times.) Again, we would like to stress the overall speed advantage in isosurface extraction time our technique provides, since it only performs the preprocessing once.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Isosurface Extraction with ioQuery</head><p>The true performance of an isosurface extraction technique is the actual time it takes to generate a given isosurface. As explained before, our code is coupled with Vtk (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2</ref>). Basically, during isosurface extraction, we find the active cells, and use Vtk's isosurface capabilities to actually generate the isosurface. In the following, we use ioQuery to denote the entire isosurface extraction code.</p><p>We ran three batteries of tests, each with different amount of core memory (128M, 64M, and 32M). Each test consists of calculating 10 isosurfaces with isovalues in the range of the scalar values of each dataset, by using our code and also the Vtk-only isosurface code (denoted by vtkiso). We did not run X-windows during the isosurface extraction time, and the output of vtkPolyMapper was saved in a file instead. Some representative isosurfaces are shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>.</p><p>We found that our approach has several advantages. Initially  we thought that our method would only be useful for really large datasets, but our experiments show that even for smaller datasets the I/O querying time is negligible when compared to the overall isosurface extraction time. Another advantage is that, for large isosurfaces, the memory requirements of the triangle mesh is very large. If the entire volume dataset is kept in the main memory, then even if the dataset itself can fit, adding the triangle mesh might make the main memory not large enough and cause system swap. The fact that ioQuery only uses two blocks of main memory during active-cell searching makes our approach very favorable: the main memory space can be saved for the triangle mesh of the isosurface, so that system swap is much less likely to occur.</p><p>We summarize in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref> the total running times for the extraction of the 10 isosurfaces using ioQuery and vtkiso with different amount of main memory. It should be clear that for larger datasets (e.g., Post and Delta) ioQuery is much faster, and the margins increase significantly as the main memory size goes down.</p><p>Figures 3 to 5 summarize detailed benchmarks, with left columns presenting the performance of running ioQuery, and the right columns for the performance of vtkiso. For each isosurface calculated using ioQuery, we break the time into four categories:</p><p>(1) I/O time (shown in red) -This is the time to identify and bring in from disk the active cells of the isosurface in question.</p><p>(2) Copy Time (shown in yellow) -In order to use Vtk's isosurface capabilities, we need to generate a vtkUnstructuredGrid object that contains the active cells we just obtained. We refer to the time for this process as "Copy Time".</p><p>(3) Isosurface (shown in blue) -This is the time for Vtk's isosurface code to actually generate the isosurface from the active cells.</p><p>(4) File Output (shown in green) -In the end we write to disk a file containing the actual isosurface in Vtk format.</p><p>As for the performance of vtkiso, only items (3) and (4) are shown in <ref type="figure">Figs. 3-5</ref>, and there are two additional costs not shown: the reading of the dataset, and the generation of the vtkUnstruc-turedGrid. These two operations are performed only once when vtkiso starts to run (i.e., at the beginning of each batch of the 10 isosurface extractions), and thus it is not possible to spread the costs over each individual isosurface extraction. Therefore we do not show them in <ref type="figure">Figs. 3-5</ref>, but only show the sum of the two costs as vtkiso I/O in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>. It is very interesting to see (from <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>) that the vtkiso I/O entries for Post in 64M and 32M, and for Delta in all three memory sizes, are all much larger than the corresponding entries of ioQuery. This means that before the time vtkiso finishes reading the dataset and generating a vtkUnstructuredGrid, ioQuery already finished calculating all 10 isosurfaces! Regarding Figs. 3-5, we make the following observations:</p><p>For ioQuery, in general the I/O time is only a small fraction of the overall isosurface extraction time (see the left columns of <ref type="figure">Figs. 3-5</ref>). In particular, for most of the time (1) is smaller  <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>: Overall running times for the extraction of the 10 isosurfaces using ioQuery and vtkiso with different amount of main memory. These include all the time to read the datasets and write the isosurfaces to files. vtkiso I/O is the fractional amount of time of vtkiso for reading the dataset and generating a vtkUn-structuredGrid.</p><p>than <ref type="formula">3</ref>, especially as the datasets get larger. This means that the active-cell searching process is not a bottleneck any more; the effect is even more significant for larger datasets. One can see the output-sensitive behavior by noting that when small isosurfaces (or no isosurfaces) are generated, ioQuery takes negligible time.</p><p>For ioQuery, the I/O times almost do not change with the amount of main memory (see the left columns of <ref type="figure">Figs. 3-5</ref>). This shows that our technique for finding active cells only needs a very small amount of main memory, and the performance is independent of the size of the main memory available.</p><p>For ioQuery, the overall running times almost do not change with the amount of main memory (see the left columns of <ref type="figure">Figs. 3-5</ref>). We expect that the overall running times will increase only when Vtk needs more main memory than available to store the actual polygons generated (and thus causes page faults). The fact that our technique only needs a very small amount of main memory to find active cells enables us to visualize much larger isosurfaces very efficiently.</p><p>Even without taking into account the two costs of vtkiso (reading the dataset and generating a vtkUnstructuredGrid), comparing the times of vtkiso and of ioQuery as shown in Figs. 3-5 (which is thus not fair for ioQuery), ioQuery is already much faster for large datasets. For example, for the 8th isosurface of Delta Wing using 128M of RAM, it takes ioQuery 11 seconds, while vtkiso takes about 34 seconds. As for small datasets, the overhead of ioQuery is negligible. But the advantages really start to show as the main memory size goes down. For instance, with 64M, for the 8th isosurface of Delta Wing, it takes ioQuery the same 11 seconds, while vtkiso takes 300 seconds!</p><p>We have presented an I/O-optimal technique for isosurface extraction from volumetric data. Our method is to preprocess the dataset to build an I/O-optimal interval tree in disk, and then to extract isosurfaces by querying the interval tree for active cells and generating the isosurfaces from those cells. We discussed the theoretical aspects of the method. It is I/O-optimal in space, query, and preprocessing. We also established its practical efficiency through experimental results, based on our implementation of an I/O filter for Vtk's isosurface extraction for the case of unstructured grids. We show that the time for searching active cells is less than the time for generating the isosurfaces from active cells, and this search time is independent of the main memory available. Also, with the interval tree built in disk, there is no need to load the entire dataset into main memory. In addition, the preprocessing is performed once and for all; its running time is the same as running external sorting a few times, and is linear in the size of the datasets. All these features make our technique especially suitable for use with very large datasets, or when there is only a small amount of main memory. In fact, even for smaller datasets with enough main memory, our method introduces only a negligible overhead.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>A schematic example of the I/O-optimal interval tree for branching factor b = 5 . Note that this is not a complete example and some intervals are not shown (in a complete example, each slab</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The root of the tree always starts from position 0 of file dataset.intTree.) Similarly, every time we create a new left (resp. right/multi) list, we allocate the next available consecutive blocks just enough to hold the list, from file dataset.left (resp. dataset.right/dataset.multi) and store the list there. Notice that we always allocate disk space of size an integral number of blocks. Each block in file dataset.left, dataset.right and dataset.multi stores up to B intervals. Each interval contains a cell ID, four vertices of the cell (x-, y-, zvalues and the scalar value of each vertex), and the left and right endpoints of the interval associated with the cell, which are the min and max values of the four scalar values. In our case with one disk block being 4,096 bytes, a block can store up to 53 intervals, i.e., B = 5 3 . Now we describe the layout of the interval tree nodes, each of size one disk block. It has a flag to indicate whether it is a leaf or an internal node. If it is a leaf, the rest of the node contains the following: (1) number ( B) of intervals stored in the node, and (2) actual intervals stored. If it is an internal node, the rest of the node contains the following: (1) number ( b , 1) of keys (i.e., slab boundaries) stored, (2) the actual slab boundaries stored, (3) b pointers to the starting positions of the children nodes in file dataset.intTree (-1 if that child is null), (4) information about its b left lists, (5) information about its b right lists, and (6) information about its b , 1b , 2=2 multi lists. The information about each left list include: (a) a pointer to the starting position of the list in file dataset.left, (b) number of intervals in the list, and (c) the minimum left endpoint value among all intervals of the list (which is just the left endpoint value of the first interval in the list, according to the sorted order of the list). Item (c) is used</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(i.e., appropriate portions of the scratch file holding a collection of all temporary lists for each Si), and then copy the temporary lists back to the corresponding portions of file dataset.intvls. Now each set Si is just the portion of file dataset.intvls starting from block i d n=be with no more than dn=be blocks. Each set Si, together with slab Ei, are then used as input for the next level of recursion.Finally, consider the construction of the multi lists for the current node u. By the same argument, each list has at most dn=be blocks. Unfortunately, there are b ,1b,2=2 such lists. If we collected all temporary lists into a single scratch file by the above method, then this scratch file would have size nb blocks, which is definitely undesirable. To solve the problem, observe that multi i; j consists of all intervals with left endpoints in the same slab Ei,1. Therefore, we construct all multi lists multi i; j for a fixed i from the left list lefti , 1 (again by a scan and distribute process), and repeat the process b , 2 times for all possible values of i. Then during each iteration, there are at most b multi lists being constructed, and thus our scratch file only needs n blocks of space.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Isosurface extraction phase. Given the four files of the interval tree and an isovalue, ioQuery filters the dataset and passes to Vtk only those active cells of the isosurface. Several Vtk methods are used to generate the isosurface, in particular, vtkUnstructured-Grid, vtkContourFilter, and vtkPolyMapper. all other children in between can only contain intervals whose two endpoint values are the same (same as q); the corresponding cells of such intervals are thus lying in the interior of the isosurface and therefore are not interesting cells to be reported.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, and right4 = fI4; I 6 g (again the intervals in each list are sorted in the order as they appear). Its multi lists are: multi 1; 1 = fI2g, multi 1; 2 = fI7g, multi 1; 3 = multi 2; 2 = multi 2; 3 = ;, and multi 3; 3 = fI4; I 6 g .For each left, right, or multi list, we store the entire list in consecutive blocks in disk, and in node u we store a pointer to the starting position of the list in disk. Observe that there are b left and b right lists, and Ob 2 = O B multi lists. Thus we need to keep OB items of information in node u, which is one disk block capable of holding OB items. This explains why the branching factor b is taken as O</figDesc><table><row><cell>). Its right lists are: right0 = right1 = ;, right2 = fI1; I 2 ; I 3 g , right3 = fI5; I 7 g</cell></row></table><note>p B.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>A list of the datasets used for testing. After normalization, each cell is 64 bytes long (data is represented as floats).</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank Pat Crossno, Lichan Hong, Joseph Mitchell and Dino Pavlakos for useful criticism and help in this work. We thank Lars Arge and Jeff Vitter for useful comments about the presentation of their I/O-optimal interval tree, and Lars Arge for useful discussions on the preprocessing of the tree. The first author would also like to thank Roberto Tamassia for his constant support and encouragement. We thank the Computational Geometry Laboratory (J. Mitchell, Director) and the Center for Visual Computing (A. Kaufman, Director), for use of the computing resources. The Blunt Fin, the Liquid Oxygen Post, and the Delta Wing datasets are courtesy of NASA. The Combustion Chamber dataset is from Vtk <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. We thank W. Schroeder, K. Martin, and B. Lorensen for Vtk; the Geometry Center of the University of Minnesota for Geomview; and Linus Torvals, and the Linux community for Linux. Without these powerful tools, it would have been much harder to perform this work.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref><p>: Running times for extracting isosurfaces using ioQuery (left column) and vtkiso (right column) with 64M of main memory. Note that two costs of vtkiso are not shown.  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal interval management in external memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Arge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Foundations of Comp. Sci</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Foundations of Comp. Sci</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="560" to="569" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast isocontouring for improved interactivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bajaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pascucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Schikore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">1996 Volume Visualization Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experiments on the practical I/O efficiency of geometric algorithms: Distribution sweep vs. plane sweep</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-J</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Workshop on Algorithms and Data Structures</title>
		<meeting>Workshop on Algorithms and Data Structures</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="346" to="357" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">External-memory graph algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-J</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Goodrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Grove</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tamassia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vengroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM-SIAM Symp. on Discrete Algorithms</title>
		<meeting>ACM-SIAM Symp. on Discrete Algorithms</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="149" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">I/O Optimal Isosurface Extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y.-J</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.ams.sunysb.edu/˜yjc/iso.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Full paper available at</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal isosurface extraction from irregular volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cignoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Montani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Puppo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scopigno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Visualization Symposium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="38" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Database management for models larger than main memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Funkhouser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Teller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Séquin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Khorramabadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Interactive Walkthrough of Large Geometric Databases, Course Notes 32, SIGGRAPH &apos;95</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">External-Memory Computational Geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Goodrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-J</forename><surname>Tsay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vengroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Foundations of Comp. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="714" to="723" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Automatic isosurface propagation using an extrema graph and sorted boundary cell lists</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Itoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koyamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="327" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Indexing for data models with constraints and classes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kanellakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ramaswamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vengroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. ACM Symp. on Principles of Database Sys</title>
		<meeting>ACM Symp. on Principles of Database Sys</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="243" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A near optimal isosurface extraction algorithm using span space</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Livnat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="1996-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching cubes: A high resolution 3D surface construction algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH &apos;87 Proceedings)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Computational Geometry: An Introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Preparata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Shamos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Visualization Toolkit</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decimation of triangle meshes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zarge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH &apos;92 Proceedings)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="70" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isosurfacing in span space with utmost efficiency (ISSUE)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Livnat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sweeping simplices: A fast iso-surface extraction algorithm for unstructured grids</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="150" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Partitioning and ordering large radiosity computations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Teller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fowler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Funkhouser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanrahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Proceedings, Annual Conference Series</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGGRAPH, ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994-07" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="450" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">I/O-efficient scientific computation using TPIE</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vengroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. IEEE Symp. on Parallel and Distributed Computing</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Symp. on Parallel and Distributed Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Octrees for faster isosurface generation extended abstract</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wilhelms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Gelder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990-11" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Running times for extracting isosurfaces using ioQuery (left column) and vtkiso (right column) with 128M of main memory. Note that two costs of vtkiso are not shown</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Figure</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
