<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Brushing Techniques for Exploring Volume Datasets</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pak</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Wong</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Daniel Bergeron</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of New Hampshire</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Brushing Techniques for Exploring Volume Datasets</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We describe several visualization techniques based on the notion of multiresolution brushing to browse large three dimensional volume datasets. Our software is implemented using public domain libraries, and is designed to run on average-equipped desktop computers such as a Linux machine with 32M of memory. Empirically, our system allows scientists to obtain information from a large dataset with over 8.3 million numbers in interactive time. We show that very large scientific volume datasets can be accessed and utilized without expensive hardware and software.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Scientific volume visualization is currently gaining popularity but the cost of rendering has hindered the development of general applications for widespread use. Although visualization researchers have developed new techniques to improve the performance of the underlying hardware <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref> and software <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>, more powerful machines with ever improving calibrations are producing larger and larger volume datasets every day. For example, the Visible Woman dataset produced by the Visible Human Project 1 occupies over 480MB of memory in compressed format. We believe that the best way to make this precious information available to the research community at large is to provide low cost versions of the technology so that more researchers can use it.</p><p>We introduced the notion of multiresolution brushing to browse very large one dimensional multivariate data in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The idea is to query interesting portions of a very large dataset by brushing a coarse but authentic approximation <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> of the data before the fine resolution data is retrieved. Traditionally, volume visualization faces greater difficulty and requires more computational resources than its lower dimension counterparts. This paper studies several visualization techniques especially designed to tackle some of these problems. We have implemented a set of volume visualization tools using the vtk library <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> running on a 133 MHz Linux machine with 32MB of memory. These tools show that large scientific volume datasets can be accessed and utilized without expensive hardware.</p><p>Our immediate interest in scientific volume visualization comes from our multiresolution multidimensional data representation model <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, whose goal is to allow scientists with limited computation resources to browse and navigate large multidimensional datasets at multiple resolutions. Using our wavelet based adaptive hierarchy, we allow scientists to determine approximations within a multiresolution hierarchy by tracking the data losses of each resolution. All the low resolution approximations illustrated in this paper are chosen using our representation model described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. pcw@cs.unh.edu, http://www.cs.unh.edu/pcw y rdb@cs.unh.edu, http://www.cs.unh.edu/rdb z Department of Computer Science, Kingsbury Hall, University of New  isosurface renderings shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. The Time(s) column specifies the CPU time of the rendering process including input, march-ing, and isosurfacing. It is important to realize that the time data presented in this paper is not meant to measure the performance of the rendering process as implemented in the vtk library. Rather it is used to reflect the differences in performance between using the original large datasets and their coarse approximations. Figures 1c and 1d are two isosurface renderings (with different isovalues) of the same dataset. From <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>, we see that the processing time of <ref type="figure">Figure 1d</ref> is much shorter than that of Figure 1c because fewer isosurface triangles are generated using isovalue 200. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref>. This implies that we may substantially speed up the rendering process if we can reduce the number of data points. The idea was explored by Muraki <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> who introduced the use of wavelets to compress three dimensional volume datasets. This approach helps to improve the performance of many three dimensional rendering techniques including the marching cubes algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Three Dimensional Brushing</head><p>As with other kinds of very large datasets, scientists dealing with volume datasets are often only interested in analyzing subsets of the data. For example, a heart surgeon is more interested in the heart and the blood vessels than the bones and joints of a human body. If we only bring out the most important portions of a large dataset at the highest possible resolution and fill in the rest with coarser data, we can cut down the costs of data rendering substantially and still provide accurate visualization of the important information. This kind of data extraction process can be considered as a form of database query, called data brushing.</p><p>In the heart surgeon example, we in fact identified two important types of three dimensional data extractions: qualitative (X-ray density corresponding to the blood vessels) and spatial (the heart region). The latter can further be categorized into planar and volume. Simplified examples of these brushes are depicted in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 2</ref>. Since data brushing is an interactive process, we need to actually see the display of the dataset before we can brush it. Our next step is to provide a coarse but authentic approximation of a very large dataset to guide brushing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Authenticity of Wavelet Approximations</head><p>Muraki <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> used Mallat's multiresolution wavelet algorithm <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> to generate a series of fine to coarse approximations of a large volume dataset for rendering. Our goal is to find the coarsest authentic approximation within the series to support brushing. The prevailing method to determine the accuracy of a volume approximation is the human visual test. In the case of a large approximation hierarchy, this means a lengthy rendering of many volume approximations. Because of the potential hardware requirements, this procedure may not be possible for every scientist who wants to use the data. We describe an objective authenticity evaluation mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref> which provides heuristics to identify the authenticity of an approximation in a hierarchy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Translucent Coarse Data</head><p>After the interesting data subset of the approximation is identified, our next step is to put both the fine and the coarse data portions together into one visualization. An obvious option to combine two separate data subsets into one display is to make one of them translucent. This can be done by reducing the alpha values of the grey level density. Since a translucent body carries less visible information, it is a logical choice to apply the reduction to the coarser representation instead of the finer one. This translucent display gives a quick but less accurate overview of the data. It helps the viewer to understand the overall structure before finer (but much slower) local detail is brought to the display.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Brushing Techniques</head><p>We present realistic examples of 3D brushing using the CT head dataset depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. All the following illustrations are rendered using the marching cubes algorithm. Because of heavy memory paging, the full resolution head dataset (256 256 128) takes up to four hours of clock time to render on a 133 MHz Linux machine with 32MB of memory. By brushing only a partial subset of either the original data or a close approximation, we achieve interactive responses on the same platform.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Qualitative Brushing</head><p>A qualitative brushing process highlights interesting areas according to the values of the data. For example, if the most important part of the figure is the skull, only the data values corresponding to bones and joints are used to generate the isosurfaces. The rest of the data, mainly flesh and skin, can be obtained from a coarser version of the data. Examples of composite displays at different resolutions are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>.  the flesh and skin portion of the body. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3a</ref> shows the skin and bone structures at original resolutions. Our investigation in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> indicates that a Daubechies wavelet with two vanishing moments (i.e., D4) is a good wavelet candidate to decompose this volume dataset. The translucent skin regions of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figures 3b -3d</ref> are generated by a D4 wavelet at 32 3 resolution. For the bone display in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3b</ref> we apply D4 to the x and y dimensions of each image plane. The same wavelet decomposition is applied to the dataset twice in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3c</ref> for the bone display. And in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3d</ref>, we apply decomposition to the x and y dimensions twice, and to the z dimension once. <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 2</ref> gives the characteristics of the datasets (including approximations)  and the statistics of their renderings. The contribution of wavelets to the brushing process is obvious: <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3c</ref> takes less than 1% of the CPU time required to process <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3a</ref>. This time difference is translated to over six hours of clock time when using a 133 MHz Linux machine with 32MB of memory. The notion of qualitative brushing allows scientists to study particular isovalues of a volume dataset. It is, however, not the end of the story. The front side of the skull blocks all the internal structure behind it. We need more spatially oriented data brushes such as the ones described in the following sections to further study the local structure of the skull.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Planar Brushing</head><p>A planar brushing process highlights cross sections of a volume dataset. There are three kinds of planar brushing: axial, sagittal, and coronal. Each of them indicates a different orientation of a plane through a volume dataset. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> shows examples of the three planar brushings using the head dataset. Like the previous brushing examples, the translucent skin portion is generated by a D4 wavelet at 32 3 resolution. Since the data brush is only a slice of the dataset, we can afford to use the finer <ref type="figure">(Figures 4b, 4d</ref>, and 4f) or even the finest <ref type="figure">(Figures 4a, 4c</ref>, and 4e) data to show the local details of the human head. Since we have already shown the effects of reducing the skin resolution in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>, we do not display the full resolution rendering here. However, the processing time of using full resolution skin data are included in <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 3</ref> for comparison purposes. The results show that all renderings depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>,  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Volume Brushing</head><p>A volume brush is a high resolution sub-volume within a coarse volume dataset. Its goal is to brush smaller regions of data values which cannot be achieved solely by a qualitative or a planar brush. For example, the jaw bone area of the skull, which is totally blocked by the forehead in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>, can easily be seen in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. Once again, D4 is used to decompose the dataset in these figures. From <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 2</ref> in Section 3.1 we realize that it is still too expensive to render the brushed bone structure at full resolution. We can, however, render a coarse resolution bone structure and then retrieve portions of the finest data using a volume brush. The results in <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">Table 4</ref> show that it is possible to access the brushed data at its finest resolution in interactive time. The rendering as well as brushing together may take minutes, but we can access any portion of the very large head dataset at its finest resolution using only an ordinary desktop computer.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusion</head><p>The field of volume visualization research will benefit greatly from putting the data into as many researchers' hands as possible. The rendering hardware previously described in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref> costs more than many scientists can afford.</p><p>We have shown that with an average-equipped Linux machine, scientists can obtain precious information from the same large datasets described in visualization literature with interactive response. Many of the brushing ideas presented in this paper are conceptually simple and easy to implement. Our software implementation is based on a public domain visualization library, vtk, which is compiled using Mesa, the public domain version of OpenGL. Based on experience with our experiments, we believe the notion of brushing will play an important role in making very large scientific datasets available to the research community at large.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Three dimensional brushing of a volume dataset.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Qualitative brushing with multiple resolutions. See also Color Plate 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>visible 2 Problem and Solutions</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">Scientific volume data is large. An ordinary computed tomogra-phy (CT) dataset, which contains 128 slice images at 256 2 reso-</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">lution, occupies more than 16MB of memory (if 16-bit format is</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">used). Two other medical imaging procedures which require similar</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">memory are Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) and ultrasound</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">scanning. Figure 1 depicts four isosurface renderings of two CT</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(a) Head (isovalue 500)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(b) Head (isovalue 1500)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">(c) Engine (isovalue 50.5)</cell><cell cols="2">(d) Engine (isovalue 200.5)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Figure 1: Isosurface renderings of two CT datasets.</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">datasets using the marching cubes algorithm [2]. Unfortunately,</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">large amounts of data usually implies high computational costs. Ta-</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">ble 1 provides characteristics of our test datasets and statistics of the</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset</cell><cell>Resolution</cell><cell>Isovalue</cell><cell cols="2">of 4 Times(s) Figure</cell></row><row><cell>Head</cell><cell cols="4">256 256 128 500 482,302 278.08</cell><cell>1a</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1500</cell><cell>575,272</cell><cell>435.82</cell><cell>1b</cell></row><row><cell>Engine</cell><cell cols="4">256 256 128 50.5 622,196 534.55</cell><cell>1c</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>200.5</cell><cell>144,716</cell><cell>36.92</cell><cell>1d</cell></row></table><note>Hampshire, Durham, New Hampshire 03824, USA. Phone: (603) 862-3778. Fax: (603) 862-3493.1 http://www.nlm.nih.gov/research/</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Statistics of the isosurface renderings.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Statistics of the renderings with qualitative brushing.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Statistics of the renderings with planar brushing.</figDesc><table><row><cell>even with the finest data brushes, can be processed in interactive</cell></row><row><cell>time using a 133 MHz Linux machine.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Volume brushing of the jaw bone area. See also Color Plate 3.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">(a) Skin: 256 256 128</cell><cell cols="3">(b) Skin: 32 32 32</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Bone: 256 256 128</cell><cell cols="2">Bone: 256 256 128</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(c) Skin: 32 32 32</cell><cell cols="3">(d) Skin: 32 32 32</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Bone: 128 128 128</cell><cell cols="2">Bone: 64 64 128</cell></row><row><cell>Figure 5: Skin Resolution</cell><cell>Bone Resolution</cell><cell cols="3">of 4 Time(s) Figure</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">256 256 128 256 256 128 734,606 555.02 5a</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">32 32 32 256 256 128 123,520 27.32 5b</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">128 128 128 50,160</cell><cell>5.78</cell><cell>5c</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>64 64 128</cell><cell>23,404</cell><cell>1.75</cell><cell>5d</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Statistics of the renderings with volume brushing.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast Isocontouring For Improved Interactivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chandrajit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Valerio</forename><surname>Bajaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pascucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Schikore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization</title>
		<editor>Roger Crawfis and Charles Hansen</editor>
		<meeting>1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGGRAPH</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="46" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching Cubes: A High Resolution 3D Surface Construction Algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A theory for multiresolution signal decomposition: The wavelet representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Stephane</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mallat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="674" to="693" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application and rendering of volume data using wavelet transforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shigeru</forename><surname>Muraki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization &apos;92</title>
		<editor>Arie E. Kaufman and Gregory M. Nielson</editor>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;92<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="28" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume data and wavelet transforms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Shigeru</forename><surname>Muraki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cube-4 -A Scalable Architecture for Real-Time Volume Rendering</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hanspeter</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arie</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization</title>
		<editor>Roger Crawfis and Charles Hansen</editor>
		<meeting>1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGGRAPH</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="54" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Visualization Toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Will</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ken</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bill</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>Prentice Hall PTR</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New Jersey</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast Rendering of Irregular Grids</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Claudio</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">S B</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Arie</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization</title>
		<editor>Roger Crawfis and Charles Hansen</editor>
		<meeting>1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGGRAPH</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="22" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Adaptive Multiresolution Representation of Large Multidimensional Multivariate Scientific Datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997-05" />
			<pubPlace>Durham, New Hampshire</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Department of Computer Science, University of New Hampshire</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Authenticity analysis of wavelet approximations in visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R. Daniel</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bergeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<editor>Gregory M. Nielson and Deborah Silver</editor>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;95<address><addrLine>Los Alamitos, California</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="191" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiresolution Multidimensional Wavelet Brushing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chung</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R. Daniel</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Bergeron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<editor>Roni Yagel and Gregory M. Nielson</editor>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;96<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="148" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hardware Assisted Volume Rendering of Unstructured Grids by Incremental Slicing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Roni</forename><surname>Yagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Asish</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Po-Wen</forename><surname>Shih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Naeem</forename><surname>Shareef</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of 1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization</title>
		<editor>Roger Crawfis and Charles Hansen</editor>
		<meeting>1996 Symposium on Volume Visualization<address><addrLine>New York, NY</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM SIGGRAPH</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1996-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="62" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
