<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of Higher Order Singularities in Vector Fields</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Gerik</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hans</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kaiserslautern</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Heinz</forename><surname>Krüger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kaiserslautern</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Menzel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Kaiserslautern</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Arizona State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alyn</forename><surname>Rockwood</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Kaiserslautern</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of Higher Order Singularities in Vector Fields</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>We present an algorithm for the visualization of vector field topology based on Clifford algebra. It is the first method allowing the detection of higher order singularities. This is accomplished by first analysing the possible critical points and then choosing a suitable polynomial approximation because conventional methods based on piecewise linear or bilinear approximation do not allow higher order critical points and destroy the topology in such cases. The algorithm is still very fast because of using linear approximation outside the areas with several critical points.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Since Helman and Hesselink <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4]</ref> introduced the method of visualizing the topology of vector fields there has been a big interest in this kind of vector field visualization. But all methods so far begin with linear or bilinear interpolation of the grid data and start the analysis of the topology from there. This is a fast algorithm and one gets good results as long as the critical points are well separated and of simple type. But this is often not the case and then the linear or bilinear interpolation of the grid cells reduces artificially the possible topological structure as we will see, especially it makes the existence of critical points of index higher than 1 or lower than -1 impossible.</p><p>This drawback let us look for different ways to analyse the topology without losing the advantage of the high speed in the conventional methods because of the big datasets occuring from all kind of vector field simulations. The starting point is to look for areas where higher order critical points are possible and then use a polynomial approximation of sufficient degree in that area to allow critical points of maximum resp. minimum order. Outside these order singularity. The eddy motions in turbulent flows are also a source for higher order critical points. More examples can be found in all kind of fields with symmetry conditions preventing the critical points from splitting into several simple points. We do not know about papers dealing with the visualization of higher order singularities in vector fields, so this is the first article dealing with this problem. Clifford algebra was used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> to analyse the topology of planar polynomial vector fields which also gives the mathematical background in more depth than this paper. Here we show how this results can be used for the visualization of vector fields.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Higher order singularities</head><p>Since the very start of the visualization of vector field topology there has been said much about critical points in a vector field so a short remark should be enough for the simple case.</p><p>A critical point of a real 2D-vector field</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">v : R 2 ! R 2<label>(1)</label></formula><p>x; y 7 ! v1; v 2 is a point P 2 R 2 where the vector field vanishes. If the derivative</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">of v at P DP v : R 2 ! R 2 (2) x y 7 ! @ v 1 @ x @ v 1 @ y @ v 2 @ x @ v 2 @ y x y</formula><p>has full rank, one gets the simple critical points with their classification by the eigenvalues of DP v as in <ref type="bibr">[6, p.96]</ref>  If DP v has one or two zero eigenvalues, more complex topological patterns around P can appear. The most important invariant for the behavior in the neighborhood of the critical point is the Poincaré-Hopf index or winding number</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">indpv = ind v = 1 2 Z v1dv2 , v2dv1 v 2 1 + v 2 2<label>(3)</label></formula><p>where : S 1 ! R 2 is a closed curve making one turn in counterclockwise sense around P and containing no other zeros of the field <ref type="bibr">[1, p. 320</ref>]. In the figure 3 one can see the classical computation by the number of turns of the field around the critical point. Some typical examples for higher order critical points are given in figure 4.</p><p>Our main goal is now to get a visualization with critical points having the right index. This means that we need simple descriptions of critical points with a given index. An easy way is given by complex analysis as is shown for example in <ref type="bibr">[2, p. 53]</ref>. Let γ <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>: Index computation at a star. The field makes one counterclockwise turn along , so the star has index +1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>index +2</head><p>index +3 index -3 index -2 </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">E : C ! C (4) z 7 ! z k</formula><p>In real coordinates one gets the field</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">v : R 2 ! R 2 (5)</formula><p>x; y 7 ! Rez k ; I m z k For k = 1 ; 2 this produces the phaseportraits in figure 5 and it is quite easy to see that the vector field E has always only one zero at the origin with index ,k.</p><p>For a negative index one uses the complex conjugatez = x , iy</p><p>and defines </p><formula xml:id="formula_5">E : C ! C (6) E(z)=z E(z)=z 2</formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">v : R 2 ! R 2<label>(7)</label></formula><p>x; y 7 ! Re z k ; I m z k with the structure as shown in figure 6 for k = 1 ; 2 .</p><p>In case <ref type="formula">4</ref>  <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>: Complex description of critical points with negative index</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Clifford vectorfields</head><p>Clifford algebra extends the classical description of an euclidean nspace as a real n-dimensional vector space with scalar product to a real algebra. It simply gives a way to multiply vectors in arbitrary dimensions and get a geometric interpretation of the result <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>. In our 2D-case it also gives a way to describe the relation between real and complex numbers in a nice way.</p><p>For the euclidean plane we get a 4-dimensional R-algebra G2</p><p>with the basis f1; e 1 ; e 2 ; i = e 1 e 2 g as a real vector space. The multiplication is defined as associative, bilinear and by the equations </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">1ej = ej j = 1 ; 2 (8) ejej = 1 j = 1 ; 2 (9) i = e1e2 = ,e2e1<label>(10)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">Er = E z;ze1 (15)</formula><p>where E : C 2 ! C is a complex function of two complex variables.</p><p>Some examples may illustrate now the results of this mathematical transformation.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_9">Er = ĩ ze1</formula><p>In general one can easily show that for Er = az + bz + ce1  Er = z 2 e 1 and Er = z 2 e 1 A generalization of this examples is given by the following theorem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 1 Let</head><formula xml:id="formula_10">E : E 2 ! E 2 G2 be a Clifford vector field with Er = a n 1 Y j =1 z , zj k j n 1 +n 2 Y j=n 1 +1</formula><p>z,z j l j e 1 (17) and a; z1; : : : ; z n 2 C , n = n 1 + n 2 .</p><p>Then has E zeros at z1; : : : ; z n and nowhere else and the index of E at zj is lj , kj.</p><p>A proof will appear in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Detection of higher order singularities</head><p>The conventional method for analysing the vector field topology starts with a piecewise linear or bilinear approximation and analyses the topology of the approximated vector field. The problem is that one never gets critical points with an index bigger than 1 or smaller than -1. Consequently we use a different way. If the selection of the approximation determines the possible critical points one should first look at the data, analyse the possible indices and then approximate in a way allowing every possible index at the critical points inside an area.</p><p>The index integral (3) has the nice property to be additive on closed curves in the following sense : If one has a boundary curve C of an area and divides that area into two parts with boundaries C1; C 2 like figure 10, one has : We now assume for a moment that the vector field is linear along the edges. This allows to compute all indices of the triangles and by the consideration above along each closed sequence of grid edges.</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">indCv = indC 1 v + indC 2 v<label>(18)</label></formula><p>If we now have a higher order critical point P, we make a mistake in the triangle or cell containing P but it is not difficult to see that we are not making a mistake if we go around a big enough region containing the point. For index -2 we can get a situation like figure 12.</p><p>If we would use linear interpolation in each triangle we would get two saddles, but in reality there is only one critical point.</p><p>In a situation like figure 12 we put all the triangles there in a region and use an approximation of the type Er = b z , a 1 z , a2e1  There is obviously no problem with an arbitrary index in the light of section 3. After this step we check if the distance between some of the ai is below a wished quality limit and if so we assume a higher order singularity by setting these ai to their gravity point.</p><p>In this way we are able to detect higher order singularities as we will show in the examples in the next section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Examples</head><p>In the following examples we analyse vectorfields with known topology by our algorithm and compare it with the conventional piecewise linear method.</p><p>Our first example is just a monkey saddle. <ref type="figure">Figure 14</ref> shows the linear approximation of the field around a monkey saddle on a 20x20 quadratic grid and a zoom into the interesting part. Instead of one critical point of higher order one gets four critical points in that area. The results of our algorithm can be seen in figure 15.</p><p>After these easy example we are now going to look at two steps of two saddles approaching each other and merging into a monkey saddle together with four index 1 singularities with fixed locations. This kind of example was computed by the methods developed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> based on Clifford algebra by extending the technique given in section 3. We used again a quadratic 20x20 grid with ,1; 1 ,1; 1 as bounding box. The results can be seen in figure 16 to 19. The distance d between the two saddles was 0.0250 and 0.0000. The missing fourth separatrix of the right saddle in <ref type="figure">figure 18</ref> comes from the fact that the saddle is close to a triangle where the main direction of the flow goes down, so that the algorithm puts this backward computed separatrix over the one coming from the source in the upper right corner. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and the well known patterns of figure 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 4 :Figure 2 :</head><label>42</label><figDesc>Higher order critical points Simple critical points z = x + iy be a complex variable for identifying R 2 and C and look at the vector field in the complex plane given by</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Complex description of critical points with positive index z 7 !z k Again the field in real coordinates is</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Examples 1 ( 1 ) 7 ( 2 ) 7 ( 3 )</head><label>17273</label><figDesc>Er = ze1gives the saddle in figure Er = ze1gives the star in figure Er = ĩ ze1gives the circle in figure 8</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7: Er = ze1and Er = ze1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Examples 2 ( 4 )( 5 )</head><label>245</label><figDesc>b; c 2 C one gets all linear fields. For higher order critical points we meet our examples from section 2 again, but the roles of z andz have changed. Er = z 2 e 1 gives the monkey saddle in figure 9 Er = z 2 ze1gives a dipole as in figure 9</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 9:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>2 Figure 10 :Figure 11 :</head><label>21011</label><figDesc>A curve splitted into two If we take now an arbitrary triangulation or grid, we can compute the index of every curve along the grid edges by computing the index of each cell and adding the indices of the cells inside our curve as in figure 11. Summing the index in a region</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>- 1 - 1 Figure 12 :Figure 13 :</head><label>111213</label><figDesc>Indices around a monkey saddle with a; b; c 2 C for our visualization. The last section showed that this allows two saddles or a monkey saddle, so we can get the right index. In the case of a positive index as in figure 13 we use an approximation of the typeEr = b z,ã 1 z ,ã2e1 (20)to allow higher order critical points in this situation.+1+1 Indices around a dipole</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 14 :Figure 17 :Figure 19 :</head><label>141719</label><figDesc>Linear approx. around monkey saddleFigure 15: New approx. around monkey saddle Figure 16: Linear approx. for d=0.0250 New approx. for d=0.0250Figure 18: Linear approx. for d=0.0000 New approx. for d=0.0000</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>with k 1 we find 2k , 2 curves going to infinity or coming from there and all other curves start at the critical point and converge again at it, producing 2k ,2 elliptic sectors. An exact analysis of the integration curves around the zeros of the field<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6)</ref> shows that only 2k + 2 curves converge to the critical point. They separate the neighborhood into 2k + 2 hyperbolic sectors.It may be emphasized that elliptic sectors are impossible in the linear case and that z 2 gives the well-known dipole pattern. In sec-</figDesc><table><row><cell>(z)=z</cell><cell>E(z)=z 2</cell></row></table><note>tion 5 we show what happens to such a field if one uses standard linear approximations.E</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This work was partly made possible by financial support by the Deutscher Akademischer Auslandsdienst (DAAD). The first author got a "DAAD-Doktorandenstipendium aus Mitteln des zweiten Hochschulsonderprogramms" for his stay at the Arizona State University from Oct.96 to Jan.97. We like to thank for this support which helped to continue our cooperation.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Gewöhnliche Differentialgleichungen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Berlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<publisher>Deutscher Verlag der Wissenschaften</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear Oscillations, Dynamical Systems and Bifurcation of Vector Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guckenheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Helman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hesselink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Automated Analysis of Fluid Flow Topology. 3D Visualization and Display Technologies (Proc. SPIE)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989-01" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">1083</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="825" to="855" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation and Display of Vector Field Topology in Fluid Flow Data Sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Helman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hesselink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">New foundations for classical mechanics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hestenes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Differential Equations, Dynamical Systems and Linear Algebra</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Smale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An interesting class of polynomial vector fields. submitted to Mathematical Methods for Curves and Surfaces II</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>M. Daehlen, T. Lyche, L. L. Schumaker</editor>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
