<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Determination of Unknown Particle Charges in a Thunder Cloud Based Upon Detected Electric Field Vectors</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dan</forename><surname>Drake</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Mississippi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Mississippi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Larry</forename><surname>Smithmier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Mississippi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Penny</forename><surname>Rheingans</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Mississippi</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Determination of Unknown Particle Charges in a Thunder Cloud Based Upon Detected Electric Field Vectors</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Climatological data about thunderstorms is traditionally collected by balloons or planes traveling through the storm along straight tracts. Such data lends itself to simple 2D representations. The data described here was gathered by a sail plane spiraling in an updraft within a thundercloud. The more complex organization of data samples demands more complex representation methods. This paper describes a system developed using vtk to explore such data. The data consists of several scalar values and a set of vector values associated with positional data on the measuring devices. The goal of this visualization is to explore the location of point charges suggested by the electro magnetic field vectors and determine if any correlation exists between the point charge location and standard cloud microstructure scalar measurements such as temperature. There are several problems associated with visualizing this rather unique set of data. They stem from the fact that the data is a sparse spiraling sample of scalars and vectors. The system allows the track of the plane to be displayed as a line, a tube, or a ribbon; scalar values can be displayed as transparent isosurfaces; the vector data as an arrow plot along that track, given a color that is constant, based on orientation, or related to the value of a scalar. Any combination of methods can be used to display the data. A single primitive can be overloaded in many ways, or several different variables can all be displayed simultaneously.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Standard climatological methods of collecting thunderstorm data involve releasing balloons into or flying aircraft through clouds <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[KES83]</ref>. This gives repeated horizontal or vertical Dan Drake &lt;dwdrake@olemiss.edu&gt; Thomas Simpson &lt;simpson@olemiss.edu&gt; Larry Smithmier &lt;larry_smithmier@earthling.net&gt; Penny Rheingans &lt;rheingans@cs.olemiss.edu&gt; (601) 232-7396 Computer and Information Science 302 Weir Hall UNIVERSITY, MS 38677 tracks of measurements easily displayed in 2D plots. Our data set contains vector and scalar data collected by a sail plane spiraling within and around a thunderstorm complex. It contains a measure of the standard microstructure components of the storm system (updraft speed, temperature, and liquid water content <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[ROG89]</ref>) as well as vector data relating to a detected electric field. The track of the plane becomes convoluted in one region, obscuring the data of interest when standard (to climatologists) methods were used. More complicated flight paths demand different representation techniques. One main goal in the analysis of this data is to approximate the position of point charges found within the thunder cloud and relate these to the scalar values.</p><p>Existing representation methods for multivariate vector data include: particle tracing <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[AND93]</ref>, illuminated stream lines <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[ZÖC96]</ref>, semi-transparent Gaussian splats <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[SCH96]</ref>, line integral convolution <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[FOR94]</ref>, and arrow plots <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[SCH96]</ref>. These methods generally are concerned with displaying a 3D vector field or showing vectors close to a surface while we only have vectors along a single path. The sparse nature of the vector field data demands a different approach.</p><p>The package described here displays atmospheric data interactively using a variety of techniques, including: a line, tube, or ribbon for the positional data; color, tube diameter, ribbon width, and semi-transparent Gaussian splats to represent scalar data; and an arrow plot to represent the vector field data. The vectors can be colored constantly, according to orientation, or according to orientation with a filter designed to emphasize vectors with a particular orientation. The emphasis filter de-saturates vectors pointing away from the direction of interest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p>The sail plane flew up into the cloud in a spiral pattern, measuring updraft speed, temperature, liquid water content, and vector data relating to the detected electric field. The position, true air speed, and heading were also recorded about the plane as it made the flight. The plane did some slow curves in a thermal until it reached the edge of the cloud and then started tighter, highly erratic curves through the cloud itself.</p><p>A standard <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[DYE86]</ref> 2D path arrow plot image of the electric field is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>.  on modest hardware limits the representation methods to simple illustrating how the spatial relationship of data points is lost using techniques. the standard method. The spiral path followed by the plane causes</p><p>An image showing the simultaneous display of several traditional methods to lose coherence. Coloring the track in the 2D scalar values, the vector data, and the positional data is shown in image based on the height of the plane would increase the amount <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4</ref>. Vectors representing the electric field are colored of information without greatly increasing the mental processing according to their orientation using a spherical color space in a necessary to understand the data but a 3D plot of the same data manner similar to that proposed by Johannsen and Moorhead more accurately shows what went on and allows for a greater <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[JOH95]</ref> and Boring and Pang <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[BOR96]</ref>. This coloration method number of variables to be displayed before the image seems maps orientation to hue and verticality to intensity. cluttered.</p><p>An illustration of the color space is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>. The main area of interest is the interaction of the electric The red, green, and blue lines sticking out beyond the edge of the field vector and the scalar data within the upper section of the color ball represent the x(left-right), y(up-down), and z(in-out) axis graph, after the plane entered the cloud (around 11:40 a.m. in the respectively. The coordinate system orientation is the same in the flight). A close-up of a portion of the convoluted path taken by the color space as in the vector space. This image shows how vectors plane while in the cloud is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>. The arrow plot aligned in similar directions are similar visually. represents the electric field vectors along the flight path. While</p><p>The directional color space utilized in the display of the this is better than the traditional 2D representation of the flight electric field data is a color sphere varying hue in the x,z plane and path and vector data, it is still difficult, even with interactivity, to intensity along the y axis. We chose this coloration scheme because determine the orientation of a vector within the vector field. This it allows the viewer to distinguish vectors pointing in a similar image lacks the depth cues needed to accurately determine vector direction easily. The hue differences are more readily apparent length and orientation.</p><p>than the intensity differences. By varying hue in the x,z plane, we The most important region to display is that where track chose to provide improved differentiation in the horizontal plane density renders standard methods most ineffective. In this paper since the sail plane was in an updraft and the vertical component of we discuss the adaptation of traditional 3D representation methods the location vector was changing more than the other component for this type of data and introduce a method of highlighting vectors parts. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref> uses directional coloring of the arrow plot, showing oriented in a particular direction.</p><p>the same region as <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Representations</head><p>We constructed a system for displaying sparse scalar and vector data along a track. Because of the importance of interactivity in understanding the complex track, methods with modest rendering requirements were emphasized.</p><p>A flexible set of representational models was included to facilitate exploration. Methods provided to represent scalar values along the track include coloring the track, following the track with a tube of varying radius, and following the track with a ribbon of varying width.</p><p>Semi-transparent 3D Gaussian splats were also investigated as a method of representing scalar values. The vtk Gaussian splat method creates a volume from a set of arbitrarily</p><p>We used the Visualization Toolkit (vtk) developed by located sample points by adding a 3D Gaussian splat to the volume Schroeder, Martin, and Lorensen <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[SCHR96]</ref> as a basis for our for each sample point. The Gaussian distribution of each splat is scaled by the associated scalar value. We create isosurfaces from this volume data around the track plot. Multiple isosurfaces are generated rather than doing volume rendering to preserve interactive rendering speeds. The vector data is displayed using an arrow plot, colored either a constant color, a color based on a scalar, or a color based on orientation and verticality. Orientation refers to the projection of the vector into the x,z plane (parallel to the ground) and verticality refers to the part of the vector orthogonal to the x,z plane.</p><p>Even with the 3D plot, the vector data along the spiral requires interactivity for a viewer to be able to perceive clearly the orientation and magnitude of the vectors. The need for interactivity</p><p>The goal of location of point charges suggested by the electro magnetic field vectors requires isolation of specific vectors or vectors meeting specific criteria. We developed a filter to emphasize vectors pointing in similar directions by varying the saturation of the vector color. The emphasis filtering for the vector space was done on a vector by vector basis. This was done via a function that took the current vector and compared its orientation with that of a target vector. The color was then de-saturated based on the difference between the two orientations passed through a Gaussian function. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7</ref> shows the same set of data as Figures 3 and 6 with both directional vector coloring and emphasis filtering. Implementation visualization package. vtk is available for Windows 95, Windows NT, and several UNIX platforms allowing us to develop on several computers simultaneously. It is built on OpenGL, using hardware display methods where available and MESA otherwise <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[SCHR96]</ref>. The availability of the source code also allowed us to extend the built-in visualization models to implement the directional color model and emphasis filter without having to develop an entire visualization package. It supports real time camera controls within the render window, allowing interactive viewing of the represented objects. vtk comes with C and Tcl bindings, allowing us to embed the visualization capabilities within an easy-to-use interface.</p><p>The application we developed allows the user to select which scalar data sets are to be represented and what display method will be used for each. There are controls for scaling and filtering the data. It allows the user to control the coloration of the vectors and whether the emphasis filter is on and what direction is emphasized.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p>This project demonstrates some problems associated with visualizing a unique set of data. Standard 2D visualization methods failed to convey all the information accurately. Directly applying standard 3D visualization techniques did not provide efficient exploration tools. By combining standard methods with ones we developed, we provide a visualization tool well suited to sparse vector data with associated scalars. We have also shown the flexibility and power of vtk to perform standard and nonstandard visualizations. Finally, we have introduced a vector coloring filter that allows the isolation of vectors pointing in a particular direction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Future directions</head><p>Additional areas for research include expanding the emphasis filter to other data representations, for example using color saturation to emphasize scalar data associated to vectors pointing in a particular direction. The filter could also be extended to emphasize data points with scalar values within a range or that occur within a time period. We also plan to introduce an interactive control for the filter similar to the one discussed by Boring and Pang <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[BOR96]</ref>. A further extension of the control planned is to allow the control point to be moved within the object representation, thus interactively emphasizing vectors pointing at a particular point in 3-space. Radar data of the cloud during the data collection time was also available and we intend to include a representation of the cloud for context.            </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 A</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Standard 2D arrow plot of the thunderstorm vector data.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>displays the same positional information on a 3D line plot,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 A</head><label>2</label><figDesc>3D line plot of the positional data utilizing color to represent time, beginning with blue.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>An arrow plot of EM field within the cloud.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>A mapping of temperature to track color, liquid water content to 3D Gaussian splat volumes, electric field to an arrow plot, and vector orientation to arrow color.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The color space used for directional vector coloring. The x,y,z axes map to red, green, blue respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>An arrow plot of the EM field within the cloud using directional coloring.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>An arrow plot of the EM field within the cloud using directional coloring and emphasis filtering.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 2 A</head><label>2</label><figDesc>3D line plot of the positional data utilizing color to represent time, beginning with blue.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>An arrow plot of EM field within the cloud.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>A mapping of temperature to track color, liquid water content to 3D Gaussian splat volumes, electric field to an arrow plot, and vector orientation to arrow color.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The color space used for directional vector coloring. The x,y,z axes map to red, green, blue respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>An arrow plot of the EM field within the cloud using directional coloring.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>An arrow plot of the EM field within the cloud using directional coloring and emphasis filtering.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We would like to thank Dr. Thomas Marshall for the meterological data and his assistance in interpreting it. Production of this paper was supported by a grant from the National Science Foundation (ASC-9703251).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of Turbulent Flow with Particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Andrea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hin</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Frits</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;93</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;93</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directional Flow Visualization of Vector Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ed</forename><surname>Boring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alex</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;96</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="392" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early Electrification and Precipitation Development in a Small, Isolated Montana Cumulonimbus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Winn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cerni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gardiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lamb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pitter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hallett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P R</forename><surname>Saunders</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Geophysical Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">D1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1247" />
			<date type="published" when="1986-01-20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Flow Over Curvilinear Grid Surfaces Using Line Integral Convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Forssell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="240" to="247" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AGP: Ocean Model Flow Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Johannsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moorhead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thunderstorm Morphology and Dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Edwin</forename><surname>Kessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Norman and London: University of Oklahoma nd Press</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Short Course in Cloud Physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Pergamon Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3 ed. rd</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Visualization Toolkit: An Object-Oriented Approach to 3D Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Will</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ken</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bill</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>Prentice Hall PTR</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New Jersey</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Design and Implementation Of An Object-Oriented Toolkit For 3D Graphics And Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kenneth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">William</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;96</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="100" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive Visualization of 3D-Vector Fields Using Illuminated Stream Lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Malte</forename><surname>Zöckler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Detlev</forename><surname>Stalling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hans-Christian</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;96</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;96</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="113" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
