<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Compound Brushing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Hong</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Analytical Solutions Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">SAS Institute Inc</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>October 19-21</addrLine>
									<postCode>2003, 2003</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Compound Brushing</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T18:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>I.3.6 [Methodology and Techniques]: Interaction techniques; I.3.4 [Graphics Utilities] brushing</term>
					<term>selection</term>
					<term>dynamic graphics</term>
					<term>data visualization</term>
					<term>higraph</term>
					<term>visual programming</term>
					<term>dynamic query</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>This paper proposes a conceptual model called compound brushing for modeling the brushing techniques used in dynamic data visualization. In this approach brushing techniques are modeled as higraphs with five types of basic entities: data, selection, device, renderer, and transformation. Using this model, a flexible visual programming tool is designed not only to configure/control various common types of brushing techniques currently used in dynamic data visualization, but also to investigate new brushing techniques.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Brushing is a widely used mechanism for a fundamental task of interactively selecting a subset of data in dynamic data visualization applications. The principles of brushing were first explored by Becker and Cleveland <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Becker and Cleveland 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cleveland and McGill 1988]</ref> who used 2-dimensional/rectangular brushes to highlight, label, and delete data points in matrices of linked scatter plots. Since then, a variety of brushing techniques and theories have been developed.</p><p>Various 2-dimensional brushing techniques have been introduced to brush not only scatter plot but also other plots, such as histogram, bar chart, and so on <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[Velleman 1988</ref>].</p><p>Ward and Martin <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[Ward 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Martin and Ward 1995]</ref> also extended brushing to include N-dimensional, multiple, composite, and fuzzy brushes in the visualization package XmdvTool. Ndimensional brushes have the same dimensionality as the data, while composite brushes are formed by logical combinations of brushes. Fuzzy brushes can partially contain data points. Up to four brushes can be supported simultaneously in XmdvTool.</p><p>The brushing process can involve different operations, such as replace, toggle, add, subtract, and intersect <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[Wills 1996</ref>]. Different brush shapes, such as rectangle and circle/eclipse, can also be used <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[Cleveland and McGill 1988]</ref>. Recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Hauser et al. [2002]</ref> proposed angular brushes for brushing parallel plots.</p><p>Brushing manipulation can be direct or indirect.</p><p>Direct manipulation is performed directly on the data display using a pointing device, such as a mouse. Indirect manipulation is ▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬▬ * e-mail: hong.chen@sas.com accomplished using separate widgets, such as sliders, to control the brushes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[Ward 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Martin and Ward 1995]</ref>.</p><p>Brushing techniques can also be classified by identifying in which space the selection is performed <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[Martin and Ward 1995]</ref>. The screen-based techniques are based on the common 2dimensional brushes specified by 2D shapes on the screen <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Becker and Cleveland 1987]</ref>. The data-based techniques refer to the use of N-dimensional hyper boxes in the N dimensional data space <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[Ward 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Martin and Ward 1995]</ref>. The structure-based brushing techniques are based on the data relationships, such as groups, orderings, clustering, hierarchies, and so on <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[Fua et al. 2000]</ref>.</p><p>This paper presents the concept of compound brushing modeling. This approach employs a nested graph formalism <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[Harel 1988</ref>] to model the brushing processes and techniques as brushing higraphs. Different types of entities, including data, selection, device, renderer, and transformation, are used as atomic nodes/blobs in the higraphs. The higraphs can also contain compound nodes/blobs, which are other higraphs. The compound brushing concept is useful in at least two areas. First, it greatly facilitates the design and implementation of brushing techniques. Based on this model, an extendable visual programming tool is implemented to configure/control various common brushing techniques and to explore new ones in data visualization. Second, the compound brushing model can also be used as a conceptual model to analyze, classify, and organize different brushing techniques.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. In section 2, the compound brushing model is introduced. In section 3, a visual programming tool based on the model is described. Section 4 uses the tool to illustrate how some common brushing techniques can be represented by the compound brushing model. Some new and special brushing techniques are also presented to illustrate the expressive ability of the model and the tool. Finally, section 5 gives some concluding remarks and future research directions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Compound Brushing Model</head><p>The compound brushing model consists of the following five basic types of related entities:</p><p>Brushing Renderer: This entity displays/consumes the brushing selection(s). Usually, graphics are used as the renderers. Occasionally, nonvisual entities such as analytical computing or database querying objects can also consume the selections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transformation:</head><p>This entity is an operation that operates on one or multiple data and/or selections and outputs another selection or derived data as the result. The operations can be logical (AND, OR, XOR), analytical <ref type="bibr">(clustering, binning, summarizing, etc.), data-centric (loading, sorting, formatting, merging, joining, subsetting, etc.), or visual (encoding, labeling, etc.)</ref> processings.</p><p>These entities are connected to form higraphs to model brushing processes and techniques. For example, <ref type="figure">Figure 1(a)</ref> shows a device that generates a selection which is consumed by a renderer. In <ref type="figure">Figure 1(b)</ref>, an entity is used as a device as well as a renderer -the brushing model of common scatter plots.</p><p>Multiple entities can be used as compound nodes to construct more complex higraphs with different hierarchical levels. Nodes/blobs can be connected within the same level or across different levels. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(a) is an example of such higraphs. It models the linked, 2-dimensional brushing process in common dynamic data visualization systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Becker and Cleveland 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cleveland and McGill 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Velleman 1988]</ref>. All graphics form a compound blob that includes individual plots (as atomic blobs) as well as plot matrices (as compound blobs). This compound blob is connected to a common selection and used as both the device and renderer. In <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(b), N-dimensional brushing is modeled. A compound blob sends the N selections in N dimensions to a boolean/logical AND transformation. The resulting selection is used in a display. More examples are discussed in detail in section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">A Visual Programming Tool for Brushing</head><p>We designed and implemented a simple visual programming tool in the Java language to configure or control brushing processes/techniques based on the compound brushing model. The default brushing model is 2-dimensional as depicted in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(a). The majority of the brushing devices and renderers are Java/Swing components. One of our goals is to support the extended brushing techniques, such as N-dimensional brushing and structure-based brushing, and to explore new ones. To provide consistency and efficiency in terms of development and usage, it is desired to reuse the existing 2-dimensional brushing entities for the more sophisticated brushing processes and techniques.</p><p>Our design and implementation also uses ideas from both the data-flow and the data-state models <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[Card et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Chi 2000]</ref>. Not only are the operations (brushing device, renderer, transformation, etc.) modeled as nodes, but the data store (selection, etc.) are as well. Nodes can be either atomic or compound.</p><p>The tool consists of two parts: an entity palette and a modeling panel. Both are configurable to suit different data visualization needs. Custom entities can be added to the entity palette as needed. The drag-and-drop operation is used to create an entity instance as a node: drag the entity from the palette and drop it in the modeling panel. A directed link can be created using a rubberband line from one node to another. The properties/behaviors of the entities can be adjusted and controlled interactively using their visual controllers and/or context-sensitive menus and dialogs. <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows the entity palette used to construct the brushing models in this paper. It contains buckets (data, color, and group selections), various operators and filters, common dynamic graphics (scatter plot, histogram, bar chart, etc.), table, query sliders, generic compound node, and so on. This tool is incorporated into an experimental data visualization environment that is used to generate the examples in the following section. The plots in this visualization environment are linked, dynamic graphics that support the traditional brushing process <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Becker and Cleveland 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Cleveland and McGill 1988;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Velleman 1988</ref>] and operations <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[Wills 1996</ref>] by default. Almost all of these plots can be used as brushing devices and renderers for compound brushing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Examples</head><p>The default brushing process in our visualization environment uses the model shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(a). The following section demonstrates how other brushing processes can be devised using the visual programming tool. To illustrate these brushing processes clearly, the first several examples use a data set with 1,000 observations of three randomly generated numeric variables and two categorical variables. A statistical convention of treating a row of data values as an observation and a column as a variable is used for describing data sets/tables.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multiple Brushes:</head><p>Each brush can be represented as a brushing selection generated by brushing devices. While the traditional brushing process modeled in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>(a) only permits one brush, our environment places no limit on the number of brushes.   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 4</ref>. Multiple Brushes group of bars in the histogram of the Z variable selects all observations summarized in these bars. The selection is shown as highlights in the scatter plots with larger markers and in the histograms with brighter bars.</p><p>Figure 4(b) illustrates how this default brushing process is modified with a new brushing model to support joined brushing effects in different dimensions at the same time. The top window shows the modified display with three brushes. The brushing model, shown in the modeling window at the bottom, was constructed using our visual programming tool. The construction process of this brushing model is described in detail as follows:</p><p>First, three nodes (histogram (x), histogram (y), and histogram (z)) were created to refer to the histograms in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 4</ref>(a) as brushing devices. Two more nodes (scatter plot (x*y) and scatter plot (x*z)) were constructed to refer to the scatter plots as brushing renderers. Next, three observation selection buckets (selection 1, selection 2, and selection 3) were instantiated and linked from the histograms. These observation selection buckets hold the brushing selections from their corresponding devices. They were also linked to the histogram nodes, which would render these selections as renderers. Then a logical OR transformation/operator was created and linked from selection 1 and selection 2 as inputs. Another observation selection bucket, selection 4, was instantiated to hold the output from the OR operator. This bucket was linked to the scatter plot (x*y) to show the union of brushing results in the X and Y dimensions. Similarly, another transformation network was completed to render the intersection of brushing results in the X and Z dimensions in the scatter plot (x*z).</p><p>Figure 4(c) shows the simple use of color selection buckets to further enhance the previous display. A red and a blue bucket were created and linked to scatter plots. Selection 4 is highlighted in red in the scatter plot (x*y), while selection 5 is in blue in the scatter plot (x*z).</p><p>Monitoring of Brushing Sequence: Any intermediate or final brushing selection can be linked to various renderers to monitor the brushing sequence during the brushing process. Those renderers can either be embedded in the modeling panel or in separate display windows. A brushing model with embedded renderers/devices is called a mixed model. <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref> is an example of a mixed model in which an embedded table and a scatter plot are used to monitor the brushing process described previously in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 4</ref>(c).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 5. Mixed Brushing Model</head><p>Filtering: In addition to the logical/boolean transformations, we also explore the idea of filtering operations with two kinds of filters: arithmetic/logical and analytical filters.</p><p>Arithmetic/logical filter: This filter uses an expression to filter the selected observations. Most of the common mathematical functions and operations, such as exponential, logarithm, square root, trigonometric functions, and so on, are supported. So are the logical operations, such as AND, OR, XOR, LARGER, LESS, EQUAL, and so on.</p><p>There are many potential uses of this kind of filter, including the masking of data subsets and brushing of outliers.</p><p>In <ref type="figure">Figure 6(a)</ref>, the data selection generated from the histogram of X variable is filtered by a filter with the expression of a circle in the X and Y space. Only the observations with (x, y) values outside the circle can pass the filter. This results in a circular mask inside the scatter plot of the X and Y variables.</p><p>Some simple expressions can be visually represented as query sliders <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[Ahlberg and Shneiderman 1994]</ref>.</p><p>(a) Filtering with an Expression/Query Filter (b) Filtering with an Analytical Filter <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. Filtering</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analytical filtering:</head><p>Many analytical operations can be implemented in analytical filters to validate/filter data selections. <ref type="figure">Figure 6(b)</ref> is an example of the use of quantile range to filter data. The display uses a GPA data set <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Moore and McCabe 1989]</ref> that was collected to determine which applicants at a university were likely to succeed in its computer science program. The variable GPA is the grade point average; HSM, HSS, and HSE are average high school grades in mathematics, science, and English; SATM and SATV are scores on the mathematics and verbal portion of the SAT exam; and SEX indicates whether an applicant is a male or female.</p><p>In <ref type="figure">Figure 6(b)</ref>, the histogram of the variable GPA is used as the brushing device. The brushing selection is sent to a quantile filter of the variable SATM. The quantile filter can support multiple quantile ranges that would be shown in different colors. In this example, a range of the top 10th percentile, as shown in red, is used. A histogram of the variable SATV is used as the renderer for the filtered selection, which shows the distribution of SATV scores for the selected applicants who not only have relatively high GPA scores but also SATM scores within the top 10th percentile.</p><p>Same Graphic as a Device and Renderer: Based on our compound brushing concept, the graphics used in the traditional brushing process can be viewed both as devices generating a selection and, at the same time, as renderers consuming that selection immediately, as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 2(a)</ref>. If the selection is sent to a transformation network and the transformed selection is then consumed, these graphics can become more flexible and powerful.</p><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 7</ref>, the histogram of the GPA variable generates a brushing selection as the brushing device. The selection is filtered with a logical filter. Only the selected female applicants pass the filter. The filtered selection is then sent back to the histogram for rendering as highlights. As the result, the histogram simultaneously shows two distributions of GPA scores in the brushed area: one for all applicants and another for the female applicants.  Depending on how the observation selections propagate within or among structures, there can be many possible propagation schemes used in diffusive brushing processes. For example, propagation can be breadth-oriented, such as the structure-based brushing proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Fua et al. [2000]</ref>, which propagates the selection either across substructures or at a certain level across a hierarchy. It can be depth-oriented, which, for example, propagates the selection from the root of a (sub)hierarchy down to the children at lower levels.</p><p>Propagation can also be neighborhood-oriented, which propagates the selection within a structure or substructure. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref> is an example of neighborhood-oriented diffusive brushing. The display uses a bio-informatics data set that was derived from an experimental design <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[Jin et al. 2001]</ref> consisting of 24 cDNA microarrays of 3,931 genes of adult fruit flies. Eight effects of sex, cell line, age, dye, and some interactions of those on gene expression in fruit flies were investigated. Each effect has two levels, e.g., male and female for the sex, 1-week and 6week for the age, and so on. For each gene, one estimate is derived, as an observation in the data set, from a statistical mixed model for each of these eight effects and marked by the spot on the microarrays. In this case, one spot is used for one gene, and therefore spot labels can be the identifiers of genes. For each of these observations, the mixed model analysis of variance was used to calculate the P-value and the fold, which is the difference between two estimates of corresponding effect levels.</p><p>The display in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref> employs a lattice of volcano plots to study the significances of the effects. Each effect is shown in a panel of volcano plots where each data point represents one of the 3,931 genes, with the negative log-based 10 of the P-value plotted against the log-based 2 of the fold value. In a volcano plot, the points near the "opening of the volcano" are of particular interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[Wolfinger et al. 2001]</ref>. Brushing techniques can be used to identify the genes represented by these points for further analysis. Since the genes in different plots are described by different observations, the traditional brushing process can only select the brushed gene for one effect represented by the brushed plot. It would be very informative to select the brushed genes for all effects in all plots, as shown in the display window in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref>. To achieve this, a brushing model based on neighborhoodoriented diffusive brushing is used, as shown in the modeling window in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref>.</p><p>The brushing model uses a discretizer on the SPOT variable. The outputs of the discretizer are 3,931 categories for the genes and are stored in an observation group/structure bucket. All volcano plots are collected and their references are stored in a compound node. Every plot inside the compound node is used as a brushing device to generate the gene selection with one effect from that plot. The selection is sent to the first observation selection bucket. The observation selection and the group buckets are linked to a diffuser, which propagates the gene selection within their corresponding category. The output selection from the diffuser is sent to the volcano plots for rendering. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 8</ref>, the data point for the gene DM3345 of sex effect is first selected from the sex panel. The diffuser then populates the selection to all other effects in the category of the gene DM3345. As the result, every panel has one point highlighted and labeled with DM3345 in black.</p><p>Moving Average: Sometimes, there is a need to brush one plot, perform some calculation on the selected observations, and display the result of this calculation in a table or second plot <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[Craig et al. 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Haslett et al. 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Martin and Ward 1995]</ref>. <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref> is an example based on this idea.</p><p>The data set used in <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref> is the customer records of a mail order company. The customers are from different cities across the continental United States. Among the variables used in the display, X, Y, and STATE are the locations and state codes of customer homes; INCOME is the estimated annual income; and PROM07 is the total dollar amount of sale promotions sent to the customers during the past seven months. <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(a) is a display for investigating the relationship between the INCOME and PROM07 variables conditioned using the STATE variable. It employs a moving average brushing technique. The main display window in <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(a) is a United States map overlaid by a point/scatter plot of X and Y variables. Only the points for the customers selected by brushing the The brushing model used for this brushing process employs a discretizer of the STATE variable and a color setter on the PROM07 variable. The discretizer generates a group bucket of categories for the states in the United States. The histogram is used as the brushing device to generate an observation selection bucket for the customers. The group bucket and the selection bucket are linked to the color setter as its inputs. For the selected observations in each category, the color setter calculates the summary statistics (in this case the average value) of the PROM07 variable. Then, using the color map, a color is assigned to these observations based on the summary value. The output of the color setter is a bucket of colors for the selected observations. The color bucket and the observation selection bucket are then sent to the brushing renderer -the point/scatter plot layer in the main display window.</p><p>The data set used in this example also contains many addtional variables. Multidimensional plots, such as parallel coordinates, can be employed to visualize these dimensions. <ref type="figure">Figure 9(b)</ref> shows a parallel coordinates plot on some of these dimensions. The plot is used as another brushing renderer in addition to the one modeled in <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(a).</p><p>Enhanced Scatter Plot Matrix: The common scatter plot matrix can be enhanced using compound brushing to display and brush the data of a binary group. The plots in the upper triangular matrix are used to display the values associated with one group, and the ones in the lower triangular matrix are used for another group. <ref type="figure">Figure 10(a)</ref> shows a histogram display of the GPA variable and a display of a conventional dynamic scatter plot matrix of the other score variables from the GPA data set. Brushing a group of bars in the histogram selects the data observations associated with the brushed bars. These selected data are then shown in all scatter plots with larger markers.</p><p>Suppose we want to investigate visually how the GPA score related to the other test scores based on the applicants' gender. <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref>(a) can be enhanced by adjusting the data brushing process and color encoding schemes. The square plot matrix is divided into upper and lower triangular matrices. The upper triangular plot matrix shows highlights in blue for the male applicants, while the lower matrix uses highlights in red for the female applicants. The modified display is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure  10</ref>(b). The applicants with high GPA scores between 5.5 and 6.0 are selected by brushing the two rightmost bars in the histogram. The selected male and female applicants are then highlighted separately in the scatter plots in the upper and lower triangular matrices. The points of all applicants are drawn in dark gray as the background for the highlights.</p><p>The above adjustment is achieved through the brushing model shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 10</ref>(c). Three groups of plots (the histogram, the scatter plots in the upper triangular matrix, and the scatter plots in the lower triangular matrix) were collected. These three collections of plots were then modeled as three compound nodes (Histogram, Males, and Females nodes) in the brushing model. A compound node is capable of sending the inputs from other nodes to its child nodes recursively. In this example, the data selected by brushing the histogram referenced by the Histogram node is passed to the first data selection bucket, which is split and filtered based on the applicants' gender by two logical filters. The selected male applicants pass through the top filter and enter a data selection bucket that is then sent to the Males compound node. A blue bucket is also sent to the Males node. Then the Males node passes the buckets to each of the scatter plots in the upper triangular plot matrix. Similarly, the selected female applicants are saved in another data selection bucket, which is sent to the scatter plots in the lower triangular matrix together with a red bucket.</p><p>The contents or children of a compound node can be inspected by expanding the node. In <ref type="figure">Figure 10(d)</ref>, expanding the compound nodes Males and Females opens two metaplots of the child nodes. In this case, the small metaplots are also dynamic scatter plots. Brushing the small metaplots selects the plots in the display of the scatter plot matrix, which clearly indicates the relationship between the matrix display and the brushing model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusions and Future Work</head><p>This paper presents the concept of compound brushing to model brushing processes and techniques in dynamic data visualization using higraphs. This model can be used as a conceptual model to describe various brushing techniques. Based on this model, a visual programming tool was designed and implemented to enable users to configure/control various brushing needs, which makes the existing dynamic data visualization more flexible and powerful. This tool also serves as a test bed to explore new brushing techniques, such as filtering, sequence monitoring, diffusion, and so on, as described in the paper.</p><p>Currently, we are working on the schemes to persist the compound nodes to enable users to reuse these nodes in the modeling process. Also under development are the schemes for persisting brushing models, which will enable the reuse of brushing models for different applicable tasks.</p><p>We plan to enhance our visual programming tool to incorporate more analytical operators, data manipulations, and database query functionalities. Such a tool can be used as a dynamic query <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[Ahlberg and Shneiderman 1994</ref>] tool with rich analysis, data, and visual processing capability as well as a data analysis tool with powerful brushing and data management mechanisms.</p><p>We also plan to improve our GUI design. For example, the palette can use tabbed panels to better organize entities in different categories.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>(a) is an example of traditional brushing. It is a display of two scatter plots with histograms as borders on the random data set. The display shows both the 1-dimensional and 2dimensional distributions of X, Y, and Z variables. Brushing a 2-Dimensional and N-Dimensional Brushings</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>Multiple Brushes with Logical Operations (c) Different Colors for Different Selections</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Histogram as a Brushing Device and Renderer Diffusion: Diffusive brushing uses structural data or metadata. Usually a data discretizer is involved. The common discretizers use binning, grouping, clustering, partitioning, or other algorithms to construct categories for the data. The categories can be organized using either flat or hierarchical structures. The selection of one data observation can propagate within or among</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Lattice of Volcano Plots of Significance Against Effect the structures, which results in the selection of other observations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) Map Overlaid with Points as a Renderer (b) Plot of Parallel Coordinates as a Renderer Figure 9. Moving Average with Color Encoding histogram of the INCOME variable are shown in the main display. These points are colored based on the average value of the PROM07 variable among the selected customers in different states. A categorical color map of five sections is used for coloring the points. Each of the first four color sections is also a small continuous color map of two end colors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) Conventional Display of Scatter Plot Matrix (b) Adjusted Display of the Scatter Plot Matrix with Enhanced Data Brushing and Highlighting (c) Brushing Model (d) Small Metaplots for the Expanded Compound Nodes Figure 10. Adjustment of the Data Brushing Process and Highlight Colors for a Dynamic Scatter Plot Matrix</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Acknowledgments</head><p>The author thanks Phil Meanor, Todd Barlow, Tzu-Ming Chu, and Russell Wolfinger at SAS Institute Inc. for their invaluable discussions and suggestions.</p><p>This work is part of the author's part-time dissertation research project at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. The author thanks Russell Taylor at the University of North Carolina for his advice, Radhika Kulkarni at SAS Institute Inc. for her support on this effort, and SAS Institute Inc. for allowing him to use its research graphics library during his research.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual Information Seeking: Tight Coupling of Dynamic Query Filters with Starfield Displays</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ahlberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of ACM CHI94</title>
		<meeting>of ACM CHI94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="317" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brushing Scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">W S</forename><surname>Cleveland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Technometrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Readings in Information Visualization: Using Vision to Think</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufman</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Taxonomy of Visualization Techniques using the Data State Reference Model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="75" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamic Graphics for Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cleveland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mcgill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Wadsworth &amp; Brooks</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Moving Statistics: An Extension of Brushing for Spatial Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haslett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Unwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Science and Statistics: Proc. of the 21st Symposium on the Interface</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="170" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structurebased Brushes: a Mechanism for Navigating Hierarchically Organized Data and Information Spaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rundensteiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="159" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On Visual Formalisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Harel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic Graphics for Exploring Spatial Data with Application to Locating Global and Local Anomalies</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Haslett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Unwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The American Statistician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Angular Brushing of Extended Parallel Coordinates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ledermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Doleisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="130" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Contributions of Sex, Genotype and Age to Transcriptional Variance in Drosophila Melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wolfinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Passador-Gurgel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High Dimensional Brushing for Interactive Exploration of Multivariate Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Visualization&apos;95</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Visualization&apos;95</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="278" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to the Practice of Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mccabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<publisher>Freeman and Company</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Datadesk Handbook. Odesta Corporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Velleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Xmdvtool: Integrating Multiple Methods for Visualizing Multivariate Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Visualization&apos;94</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Visualization&apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="333" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selection: 524,288 Ways to Say &quot;This is Interesting</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessing Gene Significance from cDNA Microarray Expression Data via Mixed Models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wolfinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wolfinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hamadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bushel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Afshari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Paules</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computational Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
