<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Particle/Flow Structure Interactions in the Small Bronchial Tubes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bela</forename><surname>Soni</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>Senior Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><roleName>Member, IEEE</roleName><forename type="first">Raghu</forename><surname>Machiraju</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Particle/Flow Structure Interactions in the Small Bronchial Tubes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-20T19:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Particle deposition in the small bronchial tubes (generations six through twelve) is strongly influenced by the vortexdominated secondary flows that are induced by axial curvature of the tubes. In this paper, we employ particle destination maps in conjunction with two-dimensional, finite-time Lyapunov exponent maps to illustrate how the trajectories of finite-mass particles are influenced by the presence of vortices. We consider two three-generation bronchial tube models: a planar, asymmetric geometry and a non-planar, asymmetric geometry. Our visualizations demonstrate that these techniques, coupled with judiciously seeded particle trajectories, are effective tools for studying particle/flow structure interactions.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The air flow in the small bronchial tubes (generations six through twelve) is laminar due to a combination of the low fluid velocity and the small diameter of the airway <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Even so, it may be quite complex with significant secondary currents, particularly transverse vortex pairs that form due to axial curvature of the tubes <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. These secondary flows can significantly affect the deposition of inhaled particulate in the bronchial tubes. Further complicating the issue is the fact that particles with mass do not follow the streamlines of the flow. Therefore, an appropriate visualization technique is needed to provide insight into the effects of flow structures on particle transport and deposition. Existing methods discussed in the literature, such as plots of deposition efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, deposition fractions <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref>, and deposition enhancement factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>, provide information about the particle distributions once they impact or exit the bronchial tubes. However, they do not provide information about the interaction of flow structures and particulates. Particle tracing, while more effective at elucidating the behavior of a specific particle or set of particles, requires knowledge of the appropriate seed points to be effective. Displaying field variables in volumes or cutting planes can also be useful but it provides only local information about the flow. What is needed is a technique or combination of techniques that correlates local information about the flow with global information such as particle deposition patterns.</p><p>In this paper, we investigate the interaction between inhaled particulate and the fluid flow in the small bronchial tubes using a combination of techniques including particle destination maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>, which indicate the zone of the computational domain in which a particle is deposited, and finite-time Lyapunov exponent (FTLE) maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, which provide a quantitative description of the coherence, or lack thereof, of particles passing through a certain region in the flow. We first describe the problem in terms of the fluid dynamics of the flow. Next, a brief literature review provides context for our efforts. We then discuss our use of FTLE and its implementation. Finally, we consider results for two different bronchial tube models and demonstrate how these techniques help us to better understand the mechanisms of particle deposition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Problem Description</head><p>While the depth of penetration into the tubular network of the lungs depends on the nature and concentration of particles, the aerodynamics of respiration plays a critical but poorly understood role in the filtration of entrained particles from inhaled air. Improved understanding of these flows has two important applications: (1) the health hazards posed by the inhalation of carcinogenic, disease-bearing, or lungdamaging aerosols and (2) the clinical delivery of both local and systemic aerosolized drugs through the lungs. The general behavior of these secondary flows is illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> for a planar, threegeneration bronchial tube model. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(a) shows stream ribbons that are colored by exit and illustrates the effects of the secondary vortical flows by the twisting of the ribbons near the bifurcations. As a fluid particle enters a curved section of a tube, its path changes due to the curvature. Conservation of angular momentum requires that the particle velocity increase. Since particles on the inside of the curve, where the radius of curvature is smaller, experience a greater change in curvature, they accelerate more than those on the outside of the curve (labeled A in the figure). The faster particles rush to the outside of the curve and displace the slower moving particles producing a counterrotating vortex pair as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>(b). In this image, the normal to the cutting plane is parallel to the axis of the tube.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Literature Review</head><p>Visualization of particle deposition in bronchial tubes gives both qualitative and quantitative information about the process. There are several techniques described in the literature to visualize particle deposition in the bronchial tubes. Plotting particle trajectories along the bronchial tree is the most common technique employed to view particle transport <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref>. Particle deposition patterns are typically viewed by plotting the particle terminal positions on the bronchial tube walls <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref>. This provides qualitative information about where the particles are deposited in the model. A surface density distribution is sometimes used to provide more information than the particle deposition patterns alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref>. The surface density is calculated in each geometrically defined zone. Then, the percentage particle density in each surface element is evaluated based on the maximum density in that particular zone. Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> plotted the deposition enhancement fraction (DEF) on the bronchial tube surface in order to identify high particle concentration regions or "hot spots." DEF is defined as the ratio of local to average deposition densities. In order to analyze the influence of the initial particle release positions on the particle terminal locations, the particle release positions can be classified based on the generation in which they are deposited <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>. Another approach is to plot the particle distribution in a cutting plane along with vectors showing each particle's direction of motion <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30]</ref>. Haller popularized the use of FTLE as a means to geometrically characterize Lagrangian coherent structures in steady and unsteady flows <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. The FTLE maps were proposed to locate both stable and unstable structures or manifolds and thereby elucidate the global flow structure. This work is in contrast to other approaches for locating and characterizing coherent structures using analytical methods based on trajectories <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. One of the significant disadvantages of using FTLE maps for three-dimensional problems is the very high cost of computing them. There has been much interest in both the CFD and visualization communities on the use of FTLE maps for studying and analyzing two-dimensional and three-dimensional flows.</p><p>Garth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> recently reported the development of optimized methods to compute FTLE maps for both two-dimensional and threedimensional flows and demonstrated superior visualizations for example applications. Sadlo and Peikert also examined the use of FTLE ridge surfaces for visualization of three-dimensional flows <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> but did not explore time-optimal implementations. The use of graphics hardware to enhance computational efficiency has been investigated by Garth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> in which methods for two-dimensional flows were implemented on GPUs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">COMPUTATIONAL MODEL</head><p>In this section, we briefly discuss the geometrical model employed and salient issues regarding the simulations. The simulations and the results of a detailed mesh refinement study are discussed by Soni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Geometrical Model</head><p>In this effort, we consider asymmetric, three-generation planar and non-planar models of the small bronchial tubes that occur in generations six through twelve. The asymmetric model described by Hammersley and Olson <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> was employed as the fundamental unit. The geometric characteristics of the model, e.g., branching angles and tube diameter ratios, are based on average values obtained from analysis of human cadaver airways <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. In the nomenclature employed here, the parent tube represents one generation and the two daughter tubes represent a second generation. This fundamental unit can be used to develop multi-generation models by attaching it to a previous generation and maintaining the appropriate parent/daughter tube diameter ratios. To develop a three-generation bronchial tree, a fundamental unit is added at each exit of the two daughter tubes of a two-generation geometry. The fundamental unit is attached such that the daughter tube is positioned centrally on its parent tube to mimic the planar three-generation asymmetric model given by Hammersley and Olson <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.   In a realistic bronchial network, the lung airways are not confined to a single plane. The individual bifurcations may not have a plane of symmetry <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. This asymmetry is typically neglected in the experimental studies and simulations reported in the literature. Additionally, branching is not confined to a plane, i.e., the subsequent generations may not lie in the same plane. The out-of-plane branch angles are randomly distributed in a manner that allows the bronchial tube network to fill the available space without intersections. Following research reported in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>, we introduce non-planarity by rotating the third generation 90 • out-of-plane with respect to second generation. The resulting geometries are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>. We adopt the terminology employed in the literature and use "non-planar" to refer to out-of-plane branching of subsequent generations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Mesh Generation</head><p>The computational domains for the bronchial tree models were discretized using unstructured meshes. We assume that, since each generation is geometrically similar to the fundamental unit, the primary flow structures in each generation are also geometrically similar. While interference effects from preceding generations in the flow path render this statement false in a strict sense, it does provide some guidance for developing a systematic method for discretizing the computational domain. Therefore, the mesh was generated using the same number of nodes to discretize geometrically similar components in each generation. The unstructured mesh was generated using the SolidMesh package <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> that employs the advancing-front/local-reconnection technique developed by Marcum and Weatherill <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. The meshes generated for this study employed a surface mesh consisting of triangular elements and a mixed-element (hybrid) volume mesh. The planar and non-planar models employed for the results reported here were composed of approximately 4.3 million nodes and 20.1 million elements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Flow simulation and boundary conditions</head><p>The laminar, steady flow solutions were computed for a Reynolds number of 1000, based on a parent tube diameter of 5mm and mean flow velocity of 3.14m/s, using the U 2 NCLE (Unstructured UNsteady Computation of fieLd Equations) flow solver <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>. Since the flow in the small bronchial tubes can be characterized by a constant density and viscosity, it is governed by the constant property, incompressible Navier-Stokes equations. The iteration converged solution was obtained by reducing residual norms to 10 −17 using local time stepping, which required about 12,000 time steps to reach a steady state. The computations were performed using 64 processors in parallel on a cluster containing 512 Sun Microsystems SunFire X2200 M2 servers.</p><p>The no-slip boundary condition was applied at the tube surface along with a zero normal pressure gradient assumption. The walls were assumed to be rigid and smooth. The velocity distribution at the inlet was specified explicitly. This defines the flow rate and differs from imposing a pressure difference between the inlet and exits because the pressure developed naturally. It also gives the flexibility to introduce different inlet velocity profiles. In this study, the fully developed parabolic inlet velocity profile was employed. Although this is obviously not realistic, only a limited number of studies have examined the sensitivity of the particle deposition patterns to the inlet velocity profile <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. A constant static pressure was specified at each of the four outlets, assuming the same pressure at each outlet of the three-generation airway. Since the precise pressure at each exit is not known, we have, like other researchers <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>, employed this approximate pressure boundary condition. The pressure at the inlet was allowed to float in response to the imposed values of exit pressure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">FINITE-TIME LYAPUNOV EXPONENT (FTLE) MAP</head><p>One possible approach to characterize particle/flow structure interactions is to employ finite-time Lyapunov exponent (FTLE). Haller <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> utilized FTLE to characterize Lagrangian coherent structures in transient and steady flows. The FTLE defines "asymptotically stable and unstable coherent structures in terms of the loci of maximized dispersion of closely seeded particles" <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and therefore provides an indication of the coherence of particles during their travel through the airway. Thus, the FTLE provide a mechanism to describe a global phenomenon (particle deposition) in terms of field values and, in some sense, couples the Lagrangian (particle-based) and Eulerian (fieldbased) viewpoints. Unfortunately, computing the three-dimensional FTLE field for a large-scale CFD simulation is prohibitive from a cost standpoint because it requires many (typically millions) Lagrangian particle trajectory computations. We follow the approach proposed by Garth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> to compute and display the FTLE on planar subsets in order to mitigate the cost of computing FTLE in a full threedimensional domain. However, we are interested in the FTLE map for the inhaled particulate rather than the FTLE map for the fluid particles.</p><p>Borrowing from the nomenclature of Garth et al., we let X 0 be the starting position of a particle i at starting time t 0 , and X be the terminal position at fixed time t = t 0 + ∆t. In this context, the value of t is taken to the time when all of the particles have either exited the domain or been deposited on the tube surface. The particle position X is a function of the final time, the initial time and the initial position X(t;t 0 , X 0 ). The computation of FTLE involves determining the spatial gradients of the final position of a point X(t;t 0 , X 0 ) with respect to its release point X 0 = X(t 0 ;t 0 , X 0 ). This provides the sensitivity of the terminal position of a particle with respect to changes in its initial position.</p><p>The spectral norm of the gradients at a point provides the maximized dispersion of particles around the particle initially located at this point. The spectral norm of any general matrix A ∈ R 3 is equal to the square root of the maximal eigenvalue of the positive definite symmetric matrix A T A <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Therefore, the maximum dispersion of the particle initially located at ε(X 0 ) is given by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ε(X 0 ) = λ max X 0 X (t;t 0 , X 0 ) T X 0 X (t;t 0 , X 0 ) .<label>(1)</label></formula><p>The FTLE value, which represents the average exponential of the dispersion rate, is obtained by dividing the logarithm of ε(X 0 ) by the time interval ∆t as shown in the equation below:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Λ(t;t 0 , X 0 ) = 1 ∆t log λ max X 0 X (t;t 0 , X 0 ) T X 0 X (t;t 0 , X 0 ) . (2)</formula><p>Higher FTLE values indicate a tendency of adjacent particles to disperse while lower FTLE values indicate less dispersion of the particles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Implementation Details</head><p>The particle trajectories are computed using a standard approach that includes the effects of aerodynamic and gravitational forces while neglecting particle/particle interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. The temporal integration needed to compute X(t;t 0 , X 0 ) is performed using a fourth-order Runge-Kutta algorithm. The initial particle release positions are defined by generating a planar, isotropic triangular mesh on a disk that has a diameter slightly less than the local tube diameter and a normal parallel to the local tube axis. The particles are then distributed on the plane at the nodes of the unstructured mesh. The number of nodes in the mesh is dependent on the specified edge length of the mesh and the diameter of the disk. In our computations, we have employed approximately 24,000 nodes (particles). The particles at the inlet are assumed to have the same velocity as the local fluid velocity.</p><p>A particle trajectory computation is terminated when the trajectory either intersects the bronchial tube wall or exits the computational domain. When a particle trajectory intersects a boundary, it is assumed to be deposited on that boundary. In reality, it may be deposited, rebound, break up, or enter into a chemical reaction that changes its properties. Further, when a particle leaves the computational domain through one of the exits, its trajectory is terminated, whereas in reality the particle continues to travel into subsequent generations of the small airways where it may be deposited or return after the beginning of the exhale cycle and be deposited in an upstream generation.</p><p>Once the trajectory computations are complete, the FTLE field can be calculated on the particle release plane using Equation 2. The gradient of the final particle position with respect to particle release position can be approximated using a linear fitting of the data on the triangular particle release mesh. The computed FTLE value is then assigned to its respective triangle for visualization purposes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Comments on This Approach</head><p>We first want to reiterate that our technique is concerned with the FTLE map of the inhaled particulate, not the air flow. Typically, FTLE computations for flow visualization employ massless particles that are assumed to move with the fluid, i.e., the particle velocity is equal to the local fluid velocity. In general, this is not true for a particle with mass. Therefore, a particle with mass cannot be seeded in the interior of the domain unless its velocity is known at the seed point and the usual approach of locating a feature in the flow and seeding particles in the region near the feature is not feasible. Further, since the trajectories of particles with mass may cross <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>, the particle velocity at a given point in space and the mapping X(t;t 0 , X 0 ) are, in fact, multi-valued at points where particles cross and the FTLE does not exist. To avoid this problem, we compute the FTLE field only on the planar surface that is used to define the initial particle release positions X(t;t 0 , X 0 ), which ensures that the mapping is single-valued and the FTLE exists.</p><p>Second, our approach is not really appropriate for predicting the particle deposition map. The reason for this is that we have assumed a uniform distribution of particles at the inlet, which is unrealistic. However, the uniform particle distribution is appropriate for determining the particle destination map and the FTLE map.</p><p>Finally, Garth et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> argue that the two-dimensional FTLE map is meaningful for a plane whose normal is nearly parallel to the local fluid motion because the plane is orthogonal to suspected Lagrangian coherent structures in the flow and that particle separation along the resulting material lines is minimal. In our cases, the predominant motion of the inhaled particulate near the inlet is along the local axis of the tube. Therefore, we anticipate that this approach will work well for our data since the particle release mesh is aligned so that its normal is parallel to the local tube axis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Particle Destination Map</head><p>An alternative approach for visualizing particle deposition is the particle destination map <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>. In our implementation, the particle destination map shows the final position of a particle, in the form of a scalar field, as a function of the particle's release position. First, the surfaces of the computational domain are decomposed and assigned a value, which is associated with a scalar map. It should be noted that this domain decomposition is arbitrary. Then, the trajectory computations used for the FTLE calculations are employed to determine the zone in which a particle is deposited or through which it exits the computational domain. The scalar associated with this zone is then assigned to the particle's release position. Deposition zone boundaries in the destination map correspond to large FTLE values when the deposition zones have significant spatial separation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">RESULTS</head><p>In this section, we discuss results that we have obtained for the threegeneration planar and non-planar bronchial airway models shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Particle Deposition for Planar Geometry -10µmdiameter Water Droplets</head><p>The deposition zone diagram, the particle destination map, and the FTLE map on a cross section located at the inlet are shown in The fact that the model and resulting flow field are symmetric about the midplane is reflected by the symmetry of the particle destination and FTLE maps. Likewise, the lack of symmetry in the geometry produces the asymmetry in the perpendicular plane. Since the FTLE map is based on the final position of the particles, the destination map and FTLE map show the effects of downstream geometry and flow structures on particle deposition. In the FTLE map shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>(c), the boundary between two widely separated deposition zones is a region in which the FTLE takes on large values due to the lack of coherence in particle trajectories. Conversely, a region of low FTLE values indicates that particles introduced in this region exhibit significant coherence in their final deposition positions. For example, the blue region just to the right of the center of the destination map shows the initial positions of particles that are deposited in the zone that includes the carina and the region just downstream of the first bifurcation. The corresponding low values of the FTLE map in this region indicate that these particles show coherence in their final position.</p><p>Taken alone, the particle destination map does not provide any detailed information about what happens within a contiguous region, i.e., particles deposited in the same zone. On the other hand, when the FTLE map is considered alone, it gives no indication of the location of particle deposition in the bronchial tubes. Thus, the simultaneous use of both techniques provides better understanding of particle deposition than considering them independently. Additionally, by using the particle destination map in conjunction with the FTLE map, it is possible to seed particles so that their trajectories have certain desired properties. This can be contrasted to a trial-and-error approach to accomplish the same task.</p><p>We now focus on the larger daughter tube and the subsequent granddaughter tubes. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref> shows particle trajectories seeded on the cutting plane located at the inlet, which is labeled A. The particle trajectories were selected using the particle destination map and the FTLE map, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figures 4(b)</ref> and 4(c), so that some would exit the domain and others would impact the tube walls. Also shown in the figure are three cutting planes labeled B, C, and D to which we refer in subsequent figures. Referring to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>, we note that red particles exhibit quite a bit of dispersion once they cross plane B. This behavior is manifested in the variation of FTLE in the region in which the red trajectories were seeded as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6(a)</ref>. Its cause is apparent in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6(b)</ref> where the red trajectories intersect one of the counter-rotating  vortices and, because of the interaction with the vortex, become dispersed. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>(c) shows that the red trajectories are further dispersed through their interactions with the vortices in the larger granddaughter tube. However, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref> and the particle destination map in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4(b)</ref>, the red particles all exit the domain in the larger granddaughter tube. In this case, we see that the FTLE, interpreted in the correct context, provides information about the interaction of particles with vortices that is not indicated by the particle destination map. Referring to <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>(a), the blue trajectories were seeded in a region of relatively low FTLE values, which suggests that their dispersal should be minimal. These trajectories are reasonably coherent along their paths up to their exit through the larger granddaughter tube. A close examination of <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6(b)</ref> shows that these particles pass through the core region of one of the counter-rotating vortices in plane B. In comparison with the red trajectories, we observe that parti- cles passing near the core of the vortex show less dispersion than those passing through regions outside the core. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>(c), the blue particles do interact with the vortices in the granddaughter tube and exhibit some dispersion, which is consistent with the results in the FTLE map. The green trajectories are seeded in a region in which the FTLE values in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>(a) suggest that there is some dispersion of the particles and the destination map in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>(b) indicates they are deposited in more than one zone. The green trajectories remain coherent until they intersect plane D where the green particles interact with the vortices as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6(d)</ref>. Some of the particles impact the smaller granddaughter tube wall while others exit the smaller granddaughter tube.</p><p>The moderate values of FTLE in the region where the green trajectories were seeded illustrate how FTLE can show a continuous variation in regions where the particle destination map shows zone boundaries. Now, we consider the orange trajectories shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>. From <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6(a)</ref>, we see that the orange trajectories were seeded in a region of high FTLE. As can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6(b)</ref>, the flow in plane B has little effect on the coherence of the orange particles. However, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>, some of the particles impact the smaller granddaughter tube wall near the carina, some deposit on the smaller granddaughter tube wall away from carina, and the remainder exit from the smaller granddaughter tube. The orange particles are deposited in two different zones in a manner similar to the green particles as indicated by the destination map in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4(b)</ref>. However, unlike the green particles, the orange particles are deposited over a relatively large region thereby demonstrating the usefulness of FTLE for illustrating intrazone and interzone particle deposition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Particle Deposition for Non-planar Geometry -10µm-</head><p>diameter Water Droplets <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref> shows the deposition zone diagram, the particle destination map, and the FTLE map on a cross section located at the inlet of the non-planar geometry. From the particle destination map, it can be ob-(a) particle deposition zones (b) particle destination map (c) FTLE map <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref>. Particle deposition zones -non-planar geometry. The destination map and FTLE map were computed on a surface located at the inlet.</p><p>served that particle trajectories are similar to those found in the planar model up to the first bifurcation and the upstream regions of the daughter tubes. The particle destination map is symmetric until the second generation. Beyond the second-generation tubes, the particle distribution is asymmetric and shows substantially more complex behavior than the planar case. Again, we focus on the larger daughter tube and the subsequent granddaughter tubes. <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> shows the cutting plane located at the inlet, labeled A, upon which the particle trajectories were seeded, and the three cutting planes labeled B, C, and D. We first consider the blue trajectories. They were seeded in a region of moderate FTLE, as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(a). However, they show minimal dispersion in the larger daughter tube as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(b) due to the fact that they are passing through one of the counter-rotating vortex cores in plane B. It is evident from <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(c) that the blue particles begin to disperse as they interact with one of the vortices in the larger granddaughter tube. Note that the crossflow velocity curvature is significant in the region where the blue particles cross plane C. <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> shows that the orange trajectories diverge in the larger daughter tube and converge in the larger granddaughter tube producing relatively low FTLE values in <ref type="figure">Figure 9(a)</ref>. In this case, the vortices encountered along the orange trajectories in the daughter tube and the smaller granddaughter tube rotate in the same direction as shown in Figures 9(b) and 9(c).</p><p>It is seen from <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(a) that the green trajectories are seeded from a region with moderate values of FTLE. The green trajectories remain coherent until they cross plane C where they interact with the vortices and are deflected toward the wall as indicated in <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(c). As a result they are deposited along the larger granddaughter tube wall, again indicating how FTLE provides information about particle dispersal in regions where the particle destination map provides no information beyond the zone in which the particles are deposited.</p><p>Finally, we note in <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>, that the red trajectories actually diverge at the bifurcation in the granddaughter tubes. From <ref type="figure">Figure 9(a)</ref>, we see that the red trajectories were seeded in a region which there is significant variation in the FTLE values. As can be seen from <ref type="figure">Figure 9(b)</ref>, the particles interact with one of the counter-rotating vortices in plane B and begin to disperse. Some of the particles, which were seeded in the region of lower FTLE, encounter a vortex rotat- ing in the opposite direction in the smaller granddaughter tube and converge as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 9(d)</ref>. The remaining particles enter the larger granddaughter tube and disperse more as they interact with the vortices shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 9</ref>(c). This case illustrates how the FTLE map can distinguish between regions of large dispersal and coherence that are in close proximity to one another.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Effects of Particle Size for Planar Geometry</head><p>The effects of water droplet size on particle deposition were investigated for the planar geometry by releasing particles on the plane located at the inlet to the parent tube. Four different particle sizes were utilized: 0µm diameter (massless), 5µm diameter, 10µm diameter,  and 15µm diameter. As expected, the variations in particle destination and FTLE maps shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref> are significant as the particle diameter (mass) increases. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10(a)</ref>, the massless particles faithfully follow the flow and no particles impact the surface. The maps for the 5µm-diameter particles, shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10</ref>(b), are very similar to the massless particle maps. There is some deposition near the carina at the first bifurcation as well as limited deposition in the carinal regions of the granddaughter tubes. However, both the massless and 5µm-diameter particles generate similar FTLE maps. As the size of the particles increases, inertial effects become more important and more particle deposition occurs as indicated by the decreasing areas of the maps that correspond to particles exiting the domain as shown for the 10µm and 15µm-diameter particles in Figures 10(c) and 10(d), respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Discussion</head><p>The visualization techniques employed in the previous section illustrate the complexity of the flow fields in the small bronchial tubes. The primary challenge associated with identifying the impact of flow features on particle deposition is that there are both local (Eulerian) and global (Lagrangian) effects that must be considered. We now summa-rize our observations regarding the efficacy of the approach we employed.</p><p>• Visualization of the particle trajectories can provide critical information about the flow field/particle interaction. However, appropriate selection of the seed locations is crucial if the particle trajectories are to be useful. The FTLE maps facilitate identification of meaningful seed point locations by indicating regions of the flow that exhibit coherence or lack of coherence.</p><p>• The FTLE map distills both local and global effects into a single image by illustrating the effects of geometry and downstream vortices on particle deposition.</p><p>• Regions of higher curvature in the crossflow velocities produce a higher FTLE value, which indicates a spreading of the particles. This can be observed in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 6</ref>(b) for the red trajectories as well as for several other cases.</p><p>• The particle destination map is based on an arbitrary userdefined domain decomposition and provides only gross information about the location of the particle deposition. In contrast, the FTLE map is independent of any user-specified domain decomposition and provides details about intrazone particle dispersal. For example, although the red trajectories shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref> all deposit in the same zone, they do show some dispersal in the zone in which they are deposited due to interactions with vortices in the larger granddaughter tube. Additionally, the FTLE map can provide information about interzone dispersal as indicated for the green trajectories in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 5</ref>.</p><p>• Since the FTLE maps are based on the terminal positions of the particles, particles seeded from low FTLE regions will necessarily deposit in close proximity to one another. However, this does not imply that there is no spreading along their trajectories. An example is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref> where the vortices in the granddaughter tube are rotating opposite to those in the daughter tube and tend to cause the red particle trajectories to converge in the smaller granddaughter tube, which results in a lower value of FTLE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Practical Considerations</head><p>One of the issues that we have not addressed is the selection of time step size for the particle trajectory computation. Our computations suggest that the FTLE values exhibit only minimal sensitivity to the time step size. In part, this is due to the fact that the FTLE is computed using a logarithm (see Equation 2), which compresses the range of functional values. Of course, excessively large time step sizes will produce unacceptable results. The computational time required to compute the FTLE field depends on a number of factors including the number of particles, the length of the particle paths, the number of cells in the computational domain, and the selected time step size. For a representative timing, consider the image shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 4</ref>(c) for the planar, threegeneration model. In this case, 24,010 particles were employed, there were 20.1 million cells in the computational domain, and computations were performed for a time step size of 5µs, which is on the low end of the values we tested. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref> shows a distribution of the time required for particles to reach their destinations. As can be observed from the plot, more than 90% of the particles deposit within one second. Other particles require more time based on their velocities and final destinations. For this particular computation, an average time of 0.385s was required per particle. This timing was obtained on a workstation using a 2.6GHz AMD Opteron 885 with 2GB physical memory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">CONCLUSION</head><p>FTLE maps and particle designation maps, in conjunction with wellplaced particle trajectories, provide effective tools to study particle/flow structure interactions and their effects on particle deposition. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Fig. 11</ref>. Distribution of time required to compute particle trajectories. Note the logarithmic scale on the vertical (particle) axis.</p><p>Our visualizations demonstrate that planar FTLE maps are useful for understanding complex flow fields and suggest that similar approaches should be investigated for other fluid dynamics applications.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Secondary flows in a three-generation bronchial tube model. The image on the left shows stream ribbons colored by exit. The image on the right shows crossflow velocity vectors superimposed on a plane shaded by velocity magnitude.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fundamental unit of bronchial tree (two generations and a single bifurcation).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Three-generation bronchial tube geometries.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figures 4(a), 4(b), and 4(c), respectively. The destination map and FTLE map are oriented as they appear in the parent tube. Contiguous regions in the destination map are colored according to the zone shown in Figure 4(a) in which the particles are deposited.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Particle deposition zones -planar geometry. The destination map and FTLE map were computed on a surface located at the inlet.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Particle trajectories initiated in parent tube at A.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>(a) seed points in plane A (b) plane B (c) plane C (d) plane D Particle trajectories and crossflow velocity vectors in cutting planes shown in Figure 5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .Fig. 9 .</head><label>89</label><figDesc>Particle trajectories initiated in parent tube at A. (a) seed points in plane A (b) plane B (c) plane C (d) plane D Particle trajectories and crossflow velocity vectors in cutting planes shown in Figure 8.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>5µm-diameter water droplets (c) 10µm-diameter water droplets (d) 15µm-diameter water droplets</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Effect of water droplets size on particle deposition in the planar geometry.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Bela Soni is a Graduate Research Assistant at the Computational Simulation and Design Center, Mississippi State University, E-mail: bela@simcenter.msstate.edu • David Thompson is an Associate Professor in the Department of Aerospace Engineering at Mississippi State University, E-mail: dst@ae.msstate.edu.</figDesc><table /><note>• Raghu Machiraju is an Associate Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at The Ohio State University, E-mail: raghu@cse.ohio-state.edu. Manuscript received 31 March 2008; accepted 1 August 2008; posted online 19 October 2008; mailed on 13 October 2008. For information on obtaining reprints of this article, please send e-mailto:tvcg@computer.org.</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>The authors would like to thank NSF (EPS-0556308 and ITR/NGS-0326386) for supporting this effort. We would also like to thank Monika Jankun-Kelly of the Computational Simulation and Design Center at Mississippi State University for her software support. We also appreciate the reviewers' careful reviews and their helpful comments and suggestions.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simulation of fiber deposition in bronchial airways</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Balashazy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moustafa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Szoke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>El-Hussein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inhalation Toxicology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="727" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Steady inspiratory flow in planar and non-planar models of human bonchial airways</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Caro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schroter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sherwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sauret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<publisher>The Royal Society</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">458</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="809" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flow structures and particle deposition patterns in double-bifurcation airway models. part 2. aerosol transport and deposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Comer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fluid Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The stream-line motion of fluid in a curved pipe</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dean</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="1928" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solidmesh: A solid modeling approach to unstructured grid generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gaither</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Marcum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 7 th International Conference on Numerical Grid Generation in Computational Field Simulations</title>
		<meeting>the 7 th International Conference on Numerical Grid Generation in Computational Field Simulations<address><addrLine>Whistler, BC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient computation and visualization of coherent structures in fluid flow applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Garth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gerhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tricoche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1464" to="1471" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of coherent structures in transient flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Garth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G.-S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tricoche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Topology-Based Methods in Visualization, Proceedings of the 2007 Workshop</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Burnside. Computation of converging and diverging flow through an asymmetric tubular bifurcation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gatlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cuichhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hammersley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Reddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conference Proceedings of the ASME Fluids Engineering Division Summer Meeting FEDSM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Burnside. Particle paths and wall deposition patterns in laminar flow through a bifurcation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gatlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cuichhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hammersley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Reddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Conference Proceedings of the ASME Fluids Engineering Division Summer Meeting FEDSM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding finite-time invariant manifolds in two-dimensional velocity fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chaos</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinguished material surfaces and coherent structures in three-dimensional fluid flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physica D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An objective definition of a vortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fluid Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">525</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="26" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physical models of the smaller pulmonary airways</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hammersley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Applied Physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2402" to="2414" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between secondary flows and particle deposition patterns in airway bifurcations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hofmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Balashazy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Heistracher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aerosol Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="958" to="968" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Horn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Matrix Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An Investigation of Parallel Implicit Solution Algorithms for the Incompressible Navier-Stokes Equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hyams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Mississippi State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deposition characteristics of aerosol particles in sequentially bifurcating airway models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aerosol Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling the bifurcating flow in a human lung airway</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>So</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Biomechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unstructured grid generation using iterative point insertion and local reconnection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Marcum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Weatherill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">AIAA Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1619" to="1625" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The gravitational settling of aerosol particles in homogeneous turbulence and random flow fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maxey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Fluid Mechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">174</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient visualization of lagrangian coherent structures by filtered amr ridge extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sadlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Peikert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1456" to="1463" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimentional visualization and morphometry of small airways from microfocal x-ray computed tomography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fujioka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yokota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Makinouchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Himeno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schroter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tanishita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Biomechanics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1587" to="1594" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The calculation of inertial particle transport in dilute gas-particle flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Slater</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Multiphase Flow</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The combined effects of nonplanarity and asymmetry on primary and secondary flows in the small bronchial tubes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Soni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lindley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal for Numerical Methods in Fluids</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparision of micro-and nano-size particle depositions in a human upper airway</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Donohue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aerosol Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of asymmetric branch flow rates on aerosol deposition in bifurcating airways</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Medical Engineering and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flow structure and particle transport in a triple bifurcation airway model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions of ASME</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aerosol deposition efficiencies and upstream release positions for different inhalation modes in an upper bronchial airway model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aerosol Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="828" to="844" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cyclic micron-size particle inhalation and deposition in a triple bifurcation lung airway model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aerosol Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Micro-particle transport and deposition in a human oral airway model</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kleinstreuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aerosol Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1635" to="1652" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
