<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Angular Brushing of Extended Parallel Coordinates</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Helwig</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
							<email>hauser@vrvis.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">VRVis Research Center in Vienna</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Florian</forename><surname>Ledermann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">VRVis Research Center in Vienna</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Helmut</forename><surname>Doleisch</surname></persName>
							<email>doleisch@vrvis.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">VRVis Research Center in Vienna</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Angular Brushing of Extended Parallel Coordinates</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T18:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>information visualization</term>
					<term>parallel coordinates</term>
					<term>brushing</term>
					<term>linear correlations</term>
					<term>focus+context visualization</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>In this paper we present angular brushing for parallel coordinates (PC) as a new approach to highlighting rational data-properties, i.e., features which-in a non-separable way-depend on two data dimensions. We also demonstrate smooth brushing as an intuitive tool for specifying nonbinary degree-of-interest functions (for focus+context visualization). We also briefly describe our implementation as well as its application to the visualization of CFD data.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>For many years now, parallel coordinates (PC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> have been well-known and an often used technique in information visualization (InfoViz). Multi-dimensional data-sets are visualized by drawing one poly-line for every datapoint across coordinate axes which are laid out in parallel, side-by-side. The poly-lines intersect the coordinate axes at points which correspond to the respective components of the particular data-vector. Thereby, up to a dozen data dimensions (or even more) are well visualized, especially when the visualization is combined with proper interaction features such as real-time re-ordering of coordinate axes or interactive brushing in single dimensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Brushing is a very effective technique for specifying an explicit focus during information visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>. The user actively marks sub-sets of the data-set, for example, by using a brush-like interface element. If used in conjunction with multiple linked views, brushing can enable users to understand correlations across multiple dimensions <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>. Focus+context visualization. Brushing also is very useful to steer a drill-down into the visualization of really big datasets -by specifying a (limited and limiting) focus, more details can be shown for the selected data-points. This relates to another very important InfoViz concept which is focus-plus-context (F+C) visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The basic idea of F+C visualization is to jointly visualize highly interesting parts of the data in detail as well as the rest of the data-set <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. Reading between the lines: whereas most of the poly-lines have a pos. slope between the 2 nd and the 3 rd axis, just a few don't -those have been emphasized using angular brushing.</p><p>in reduced style, for orientation and improved navigation.</p><p>Degree-of-interest functions. For specifying which parts of the data are to be drawn in detail, i.e., for specifying the focus, a degree-of-interest (DOI) function is used <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, usually assigning a value of 1 or 0 to each data-point, depending on whether the data-point is of current interest or not. Brushing is an effective method to actively (and explicitly) assign values of ½ to data-points of interest <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>.</p><p>Brushing extensions. In addition to standard brushing, several useful extensions have been proposed in literature. The introduction of composite brushes <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, for example, enabled users to more specifically define their focus. The combination of brushing and non-binary DOI functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> proved to be useful for data-sets with gradual changes in their data attributes, for example, data from scientific simulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, we demonstrate angular brushing and smooth brushing as two effective extensions to interactive brushing of parallel coordinates (Sect. 2). Afterwards, we briefly present some implementation issues (Sect. 3). The <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. Extended parallel coordinates, a sample view of the cars data-set: cars with six cylinders were emphasized through brushing, histograms are laid over axes, and one data-point is shown with all details. application itself and some results from visual data analysis are demonstrated in Sect. 4. A longer paper, describing more extensions of our prototype like composite brushes, histogram-overlays per axis, a very flexible axis-layout, a detail-on-demand feature, etc., is available from VRVis as a technical report (http://www.VRVis.at/vis/).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Extended Brushing for Parallel Coordinates</head><p>Brushing effectively enables the user to (explicitely) specify his or her focus. In parallel coordinates, this usually is accomplished by marking a certain data sub-set of interest according to values within a single data dimension. In the cars data-set <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, for example, a user could focus on cars with six cylinders by brushing the respective portion of the cylinders-axis (cf. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref>).</p><p>In our application of visually investigating multidimensional data-sets originating in a physically-based simulation of dynamic processes based on computational fluid dynamics (CFD), we found standard brushing of PC very useful, however, we needed to go further. The requirement was to specify a focus not only in dependence of one data attribute (one dimension), but to do so with respect to at least two of them -like brushing all those data-points whose Þ-velocity is larger than the respective Ü-velocity. The consequence was to introduce a new brushing technique which we call angular brushing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Angular Brushing of Parallel Coordinates</head><p>One strength of PC is its effectiveness of visualizing relations between coordinate axes. Bringing axes next to each other in an interactive way, the user can investigate how values are related to each other with special respect to two of the data dimensions. This way, it is not only possible to see whether data-points exhibit high or low values in single dimensions, but also their relation can be understood. More specifically, the slope of the line-segments between two axes tells the user, whether there is a positive or negative correlation between values (of course assuming that the user set up a proper visualization mapping). Outliers also can be easily found with respect to two data dimensionswhen all but a few line-segments have a positive slope, then the few others clearly stand out (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>).</p><p>In this paper, we demonstrate how this feature of PC easily can be exploited for an extended brushing technique, i.e., angular brushing. In addition to standard brushing, which primarily acts along the (parallel) axes, we enable the space between axes for brushing interaction, as well. The user can interactively specify a sub-set of slopes which then yields all those data-points to be marked as part of the current focus. See <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> for an example, where negative slopes have been marked between the second and third axis.</p><p>Angular brushing as described above is a useful extension to PC, also because it very well corresponds to the effective visual cues provided by PC. In addition to composite brushes which are composed multiple single-axis brushes by the use of logical operators, angular brushes allow the selection of (non-separable) rational properties with respect to two of the data dimensions. When compared to composite brushes by the use of a scatterplot visualization (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 3</ref>), we clearly see that brushes based on logical operators select sub-sets which are aligned with the display axes, whereas angular brushes select sub-sets which are aligned with the diagonals when visualized in a scatter-plot.   Linking and brushing, an example: in a scatter-plot (shown on the left side), smooth brushing was used to mark data-points of low pressure and low velocity; a linked 3D view (on the top right) shows the same data with the brushed data-points high-lighted; thirdly, the PC view (on the lower right) also shows the same data, also high-lighting the brushed sub-set.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Smooth Brushing and Non-Binary DOIs</head><p>tion between focus and context, but allow a multi-valued or even continuous transition, which inherently supports the mental connection between data-points in focus and their context. This corresponds to a degree-of-interest function, which non-binarily maps into the ¼ ½ -range.</p><p>Brushing easily combines with non-binary DOI functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, i.e., when using smoothly delimited brushes <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Thereby, at the brush boundaries, fractional DOI-values are assigned. When composite brushes are composed through the use of logical operators, fuzzy logic is employed to aggregate final DOI-values for every single data-point.</p><p>In conjunction with PC we extend the interactively specified brush by a certain, user-defined percentage to accommodate a smooth gradient of DOI-values at its borders. When combining smooth brushes through logical operators, we apply the Łukasiewicz norm, known from fuzzy logic as a comparably large norm <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, i.e., a norm which (when applied repeatedly) only slowly converges to ¼ and therefore better conserves the transitional DOI-gradients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Implementation</head><p>To deal with real-world data-sets -in our case consisting of ½¼ -½¼ data-points each -we quickly experienced the limitations of a brute-force implementation of parallel coordinates. Especially as we also needed semi-transparency, coloring, and anti-aliased line-segments, load is high on the graphics hardware during PC visualization.</p><p>In the following, we briefly describe some of the approaches we utilized to still provide real-time response: (1.) Coherence is exploited during interaction by re-using as much visual output as possible. If one axis is modified during interaction, for example, line-segments are only redrawn locally. (2.) Progressive rendering provides immediate feedback through a preview-style of rendering, i.e., without anti-aliasing or semi-transparency. As soon as there is time, high-quality results are computed. (3.) Bi-threaded implementation de-couples rendering and interaction. One thread serves the user interface and guarantees interactive response, while the other thread deals with rendering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Application and Results</head><p>In our application, we investigate multi-dimensional datasets which originate in CFD simulations with a dozen of data dimensions, or more. During flow simulation, values like temperature, pressure, velocity, as well as others, are computed for all cells within a detailed CFD grid.</p><p>Parallel coordinates proved to be very useful for data investigation. The interactive character of our implementation allows for fast and flexible data exploration, even when simultaneously investigating multiple dimensions. Linking PC and other types of views (like a 3D SciViz view, cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 4</ref>, top right) and using our brushing features eased data exploration. Also the combination with scatter-plots was found to be useful, primarily because 2D-composite brushes are specified more easily in a scatter-plot.</p><p>Figs. 3 and especially 4 show results of data exploration by the use of PC. The data shown is the result of a simulation of flow through pipes shaped as a T-junction. Flow is coming from the left and the top <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">(Fig. 4, top left)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Summary and Conclusions</head><p>In this paper, we have presented angular brushing as a new technique to effectively select data sub-sets which exhibit a data correlation along two axes. We also showed how smooth brushing can be used, even in combination with composite brushes. More details, more images, a short video, as well as a longer technical report are available via http://www.VRVis.at/vis/.</p><p>We conclude that the worth of a visualization by the use of parallel coordinates increases drastically when interaction features like axis re-ordering, etc., are added.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Many well-known F+C techniques in InfoViz such as fisheye views<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, for example, do not use a discrete distinc----composite brushes ------angular brushes ---AND-brushOR-brush angular brush angular brush, after axis flipping</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Comparing composite brushes (on the left) and angular brushes (on the right), using PC (top row) and scatterplots (bottom row): composite brushes address "horizontal/vertical" features, whereas angular brushes emphasize "diagonal" ones.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Linking and brushing, an example: in a scatter-plot (shown on the left side), smooth brushing was used to mark data-points of low pressure and low velocity; a linked 3D view (on the top right) shows the same data with the brushed data-points high-lighted; thirdly, the PC view (on the lower right) also shows the same data, also high-lighting the brushed sub-set.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Acknowledgements. As (partially) being part of VRVis' basic research on visualization (http://www.VRVis.at/vis/), this work also was funded by K plus (http://www.kplus.at/). The authors also thank AVL.com for providing data as well as Robert Kosara for his valuable hints.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Brushing scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cleveland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="142" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technometrics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smooth brushing for fo-cus+context visualization of simulation data in 3D</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Doleisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of WSCG 2002</title>
		<meeting>of WSCG 2002<address><addrLine>Plzen, Czech Rep</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="154" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized fisheye views</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Furnas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the ACM CHI &apos;86 Conf. on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<meeting>of the ACM CHI &apos;86 Conf. on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WEAVE: A system for visually linking 3-D and statistical visualizations, applied to cardiac simulation and measurement data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gresh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="492" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of parallel coordinates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Inselberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Mathematical Visualization</title>
		<editor>H.-C. Hege and K. Polthier</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="179" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parallel coordinates: a tool for visualizing multidimensional geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Inselberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dimsdale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Visualization &apos;90</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Visualization &apos;90</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="378" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Triangular Norms, volume 8 of Trends in Logic</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klement</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mesiar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<publisher>Kluwer Acad. Publ</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High dimensional brushing for interactive exploration of multivariate data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Visualization &apos;95</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="278" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Vlachos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://lib.stat.cmu.edu/" />
		<title level="m">StaLib -data, software and news from the statistics community</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">XmdvTool: Integrating multiple methods for visualizing multivariate data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Visualization &apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="336" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">524,288 ways to say &quot;this is interesting</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wills</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of IEEE Symp. on Information Visualization</title>
		<meeting>of IEEE Symp. on Information Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="61" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
