<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Virtual Colon Unfolding</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Vilanova Bartrolí</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Rainer</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>König</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">£</forename><forename type="middle">Eduard</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Tiani</forename><surname>Medgraph</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Virtual Colon Unfolding</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Volume Rendering, Virtual Endoscopy</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Figure 1: Outside view and virtual unfolding of a segment of a CT data set of a healthy colon with a resolution of 198x115x300.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The inspection of anatomical cavities using medical imaging (e.g., CT and MRI) and computer visualization techniques is called virtual endoscopy. A real endoscopy is an invasive procedure which involves a certain degree of risk for the patient. In some diagnostic procedures, virtual endoscopy has the potential to be used in clinical routine to avoid the inconvenience of a real endoscopy.</p><p>Most of the developed techniques concentrate on simulating the results that would be obtained with a real endoscope <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>. Although this can be useful in some cases, like in an intraoperative £ email: anna,koenig,meister @cg.tuwien.ac.at, http://www.cg.tuwien.ac.at † email: rainer.wegenkittl @tiani.com, http://www.tiani.com scenario, virtual endoscopy should not constrain itself to simulate the results of a real endoscope. In a virtual environment, without physical limitations, more suitable visualization techniques can be thought of. In this work, we concentrate on virtual colonoscopy, which focuses on the examination of the colon. In the case of diagnosis, the physicians are mainly interested in exploring the inner surface of the organ where polyps might be detected. Large polyps are more likely to develop into malignities than small ones. Usual endoscopic views visualize just a small part of the surface of the organ. Furthermore, it is difficult to detect polyps that are located behind folds. Recently, new methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref> to visualize anatomical cavities (e.g., the colon) have been proposed. These methods allow an efficient inspection of the inner colon surface by opening and unfolding it. In the real world this is not possible, but there is no patient damage involved if this dissection of the organ can be achieved virtually with the medical data obtained by CT or MRI.</p><p>In this paper, we describe a new method to obtain a single image of the entire unfolded colon. The physician can easily detect areas where polyps are located, and additionally get an idea of their shape and size. Afterwards, the physician can concentrate on an exhaustive inspection of the problematic areas. This method proposes solutions to several of the problems that appear in similar previous techniques. Although, in this paper we concentrate on the colon, the technique can be applied to any tubular organ.</p><p>In the next section, we review related work and discuss the differences compared to our method. Section 3 gives an overview of the new approach. Sections 4 and 5 present in detail the main steps of the method. Results are presented in section 6 and conclusions and future work are described in section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Related Work</head><p>Straightforward techniques to unfold an organ <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> start with defining a path which is closely following the center of the cavity.</p><p>Afterwards, a sequence of frames is calculated. For each frame, a cross-section orthogonal to the path is computed. The central path is straightened, and the cross-sections are piled up to form a stack. In the last step the straightened colon is unfolded to obtain a volume model of the unfolded colon. The volume model is displayed using standard volume rendering techniques.</p><p>These methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> allow to visualize the entire surface in a single image. They however encounter a major problem in high curvature areas of the central path, i.e., at path locations where the radius of curvature is larger than the organ diameter. In such cases, orthogonal cross-sections intersect each other or are far apart in other regions (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">figure 2)</ref>. As a consequence, a polyp might appear twice in the flattened model or it can be missed completely. In more recent work, Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> try to overcome this problem. The authors use electrical field lines generated by a locally charged path to generate curved cross-sections instead of the planar sections. The cross-sections tend to diverge avoiding conflicts. If the complete path is charged then the curved cross-sections will not intersect. However, for each point of the field lines the contribution of each charge in the path must be calculated. This operation is so computationally expensive that the authors propose to just locally charge the path. A small segment of the path contains the charges for each cross-section. In this way, the method is feasible in practice, but it cannot ensure that the curved cross-sections will not intersect each other anymore.</p><p>Flattening a polygonal representation of a colon involves tasks that have already been used in texture-mapping techniques. A major step thereby is to come up with a suitable surface parameterization. For texture mapping, this parameterization is used to assign texture values to surface points. For surface flattening the parameterization allows to display surface values (e.g., color) in the 2D parameter space <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. A huge amount of techniques are dealing with texture distortions which in many cases cannot be avoided entirely. The distortions depend on the chosen surface parameterization (e.g., length and area preserving <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, or angle preserving <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> or a combination of both <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>).</p><p>Haker et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> use conformal (i.e., angle preserving) texture mapping to map the polygonal colon surface, colored according to its mean curvature, to a plane. One of the main problems of this method, or any other which directly uses texture-mapping techniques, is that a highly accurate segmentation is necessary to ensure good results for diagnosis. The entire polygonal surface is flat and the result is a triangulated plane where the polyps have also been flattened. The color-coded mean curvature of the extracted surface is the only information which helps the physicians in identifying polyps. Furthermore the surface needs to be smoothed to achieve a good mean-curvature calculation.  Paik et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> propose various types of camera projections for virtual endoscopy. With a typical endoscopic view just 8% of the solid angle of the camera is visible in each frame. Paik et al. project the whole solid angle of the camera by techniques known from cartographic projections. They suggest to use the Mercator projection to map the solid angle to the final image. This technique samples the solid angle of the camera, after which the solid angle is mapped onto a cylinder which is mapped finally to the image.</p><p>In our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, an animation sequence is generated by projecting the organ surface onto a cylinder which is moved along the path. This avoids the appearance of double polyps since intersections can only appear between different frames. Similar to the technique of Paik et al. our previous approach does not provide the physicians with a complete overview of the colon. An entire animation sequence must be inspected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cross-sections c e n t r a l p a t h missed polyp</head><p>All of the unfolding methods introduce some kind of deformation. If two surfaces do not have the same Gaussian curvature there does not exists a mapping which is length, area and angle preserving at the same time.</p><p>In this paper, a method is proposed which produces a complete view of the unfolded colon. It avoids double appearance of polyps and the possibility of missing polyps. In our approach the colon unraveling does not just produce a surface but also a height field (distance of the colon surface to a central path). This avoids that the polyps are flattened as with the methods proposed by Haker et al. The height field gives a more natural visualization than a flattened surface with color-coded mean curvature. In the next sections, this method will be discussed in detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Method Overview</head><p>Our method of unfolding the colon can be divided into two main steps: nonlinear ray casting, which solves the problem of double appearance of polyps, and nonlinear 2D scaling, which improves the nonuniform sampling and avoids to miss polyps.</p><p>The input data of the technique is a segmented volume data set of a colon. The segmentation is needed to find the central path. It is important that the segmentation is conservative. The segmentation mask does not contain any point outside of the colon. The central path is computed by thinning the segmented volume. The path is smoothed, but it is ensured that it does not cross the colon surface. We use the algorithm presented in our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. A distance map is generated from the calculated central path <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. A distance map is a volume data set whose voxels contain the distance to the nearest voxel on the central path.</p><p>A coordinate frame is moved along the path. For each position on the path, rays are traced starting in the plane orthogonal to the path, and following radial directions (constant angle sampling). To avoid double polyp appearance in high curvature areas of the path, the rays follow the negative gradient direction of the precalculated distance map. The rays are not straight lines any more, and they do not cross each other, at most they meet (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">figure 3</ref>). Nonlinear ray casting has already been investigated before <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Section 4 explains how these rays are traced.</p><p>Along each curved ray, the volume is sampled in a uniform way and direct volume rendering is performed. The ray is terminated when it hits the surface of the colon. The result of the nonlinear ray casting can be interpreted as a 2D cylindrical parameterization of the inner colon surface. One parameter corresponds to the position along the path. The second parameter specifies the ray within the plane orthogonal to the current path position. The distances between ray origins on the central path and intersected points on the colon surface determine a height field. The height field is unfolded, and the result corresponds to a parallel projection of the unfolded height field.</p><p>Nonlinear ray casting samples the height field nonuniformly. A straightforward unfolding to a regular grid contains severe area distortions and is therefore not optimal. In the second step an iterative scaling transforms the previously generated 2D parameter grid to compensate for these distortions. After the scaling, the ratios between the area that the samples represent and their area in the 2D grid are approximately equal. The second step is based on nonlinear 2D scaling that is used in a similar way for magnification fields in information visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. In section 5, the algorithm is described in detail. Next, the colon surface is resampled with an almost-uniform sampling rate using the transformed 2D grid.</p><p>In the next section, we describe the major steps of our algorithm in more detail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Nonlinear Ray Casting</head><p>The curve c´vµ, which represents the central path of the colon, is calculated using thinning and the smoothing algorithm presented in our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. In order to trace the nonlinear rays, a distance map Dist´pµ of a point p to the central path c´vµ is computed. Dist´pµ is calculated in discrete space. Dist´pµ is a volume data set that contains for each voxel the minimum distance to the path. A reconstruction filter is used to approximate the distance map in continuous space dist´pµ.</p><p>For the calculation of Dist´pµ, a minor modification of the Euclidean distance transformation presented by Lohmann <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> is used. The modified distance transformation saves for each voxel the vector vDist´pµ from the voxel to the closest central path point, Dist´pµ vDist´pµ . Using this information, the distance map dist´pµ in any point p ¾ IR 3 is defined using the following re-</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">construction function. dist´pµ min´ p i • vDist´p i µ p µ i 0 i 7 p i ¾ IN 3</formula><p>where p i represent the eight vertices of the cell that contains p. This reconstruction gives the exact value when one of the eight neighbors p i has the same closest curve point as p. Trilinear interpolation of the scalar values Dist´p i µ gives a good performance when the distance map has a linear behavior, which happens just in some special cases. The nonlinear rays are traced from the central path in uphill direction, i.e., along the negative gradient direction, ∇dist´pµ, of the distance map dist´pµ. dist´pµ is continuous in the first derivative nearly everywhere, except for ridge and valley lines. The distance map dist´pµ induces a vectorfield ∇dist´pµ which is defined by the gradient of the distance map. It is known that trajectories of such vectorfields will not cross each other and are unambiguous (see Abraham et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> for details). These trajectories will correspond to our nonlinear rays. Furthermore, in our situation, they will not produce cycles, since it is impossible to return to the same point if you always move uphill. In the worst case, the nonlinear rays will merge in ridge and valley lines, but they will not cross. With these curved rays the appearance of double polyps is avoided and an unambiguous and correct parameterization of the colon inner surface is obtained. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Casting of Nonlinear Rays</head><p>The first step to trace the nonlinear rays is to move a coordinate frame along the curve c´vµ. The frame is moved using a minimalrotation frame (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> for more details). For each position on the path, a constant number of rays is traced. The initial point of each ray is placed in the plane orthogonal to the path. Note that the gradient is not defined along the path c´vµ since it is a valley line of the distance map dist´pµ. Therefore, the initial points are located in a circular arrangement at a small distance from the path position.</p><p>Once the initial points have been determined (u parameterization), the rays are traced incrementally following the negative gradient of the distance map (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">figure 4)</ref>. The rays have the tendency to be perpendicular to the path c´vµ since it is the direction of maximal change of dist´pµ in linear segments of the path. The rays become curved in areas where the curvature of the path increases (see figure 3 and 4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Colon Surface Parameterization</head><p>In the previous section, nonlinear and especially non-crossing rays were traced from the central path c´vµ towards the colon surface. While the rays are traced, direct volume rendering is performed. The ray terminates when the colon surface is hit. The result of the nonlinear ray casting is a sampling of the inner surface of the organ.</p><p>The tracing of the nonlinear rays defines an unambiguous parameterization of the inner colon surface s´u vµ. Here, v is the parameter along the central path c´vµ, and u is the radial angle along which the nonlinear rays are started (u ¾ 0 2π ). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 5</ref> shows s´u vµ which results from applying nonlinear ray casting to a piece of the colon. The lines correspond to the isolines of the parametric surface s´u vµ. The parameter space is sampled uniformly in the u and v direction, but this does not correspond to a uniform sampling of s´u vµ.</p><p>Unfolding of the s´u vµ surface can easily be done by mapping s´u vµ onto a regular grid in the 2D u v-parameter space. In figure 6a a parameterization of the colon surface is done with straight rays (ambiguous, non-uniform sampling). In figure 6b, a parameterization of the colon surface is done with curved rays ( unambiguous, but still non-uniform sampling). Nonlinear ray casting avoids that features appear more than once, but on the other hand the sampling of the surface is far from being uniform. There are oversampled areas, which lead to geometric deformations, and also undersampled areas. In the latter case, deformations appear but also features of the surface can be missed. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6a</ref> is the result of unfolding the colon surface to a regular grid using straight rays (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">figure 2)</ref>. The solid circles indicate areas where features appear more than once. Using nonlinear ray casting, the double polyps disappear, and instead an enlargement of the feature appears. The areas encircled with dashed circles indicate undersampled areas and therefore areas where features are possibly missed. Note that the same undersampled areas are present in both figures.</p><p>In the next section, an algorithm is presented to obtain an unfolding of the parametric surface s´u vµ which avoids geometric deformations and to miss features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Nonlinear 2D Scaling</head><p>In the previous section, an unambiguous parameterization of the inner colon surface projected to the central path has been introduced. The sampling of the surface s´u vµ defines a quadrilateral mesh on the colon surface (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">figure 5)</ref>. The curved rays generated by the nonlinear ray casting do not intersect, therefore, the resulting quadrilateral mesh is valid and also not self intersecting. Furthermore, the distance between the surface point s´u vµ and the corresponding path position c´vµ defines a height field r´u vµ.</p><p>The goal of nonlinear 2D scaling is to achieve a 2D grid which approximates a parallel projection of the unfolded height field defined by the nonlinear ray casting. We desire that the unfolded height field preserves the length of the edges of s´u vµ in u and v direction and, therefore, we also preserve the area. In section 5.1, we define the length of the edges of the 2D grid to achieve the area preservation. Section 5.2 describes the iterative algorithm which yields a 2D grid with such edge lengths. If r´u vµ has a high value (i.e., s´u vµ is far from the center) the object shrinks. If r´u vµ has a small value (i.e., s´u vµ is close to the center), the object is enlarged. This is since the area that the samples represent depends on their distance to the central path and is not constant as is assumed by mapping them to a regular grid.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Height field unfolding</head><p>From the 3D quadrilateral mesh obtained in the nonlinear ray casting, we know the distances between adjacent quadrilateral vertices (i.e., the length of the edges of the quadrilateral). If these distances are preserved in the 2D grid, the sizes of the quadrilaterals will be preserved. <ref type="figure">Figure 7c</ref> shows the result of preserving the 3D edges of the quadrilateral mesh that corresponds to figure 7a. Note that geometric deformations also appear. In this method, we flatten the surface and the polyps. This is due to the fact that we do not take the height field into account. We do not want that the 2D grid has the same edges as the 3D quadrilateral grid, but we want that the edges of the unfolded height field have the same length as the edges of the 3D quadrilateral mesh (see <ref type="figure">figure 7d)</ref>. This implies that the distance between edges in the 2D grid should correspond to the length a that each sample represents in u and v directions. To calculate the edge lengths, we use different approximations for the u and v direction. For simplicity, we define w i j as a point in parametric space´u i v j µ (u i is the ith sampled parameter value in the u direction and v j the jth in the v direction). In the u direction (see <ref type="figure">figure 7d)</ref>, each sample represents a length approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">a´w i j µ 2 £tan α 2 £r´w i j µ</formula><p>where α is the angle between the straight rays from the path to s´w i j µ and s´w i•1 j µ. For simplicity, we illustrate in figure 7d the case where the angle α is the same between consecutive rays. In general, α is not constant due to the nonlinear rays. The edge distance between two consecutive samples in the u direction is approximated by</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">e´w i j w i•1 j µ a´w i µ • a´w i•1 j µ 2<label>(1)</label></formula><p>This equation cannot be used for the v direction since angle α is not defined. Therefore, in the v direction the following expression is used the distance due to the difference in height (i.e., the distance from the sampled point to the central path) of the two samples.</p><p>Using equations 1 and 2, we have defined the length of the edges of the 2D grid such that the unfolded height field preserves the length of the edges of s´u vµ in u and v direction. In the next section, an algorithm to obtain such a 2D grid is presented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Nonlinear 2D scaling</head><p>The objective of the nonlinear 2D scaling algorithm is to generate a 2D grid whose edges preserve the length of the edges calculated by e´w i j w k l µ (see equation 1 and 2). To find an analytical solution to the problem is too complex, so a numerical solution is adopted. To generate such a grid we use an approach similar to the one presented by Keahey et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. The main difference is that the new algorithm not only preserves areas, but also the edge lengths.</p><p>A transformation of a 2D regular grid is defined by function T´i jµ : IN <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> IR <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> . T´i jµ has to be C 0 -continuous and it should preserve the order (i.e., no edge or grid node flipping). For</p><p>T´i jµ x yµ and T´k lµ x ¼ y ¼ µ the condition to preserve the order is defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">i k´µ x x ¼ j l´µ y y ¼ (3)</formula><p>We define a 2D scaling field S as a field of scalar values for each edge. Each scalar value indicates the scaling factor that a transformation T has applied to the edge. The 2D scaling field S for an edge defined between T´i jµ and T´k lµ is S´i j k lµ :</p><p>T´i jµ T´k lµ . A 2D scaling field S is defined for any transformation T.</p><p>The goal of the nonlinear 2D scaling algorithm is to find a transformation T g such that for all values of i and j the equation e´w i j w k l µ T g´i jµ T g´k lµ holds, where w k l is a 4connected neighbor of w i j . In other words, we want to find a transformation T g whose 2D scaling field is S g´i j k lµ e´w i j w k l µ (see equations 1 and 2) for each edge of the grid.</p><p>The major problem is to find the coordinates´x yµ of the transformation T g , given the scalar values of the 2D scaling field S g . It is clear that for the same 2D scaling field several transformations are possible.</p><p>We have used an iterative method which provides a numerical solution. The goal of the algorithm is to find a transformation T a that provides a good approximation of T g .</p><p>Given a transformation T a , the corresponding scaling field can be easily calculated by S a´i j k lµ T a´i jµ T a´k lµ . A scaling field error can then be computed by S e S g S a . S e gives the difference between the computed scaling field S a and the desired scaling field S g .</p><p>The iterative algorithm starts with T a as a regular grid. Then S a and S e are calculated. The algorithm iterates over each node of the grid. For each node, the value of S e at each of the 4connected neighbors is investigated. If S e 0 (i.e., the edge is not long enough) then the neighbor is moved away from the node . If S e 0 (i.e., the edge is too long) then the neighbor is pulled towards the node. The edge is modified by a length of S e´i j k lµ£C r 2 where C r ¾ 0 1 is a parameter of the algorithm. The division by 2 is necessary because each edge is treated twice, once for each limit node of the edge. Changing an edge is thus done by modifying each of its limit nodes. An important requirement of the algorithm is to preserve the order. So the neighbors are moved as far as S e and C r allow without violating equation 3.</p><p>The neighboring nodes are changed with coordinate-aligned movements. The movements correspond to the original orientation of the edges in the regular grid (i.e., horizontal and vertical). The movement is computed such that the resulting edge has the expected length determined by S e and C r . These movements have the tendency to preserve the rectangular appearance of the quadrilateral defined by</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">T a´i jµ T a´i • 1 jµ T a´i • 1 j • 1µ T a´i j • 1µ ,</formula><p>which, for example, does not degenerate to a triangle.</p><p>Once the iteration has run for all the nodes, the new T a is generated. Then, a new S a and a new S e are calculated from the resulting T a . S e is calculated just once per iteration.</p><p>The algorithm's convergence depends on the complexity of the scaling field S g and the value of C r . If C r 0, no movement will occur. If C r 1, the neighbors will be moved the maximum possible displacement. This can make the convergence faster, but can also lead the approximation to a state where the algorithm does not converge at all. A trade-off between speed and quality has to be made in defining the value of C r .</p><p>The convergence factor is measured using the distance between the approximated scaling field S a and the desired 2D scaling field S g . This is expressed as the root mean squared error σ of S e . Given a grid of size n ¢m the convergence factor σ is defined as follows. occurs anymore.</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">σ Ú Ù Ù Ù Ø m 1 ∑ j 0 n 2 ∑ i 0 S e´i j i • 1 jµ 2 • m 2 ∑ j 0 n 1 ∑ i 0 S e´i j i j • 1µ</formula><p>The convergence of the algorithm can be improved by starting with a T a which is a closer approximation of the desired result than a regular grid. The length of the edges within a horizontal line (i.e., the horizontal edges between nodes with the same j value) are set such that the line approximates the perimeter of the colon in the corresponding cross-section (i.e., ∑ n 2</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">i 0 S g´i j i•1 jµ n 1</formula><p>). The distance between two consecutive horizontal lines is set to the average of the vertical edge lengths in S g which join the nodes between the two lines (i.e., ∑ n 1</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">i 0 S g´i j i j•1µ n</formula><p>). Starting with this modified grid leads to a faster convergence by generating basically the same result as a regular grid would give.</p><p>The pseudocode to illustrate the presented algorithm is given below.</p><p>proc NonLinear2DScaling( in:</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">2DScalingField S g ,float C r , out: 2DTransformation T a )</formula><p>2DScalingField S a ; 2DScalingField S e ; boolean bNoEnd;</p><p>T a = IntialGrid(S g ); S a = Calculate2DScalingField(T a ); S e = S a S g ; σ = CalculateRootMeanSquare(S e ); bNoEnd = FinishApproximation(σ);</p><p>while (bNoEnd) forall T a´i jµ MoveNeighbors(T a ,i, j,S e ,C r ); S a = Calculate2DScalingField(T a ); S e = S a S g ; σ = CalculateRootMeanSquare(S e ); bNoEnd = FinishApproximation(σ); <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8a</ref> shows the initial grid T a for the segment of the colon presented in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">figure 5</ref>. The resolution of the grid is 128x171 and the initial value of σ is 0 8008. After 960 iterations T a has been evolved into the grid in figure 8b. The value of σ is 0 2808. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8c</ref> is the result of the algorithm after 1687 iterations. The grids of figures 8b and 8c are similar. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">figure 8c</ref>, the value of σ is 0 2650. Once the nonlinear 2D scaling has been performed, we obtain a parallel projection of the unfolded height field to a 2D grid preserving the edge lengths. This avoids geometry deformation due to the nonuniform sampling. In the next section, a method to resample the undersampled areas and to detect possible missing features is presented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Resampling</head><p>The nonlinear 2D scaling provides a mapping between the 3D quadrilateral mesh and a 2D grid avoiding geometric deformations. The color of each ray obtained in the nonlinear ray casting step is assigned to its corresponding node in the 2D grid. Bilinear interpolation is used to fill the quadrilaterals of the grid. An example can be seen in figure 9a. The areas encircled by dashed ellipses are the same as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">figure 6</ref>. Some features are missing due to undersampling.</p><p>The undersampled areas are easily identifiable from the 2D grid. A minimum sample step h for the 2D grid is defined. The sample step corresponds directly to a sample step in the 3D space. A quadrilateral is subdivided if at least one of its edges is longer than h. For a quadrilateral, the subdivision consists in generating a subgrid whose edge lengths are smaller or equal to h. The result of subdividing the quadrilaterals of a grid can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">figure 9b</ref>.</p><p>The resulting subdivided grid has assigned color values just in the nodes of the original quadrilateral. Therefore a resampling of the colon surface has to be done for each of the newly generated nodes. Each point in the grid can easily be identified with its corresponding point in 3D using linear interpolation. The 3D points do not correspond to surface points, but they are close to the colon surface. Therefore, curved rays are traced several steps backwards following the nonlinear ray casting algorithm. Then the rays are traced forward again to find the correct surface point. The color of the sampled point is determined by the same procedure as described in section 4.</p><p>The resulting color values are mapped directly to the corresponding point in the 2D grid. The results of the resampling procedure can be seen in </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Results</head><p>In this section, we describe the results of applying virtual colon unfolding to several data sets.</p><p>One data set is a CT volume data of an extracted colon with a resolution of 381x120x632 (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">figure 10)</ref>. The colon is 50 cm long and contains 13 polyps. These polyps have a size between 3.5x2.5 mm and 11.8x9.0 mm. The results of the unfolding procedure for this colon can be seen in color plate 1 left. All the polyps could be easily detected by inspection. The extracted colon was physically dissected and several pictures of the dissected colon were also taken. These pictures enable a qualitative comparison between the real data and the results of the presented algorithm (see color plate 1 right).</p><p>A second data set is a segment of the extracted colon with a resolution of 190x120x150. This data set has been used throughout the paper to illustrate the algorithm. It corresponds to the right-bottom picture of color plate 1 and contains three polyps.</p><p>The third data set is from a CT data set of a healthy colon segment with a resolution of 198x115x300. The unfolding of the data set and an outside view can be seen in figure 1. This colon is healthy, so no polyps could be found after the unfolding.</p><p>For videos and further images please refer to:</p><p>www.cg.tuwien.ac.at/research/vis/vismed/ColonUnfolding/. <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> shows the calculation times of the presented method on a Pentium II (400MHz). The timings correspond to preprocessing time. Once the method has been executed the physician can inspect the resulting overview image interactively. The table is divided into three parts. The first part presents the timings obtained from generating the nonlinear rays and doing direct volume rendering. The timings depend on the resolution of the sampling, i.e., the number of samples taken in the u and v direction, and the data set resolution.</p><p>The middle part of the table shows the timings of the nonlinear 2D scaling algorithm. The convergence speed of the algorithm depends basically on the grid resolution, the value of C r and σ (i.e., the precision achieved by the unfolding). In the first two data sets the increase of C r produces a reduction of the convergence rate while for the healthy colon it improves. The value of C r has to be tuned for each data set.</p><p>The last column in table 1 gives timings concerning the resampling process. The times depend basically on the sampling step of the grid and the difference between the original grid and the resampled grid (i.e., number of resampling points). We present the times with a resampling step h of 0.5 and 1.0 times the size of a voxel in 3D space.</p><p>The time of the entire process depends on the data set and the precision of the result. In total, the time of the whole process, including the distance map calculation, is in the range of hours. This is, however, preprocessing time. Once the computation has been done, the resulting 2D grid can be inspected interactively by the physician. The result can be seen like an overview map. If suspicious areas are identified they can be inspected more carefully using other tools like cross-sections of the original data set or conventional rendering of the region in question.</p><p>Experiments have shown that the algorithm is quite sensitive to the smoothness of path c´vµ. For a good result, it is important that the path is smooth and has as many linear segments as possible.</p><p>The nonlinear ray casting produces a problem that occurs when a ridge line of distance map dist´pµ is inside the colon. Then, there will be rays that never reach the surface of the colon. Although, this case never appeared in the tested data sets, a solution to this situation has to be studied. A possible solution would be to combine the central path distance map with the colon surface distance map.</p><p>In the presented algorithm just the areas that are directly projected to the central path are taken into account. Areas which are behind mushroom-like folds are not visualized. Using more than one surface point per ray, could solve the problem of occluded areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Conclusions and Future Work</head><p>In this paper, a new unfolding method to inspect cavity organs, e.g., the colon has been presented. The goal is to enable the physician to inspect and get as much information as possible of the inner organ surface at a first glance. The problematic areas can be identified quickly and inspected afterwards in more detail. The presented approach solves the problem of double appearance of polyps using nonlinear ray casting. Compensation of distortions due to the unfolding of the colon is achieved using an iterative method called nonlinear 2D scaling which is similar to nonlinear magnification fields used in information visualization. Finally, a method is presented to resample areas where features have been missed due to undersampling. The methods have been tested with several data sets. One of them enabled a qualitative comparison of the resulting images with images of the corresponding extracted colon.  <ref type="table">Table 1</ref>: Calculation times depending on the different parameters of the algorithm. The times are calculated using a Pentium II CPU (400MHz).</p><p>Improvements of the method in the case of ridge lines inside the colon and occluded areas due to mushroom-like folds are subject of future work.</p><p>The current implementation of the algorithm has not been optimized so there is room for temporal improvement. Although the virtual unfolding is a preprocessing step, there is a need to accelerate it to facilitate parameter tuning.</p><p>Once the physicians have detected a polyp, they are interested in going back to the original volume data and inspect it using other visualization techniques like perspective volume rendering or multiplanar reconstruction. An application allowing such an inspection must be developed using the relation between the points in the 2D unfolded map and 3D volume data.</p><p>The nonlinear 2D scaling step unfolds the colon with area preservation. This allows the physicians to estimate the sizes of the polyps. However, the shape is not preserved as the angles are not preserved. Methods for preservation of the angles or a combination of angle and area preservation will be subject of future study.</p><p>The presented method has shown promising results, and it should be tested with more data sets of real pathological cases. The algorithm is not restricted to the colon alone. It has the potential of being used for other tubular organ as well.  Color Plate 1: Left Virtually unfolded extracted colon with the polyps numbered according to the real dissection. Right top and middle qualitative comparison of the virtually unfolded colon with pictures taken from the real dissection. Right bottom image corresponding to the segment of the extracted colon data set which was used throughout this paper as example. The orientation in which the pictures were taken does not correspond to the orientation of the virtually unfolded colon.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Possible undersampling and double appearance of polyps due to intersections of the cross-sections in high curvature areas. The dashed cross-section line produces a double appearance of a polyp.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Elimination of double polyp appearance by nonlinear ray casting.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Nonlinear rays traced from a specific position along the path c´vµ: a) the curved rays in areas of high curvature for two consecutive points along c´vµ, b) nonlinear rays traced in u direction.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Surface obtained after nonlinear ray casting. The sampling of the surface is nonuniform.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>7a is an illustration of a cross-section of the height field for a given value of v. The unfolding of the height field r´u vµ in figure 7a to a 2D regular grid is shown in figure 7b. The parallel projection of the unfolded height field corresponds to the mapping of the surface s´u vµ presented in section 4.2. The edges in the 2D grid have a constant length e. The unfolded object is locally scaled depending on the height-field value r´u vµ.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>a) Unfolding of the colon surface of the data set presented in figure 5 using straight rays. Solid circles indicate double polyp appearance areas. Dashed circles indicate undersampled areas. b) unfolding of the parametric surface generated using nonlinear rays shown in figure 5, by mapping the parametric space to a regular grid. Double polyps disappear, but undersampled areas not.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>l j r´w i j µ•r´w i j•1 µ 2 m j k c´v k µ • s´w i k µ c´v k µ r´w i k µ £l j ( 2 ) e´w i j w i j•1 µ m j j m j j• 1 Figure 7 :</head><label>2217</label><figDesc>If the rays are parallel, equation 2 results in the projection of the edge between two samples to the central path (see figure 7e). Equation 2 approximates the distance between two samples subtracting Illustration of height field unfolding in u direction: a) cross-section of r´u vµ for a fixed value of v, b) unfolding to a regular grid, c) unfolding preserving the edge lengths b i of the 3D quadrilateral mesh in the 2D grid, and d) unfolding preserving the edge lengths b i of the 3D quadrilateral mesh in the height field. e) Unfolding in the v direction.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>2 2nm n mThe algorithm terminates, if σ becomes smaller than a defined constant or if after several iterations no considerable improvement aIllustration of the nonlinear 2D scaling algorithm using the same data set as infigure 5. a) Initial T a corresponding to a 128x171 grid. b) T a after 960 iterations of the algorithm. c) T a after 1687 iterations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc>figure 9c. The encircled areas show regions where features that were not present in figure 9 have been identified. Resampling after the nonlinear 2D scaling. a) 128x171 shaded grid using bilinear interpolation. b) the resulting grid of the nonlinear 2D scaling after resampling c) Shading of the resampled grid.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 10 :</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Outside view of the segmented surface of the extracted colon CT data set with resolution 381x120x632.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The work presented in this publication has been funded by the V is M ed project. V is M ed is supported by Tiani Medgraph, Vienna (http://www.tiani.com), and the Forschungsförderungsfonds für die gewerbliche Wirtschaft, Austria.</p><p>We thank Dr. Erich Sorantin from the Department of Radiology in Graz for his collaboration and for providing the data sets used in this paper and the images of the dissected colon.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Dynamics: The Geometry of Behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Piecewise surface flattening for nondistorted texture mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vézien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Iglésias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH&apos;91</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="246" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Parametrization and smooth approximation of surface triangulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Floater</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Aided Geometric Design</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="250" />
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nonlinear ray tracing: Visualizing strange worlds. The Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="274" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conformal surface parameterization for texture mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Angenent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Halle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nondistorting flattening maps and the 3D visualization of colon CT images</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Angenent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Allen</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kikinis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. on Biomedical Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="665" to="671" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual voyage: Interactive navigation in the human colon</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Muraki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH&apos;97, Annual Conference series</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="34" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear magnification fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keahey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="58" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-distorted texture mapping for sheared triangulated meshes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lévy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mallet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH&apos;98</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="352" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Volumetric Image Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lohmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Chichester Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization modes for CT colonography using cylindrical and planar map projections</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Paik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Beaulieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Jeffrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jr</forename><forename type="middle">C A</forename><surname>Karadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Napel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Computer Tomography</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="188" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Texture mapping and distortion in digital graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Samek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Slean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Weghorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Visual Computer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">MEDICAL RADIOLOGY -Diagnostic Imaging, chapter Technique of Virtual Dissection of the Colon based on Spiral CT data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sorantin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Balogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vilanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bartrolí</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Palágyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nyúl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Loncaric</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Subasic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Kovaćević</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<publisher>Springer Verlag Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cylindrical approximation of tubular organs for virtual endoscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bartrolí</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>König</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Computer Graphics and Imaging</title>
		<meeting>Computer Graphics and Imaging</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IASTED/ACTA Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="289" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virtual colon flattening</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bartrolí</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wegenkittl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>König</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sorantin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">VisSym &apos;01 Joint Eurographics -IEEE TCVG Symposium on Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="136" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume rendering based interactive navigation within the human colon</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wax</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization &apos;99</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="400" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Colon unraveling based on electrical field: Recent progress and further work</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcfarland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Vannier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999-05" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">3660</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="132" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GI tract unraveling with curved cross sections</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcfarland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Vannier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. on Medical Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GI tract unraveling by spiral CT</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Vannier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings SPIE</title>
		<meeting>SPIE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">2434</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="315" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
