<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Transport and Anisotropic Diffusion in Time-Dependent Flow Visualization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bürkle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">San Diego Paradise Point Resort</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Preußer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">San Diego Paradise Point Resort</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">¡</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rumpf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">San Diego Paradise Point Resort</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Transport and Anisotropic Diffusion in Time-Dependent Flow Visualization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>flow visualization</term>
					<term>multiscale image processing</term>
					<term>nonlinear diffusion</term>
					<term>transport diffusion</term>
					<term>upwind method</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The visualization of time-dependent flow is an important and challenging topic in scientific visualization. Its aim is to represent transport phenomena governed by time-dependent vector fields in an intuitively understandable way, using images and animations. Here we pick up the recently presented anisotropic diffusion method, expand and generalize it to allow a multiscale visualization of longtime, complex transport problems. Instead of streamline type patterns generated by the original method now streakline patterns are generated and advected. This process obeys a nonlinear transport diffusion equation with typically dominant transport. Starting from some noisy initial image, the diffusion actually generates and enhances patterns which are then transported in the direction of the flow field. Simultaneously the image is again sharpened in the direction orthogonal to the flow field. A careful adjustment of the modelś parameters is derived to balance diffusion and transport effects in a reasonable way. Properties of the method can be discussed for the continuous model, which is solved by an efficient upwind finite element discretization. As characteristic for the class of multiscale image processing methods, we can in advance select a suitable scale for representing the flow field.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Time-dependent flow is still one of the challenging topics concerning its efficient computation as well as its effective visualization. The typically different local scales in a single data set and the fact that the motion itself is related to an integration of the given velocity field rather than to the field itself had stimulated many different solution strategies.</p><p>In the last decade various methods for the visualization of flow fields and interesting flow features have been presented. The spot noise method proposed by van Wijk <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> and its later extension <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref> uses a blending of many spot like texture splats aligned by deformation to the velocity field in 2D or on surfaces in 3D. The Line Integral Convolution (LIC) approach of Cabral and Leedom <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> integrates a white noise along particle lines making use of the accompanying strong correlation of the resulting intensities along streamlines. This method has been extended in various directions <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. Other texture based methods are discussed by Max et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, Max and Becker <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, Becker and Rumpf <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Weinstein et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> have presented a method for advection diffusion based propagation through tensor fields.</p><p>Most of the methods presented so far have in common, that the generation of a coarser scale requires a re-computation. Timedependent flow fields, which will be our main focus here, have been discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref> and an animated version of LIC is given by ¢ Institut für Angewandte Mathematik, Freiburg University, Hermann-Herder-Str. 10, 76104 Freiburg, Germany, buerkle@math.uni-freiburg.de £ Fachbereich Mathematik, Duisburg University, Lotharstraße 65, 47048 Duisburg, Germany, [ preusser, rumpf ]@math.uni-duisburg. <ref type="bibr">de</ref> Shen and Kao <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. For further references we refer to <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and the bibliography given there.</p><p>Here, we will extend previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> on image processing methodology applied to the visualization of flow fields. This method was based on the solution of an anisotropic diffusion problem with an anisotropy strongly aligned to the flow field. Diffusion type methods are popular methods in image processing and go back to the early work of Perona and Malik <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. Theoretically this class of methods has been studied by Alvarez, Guichard, Lions and Morel <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, Kawohl and Kutev <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, and others. Anisotropic diffusion was introduced by Weickert <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Appropriate finite element discretization and its convergence properties have been studied by Kačur and Mikula <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Now, for time-dependent flow fields we generate a flow aligned texture, which moves continuously with the flow. Especially in an animation, the underlying transport will intuitively be visualized on a previously selected scale of resolution. Thus, instead of a diffusion problem we now solve a transport diffusion equation. The equation models the underlying motion and the diffusion together with a suitable source term on the right hand side. This leads to the generation of a flow aligned pattern. Qualitative properties of the method are studied on the level of the continuous model. Finally, a finite element discretization in space and a semi implicit upwind scheme in time are applied to solve this problem numerically.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Reviewing the Anisotropic Diffusion Method</head><p>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> a method based on anisotropic diffusion is presented which allows to build a texture representing a given steady state flow field globally on the spatial domain. This method, which will be briefly reviewed in this section, generates streamline like patterns and in addition carries the possibility to successively coarsen those patterns. Thereby we pick up the line integral convolution (LIC) approach as proposed by Cabral and Leedom <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> using the observation that the built in convolution along streamlines corresponds to solving the heat equation on the streamlines. The desired coarsening will be steered by a Perona Malik <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> type diffusion that acts in the direction orthogonal to the flow field.</p><p>To be more precise, let</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">¤ ¦ ¥ § ©</formula><p>be a given vector field on a domain § , which we assume to be continuous and non vanishing on §</p><p>. Clearly there exists a family of orthogonal mappings</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">" ! # ¥ § $ © &amp; % ( ' ) 0 1 ! such that 2 3 ! 4 ¤ " 3 ! 6 5 8 7 @ 9</formula><p>, where </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">U ¤ d c Q V e X ! f 5 g 2 3 ! i h p r q t s u ¤ " 3 ! v s I ! w w x y t s v V Y X à T s I ! I d @ R 1 S 2 3 ! u c</formula><p>with e.g.</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">x y W C ! 5 C v " c Y c</formula><p>and solve the parabolic boundary initial value problem b X instead of a scalar diffusion provides additional asymptotic states of the process. We then select the corresponding initial data randomly distributed within the cube   : Three different time-steps of a convective flow visualized by the anisotropic diffusion method for steady flow fields, which nicely represent the vector fields but not the underlying timedependent motion. Thereby, the resulting pattern is directed along streamlines. Cf. <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref> for streakline type pattern generated by the new transport diffusion method corresponding to the same timesteps.</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">V Y X I ¤ e div U ¤ d c t V e X b t ! Q V Y X d ! ( 5 f e T g X d ! in i h k j l §</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">A Transport Diffusion Model</head><p>The above reviewed anisotropic diffusion method generates streamline type patterns, which are aligned to trajectories of the vector field for a fixed given time. I. e. for a time-dependent vector field</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">¤ ¥ f h j § © on a computational domain § and 5 a c t , we consider integral lines A C W C ! 3 Q s D with u W C ! 5 g ¤ " g m u c Q W C ! Q ! for fixed m</formula><p>. Thus, the method intuitively visualizes the vector field freezed at time m but offers only very limited insight in the actual transport process governed by the underlying time-dependent flow field.</p><p>To ensure that our visualization actually displays this process we have to consider the true transport problem and its particle lines respectively. Hence we take into account the particle motion obeying the equation</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">g m Q ! y 5 n ¤ " g m u c Q g m t ! Q !</formula><p>and the induced transport of a given density</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">X 3 g m u c Q 3 !</formula><p>. Due to the fact that such a purely advected density X stays constant along particle trajectories, i. e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">X 3 g m I c i g m t ! Q ! ( 5 r X V Y X I ¤ b ! I g m I c Q g m Q ! Q !</formula><p>we finally obtain as a conservation law the vanishing of the material derivative</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">q m X 2 ¥5 m X V Y X I ¤ ) 5 g w ¡</formula><p>The material derivative will later play a crucial role concerning our choice for a proper discretization. Furthermore, we have to incorporate a mechanism for the generation, the growth and enhancement of flow aligned patterns. Here we pick up the previous model and consider a simultaneous anisotropic nonlinear diffusion process with linear diffusion along the particle line and sharpening in the perpendicular direction. Let us emphasize here, that this diffusion process acts in forward and backward direction of the particle line. Thus, a careful control of the parameters is indispensable to avoid an artificial propagation in downwind direction with the accompanying visual impression of a wrong velocity. In Section 4 we will discuss in detail a suitable balance of parameters and in Section 5 a modified approach will be presented which copes with this problem in a slightly different way. Finally, our basic transport diffusion model for time-dependent vector fields looks as follows: On the computational domain § we consider for a given vector field ¤ ¢ ¥ ( i h g j § 8 © the boundary and initial value problem:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">b X V Y X I ¤ e div U ¤ d c t V e X b t ! Q V Y X d ! £ 5 ¤ e T g X d ! in h j § 6 c U V e X d ! T ¦ ¥ 2 5 g w on h j § 6 c X 3 p w a c v ! f 5 X 9 in § 6 c where U ¤ d c V e X b Q !</formula><p>is the diffusion tensor already known from the anisotropic diffusion for steady flow fields</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">U ¤ d c t V e X b t ! 5 g 2 3 !h p r q t s ¤ 3 s v ! w w x y W V e X v ¤ b ! I d C R T S 2 3 ! u c</formula><p>in the flow aligned coordinate system. Initial data X b 9</p><p>is again assumed to be a white noise of appropriate frequency. Still the role of the right hand side e is to ensure contrast enhancement. Thus we assume functions e which fulfill the properties mentioned in Section 2.</p><p>The new model generates and stretches patterns along the flow field and transports them simultaneously. The resulting motion texture is characterized by a dense coverage of the domain with streakline type patterns, which do not have a fixed injection point but move in time with the fluid (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figures 3 and 6</ref>). At least at the head of the patterns the enhancement direction is orthogonal to the stretching direction of the corresonding streaklines.</p><p>In case of inflow boundary conditions we have to ensure the same scale of patterns close to the inflow. Unfortunately, such a pattern needs to be transported into the domain from outside. Therefore we enlarge the computational domain, extrapolate the velocity, compute the transport diffusion problem and finally extract a region of interest from the enlarged computational domain.</p><p>As already mentioned in the introduction, the new model comes along with an image processing multiscale of successively sharper and coarser images in time -typically represented by a separate time in the corresponding diffusion problem -and the actual time corresponding to the underlying transport process. Fixing the process time and varying the scale we are back at the original anisotropic diffusion method for steady vector fields. Identifying process time and scale parameter -as we propose here -we end up with a pattern advection method but the resulting images correspond to successively coarser scales. The ideal case would be to fix the scale and vary the process time only. Unfortunately this is not possible within the scope of our method. Nevertheless we can prescribe a suitable scale interval and apply a blending technique, where we select from different transport diffusion problems with temporal overlap always those, which correspond to a given scale range. Compare Section 7 for details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Balancing Parameters</head><p>In general, transport and diffusion are contrary processes. Our goal in mind -the generation and transport of patterns which simultaneously diffuse along the flows, there has to be a careful weighting of the parameters that steer the transport and the diffusion respectively. Otherwise the diffusion may overrun the transport, resulting in a process that is rather diffusion than transport with some pattern generating diffusion.</p><p>It is well known that the solution of the heat equation at a time m corresponds to the convolution of the initial data with a Gaussian kernel of variance § ¦ m</p><p>. Since the diffusion tensor </p><formula xml:id="formula_12">U ¤ b ! invokes linear diffusion with a coefficient q t s ¤ " 3 ! v s v</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U</head><p>of our transport diffusion model. Furthermore, let us study the amplification of certain frequencies of the initial image due to the right hand side of our model. Our focus will be on the influence of the shape of e T i ! on the constrast enhancing property of the model. To this end let us consider a much simpler setting of a high frequency initial data given by  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Generating directed patterns</head><p>The above discussed balancing of parameters with respect to a dominated transport does not completely diminish diffusion effects downstream. At least at the head of the evolving pattern a slight modification of the proposed model helps to avoid this misleading drawback. Hence, we incorporate a "one-sided" diffusion related to our model for flow segmentation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. I. e. we replace the tangential diffusivity</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">q ¤ b ! by q ¤ d c V Y X d ! £ 5 Í q ( i x Q W V e X e v ¤ b ! h ! if X 2 Î k w b a c q ( ( i else,</formula><p>which depends in addition on the evolving intensity. Then lighter pattern will not diffuse downstream and a sharp front at the tip of the pattern together with a typically blurred intensity in the upstream direction will underline the direction of the flow (cf. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 5</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Discretization</head><p>For the discretization of the above transport diffusion problem we pick up an algorithm due to Pironneau <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> for the discretization of transport dominated problem. Furthermore, for the diffusive term of the equation we apply a semi-implicit scheme, where the diffusion coefficient </p><formula xml:id="formula_14">m i Ï z 5 0 « is given by q m X 3 g mÏ c v ! £ ± X Ï h S °X Ï s Ð ¡ Ñ Ò Ï « c where Ñ Ò Ï</formula><p>is a numerical upwind integration of the velocity field, i. e.</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">Ñ Ï 3 ! ( ± g m i Ï Ó ! with Ô 1 g m t ! 5 ¤ " g m I c Q g m Q ! Q ! and g m i Ï h S ! 5</formula><p>. We consider the following second order approximation:</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">Ñ Ï 3 ! ( 5 z « Ó ¤ •m i Ï h S « c Ó z « ¤ " g m i Ï h S c Q 3 ! ¹</formula><p>Next, following Pironneau we incorporate this approximation of the transport into a variational formulation of the transport diffusion problem and obtain:</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">p X Ï h S °X Ï Ð ¡ Ñ Ï « c t Õ À U ¤ d c V e X Ï Ð Ñ Ï ! Q V e X Ï h Sc V Õ Á 5 $ W e T g X Ï Ð # Ñ Ï ! u c t Õ ! Ö 3 Õ Ò × | p § ! u c where i x c ¦ ! denotes the Ø scalar product on §</formula><p>. Finally, from this variational formulation a spatial finite element discretization can be easily derived. I. e. in 2D we consider bilinear finite elements on a regular grid and lumped mass integration. As proposed in the original anisotropic diffusion method for steady flow fields the same regularized</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X b</head><p>is considered in each time-step based on a single short implicit time-step for the corresponding heat equation with respect to initial data X .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">A Blending Strategy for Long-Term Animation</head><p>One of the characteristics of nonlinear diffusion methods in image processing is that the corresponding evolution generates a scale of representations, ranging from fine and typically noisy to coarse images with enhanced features such as edges. We have observed this scale of representations already in the anisotropic diffusion method for steady flow fields. As proposed above, the scale parameter is now coupled to the actual transport process in our transport diffusion model. But especially for long-term visualization purposes this coupling obviously leads to non satisfying results. Unfortunatly, due to the nature of our model, we are unable to freeze the scale and solely consider the evolution of suitable patterns at that specific scale in time, which would be the optimal choice. The solution we propose here is a compromise based on the blending of different results from the transport diffusion evolution started at successively incremented times. <ref type="figure">Fig. 7</ref> gives a sketch of the different approaches in a diagram <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>: Three time-steps of the transport diffusion process of a Bénard convection, generating directed patterns. On the top row we consider a finer scale than on the bottom row. Color represents the velocity.</p><p>whose axes are the involved scale and time parameters. In detail we proceed as follows: First, we select a suitable interval for the scale parameter always considering some white noise of a fixed frequency range as initial data and denoting the resulting solution by X B</p><p>. For negative time we suppose a suitable extrapolation of the velocity field to be given. Finally, applying blending of at least two different solutions we compute</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">X 3 g m I c Q 3 ! ( 5 ¤ à B Ù B Q g m Q ! E X b B t g m u c Q 3 ! d</formula><p>This intensity function is well defined for arbitrary times and characterized by the initially prescribed scale parameter interval. We especially use this construction for a animation of the flow over a certain time interval (cf. <ref type="figure">Fig. 8</ref> for a graph of the blending functions). Such an animation involves all solutions</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>X B</head><p>for which the blending function Ù B has a nonvanishing overlap with the given time interval. Other constructions of a partition of unity and corresponding blending functions are near at hand and especially multiple overlaps can be considered which requires the blending of more than two intensity functions at the same time.</p><p>We emphasize that the application of this blending technique does not introduce any inaccuracy, because for any time m the resulting image</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">X 3 g m I c Q " ! consists of images X B g m I c 4 3 !</formula><p>showing streaklines at time m and at slightly varying scale. The transport diffusion method creates a dense coverage of the domain with streakline patterns. These patterns are transported with the flow. Thus, this approach is capable of visualizing time dependent flow corresponding to streaklines of the same length as the evolving patterns. Since the evolving patterns are transported by the underlying flow this approach together with the blending technique discussed here is comparable to animated spot noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Conclusions</head><p>We have generalized and expanded the anisotropic diffusion method in flow visualization for time-dependent vector fields. As a resulting continuous model we obtain a transport diffusion problem, where flow aligned patterns evolve under a dominating transport controlled by the vector field and an anisotropic diffusion process which stretches the patterns along the flow direction and sharpens them simultaneously in the perpendicular direction. This model can efficiently be discretized using an appropriate low viscous upwind scheme in time combined with a finite element scheme in space. For long-term animation purposes we select a suitable window for the involved scale parameter and use blending techniques to provide a dense pattern motion in the selected scale range at any time. As in the original method, most of the essential properties of the Finally, we will work on a further improvement of the contrast enhancement and a better constrast preservation in the blending process.</p><p>On the web site http://numerik.math.uni-duisburg.de/exports/flowVis/ different animations showing the performance and the underlying blending strategy are available. <ref type="figure">Figure 7</ref>: A schematic sketch of the general relation between scale and time parameter in our combination of image processing and flow computation is depicted. We compare the case of varying scale for steady state flow fields at fixed time (magenta), the simultaneously time and scale evolution (green), the optimal but non practical case of a fixed scale for varying time (blue) and our blending approach (red).</p><p>...</p><p>...</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>...</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Process 1 Process 2 Process 3</head><p>Resulting Intensity Time t s 0 s 1 <ref type="figure">Figure 8</ref>: The weighting factors in the blending operation together with the overlapping scale/time intervals of the considered transport diffusion processes are shown in a diagram over time.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>,</head><label></label><figDesc>interpret the components of X as color-components and define the force e to work on the luminance ofX. InFigures 1 and 2we have depicted scales of vector field representations. For details we refer to the original paper<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>From top left to bottom right four successive scale steps of the anisotropic diffusion process are depicted. The vector field visualized here results from a CFD computation, where a fluid flows from the inlet (black circle) toward an outlet on the lower right corner.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Three different time-steps of a convective flow visualized by the anisotropic diffusion method for steady flow fields, which nicely represent the vector fields but not the underlying timedependent motion. Thereby, the resulting pattern is directed along streamlines. Cf. Fig. 6 for streakline type pattern generated by the new transport diffusion method corresponding to the same timesteps.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Source terms with different slopes at S , which are applied to amplify different frequency ranges in the evolution.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Three successive time-steps of the transport diffusion process generating directed patterns of a Bénard convection (cf. Section 5). The additional coloring indicates the speed of the flow field. Red colors indicate high velocity, whereas blue colors indicate low velocity. To emphasize the transport of patterns we have magnified the marked sections of the images in the lower row.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the previous time-step. Let us indicate by an upper index 0 the time-step and by « the time-step size. Then, a suitable approximation of the material derivative at time</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>A comparison of directed and symmetric patterns generated for a circulating flow. On the left directed patterns are generated based on the incorporated "one-sided" diffusion and on the right the original model with linear diffusion along motions paths is depicted. The bottom row shows zoomed images of the marked regions in the top row. model can be discussed based on the physically intuitive continuous model. From the authors' point of view exciting future research directions are á investigations of time-dependent flow visualization in 3D, á combination of the flow visualization approaches with the accelerated solving strategies presented in [14] which will probably enable fast visualization also in 3D, á the combination of this technique with other visualization methods to simultaneously display for instance chemical reactions in the moving fluid, á an improved understanding of the nonlinear dependencies between the involved parameters.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank S. Turek from the University of Dortmund for his contribution to the efficient implementation of the public software and him and E. Bänsch from the Weierstraß-Institute at Berlin for providing the CFD data sets used in our computations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Time Scale</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Axioms and fundamental equations of image processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Guichard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P.-L</forename><surname>Lions</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Morel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch. Ration. Mech. Anal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="257" />
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximum and comparison principle for one-dimensional anisotropic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kawohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kutev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Ann</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">311</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of time-dependent velocity fields by texture transport</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rumpf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eurographics Scientific Visualization Workshop &apos;98</title>
		<meeting>the Eurographics Scientific Visualization Workshop &apos;98</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging vector fields using line integral convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cabral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Leedom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (SIGGRAPH &apos;93 Proceedings)</title>
		<editor>J. T. Kajiya</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-08" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="272" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced spot noise for vector field visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>De Leeuw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Visualization &apos;95</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;95</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stragegies for effectively visualizing 3D flow with volume LIC</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Interrante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Grosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Visualization &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;97</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="292" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solution of nonlinear diffusion appearing in image smoothing and edge detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kačur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mikula</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Numer. Math</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flow visualization using moving textures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Max</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ICASE/LaRC Symposium on Time Varying Data, NASA Conference Publication 3321</title>
		<meeting>the ICASE/LaRC Symposium on Time Varying Data, NASA Conference Publication 3321</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="87" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing 3D Velocity Fields Near Contour Surface</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Max</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Crawfis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="254" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scale space and edge detection using anisotropic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Computer Society Workshop on Computer Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scale space and edge detection using anisotropic diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Perona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methodes des elements finis pour les fluides</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Pironneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Recherches en Mathematiques Appliquees</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Masson</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anisotropic nonlinear diffusion in flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Preußer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rumpf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Visualization</title>
		<meeting>Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="332" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Level set segmentation in graphics hardware</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rumpf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Strzodka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings ICIP&apos;01</title>
		<meeting>ICIP&apos;01</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uflic: A line integral convolution algorithm for visualizing unsteady flows</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings Visualization &apos;97</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;97</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="317" to="322" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast and resolution independent line integral convolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stalling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-C</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SIGGRAPH 95 Conference Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="256" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spot noise-texture synthesis for data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics (SIG-GRAPH &apos;91 Proceedings)</title>
		<editor>T. W. Sederberg</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991-07" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="318" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flow visualization with surface particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anisotropic diffusion in image processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Teubner</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tensorlines: Advection-diffusion based propagation through diffusion tensor fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Weinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kindlmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="253" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
