<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Reconstruction, Visualization And Quantification Of Neuronal Fiber Pathways</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Zhaohua</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
							<email>ding@boreas.med.yale.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gore</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Adam</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Diagnostic Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<settlement>San Diego</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Case Study: Reconstruction, Visualization And Quantification Of Neuronal Fiber Pathways</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>neuronal fiber pathway, diffusion tensor imaging</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>It is of significant interest for neurological studies to determine and visualize neuronal fiber pathways in the human brain. By exploiting the capability of diffusion tensor magnetic resonance imaging to detect local orientations of neuronal fibers, we have developed a system of algorithms to reconstruct, visualize and quantify neuronal fiber pathways in vivo. Illustrative results show that the system is a promising tool for visual analysis of fiber connectivity and quantitative studies of neuronal fibers.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Reconstruction, visualization and quantification of brain neuronal fiber pathways in vivo is of considerable interest for neurological research and clinical studies. For example, a precise knowledge of neuronal fiber connections can be used to better interpret functional relations between different brain regions. Visualization of neuronal fiber pathways can assist the analysis of fiber connectivity and potentially guide brain surgery, while quantification of geometric and physical properties of neuronal fibers in vivo, along with their changes with time, may provide valuable insight into the progression of brain disease.</p><p>Reconstruction of neuronal fiber pathways in vivo has become feasible with the advent of diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) using magnetic resonance <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>. With the DTI technique, the diffusive motion of water molecules within a voxel of brain tissue can be measured, which is characterized by a diffusion tensor matrix:</p><p>Diagonalization of D gives three pairs of eigenvalues and eigenvectors(λ i and V i , i=1, 2, 3). Since molecular diffusion is retarded by encounters with cell membranes and cytoskeletal structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, the water diffusion rate parallel to a fiber is higher than perpendicular to it. The eigenvector corresponding to the largest eigenvalue is parallel to the local tangent of a fiber <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 1</ref>. By integrating such local tangent directions, entire neuronal fiber pathways can in principle be reconstructed.  Using the capability of DTI to detect the local orientation of neuronal fibers, and motivated by the potential importance in neurological applications, we have developed computer algorithms to reconstruct, visualize and quantify neuronal pathways in vivo. In the following, a novel algorithm for reconstructing neuronal fiber pathways is first presented. Then an algorithm for bundling fibers into natural groups is described. Finally, algorithms for surface rendering of the fiber bundles, and quantification of their geometric and physical properties of the fiber bundles, are discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Fiber Reconstruction</head><p>DTI provides a set of 3-D diffusion tensor data for the brain volume to be studied. In this study, a volume of 20x20x9 cm <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> is imaged which generates a dataset of 64x64x18 voxels. Neuronal fiber pathways are reconstructed from the 3-D diffusion tensor data as follows. First, a 2-D region which includes the fiber fascicles of interest is specified. Inside the 2-D region, a regular grid of closely spaced seed points is then defined. Fiber paths are tracked from each of the seed points along both forward and backward directions, as illustrated in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. The diffusion tensor matrix at a seed point is calculated by tri-linear interpolation using the diffusion tensors of its eight neighboring voxels. The path direction for the seed point is the direction of the eigenvector corresponding to the largest eigenvalue of the interpolated diffusion tensor matrix. By adding the path direction to the 3-D coordinate of the seed point, a new point along the fiber can be obtained as follows: fibers tracking process stops when the fiber reaches a voxel whose anisotropy falls below a preset threshold value or the direction change of the fiber path exceeds a threshold. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>. Illustration of the fiber tracking process.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">P 1 = P 0 + V</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Fiber Bundling</head><p>The process of fiber tracking generates a set of neuronal fiber pathways. Fiber pathways connecting the same functional regions of the brain form a natural anatomical group (bundle). Fibers in the same bundle usually are clustered in 3-D space, are approximately parallel to each other, and constitute a distinct pattern from other fiber bundles. The process of fiber bundling is to partition a set of fiber pathways into different natural bundles.</p><p>In this study, we employ a "K most-similar-fibers algorithm" to bundle fibers automatically.</p><p>Fiber bundling begins with a definition of a similarity measure between a pair of fibers. First, we introduce the concept of corresponding segment, which is loosely defined as the portion of a fiber (F i ) that has point-wise correspondence to a portion of another fiber (F j ), as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>. In our reconstructed fiber data, all fiber pathways pass through a 2-D plane that contains the seed points. Hence, corresponding segments of a pair of fibers can be determined by searching the shorter end along both directions from the seed point. A corresponding segment ratio is then defined as:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">R cs L L L L cs i j c s = + −</formula><p>Where L cs is the length of the corresponding segment; L i and L j are the length of F i and F j respectively.</p><p>The similarity between a pair of fibers F i and F j is</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">S R exp( D/C) ij cs = • −</formula><p>Where R cs is corresponding segment ratio; D is mean Euclidean distance between corresponding segments of F i and F j ; and C is a coefficient for D.</p><p>Similarity defined as such is 1.0 when F i and F j are identical. It gets smaller when the corresponding segment ratio decreases or the mean distance D increases.</p><p>With these definitions of corresponding segment and similarity, the following steps are taken to achieve fiber bundling:</p><p>(1) For a fiber F, find eight fibers whose seed points are the neighbors of the seed point of F.</p><p>(2) Calculate similarity S between F and each of the eight neighboring fibers.</p><p>(3) Threshold similarity such that any similarity value smaller than T is set to 0. (4) Find up to K neighboring fibers whose non-zero similarity to F are greatest. (5) Connect F to each of the fibers found in (4).</p><p>The above steps are repeated until all fibers are processed. This procedure results in partitioning of a set of fibers into different connected components, each of which constitutes a fiber bundle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Surface Rendering Of Fiber Bundles</head><p>To render the surface of a fiber bundle, we first extract its medial axis, along which a series of closed contour of the bundle is derived (See <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref> for illustration). To begin with, a crosssectional plane that contains seed points of all the fibers in the bundle is identified (called the seed plane). The average of the coordinates of all seed points is taken as the centroid of the seed plane, and the average of the path directions of all seed points is taken as the path direction of the seed plane. The next crosssectional plane is determined to be the one which is perpendicular to the path direction and has distance d to the centroid. By repeating this process, we obtain a series of centroids, the sequential connection of which gives the medial axis of the fiber bundle. Meanwhile, in each cross-sectional plane, we obtain a closed contour of the bundle which is defined as the convex hull of all points at which fibers in the bundle intersect the crosssectional plane. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Quantification Of Bundle Properties</head><p>Explicit bundling of a group of fiber pathways allows collective properties of a fiber bundle to be characterized. Parameters of potential clinical value include geometric parameters such as curvature and torsion along the bundle length, and physical parameters such as mean longitudinal and perpendicular diffusivity along the bundle length, all of which can be readily quantified.</p><p>Curvature and (helical) torsion along the length of each bundle medial axis are calculated using a cubic polynomial fitting method <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>: for a given point P at the medial axis, a window of 2N+1 points centered at P is selected. These 2N+1 points are then fitted with a cubic polynomial curve by least square fitting to the x, y and z coordinates separately; i.e. First, second and third derivatives of x, y and z with respect to µ are taken at µ = 0.5; these derivatives are used to calculate curvature (κ) and torsion (τ) according to the following equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>:</p><p>The mean longitudinal diffusivity at a medial axial point is defined as the average of the largest eigenvalues of all fibers in the bundle measured at the location where the fibers intersect the cross sectional plane, and mean perpendicular diffusivity is the average of the geometric mean of the median and smallest eigenvalues.   <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 6</ref>. Local curvature peaks correspond to the major curves of the fiber bundle seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 6</ref>. Variations of mean longitudinal and perpendicular diffusivities along the length of bundle medial axis are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">DISCUSSIONS</head><p>This report presents our preliminary results of reconstruction and visualization of in vivo neuronal pathways.</p><p>We have demonstrated the feasibility of reconstructing and bundling in vivo neuronal pathways using diffusion tensor images, and visualizing reconstructed fiber bundles and quantifying their geometric and physical properties. x" y'' z"</p><p>x''' y''' z''' (y' z" y" z') (z' x" z" x') (x' y" x" y')</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">2 2 2</formula><p>the current stage we employ a simple tri-linear interpolation of diffusion tensors, we are considering incorporating global constraints on fiber pathways to minimize the impact of local artifacts on the tracking process in our future study.</p><p>While fiber tracking as a technical problem has been the focus of a number of studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>, bundling of neuronal fibers has not been explicitly implemented. Most studies to date visually or manually combined the reconstructed fibers to demonstrate tracking algorithms. Therefore, our bundling algorithm, as well as visualization of fiber bundles and quantification of their properties, represents the first effort of this kind in the area of quantitative study of in vivo neuronal pathways.</p><p>Quantitative characterization of in vivo neuronal fiber pathways is of potential clinical importance. For example, in multiple sclerosis, axonal degeneration not only occurs in the lesion area, but also propagates along certain fibers passing through the lesion.</p><p>As axonal degeneration is associated with diffusion anisotropy, measuring physical parameters such as mean parallel or perpendicular diffusivity of fibers around multiple sclerosis lesions may give more accurate assessment of the extent of this disease. In hydrocephalus, cerebral-spinal fluid accumulates excessively in ventricles. This causes buildup of pressure inside the brain which in turn compresses the brain tissue. The mechanical impact of the hydrocephalus on brain tissue can be evaluated by examining the geometric parameters such as curvature or torsion of neuronal fiber bundles, particularly of those near the enlarged ventricles. Furthermore, quantification of in vivo neuronal fiber pathways can be applied to developmental studies of infant brains. As the infant brain develops, the physical and geometric properties of neuronal fibers evolve; characterization of these properties can provide a structural basis for neurological and psychological studies of developing brains.</p><p>It is of clinical interest to characterize the collective properties of a group of neuronal fibers. As brain disease usually affects a large number of neuronal fibers, quantifying the properties of a fiber bundle is likely more meaningful and informative than measuring individual fibers. In this study, we employed a K most-similar-fibers algorithm to bundle fibers. This algorithm is global in nature, and belongs to the category of hierarchical, agglomerative clustering methods. The effectiveness of this algorithm is affected by a number of parameters, which include the coefficient C, threshold T and number of most-similar-fibers K. These parameters affect the compactness of the bundles. In particular, the coefficient C in the similarity definition regulates a trade-off between mean Euclidean distance D and corresponding segment ratio R cs (C is chosen to be 1 in this study); the threshold T precludes bridging of fiber bundles by noise. In our implementation of the fiber bundling algorithm, their values are chosen such that a set of fibers are partitioned into finer or smaller fiber bundles. This leaves open the option to combine bundles of interest for quantitative characterization.</p><p>We define similarity between a pair of fibers in terms of the corresponding segment ratio R cs and mean Euclidean distance D.</p><p>In fact, we consider two fibers to be similar when they have comparable length, similar shape and are separated by a small distance. The first one is explicitly specified in the similarity definition, while the latter two are described by one measure, the mean Euclidean distance D. Because similarity is always calculated between a pair of neighboring fibers, a single measure D can well describe their similarity in shape and proximity in space.</p><p>There are a number of limitations in the system of algorithms we propose. First, the fiber tracking algorithm is not able to handle fiber bifurcating. Second, it does not distinguish between fiber touching and crossing. Nevertheless, these problems are largely dependent on image spatial resolution, and hence can be ameliorated by advances in high resolution diffusion tensor imaging. The spatial resolution used in this study is approximately 3x3x5 mm <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> . Higher resolution such as 1x1x2 mm <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> can be available in the near future with the use of high magnetic field and improved pulse sequences. However, using higher spatial resolution increases the size of diffusion tensor data proportionally; computational cost will also be increased as higher density of seed points can be used to reconstruct neuronal fiber pathways with higher resolution.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>________________________________________________ Corresponding author: Zhaohua Ding Address: 333 Cedar Street, Fitkin-B, Room 15 New Haven, CT 06510 USA Tel: (203)785-3963 Fax:(203)785-6534</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Three eigenvectors of diffusion tensor matrix D. Corresponding eigenvalues are proportional to the vector length.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Definition of corresponding segment.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Extraction of bundle medial axis and derivation of a closed contour in a cross-sectional plane.The contour in each cross-sectional plane is interpolated with a Catmull-Rom spline between neighboring vertices. Surface rendering of a fiber bundle is achieved by triangulating the closed contours between neighboring cross sectional planes to form triangle surface patches, and rendering all patches with flat</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>x = a 0 + a 1 µ + a 2 µ 2 + a 3 µ 3 y = b 0 + b 1 µ + b 2 µ 2 + b 3 µ 3 z = c 0 + c 1 µ + c 2 µ 2 + c 3 µ 3 where µ ∈ [0, 1].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 (</head><label>5</label><figDesc>a) shows a set of fiber pathways reconstructed from seed points in a region that contains the right internal capsule. The density of seed points is 1/3x1/3 voxel dimensions.Figure 5(b)-(d) show the three largest bundles formed from these pathways by the fiber bundling algorithm. Figure 6 (a) and (b) are the coronal and sagittal views of surface rendering of the fiber bundle in Figure 5(b).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>shows curvature and torsion measured along the length of the medial axis of the bundle in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Variation of curvature (in solid line) and torsion (in dashed line) along the length of bundle medial axis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Variation of mean longitudinal (in solid line) and perpendicular (in dashed line) diffusivities along the length of bundle medial axis.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The major difficulty in the study of this kind is to reconstruct fiber pathways from diffusion tensor images. Random noise as well as other artifacts can divert the tracking path significantly. While at</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>A set of reconstructed fiber pathways (a) and its three largest bundles (b-d).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Surface rendering of the fiber bundle shown in Figure 5 (b) in coronal view (a) and sagittal view (b).</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MR Diffusion Tensor Spectroscopy And Imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Basser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mattiello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lebihan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophysics Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microstructural And Physiological Features Of Tissues Elucidated By Quantitative-Diffusion-Tensor MRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Basser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pierpaoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Magnetic Resonance</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Basser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pajevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pierpaoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Duda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aldroubi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Vivo Fiber Tractography Using DT-MRI Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="632" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking Neuronal Fiber Pathways In The Living Human Brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Conturo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cull</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Akbudak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shimony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mckinstry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Raichle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurobiology. Applied Physical Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="10422" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantification Of 3-D Coronary Arterial Motion Using Clinical Biplane Cineangiograms</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The International Journal of Cardiac Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-Invasive Assessment Of Structural Connectivity In White Matter By Diffusion Tensor MRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Simmons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Scr</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Horsfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of International Society for Magnetic</title>
		<meeting>International Society for Magnetic</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<biblScope unit="page">531</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-Dimensional Tracking Of Axonal Projections In The Brain By Magnetic Resonance Imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chacko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pcm</forename><surname>Van Zijl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion-Weighted MR Imaging Of Anisotropic Water Diffusion In Cat Central Nervous System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moseley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kucharczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mintorovitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Asgari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wendland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tsuruda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="445" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusion Tensor MR Imaging Of The Human Brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pierpaoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jezzard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Basser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Barnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="648" />
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regularization Of Diffusion-Based Direction Maps For The Tracking Of Brain White Matter Fascicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Poupon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Frouin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Regis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bloch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lebihan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mangin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In Vivo Three-Dimensional Reconstruction Of Rat Brain Axonal Projections By Diffusion Tensor Imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pcm</forename><surname>Van Zijl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Solaiyappan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1123" to="1127" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Fundamentals Of Computational Geometric Modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<publisher>Aviation Industry Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Beijing</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
