<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Orientation Maps: Techniques for Visualizing Rotations (A Consumer&apos;s Guide)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bowen</forename><surname>Alpern</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Larry</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Matt</forename><surname>Grayson</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Pelkief</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Orientation Maps: Techniques for Visualizing Rotations (A Consumer&apos;s Guide)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The .sei of possible oraeiilalaons of a ragad three-dani~nszonnl object as a topologzcal space wath three degrees of freedom. Thas papcr ini1csiigates the suaiabilaty of various Iechnzqucs of vasualazang thas space. Wath a good tcthniquc the natural dasiance between oraenlalions will be i uprcnented fisarly accurately, and dastortion to the &quot;shape&quot; of a collectzon of oraentataons andtic r d by tlic change of rcfererence orzentataon wall be manor. Thc traditional Eiilcr-angle parainctertzation fails on both coiiiits. Lcss well-knou~ii iechnrquea erploat the facl thnl there is a rotation ihal lakes Ihe reference oraentailon to a garen one. The gaaen oraentaiaon as represcnled as a poivi along the of this rotation. The distance of this potnt froni the oragaii as determined b y soiiic scaling function of the magnitude of that rotataoir F i w nalural scalang fuiictaons are studied. None zs pcrfcci, but sciicral arc salasfactory. &apos;Thus, a better analogy would be with techniques for m a p ping the Northern Hemisphere. &apos;In fact, the boundary of most orientation maps has a twist, somewhat like the twist in a Moebius strip. 3 A consequence of the curvature of the N-sphere is that the sum of the angles of a large trianglp is significantly g r e a t e r than a. Thus, one cannot map large figures without noticeable distortion. However, one might hope that small figures are mapped relatively faithfully.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>physicist,^ and nia.terial scientists are oftsen concerned with t.he orirntat,ions of particles and crystals, respectively. Sequences of orient,at,ions are also used t&gt;o specify camera angles in coniput.er animation <ref type="bibr">[N93]</ref>.</p><p>This paper explores t,echniques for visualizing collections of oriait,a.t,ions. An orieiila,tion map represents orientmations as positions in 3-space. A typical use of an orient,at,ion map is to find clusters of crystals that are aligned siniilarly, or t*o watch how a particle rotates into a. new oricwt.a.t,ion as it is influenced by a magnetic field. The dist.ance between two orientat,ions is t8he sinallest, anglc through which one orientation must rota.t,e t.o prodwe t,he other. A good orieiitatioii map should be fait81ifiil bot,h t.0 this distance measure and to other aspects of the mathematical structure of the set of all possible orientations.</p><p>There is a direct correspondence between orientations and rotations: once a reference orientation has been fixed, any other orientation is uniquely identified by the rotation that transforms the reference orientation into it. This identification will be exploited mercilessly in what follows. Particularly useful will be the transformation induced by changing froni one reference orientation to another. This operation will be called reoncntatzon.</p><p>A helpful analogy exists between orientation maps and maps of the Earth's surface <ref type="bibr">[P90]</ref>. An Earth map represents places on the Earth, topologically a 2-sphere, as positions on a piece of paper, a (usually bounded) region of 2-space. As will be explained below, rotations can be identified with pairs of dianietrically opposed points on a 3-sphere (the points of unit distance from the origin in 4-space). Orientation maps represent points on the top half of the 3-sphere a s positions in a (usually bounded) region of 3-space.l An obvious problem with any Earth map concerns the boundary: for instance, as one moves East on the Earth one eventually falls off the right-hand edge of a map and reappears on the left. Such problems are unavoidable for orientation maps as well '. It is not particularly difficult for a viewer to become familiar with the boundary's peculiar topology.</p><p>The Earth has a number of geometric properties (distanccs, angles, areas, etc.). Earth maps can be evaluated by how well such properties are preserved. For instance, the Mercator Projection draws both lines of latitude and of longitude as straight lines. It distorts the latitude scale in such a way that the map is conformal, that is, the angle between three nearby3 'points on the map will be nearly the same as the angle bet,ween t,he corresponding points on the Earth's surface. Counterbalancing this desirable property of the Mercator Projection are its distortion of areas (e.g., Greenland and Antarctica appear huge), and the fact that the shortest path between two points on the Earth (an arc of a great circle) is not mapped as a straight, line. A map that is perfectly faithful to one geometric property necessarily distorts others. The same is true of orientation maps. This paper is intended t,o be a guide to the selection of a satisfactory orient,ation map.</p><p>The next, section rehearses ma,thematical properties of rot,ations. Section 3 reviews six orientation maps.</p><p>Section 4 establishes bounds on the distortion inherent in these maps. Section 5 describes our investigation into the appropriateness of these maps for visualizin,g orient,at,ions. The final section presents our conclusions. An a.ppendix considers a notion of rotation appropriate to quantum physics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">The Matheiliatics of Rotations</head><p>In two papers in 1775, Euler established most of the mathematics of rotation^.^ The first showed that any rotat.ion could be accomplished by a sequence of three rotations about coordinate axes. This is the basis for the Euler angle orientation map. The second paper offered a different, characterization of rotations: every rotation is shown to be a rotation of some angle Q around some fixed axis 11. This characterization is the basis for neo-Eulerian orientation maps <ref type="bibr">[F88]</ref>.</p><p>Euler's second paper also proved, although not constructively, that the composition of t,wo rotations is a rotatmion. This is the key to establishing that the rotations form a group with the null rotation as the identity and composition as the operator. This group is identical to t,he group of orthonormal 3 x 3 matrices with determinant. 1 called the Special Orthonormal group SO(3).</p><p>A technique for constructing the composition of two rotations was given by Rodrigues in 1840. For The norm of such quaternions is 1, so they represent points on the 3-sphere.</p><p>It is easy to establish that opposite points on the 3-sphere correspond to the same rotation: the quater-</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">nion [-cos( $), -sin( $)n] is equal to the quaternion [cos(ir -$1, sin(ir -$)(-n)], representing a rotation of 2 x -4 (or, equivalently, -4) around axis -n. This</formula><p>is the same as a rotation of Q around axis n . Thus, the set of rotations is equivalent to the 3-sphere with antipodal points identified.</p><p>The fixed axis characterization of rotations also provides a natural notion of the distance between rotations. Given a clockwise rotation around some fixed axis n of angle Q with 0 5 Q 5 x that takes rotation A to rotation B , the rotational distance between A and B is Q. Also, the set of rotations formed by composing a rotation of any angle about n to rotation A is the projective line through A and B . Any additional rotation C not on this line determines the projective plane containing A , B , and C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Orientation Maps</head><p>Traditionally, rotations are parameterized by Euler angles.6 A rotation is represented by a triple ( a , p, y) with -ir &lt; (Y 5 ir, 0 L p 5 x , and -ir &lt; y 5 x .</p><p>The triple denotes the following sequence of clockwise rotations: first, by y around the z-axis, then by /3 around the y-axis, and finally by a around the z-axis. Although any rotation can be so represented, this representation is not unique when /? is either 0 or ir. This orientation map also badly distorts the geometry of rot at ions. The null rotation is represented by the zero vector. Following Frank <ref type="bibr">[F88]</ref>, such orientation maps will be called neo-Eukrzan. Except for the unbounded stereographic orientation map, each of the neo-Eulerian maps represents the set of all orientations by the set of points inside and on the surface of a unit ball in 3-space. Because antipodal rotations are identified, antipodal points on the surface of a neo-Eulerian map are also identified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Bounds on Distortion</head><p>Any method of mapping the set of rotations into 3-space must distort distances to some extent, but the neo-Eulerian maps described above differ in the amount of distortion introduced. To study the distortions, consider any orientation P , and let Q be the orientation resulting from rotating P through angle 4</p><p>around the x-axis. Thus, the rotational distance between P and Q is 4, but the distance between P and Q on an orientation map will depend on the location of P . This section studies how the mapped distance varies as P is moved through the set of possible orientations. In particular, we will find the maximum ratio of map distances between orientations at rotational distance 4. (Only placements of P and Q for which the shortest path from P to Q does not cross through the surface of the map are considered.)</p><p>Three placements of P and Q are of particular interest. The first has P and Q being equidistant from the origin of the orientation map along the x-axis.</p><p>In this case, they are mapped as PI = (-f($),O,O) and Q1 = (f($),O,O), where f is the scaling function of the orientation map. In the second case, P appears on the surface at P2 = ( -l , O , 0 ) , and Q will be at Q2 = ( f (~ -#),O,O). In the final case, with P3 = (0,1,0) and Q3 = (0, cos($), sin($)), both lie on the surface of the map.</p><p>For each of the five neo-Eulerian maps, it can be shown that both the maximum and minimum mapped distances between P and Q occur for one of the three placements described above. Thus, the greatest distortion of distance will be the ratio of two of these distances. Given an orientation map, define the radial dilation to be the ratio of the distance between P2 and Q2 to the distance between PI and Q1. Thus, it is the factor by which a segment of the z-axis grows as it is moved from the center toward the surface of the orientation map. Similarly, define circumferential dilation to be the ratio of the distance between P3 and Q3 to the distance between P2 and 9 2 . Thus, it is the dilation experienced by a line segment when it moves from being perpendicular to the surface (with one end on the surface) to lying entirely on the surface.</p><p>For each of the orientation maps under consideration, the radial and circumferential dilations are most extreme for very short segments. Computing the limits as q5 approaches zero yields the following results, which are summarized in the table in the conclusions: 0 For the lincar orientation map, the radial dilation is 1 (that is, the line segment, remains the same length), while the circumferential dilation is at most 5 x 1.57. This ma,p has the smallest distortion of the techniques considered.</p><p>0 The conformal niap has maximum radial dilation 2 and circumferential dilation 1. Thus, it dilates distances a bit more than the linear map. However, the shape of collections of nearby orientations remains unaffected as the collection is moved around the map (via a reorientation). For instance, a small equilateral triangle will grow as it moves from the center to the surface, but it will remain equilateral. With the other techniques, the triangle's angles are distorted.</p><p>In this case, the other maps will also have little distortion. The possible benefit of the stereographic map is that projective lines are mapped to straight lines and projective planes to planes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Visualizing Triangles of Orientations</head><p>To get a better feel for the various orientation maps the authors built an apparatus for viewing them using IBM's Data Explorer (DX) visualization software.8 With this system, we studied the effect of changing the reference orientation on standard figures in the various maps. We use equilateral triangles of orientations of differing sizes as our standard figures.</p><p>A triangle of orientations is just a triple of orientations A , B , and C. A triangle will be said to be in standard position if A is the reference orientation, B is obtained by rotating A around the x-axis, and C by rotating A about a line (through the origin) in the</p><p>xy-plane with positive slope. Any triangle can be put in standard position by a reorientation followed by a change in viewing point. Given an orientation map, a new map with reference orientation A can be constructed by transforming every orientation X (in the old map) t,o XA-'. Once A has been moved to the origin, it is easy in DX to change one's viewing point so that B and C appear as required. A triangle of orientations ABC is equilateral if the rotational distance between its vertices is the same. The size of an equilateral triangle is taken to be this d i~t a n c e .~ It is easy to prove that change of reference orientation and change of point of view preserve 0 Dilation in the orthographic orientation map depends on 4, the rotational distance between P and Q . When 4 is sufficiently small, the radial dilation is approximat8ely $ and the circumfer-entia1 dilation is t'he inverse quantity $. Thus, the circumferential dilation is unbounded, but is extremely large only for short distances 4. For instance, when 4 is greater than i , (one tenth of the ball's diameter), distances get dilated by at most a factor of about 6.</p><p>0 Wit.h t,he volwnet,ric map, t,he most extreme r a dial dilation is (F)-P x ,565 and the maximum circumferential dilation is % x 2.36. A collection of points near the origin appears to get squashed in the z-direction but to expand in the other two dimensions as it is moved along the x-axis, these two effects balancing out so the object covers the same volume.</p><p>0 The stereographic orientation map is problemat,ic, since it is unhounded. The radial dilation is infinite, since two points become arbitrarily far apart as t,hey are moved away from the origin. This map may find use when the orientations being considered are all within a reasonably small distance of the reference orientation, such as those that arise after "niodding out" by symmetry relations of crystals [G74, B80, F88, HN911.</p><p>--"equilateralness." Equilateral triangles of orientations offer a convenient vehicle for exploring the distortions introduced by reorientation to such properties as d i s tance, angle (between P and $), area, linearity, and planarity. Distortions to volume can only be judged indirectly.</p><p>The results of this investigation are summarized here. First consider the bounded neo-Eulerian maps. In standard position, small equilateral triangles of orientations get mapped as small equilateral triangles. As the triangle size increases, the angle at the origin increases and the opposite side bows out. At, size s, ('This apparatus will be publicly available through the Cornell Theory Center's DX Repository which can be accessed via anonymous ftp (info.tc.comell.edu), the Comell Theory Center gopher server (gopher.tcxomell.edu, port 70), or mosaic at Document URL "http://www.tc.comell.edu:80/DX/dx.htd".</p><p>' gThis is proportional to a standard notion of the area of triangles in a projective geometry.  Dist,ort,ions in size are hardly noticeable in the linear, conformal, and volumetric orientation maps. In t,he orthographic orientation map, figures get noticeably smaller as they approach the boundary. Distortions in size are even more significant in the stereographic case. Here the figures are always planar trian-No B ,b gles but they quickly get big (due to the unbounded nature of this projection) and move out of view under continuous reorientation along a common axis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Radial Circumferential</head><p>In the Euler angle orientation map, the reference orientation is not represented by a unique point but by the line <ref type="figure">( a , 0, -a)</ref>. Thus, a figure in standard position looks more like a rectangle than a triangle. Under a sequence of reorientations (by rotati6ns around the y-axis of increasing magnitude) the figure changes shape wildly. The most that can be said is that the figure remains contiguous except when it leaves one boundary of the map and reappears through another. The strengths and weaknesses of the different Orientation Maps are summarized in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 1</ref>. Three of the four finite neo-Eulerian orientation maps considered seem to be nearly equally viable candidates for visualizing orient,at,ions. The orthographic orientation map is only slightly less so. This is somewhat disappointing. We had hoped to be able to point to one map as being clearly better than the other three. On the other hand, it leaves researchers free to choose an orientation map for reasons intrinsic to their research without fear of compromising their ability to visualize t,heir results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix: Tethered Rot at ions</head><p>A somewhat different notion of rotation arises in quantuin mechanics. When an electron is rotated 2n it,s wave funct,ion is negated. [A861 This leads physicists to take t.he view that a rotat,ion of 47r is required to attain the null rotatmion. The term idhered rotation is sometimes used to denote this concept. A tethered rotation is characterized by a fixed unit vector and an angle of clockwise rotation between 0 and 2x. The space of kthered rotations corresponds to the 3-sphere witshout any ident#ifica.tion of points.</p><p>Neo-Eulerian maps can be coerced to represent t,et,hered rotat,ions by extending the domain of the scaling function to <ref type="bibr">[0,2n]</ref>. In extended orthographic and st(ereograp1iic orientat,ion maps, each point represents two tethered rotations. They could be differentiated by the use of two different colors; a user must remember t,hat points of opposite color are far apart unless they are both near the same boundary point.</p><p>The extended conformal orientation map provides unique representat,ions but is unbounded. This map has the interesting property that projective planes map to spheres (and projective lines to circles). Such spheres intersect the unit sphere (that is the boundary of the conformal orientation map proper) in great circles <ref type="bibr">[F92]</ref>.</p><p>The extended linear and volumetric orientation maps are bounded and provide unique representations. Note however that the extended volumetric map does not preserve volume under reorientation, and the d i l a tion bounds given earlier do not hold for either map. In particular, the entire surface of either map represents the same tethered rotat8ion (the rotation that</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>'</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>0 5 Q</head><label>5</label><figDesc>5 x , a clockwise rotation of 4 radians about a fixed unit, vector n is represented by a fourtuple [cos($), sin($)n]. This is the so-called Euler-Rodrigues parameterization of a rotation. This fourtuple can be regarded as a quaternion; cos($) is the 'Altmann [A861 in an excellent source for information on rotations. It is the source for the unattributed facts stated in this section. The introductory chapter is a fascinating overview of t,he subject's sordid hist,ory. scalar pari, and sin( $)n the vector part of the quaternion. If rotations A and B are represented by quaternions [a, a] and [b, b] then the composition A B is represented by their quaternion p r~d u c t :~ [a, a] * [b, b] = [aba . b, ab + ba + a x b].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A number of other representation maps have been suggested [IL72, F88, HN91, F92] but have not yet gained wide acceptance. These orientation maps represent a rotation of angle 0 5 Q 5 x about a fixed unit vector n by f(Q)n for some continuous increasing scaling function f : [0, x ] + [0, CO] with f(0) = 0. a= ( a , , a y , a , ) a n d b = ( b , , b y , b z ) , thena.bdenotes the dot product a,b, + a y b y + a , b , and a x b denotes the cross product ( a y b za z b y , a l b za z b z , a t b ya y b z ).'The formulation given here follows Altmann [A86]. Many other formulations are possible [GSO].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Comparison of neo-Eulerain Maps. Techniques are listed in order of estimated overall usefulness. Techniques separated by a single line are judged to be nearly equal. Stereographic infinite undefined No the figure is a qua.rt.er disk covering the first quadrant of the ty-plane of the orientation map. Changing the reference orientation to a point on the x-axis distorts the figure further but leaves it planar and perpendicular t,o the yz-plane. Reorientation to a point in the xy-plane leaves the figure planar. Even planarity is lost, under arbitrary reorientations: the figure resembles a triangle drawn on the surface of a balloon.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>function of an electron) and all points near the surface represent nearby tethered rotations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>If f(r) &lt; 00 thc corresponding map is said to be bounded. Notice that if f(z) is a suitable scaling function then so is c f ( z ) for any constant c &gt; 0. It will be convenient to use this fact to normalize bounded maps by requiring f (~) = 1. Although this is not a This map is analogous to taking an orthographic projection of the Northern Hemisphereplaces near the equator get crowded to the boundary. The stercogruphzc orient,ation map.7 This map has t,he property that projective planes and lines of rotat$ions map to planes and lines, respectively. This is analogous to a stereographic projection for the Northern Hemisphere from the Eart,li's center. Notice that like a stereographic projection of the Earth, this orientation map is unbounded<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[F88,</ref> HN911.  Thus, only a portion of the entire set of orientations can be viewed at one time.</figDesc><table><row><cell>standard convention, it facilitates visual comparison</cell></row><row><cell>among different, maps.</cell></row><row><cell>The following neo-Eulerian maps have been consid-</cell></row><row><cell>ered:</cell></row><row><cell>an This will be called the lznear orientation map.</cell></row><row><cell>It is the simplest to compute [IL72, F88]. It is</cell></row><row><cell>somewhat analogous to representing the North-</cell></row><row><cell>ern Hemisphere in polar coordinates.</cell></row><row><cell>tan( $)n The conformal orient,ation map. This map</cell></row><row><cell>preserves the angle between projective lines when</cell></row><row><cell>the reference orientation changes [IL72, F92]. It</cell></row><row><cell>is analogous to t,aking a stereographic projection</cell></row><row><cell>of t8he Northern Hemisphere from the South Pole</cell></row><row><cell>orit,o a plane tangent to the Earth at the North</cell></row><row><cell>Pole.</cell></row></table><note>sin($)n The orthographic orientation map. A rota- tion is represent,ed by the vector part v of its quaternion [F88]. The scalar part can be ob-tained as Jm-.((4 -sin(d))/x)+n Tlie zrolumetrzc orientation map. Small solids are transformed to solids with equal volume by reorientation of the map. Conse- quently, a uniform random distribution of points in the map represents a uniform random distribu- tion of rotations [IL72, F88]. This map is some- what analogous to an area-preserving map of the Nort,hern Hemisphere.tan( $)niFrank [F88] calls this the Rodrigves map.</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We wish to thank Bernice Rogowitz for her many helpful comments on an earlier version of this paper. Special thanks are due to Professor Paul Dawson of the Cornel1 Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering department and his graduate students, Yvan Chaste1 and Ashish Kumar in particular, for suggesting the problem of visualizing rotations and pointing out the relevant literature.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Altmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Rotations, Quaternions, and Double Groups</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1986" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disorientation Between Any Two Lattices</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bonnet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Cryst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="116" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orientation Mapping</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eighth International Conference on Textures of Materials (ICO-TOM 8)</title>
		<editor>Kallend, J. S., and G. Gottstein</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>The Metallurgical Society</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The conformal neo-Eulerian orientation map</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philosophical Magazine A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1149" />
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Classical Mechanics</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Reading, MA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second Edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disorientations and Coincidence Rotations for Cubic Lattices</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Grimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Cryst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="685" to="688" />
			<date type="published" when="1974" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation of Orientation and Disorientation Data for Cubic, Hexagonal, Tetragonal and Orthorhombic Crystals</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Heinz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Cryst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="780" to="789" />
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Description of Orientation Distributions of Cubic Crystals by Means of 3-D Rotation Coordinates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ibe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tezture</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="1972" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smooth Interpolation of Orientations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Thalman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Animation &apos;93</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Digital Cartography for Computer Graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Paeth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="320" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Graphic Gems</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
