<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">3D Simulation of Delivery</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Boissonnat</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<postBox>BP 109</postBox>
									<postCode>06902</postCode>
									<settlement>Sophia-Antipolis</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Geiger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<postBox>BP 109</postBox>
									<postCode>06902</postCode>
									<settlement>Sophia-Antipolis</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">3D Simulation of Delivery</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>W e show how t o create 9D models of maternal pelvis and fetal head f r o m magnetic resonance images (MRI. The models are used t o simulate the progress of dedvery in order t o give a prognosis of successful labor.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Overview</head><p>An important problem in obstetrics is the prognosis of successful labor. Some of the factors are: (1) the size and shape of the bony pelvis, (2) the size of the fetal head, (3) the force of the uterine contraction, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref> the moldability of the head, (5) the presentation and position of the fetus. In a small number of cases, a disproportion between the fetal head and the maternal pelvis makes a normal vaginal delivery impossible, or leads to a prolonged course of labor, which may be hazardous for mother and infant. Such a disproportion may be due to a contracted pelvis or due to an enlarged fetal head. The measurements of factors $"band j5) are possible before the onset of labor. oget er with other informations like the age of the mother and the knowledge of the outcome of previous labor, they are used to decide whether to do an elective cesarean section at an appointed time or to go into a trial of labor. The trial of labor may result in a successful delivery, or in an emergency cesarean section.</p><p>The decision where to draw the borderline is difficult, since doing elective cesarean sections may avoid an otherwise inevitable emergency cesarean section thus preventing mother and child from unnecessary distress. However, since not all factors are assessable before the onset of labor, elective cesarean sections may also be done on patients who would have been able to do a spontaneous delivery. A carefully managed vaginal delivery is usually preferable, even if today the danger of a cesarean section is minimal. So the goal is to decrease both the number of emergency cesarean sections and the number of elective cesarean sections.</p><p>At the present time, the general procedures to assess the principal diameters of the pelvis are: clinical measurement, X-ray pelvimetry, CT-pelvimetry and MRI. The diameters of the fetal head are generally e 5 timated by ultrasound. Usually, the deep pelvic structures are not visible with this method.</p><p>The articles <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr">81</ref> show that pelvimetry alone is a poor predictor of the outcome of a trial of labor. The need to combine both the head and the pelvic diame-ters to predict a successful delivery is clearly demonstrated i n [6].</p><p>In our opinion, the confrontation of the true 3D forms of both pelvis and fetal head should be more accurate for thk prediction of a successful labor, especially since the human pelvis has a very complex shape. Therefore, we have to accomplish two major tasks: Firstly, we must produce 3D models of the pelvis and the fetal head (geometric modeling). Secondly, the essential physical mechanisms of delivery have to be formulated and applied to the 3D models (physical modeling).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Geometric modeling</head><p>The 3D models can be computed from magnetic resonance images taken near the end of pregnancy. From these images, we can extract manually the contours of the pelvis and the fetal head. There are various methods for reconstructing 3D models from tomographic ima es. We use a spatial triangulation tetrahedrizametric closeness, similar to the voxel technique. However, in addition to connecting orthogonally overlapping contour parts from adjacent cross-sections vertically, we also connect non-overlapping parts to their nearest neighbors. The method has several properties:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">0 It gets directly to a 3D polyhedral representation.</formula><p>The object volume is represented by tetrahedra, the surface triangles being a subset of the tetrahedra faces. It also provides normal interpolation for Gouraud shading.</p><p>0 The property of connecting contours on adjacent cross-sections directly by triangles avoids the need for anti-aliasing or interpolation steps, especially for large cross-section distances.</p><p>0 Complex contours with multiple branchings, birth and death of holes and complicated splitting lines are handled correctly.</p><p>0 We get a considerable data reduction compared to other volume oriented methods. Real time display of reconstructed human organs is therefore possible on standard graphic workstations.</p><p>The tetrahedral structure can be used for applications like simulation of motion or finite element methods</p><p>We use the surface triangles for visualization. The tetrahedrization is used for force calculation.</p><p>tionf.described in [I, 21. This method is b ased on geo-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Physical modeling</head><p>The second task is a well known problem in robotics: an object has to be moved from one position to another in the presence of obstacles. The classical way to solve this problem consists in computing an appropriate representation of the set of free configurations (i.e. positions and orientations such that the object does not collide with the environment), the socalled free space. These solutions are usually global, that is, they calculate a solution over all possibilities. These methods are not easily adaptable for our problem since</p><p>The fetal head and the maternal pelvis are deformable, and we would like our method to take account of this.</p><p>Constraints on position and orientation of the fetal head are different from those encountered in robotics.</p><p>Their complexity depends on the number of vertices, edges or faces of a polygonal robot and environment, and is very high, especially in 3D.</p><p>We therefore decided to choose a local method, which is inspired by another problem in robotics: compliant motion. Compliant motion occurs in automatic assembly tasks. Fitting parts together generally requires motion between objects in contact. We consider the fetal head covered with force sensors and mounted on an imaginary effector. When the head comes in contact with the pelvis surface, we "measure" the forces on the head. The forces are typically along surface normals.The effector produces then small corrective motions to reduce the forces. In this way, we can take into account the physical constraints and even allow a certain interpenetration of the objects to compensate for deformations.</p><p>We made the following simplifications:</p><p>We only consider the maternal pelvis and the fetal head.</p><p>We assume the resultant of the force applying to the center of gravity of the head.</p><p>In this first approach, we do not consider the effects of any kind of soft tissue like uterine musculature or the perineum.</p><p>There are two forces involved in labor: those of the uterus and those of the abdomen, both of which are unknown before the onset of labor. Hence we have no notion of time for the simulation. We therefore divide the z-axis in discrete intervals, and, from a defined starting position and orientation, advance the headmodel downwards by discrete steps. If at any height the head polyhedron penetrates the pelvis polyhedron, we calculate the resulting force and moment applied to the center of gravity g of the head. According to this force and moment, we execute a number of translations and rotations to reduce the force to zero (optimization step). Persisting forces and moments indicate a position where the head cannot pass without deformation. These forces contribute to a measure of adequateness. We calculate the forces at discrete sample points spread evenly over the head surface. The force at a point h of the head depends on the depth of penetration. Its direction is the opposite direction of the surface normal at h. For each sample point on the head surface, we have to calculate if it is inside or outside the pelvis, and if inside, we need to calculate the depth. This calculation can be done efficiently with the tetrahedra data structure, since it allows fast point location. Moreover, we may associate a weight to each tetrahedron in order to locally allow an interpenetration. In this way, we can take into account the mobility of the coccyx.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Experimental results</head><p>A major problem was to find suitable MR images taken during pregnancy. Therefore we used pelvic images of a nonpregnant person. The pelvis was reconstructed from 23 axial MR images, separated by a distance of 0.86cm. The head was reconstructed from 16 MR scans of an adult. We changed manually the proportions to obtain a resemblance with a newborn. The diameters were then scaled to the sizes given in e biparietal diameter was 9.4 cm in this model P. average Th size).</p><p>To determine the reconstruction accuracy, we generated synthetic cross-sectional contours from an algebraic object (torus). These contours underwent the reconstruction procedure, and the resulting polyhedron was compared to the true object. We measured both the surface distance errors and the surface normal errors. We also compared our results with reconstructions obtained by the marching cube method (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). With our method, the surface distance error may be up to the slice distance in the worst case, but the error distribution is significantly better than with the marching cube method. This is especially the case with large slice distances. The data reduction effect also is significant. Another interesting result is the fact that the quality of surface normals does not increase with decreasing cross-section distances.</p><p>The implementation of the simulation program was done in C. The program was divided into a force calculation and simulation module and a visualization module. The calculation module is relatively machine independent and is intended to run on a fast machine. The display module runs uniquely on a Silicon Graphics computer. On the display module, we have additional functions: We can visualize the locus and strength of the forces on the head by changing the colors of vertices. We can interactively measure distances on the 3D models, and we may pick specific triangles and change their color. This may be useful to mark the small and large fontanels on the model, which helps to identify the orientation of the fetal head during the simulation.</p><p>The computation of a complete trajectory takes about one hour of CPU time on a DECstation 5000. Here, visualization is the only possibility to verify the result. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 2</ref> shows the trajectory of the large head-model starting from ROP (right occiput poste- Although our model is limited to the bony structures, the head makes exactly the same movements as illustrated in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. It enters the pelvic inlet with its sagittal suture directed transversely, then performs an internal rotation that brings the occiput towards the symphysis pubis. The fact that the head follows the principal movements as described in the literature validates our physical model. Below each image, the adequateness function is plotted; a vertical line indicates the current head position. Apparently, the passage of the outlet is somewhat constrained.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Future</head><p>We are able to model the physical mechanism of delivery, restricted to the bony pelvis and fetal head. The 3D confrontation of the fetal head and the pelvis gives indications on the success of labor, which should be more accurate than comparing a number of diameters. Up to now, the encouraging features have been the realistic movement of the head in all the tests (which corresponds to the trajectory described in literature), and the repeatability with different parameters. We have just started to explore the potential of 3D modeling and motion planning. The major part of work must still be done: 0 The fetal head has been produced artificially. It may not correspond to a head of a newborn. It has to be shown that a real fetal head will also be assessable from MR images using our method.</p><p>0 We worked with one single model of pelvis and head. It is difficult to generalise such results. We have to verify the results on a large number of different casea, especially with pelves from different pelvic types.</p><p>0 We should also include soft tieeue into the model.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>0</head><p>We have to show that the adequateness function is statistically significant for a prediction of a successful labor.</p><p>Of course a long term collaboration with a department of obstetrics would be necessary to establish statistics and to evaluate the possible benefit of this method. The first stage would be a kind of supervised learning by studying the outcome of borderline cases which went into a trial of labour. For this purpose, the necessary measurements may also be taken after the delivery. The goal of this step is to estimate the different threshold values of the adequateness functions for borderline cases. In a second stage, the method may be used parallel to conventional diagnosis, but without influencing the decisions. If this step shows a sufficient statistical significance, a future use of this method may be appropriate.   </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Histogram of surface distance error. Top: A polyhedron, reconstructed from vector-contours at a slice distance of 4. The surface distance error lies within the interval [-2.8, 0.51. About 10% of the sample points have an error of 0. Bottom: the same set of torus-sections, reconstructed with the marching cube algorithm. Only 7% of the surface samples are correct rior) presentation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Three snapshots showing the internal rotation</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4a :</head><label>4a</label><figDesc>Magnetic resonance image, Figure 4c: 3D models of the brain and tumor.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5a :</head><label>5a</label><figDesc>Planning: Computer model and video.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6a :</head><label>6a</label><figDesc>Surgery: Computer model Figure 5b: Planning: Video of patientFigure 6b: Computer model and video CP-46</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Three dimensional reconstruction of complex shapes based on the Delaunay triangulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Boissonnat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Geiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>1697</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-05" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Institut National de Recherche en Informatique et Automatique</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical Report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three dimensional reconstruction of complex shapea based on the Delaunay triangulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Boissonnat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Geiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ISOTSPIE Symposium on Electronic Imaging Sienee and Technology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Jose CA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three dimensional simulation of delivery for cephalo elvic disproportion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Geiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Firsf international tuo&amp;hop on mechatrvnics in medicine and suryery</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="146" to="152" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Three-dimensional modeling of human organs and its application to diagnosis and sur ical plannin . T h b e de doctorat en sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Geiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<pubPlace>Paris, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>#cole Nationde Supc5rieure des Mines de</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of radiological pelvimetry in the management of p* tients who have had a previous caesarean section</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mahmood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Obstetrics and Gynaecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of the predictive value of X-ray pelvimetry and biparietal diameter in cephalopelvic disproportion</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Si</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mandry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Grandjean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Reme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pastor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Levade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pontonnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europ. J. Obstet. Gynec. reprod. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Prkis d&apos;obstdtrique</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Merger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Melchior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
			<publisher>Masson</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective randomized study of X-ray pelvimetry in the primigravida</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Si</forename><forename type="middle">M T</forename><surname>Parson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Spellacy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="1985-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pritchard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Macdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gant. Wtlltams Obstetrics. Appleton-Century-Crofts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
