<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of Stratospheric Ozone Depletion and the Polar Vortex</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Lloyd</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
							<email>lloydt@watson.ibm.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yorktown Heights</settlement>
									<region>NY</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of Stratospheric Ozone Depletion and the Polar Vortex</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Direct analysis of spacecraft observations of stratospheric ozone yields information about the morphology of annual austral depletion. Visual correlation of ozone with other atmospheric data illustrates the diumal dynamics of the polar vortex and contributions from the upper troposphere, including the formation and breakup of the depletion region each spring. These data require care in their presentation to minimize the introduction of visualization artifacts that are erroneously interpreted as data features. Non-geographically registered data of differing mesh structures can be visually correlated via cartographic warping of underlying geometries without interpolation. Since this approach is independent of realization technique, it provides a framework for experimenting with different visualization strategies. 7&apos;his methodology preserves the fidelity of the original data sets in a coordinate system suitable for three-dimensional, dynamic examination of upper atmospheric phenomena.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>In the earth and space sciences, it is very common to organize geographically located data in terms of a rectilinear grid with horizontal extent over the entire surface of the earth (i.e., latitude and longitude). In two dimensions that implies a topological primitive that is a rectangle of various sizes. In three dimensions the cell is a parallelpiped, with the height corresponding to altitude or atmospheric pressure, for example. These rectilinear mesh structures are ill-suited for the study of phenomena that occur continuously over a nominally spherical surface (i.e., they tear the data). In addition, these grids may not be fully populated due to missing data (i.e., when observations could not be made). In such cases, the grids could be viewed as being irregular.</p><p>Whether the original grids are regular or irregular, cartographic techniques are often introduced to suitably deform the data to compensate for the problems inherent in the original structure (i.e., the use of a rectilinear representation for a spherical surface). Traditionally, such a transformation is accomplished by defining a new Cartesian grid in the cartographic projection coordinate system, and then interpolating from the original rectilinear grid to the new one prior to any other operation. Given the curvilinear nature of such transformations, non-linear interpolation techniques are typically required to make the transformation of acceptable quality. <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> illustrates this operation schematically in which the data values at three points in the original rectilinear, regular grid are combined to define the value at a single point in transformed space (e.g., the values are weighted averaged, where the weight is a function of distance from their original points to that in transformed space). In addition to being computationally expensive, such inteipolation make it impossible to preserve the fidelity of the data prior to rendering, especiallv if regions of no data or other discontinuities are pre-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1. Data Transformation by Interpolation</head><p>Alternatively, by warping the underlying mesh structure, the geometry itself is transformed without affecting the data. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> illustrates this operation schematically in which there is a one-to-one mapping of each point in the original and the transformed grid. At each node in the deformed grid there is a data value that corresponds to a specific node in the regular grid.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Regular Grid</head><p>Deformed Grid</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2. Grid Transformation by Coordinate</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Warping</head><p>Thus, any realization (the application of one or more visualization strategies that generate renderable geometry from a collection of data) that is to be done to visualize the data is independent of the choice of a specific cartographic coordinate system, the data or mesh themselves, or how the data are specified with respect to the underlying mesh (e.g., the data values are assigned at each node of the mesh or the data values are assigned to an entire cell at its center). In addition, interpolation is not required as the initial operation to be applied to the data to be visually correlated. Instead, interpolation can be isolated to be the last step in the visualization process, namely rendering (e.g., Gouraud-shaded surfaces). The use of appropriately warped curvilinear grids can preserve the fidelity of the data prior to rendering. This does require an environment that supports direct realization and rendering of data on curvilinear grids as well as regular ones. This must be coupled with the ability to independently manipulate data and its underlying mesh structure or base geometry. In addition, the ability to simultaneously render disparate geometry (e.g., points, lines, surfaces and volumes of varying color and opacity) is very helpful in viewing the realization of multiple data sets.</p><p>Correlative visualization implies the two tenets. First is the capability to look at multiple sets of data in exactly the same fashion (i.e., visual comparison within a common framework). That is, displaying different sets of data of disparate structure in an arbitrary geographic coordinate system independent of the data sets. Second is the capability to utilize a variety of visualization strategies within the chosen coordinate system, for examining a single set of parameters from one source or many parameters from multiple sources. Specific representation techniques illustrate different aspects of data. Hence, no single method is always suitable and not all techniques are useful for all data sets.</p><p>Therefore, methods that support the registration of multiple data sets in geographic coordinates, using similar cartographic warping of the respective data locations for the data sets in question shows promise as an alternative to meshing, interpolating or resampling the original grids of each data set to a common rectilinear grid in projected space for correlation visualization in the earth and space sciences. The former is used via the IBM Visualization Data Explorer developed by Visualization Systems, IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>. This is in contrast to the latter approach used by the author via the NSSDC Graphics System, developed by NASNGoddard Space Flight Center [9] <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stratospheric Ozone Depletion and the Polar Vortex</head><p>The aforementioned approach for the analysis of multiple data sets via correlative visualization can be illustrated by an example scientific problem. There is a phenomenon that occurs in the earth's upper atmosphere (qrimarily the stratosphere) above Antarctica during the winter and early spring of every year known as the polar vortex <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref>. This effect is characterized by a cyclonic circulation pattern around the south pole. Many researchers believe that ozone-destroying chemicals are trapped in this vortex during the cold and darkness of Antarctic winter. Once spring begins and the polar region emerges from the long night, it is theorized that these substances react photochemically with ozone to break the molecule apart and thus, aid in the creation of the so-called Antarctic ozone hole. Hence, in late winter, regions of ozone depletion around the pole begin to form. Within a few weeks the ozone hole is completely established. By late spring the vortex weakens, causing the ozone depletion region to fragment and eventually dissipate. The question of interest is, what are the characteristics of the south polar vortex that can be derived from diurnal observations of atmospheric dynamics and how do they relate to independent measurements of ozone? The study of the appropriate data sets for the southern hemisphere winter and spring (June through December) are relevant. The examination of a single year, 1987, is made because that year showed the greatest amount of ozone depletion until recent years <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Total Column Ozone Data</head><p>Perhaps the most critical effort to study stratospheric ozone has been via observations made by the Total Ozone Mapping Spectrometer (TOMS) aboard NASA's Nimbus-7 spacecraft. Nimbus-7 is in a (polar) sun-synchronous orbit, which means that it can roughly provide global coverage of the earth for its suite of instruments once per day. Each portion of the earth that is observed is nominally under the same illumination conditions from day to day. Measurements made by TOMS show the daily global distribution of stratospheric ozone from late 1978 until early May 1993. It measured the total column density of stratospheric ozone by observing backscattered solar ultraviolet radiation in seven spectral bands. Approximately 200,000 such measurements were made each day, which covered the entire globe [ 11.</p><p>TOMS required sunlight to operate. Hence, there are periods of missing data due to local polar winters (i.e., it is dark) in addition to the usual data dropout problems associated with spacecraft observations. These regions are visible as gaps in surfaces or images in various realizations of the data. They are NOT the ozone hole. The data have been gridded in a regular lattice of 180 (one degree in  Non-rectilinear cartographic projections are used relatively often by earth scientists as a way of preserving area in a display of the entire globe compared to the cylindrical equidistant projection. Other projections may preserve shape or linear distance, for example, on selected portions of the globe 161.</p><p>To examine a continuous phenomenon with a central focus far from the equator and the Prime Meridian, such as the ozone hole, a non-cylindrical projection is required. <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> illustrates the same data as in figure 3 except a polar orthographic projection for both the southern and northern hemispheres is employed, which are shown in the left and right side of the figure, respectively. For the orthographic projection, all meridians are straight lines radiating from the central pole. The parallels are concentric circles, which become compressed toward the equator. The orthographic projection can be characterized by:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">= c o s~~~c o s~e~ (1) y = cos ( q ) sin(0)</formula><p>where represents the location of each node in the deformed, curvilinear (orthographic) coordinate system with an assumed pole point of 90" north latitude and 0" east longitude and an assumed pole point of 90" south latitude and 0" east longitude for the northern and southern hemispheres, respectively.</p><p>In addition to the pseudo-color spectrum, this two-dimensional cartographic projection of the data is extended by redundant realization as a deformed surface (i.e., both height and color correspond to ozone density). The bluish contiguous area over Antarctica clearly depicts the depletion region, illustrating the advantage of choosing an appropriate cartographic coordinate system. The height mapping clearly dramatizes the concept of a hole or depression in the ozone layer while the color enhances this perception as color would enhance a topographic map.</p><p>It should be noted that the use of hue-based pseudocolor mapping for realization and rendering of data as images can create problems in interpretation due to how the human visual system responds to color <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[7]</ref>. For example, discontinuities may appear to be present in the pseudocolor representation that are not in the data. However, such pseudo-color maps are virtually standard in many earth and space science disciplines. The acceptance of alternate, perceptually correct pseudo-color maps (e.g., luminance-based, [4]) would be limited in these disciplines because of their unfamiliarity. Therefore, the introduction of redundant realization techniques retains the familiar pseudo-color scale but helps to lessen its negative perceptual impact.</p><p>Below each translucent surface is a hemispherical map that has been registered in the same orthographic coordinate system as the ozone data. This map consists of a a pseudo-colored topographic surface, which is deformed based upon height above or below sea level. The pseudocolor scale is chosen to impart the appearance of a topographic map (e.g., the oceans are blue) for each hemisphere. This surface is created from a topographic data base on a rectilinear grid at one-half-degree resolution. The grid is warped by the same orthographc projection that was applied to the ozone data, although the data were originally in a different coordinate system at different resolution. Both the ozone and topographic surfaces are Gouraud-shaded. In addition, the topographic map is overlaid with the same coastline map in magenta with political boundaries corresponding to each hemisphere that was used in figure 3. The map geometry was transformed in a manner similar to that of the ozone and topographic data.</p><p>There is a seam in each of the orthographic surfaces corresponding to where east longitude is either -180 or +180 degrees -nominally the International Date Line, which is an artifact of the warping of the original rectilinear data onto a continuous surface, welding the discontinuity in the provided form of the data. The use of coordinate warping does preserve this inherent discontinuity in the data, which would not be the case if traditional interpolation techniques were chosen. In general this seam will not smoothly connect the surface due to how TOMS gathers data. This scanning instrument examines each portion of the earth at a different time of day, but still covering the entire globe once per day. Hence, observations on each side of that line were taken approximately 24 hours apart and usually are not the same.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dynamics Data: Atmospheric Temperature and Winds</head><p>Global atmospheric dynamics data (e.g., temperature and wind velocity) are often derived from spacecraft, balloon and aircraft observations, which have been modelled and gridded on a 2.5 degree grid, 144 x 73 cells (longitude x latitude) at different levels in the atmosphere, based upon their pressure. Hence, a two-dimensional slice of these data at a specific pressure level is organized in a torn mesh similar to that of the total column ozone, but at lower resolution and in a different geographic coordinate system. These data may also have gaps in coverage, including only a partial value for some wind cells (i.e., one or two of the three vector components are missing).</p><p>If this cartographic theme is extended to three dimensions by performing a Cartesian to spherical coordinates transformation, then for a "spherical" projection, all meridians are great circles converging at the poles. The parallels are also great circles, which become compressed toward the poles. The spherical projection can be characterized by: graphic globe such that all data are registered in a common, spherical, earth-centered coordinate system. The radius of the globe is chosen to be the same as the inner radius of the spherical shell corresponding to the 1000 mb level. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 5</ref> illustrates these ideas for both the temperature and wind data on October 1, 1987. For the temperature data, surface extraction techniques are employed because direct volume rendering shows little quantitative information. The temperature data are realized as pseudocolor and opacity-mapped isothermal surfaces. The isosurfaces are at 194 and 294 K with the higher value being more opaque. The pseudo-color spectrum on the right corresponds to that of the temperature isosurfaces. The wind data are realized via stream ribbons generated by numerically integrating the paths taken by injecting massless particles in the wind field. The twist in the ribbons is derived from the vorticity (i.e., V x v, where v is the wind velocity). The ribbons are pseudo-color-mapped by horizontal speed. The magnitude of the horizontal winds range from 0 to about 80 meterdsecond, which correspond to the pseudo-color spectrum on the left. The vertical component of the wind ranges from about -33 to about +45 mblsecond.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">x = (h +</formula><p>Further study of the data using the techniques shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">figure 5</ref> shows that there is a region of cold air (i.e., around 200 K) over the Antarctic during this period that is concentrated near 100 mb in pressure height, that is surrounded by high-speed winds. The shape of this cold air mass and its diurnal variation at first glance appear to be similar to what can be seen as the depletion region in the total column ozone data. The shape of this air mass can be seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">figure 6</ref>. Two spherical, wire-frame meshes surround a monochromatic globe (land is white, ocean is gray). The outer green mesh of quads is at the 100 mb pressure level. The inner blue mesh of triangles is at the 200 mb pressure level. An isosurface at 194K is shown for October 1, 1987, which has two components, south polar and equatorial. The isosurface is pseudo-colored on a linear scale according to the pressure height at which the 194K value is determined. The pseudo-color scale ranges from blue (100 mb) to green (200 mb). Regions below 200 mb are colored pink. The south polar component of the isosurface is mostly at the 100 mb level. Hence, further study focuses on 100 mb data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Correlating Ozone with Temperature and Winds</head><p>Two different approaches to visually correlating the ozone and dynamics data for the 100 mb level are taken utilizing the concept of coordinate warping to achieve geographic registration. The 100 mb data are the same as used in figures 5 and 6, and hence, are of a different grid than that of the ozone data. Since the aim of this study is to examine a phenomenon that is focused on a polar region and is nearly hemispheric in geographic extent, the orthographic cartographic projection discussed in equation (1) is utilized. They are illustrated using data from October 1, 1987 in an attempt to show the formation of the polar vortex and the ozone hole itself in figures 7 and 8. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">Figure 7</ref> shows four separate and different data-driven representations of the atmosphere over the southern hemisphere in the same geographic coordinate system utilizing the same three redundant realization techniques: pseudocolor mapping, surface deformation and iso-contouring. This is the same approach as used for the ozone data in <ref type="figure">figure 4</ref>, except for the addition of contour lines. In the upper left is the ozone column density with contours every 50 DU from 100 to 650 DU. The upper right shows the 100 mb temperature with contours every 5 K from 180 to 245 K. The lower left shows 100 mb horizontal wind speed with contours every 10 mhec from 0 to 85 &amp;sec. Cells where one or more components of the wind velocity or missing are shown as gaps in this surface.</p><p>In an attempt to show the correlation among these observable quantities in data space, the ozone data are interpolated to the grid on which the 100 mb data are available. Hence, independent gaps in both the ozone and wind measurements are properly maintained. These quantities are arithmetically combined to yield a single scalar, such that</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">M = 0 IvI / T (3)</formula><p>where M represents the combined field in m-DU/sec-K, 0 is total column ozone in DU, v is 100 mb horizontal wind velocity, I v I in &amp;sec, T is 100 mb temperature in K The lower right shows this combined quantity with contours every 20 m-DU/sec-K from 0 to 150 m-DU/sec-K.</p><p>Each of the surfaces shows a similar structure -a depression of comparable shape and areal extent over Antarctica for low ozone, temperature and wind speed, re- <ref type="figure">(See color plates, p. CP-42.1</ref> spectively, each with a boundary corresponding to that of the polar vortex. For both presentations of the ozone and dynamics data, a daily animation sequence beginning in early winter (late June or early July) through September, the availability of polar ozone data is apparent as well as the formation of the depletion region. Precursor and correlative signatures are visible in the temperature data as a cold air mass forms over Antarctica and persists into spring. As Antarctic winter progresses, the temperature over the pole plunges as seen by a blue region while a similar but less well-defined shape forms in the wind surfaces. With the onset of spring, ozone observations become available and form a similar depression pattern to that of the temperature and wind, This sequencing also shows the (super)rotation of the depletion region surrounded by the boundary of the polar vortex. This rotation usually has a period of several days. As spring progresses, the air over Antarctica warms up with a corresponding dissipation of the ozone depletion region and unifonnization of the winds.</p><p>Although the four time-varying surfaces do show the correlation among the ozone and dynamics data, they are difficult to observe. The eye tends to focus on one or two of the surfaces only. Therefore, at the cost of obscuring some of the data, the stacked approach shows the synchronous circulation in each data set for the southern hemisphere during this period at single glance. The patterns of the wind as shown via vector arrows in figure 8 evoke a cyclonic pattern corresponding to the polar vortex, that appears almost steady-state in the winter and early spring. As the sequences continue into late spring, the warming of the upper atmosphere over Antarctica is obvious, with direct correspondence to the dissipation of the polar vortex in the wind data and the breakup of the ozone hole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implementation</head><p>The techniques described herein have been developed via the IBM Visualization Data Explorer (DX), a general-purpose software package for scientific data visualization. It employs a data-flow-driven client-server execution model and is currently available on Unix workstations (e.g., IBM, Silicon Graphics, Hewlett-Packard and Sun) as well as a medium-grain, coherent shared memory parallel supercomputer (IBM POWER Visualization System) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[ 5 ]</ref> . DX simplified the implementation of cartographic warping and its simultaneous application to disparate data sets for correlative visual display by providing an extensible tool kit of polymorphic operations that are interoperable and appear typeless to the user. This polymorphism is a consequence of DX being built on a foundation of an unified data model, which describes and provides consistent access services for any data that is to be studied independent of shape, rank, type, mesh structure or dependency or aggregation. As a result, regular and irregular, structured and unstructured data are uniformly supported as well as missing data.</p><p>The features of DX relevant to this class of visualization problems are best illustrated with a simple example. Although DX offers several interfaces, the implementation of these techniques utilized visual programming, in which each computational task is assigned an icon and the flow of control and data are defined by connecting the icons as a direct acyclic graph. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 9</ref> shows a visual program that generates a visualization of the total column ozone as a radially deformed, psuedo-color and opacity mapped spherical surface surrounding a globe. The visual program has the following operations: 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7.</head><p>8.   ., 2., and 3., followed by a cartographic projection, such as the Mollweide oDeration. and then Imane (steD 9.). than is the case for comparable southern polar regions. Although these data require more care in their presentation an approach similar to that used for the southern hemisphere still applies. In addition, comparison of these data with spacecraft observations of clouds may yield additional insight into the dynamics of ozone depletion since polar stratospheric clouds are believed to provide sites for trapping ozone-destroying chemicals during the darkness of polar winter <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The Sphere and Globe are implemented as macros -their operation is specified in terms of other visual programming operations -without custom coding. The Globe operation actually utilizes steps l., 2., 5., and 6. (with an option for 4.) applied to topography data. Hence, this program could be further simplified by encapsulating these steps into a macro.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>9.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Import: read data from disk</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summation and Future Work</head><p>The application of cartographic warping to the correlation of global atmospheric data sets yields visualizations that illustrate a simple notion about the possible relationship between temperature and winds, and their contribution below the ,tropopause to the formation of the polar vortex and ozone depletion. The use of interpolation prior to realization appears to be unnecessary for the visualization of gridded data in a system with a sufficiently robust infrastructure of data structure and geometric support.</p><p>The ideas introduced with the analysis of observational data related to ozone and tropospheric dynamics can be extended by considering the correlation between these same ozone data and objective analyses that include the entire troposphere and stratosphere as a continuum. Visual correlation of these data is also useful for the examination of potential depletion regions in the northern hemisphere or the dynamics conditions for their possible formation. Data reflecting the typically disturbed conditions in northern polar regions in mid-winter through spring relative to the southern hemisphere yield more complex realizations Visualization of Stratospheric Ozone Depletion and the Polar Vortex, L A . Treinish, pp. 391-396.     </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CP-42</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>latitude) x 288 (1.25 degree in longitude) from the raw observations for daily global coverage with cells without data being flagged. The locations of missing cells are used to irregularize the data mesh prior to any realization. The total ozone measurements are in terms of Dobson Units (DU), corresponding to a column density of 2.69 x 1016 molecules of ozone cm-2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>shows a traditional two-dimensional visualization of the ozone data. The data are realized with a pseudo-color map for October 1, 1987, which is during the ozone depletion season. The rectangular presentation of the data is consistent with the provided mesh in that it is torn at the poles and at a nominal International Date Line. This cartographic representation of the earth is known as a cylindrical equidistant or plate carre projection. The ozone data are overlaid with a map of world coastlines and national boundaries in magneta as well as fiducial(See color plates, p. CP-42.)lines (lines of latitude or parallels and longitude or meridians) in white, which have been registered in this same rectilinear coordinate system. The grid cells where there are no data are quite visible as gaps in the pseudo-color realization. The area of low ozone is visible as a bluish band stretched across the bottom of the pseudo-colored rectangle.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>r)cos(cp)sin(O) (2) y = -( h + r)cos(cp)cos(O) z = (h + r ) s i n ( c p ) where [ cp , 8, r I represents the location of each node on the earth's surface as [ l a t i t u d e , longitude] at its radial distance, [ r ] , from the earth's center in the original mesh h is the height above the surface of the earth, and [ x , y , z 3 represents the location of each node in the deformed, curvilinear (spherical) coordinate system For the data being examined, there are seven pressure levels (1000, 850, 700, 500, 300, 200 and 100 millibar [mb]). The data are treated as a true volume by warping the parallelpiped mesh representation of the atmosphere into a collection of concentric spherical shells that compose a volume of 73,584 sphericaYannular cells. The maps used in figures 3 and 4 are replaced by a topo-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>combines each of the three different atmospheric data into one visual object. As with figure 4, southern and northern hemispheric views are shown, which are shown in the left and right side of the figure, respectively. The data are stacked vertically and shown with topographic, coastline and national boundary maps. The difference between figures 8 and 4 are representations for the 100 mb horizontal wind velocity and temperature stacked between that of the ozone and the maps. Below the ozone surfaces are plates of vector arrows representing horizontal winds. The direction of the arrows correspond to the direction of the wind. The size and color of the arrows corresponds to wind speed, which ranges from 0 to 80 meterskecond. Below the winds and above the maps are flat, pseudo-color-mapped translucent planes corresponding to the 100 mb temperature. These disks also show pseudo-colored isothermal contour lines every 5K, with the data ranging from 180 K to 235 K.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Color:</head><label></label><figDesc>assign pseudo-color and opacity maps Include: subset data and mesh by value</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Rubbersheet:</head><label></label><figDesc>deform mesh by value Sphere: warp mesh onto a sphere Normals: compute normals for Gouraud shading Globe: generate a globe representation of the earth Collect: aggregate inputs into a single entity Image: render an image and provide direct interaction</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>also shows the pseudo-color and opacity -map f;;r the ozone surface via ;color map editor as well as the resultant image of the ozone data registered with a globe. Almost the same visual program could be used to generate the atmospheric temperature around a globe, although the data are quite different in structure. If the data are to be volume rendered, one would eliminate the Rubbersheet operation from the program. If surface extraction techniques are to be used then the Rubbersheet(See color plates, p. CP-42.)module would be replaced with the Isosuflace module. For a simple pseudo-color image display similar to figure 3, for any of these data, one would only have steps 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>DX program to create a radially deformed pseudo-color and opacity-mapped spherically warped surface of global column ozone on October 1, 1987.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 3 : 4 :</head><label>34</label><figDesc>Pseudo-color-mapped global column ozone on October 1, 1987. figure Polar orthographic warped pseudo-colored deformed surfaces of total ozone.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>lsosurfaces of atmospheric temperatures and wind stream ribbons.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>194 K temperature surface pseudo-colored by pressure height.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Southern hemisphere orthographic warped atmospheric data on October 1, 1987.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Polar orthographic warped atmospheric data on October 1, 1987.</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1070">-2385/93 $3.00 0 1993 IEEE</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>All of the data sets discussed herein were provided courtesy of the National Space Science Data Center, NASAlGoddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Seven years of total ozone from the TOMS instrument -a report on data quality</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fleig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bhartia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wellemeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Silberstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophysical Research Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1986-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polar Stratospheric Clouds and the Ozone Hole</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hamill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Toon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schoeberl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antarctic Ozone Hole: TOMS Observations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Stolarski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>The</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geophysical Research Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1215" to="1218" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-06" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Color Scales f o r Image Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lefkowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-01" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Abram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A n Architecture f o r a Scientific Visualization System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Epstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gresh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Mcauliffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings IEEE Visualization &apos;92</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization &apos;92</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-10" />
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Frederick</forename><surname>Pearson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>11</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Map Projections: Theory and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Task Dependence, Veridicality, and Pre-Attentive Vision: Taking Advantage of Perceptually-Rich Computer Environments</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rogowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Ling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kellogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>RC 18165</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center Report</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamics of the stratospheric polar vortex and its relation to springtime ozone depletions</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Schoeberl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hartmann ; Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>An Interactive, Discipline-Independent Data Visualization System</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlative Visualization Techniques for Multidimensional Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Treinish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goettsche</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IBM Journal of Research and Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
