<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Quantum Coulomb Three-Body Problem -Visualization of Simulation Results and Numerical Methods</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ab</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Amov</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gusev</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Klimenko</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ponomarev</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Renz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Theoretical Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">S.-Petersburg State University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for High Energy Physics</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Protvino</settlement>
									<country>Moscow Region</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Russian Scientific Center &quot;Kurchatov Institute&quot;</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Moscow</settlement>
									<country key="RU">Russia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">German National Research Center for Information Technology -GMD</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sankt Augustin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Quantum Coulomb Three-Body Problem -Visualization of Simulation Results and Numerical Methods</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Some years ago it was established that the muon catalysed fusion phenomenon could be used for the production of energy. This fact has been causing a rebirth of interest in the universal methods of solving the Quantum Coulomb Three-Body Problem. The Adiabatic Hyperspherical (AHS) approach considered in this joint project has definite advantages in comparison with other methods. The case study proposed will focus on the study of the structure and behavior of the wave function of bound states of quantum three-body system as well as of the basis functions of the AHS approach. Adapted scientific visualization tools such as surface rendering, volume raytracing and tezturing will be used. Visualization allows to discover interesting features in the behavior of the basis functions and to analyze the convergence of the AHS-ezpansion for the wave functions.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>This study describes first results of a joint work of physicists and mathematicians from Russian research centers and specialists in scientific visualization at the GMD in Germany. The algorithms of the Russian scientists have been implemented on workstations and massive parallel machines at the GMD to evaluate the models of the quantum three-body problem and to visualize and analyze the results on modern graphic workstations interactively.</p><p>This incorporation of visualization techniques has made it possible to perform a visual investigation of complex quantum physical phenomena. Several techniques have been developed for the presentation of 3D and higher dimensional scalar fields (1-31. We incorporate visualization for both the analysis of the Coulomb three-body quantum states and for the validation of the computational methods used for the numerical solution.</p><p>The quantum Coulomb three-body problem has been under attention since the conception of quantum mechanics. Recently it appeared to be of great importance to analyze the problem of muon catalyzed fusion (pCF) [4]. This problem is concerned with the bound states and the continuous spectrum of the systems proton-deuteron-muon (pdp), deuteronde utero n-m uon (ddp), d eut eron-t rit ium-mu on (dt p), etc. Several methods have been developed for the solution of the different problems of pCF, e.g., the adiabatic approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5)</ref>. The wave function of the threeparticle system is represented in this method as an expansion over the complete set of the solutions to the Coulomb two-centre problem. Especially, the discovery of the loosely bound state of the dtp-mesic molecule in this approach has revived the old hopes to use muon catalysis for energy production.</p><p>Recently this method has been extended by the adiabatic hyperspherical approach for the three-body problem to describe the pCF processes [SI. The main advantage of this method is a rapid convergence of the AHS-expansion. In the three-body problem there is a lack of proper intuition compared to the insight into the two-body problem. This leads to some difficulties in the interpretation of the numerical results. The configuration space of the three-body problem is sixdimensional rather than three-dimensional. It is ,difficult to describe and imagine the properties of different functions in this space. Visualization appears to be helpful, e.g., for choosing the optimal expansion of the unknown wave function.</p><p>We will investigate the structure of the wave function of the bound state of dtp system at zero total momentum, J=O, calculated in the framework of AHS approach. Visualization allows to discover interesting features in the behavior of the basis functions (AHS harmonics) for small values of hyperradius and to study the convergence of the AHS-expansion for the wave function.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Physical and numerical problems</head><p>The research in the field of the quantum mechanical three-body problem is concerned with the following issues:</p><p>Construction of the hyperspherical basis functions (the so called AHS harmonics). Discussion of it's topological features and it's physical consequences.</p><p>Exploration of different 3-dimensional coordinate representations of the originally 6-dimensional space and the appropriate physical interpretation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Numerical solution of the radial equation on the AHS-basis and construction of ground and exited states.</head><p>Discussion of the convergence properties of the numerical solution, and in particular, the problem of local convergence of wave functions vs. convergence of global integrals like the energy. Basically, a system of 3 particles has 9 degrees of freedom ( d o n : 3 translational dof for each particle and using the center-of-mass frame of reference (translation in 3d-position space) we are left with 6 dof. These can be divided into 3 angular dof corresponding to the total angular momentum and another 3 dof referred to as iniernal dof. In our approach the hyperspherical coordinate system is the canonical way to represent these internal dof. It consists of a measure of the internal distances, the so called hyperspherical radius p, and two internal angles x and 19. Within this coordinate system the topology of the AHS basis can be observed most clearly <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">(Fig.1)</ref>.</p><p>The disadvantage comes from the fact that the hyperspherical coordinates are not closely related to the 3D coordinates of real space. Therefor we have considered other coordinate systems which are much closer to the physical intuition. For this purpose we have constructed the following Cartesian coordinates: Take the distances of each of the three particles from their center of mass and plot each of it at the one of the three coordinate axis. That way we obtain nice closed representation of the three particle wave function reminiscent of the common two particle wave functions, but with 8 quite complex structure <ref type="figure">(Fig.2</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Visualization</head><p>Generally, scientific visualization should transfer the essential content of large data sets into a visual comprehensible form. In the special case considered large 3D scalar data fields originating from numerical solutions of the quantum mechanical three-body problem have to be visualized. Specific visualization problems in this context are:</p><p>Generally, the solution of the underlying physi-</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">_ .</formula><p>cal problem is a 6-dimensional scalar field (wave function) such that an adopted reduction to a 3-dimensional subspace has to be found. Then the variation of the data in this subspace can be studied by animation sequences controlled by different pathes in the additional 3-dimensional space. A first attempt to solve this problem is the visualization of the case of zero angular momentum where the whole problem reduces to a 3-dimensional configuration.</p><p>The solution of the different problems involved essentially depends on the functional system chosen as the basis of the series expansion. The specific functional system (AHS) recently constructed shows complex spatial behavior compared to the standard functional systems. The understanding of this behavior has to be improved by analysis of the topological features.</p><p>Specific visualization tools, e.g. volume texturing, have to be developed to indicate the quality of the different solution methods. It is essential to understand the local and global convergence properties of the series influencing the correctness of the calculations of the physical parameters, for example.</p><p>The role of different coordinate systems has to be tested to find the most visual comprehensible case. It is expected that new spatial features hidden in this complex large data fields will appear.</p><p>The visualization tools used are surface rendering to show the location of iso-surfaces and volume raytracing to visualize the complex spatial behavior of the wave function, e.g., the distribution of positive and negative values, and the spatial decay at infinity. It would be very desirable to obtain an intuitive picture of the relative spatial position of the three particles involved in a bound state. For the visualization of the relative quality of different solution methods an adopted volume texturing method will be used.</p><p>Another issue of this case study will be a combined implementation of the simulation and the visualization algorithms on a massive parallel supercomputer to allow for interactive visual steering of the calculations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Analysis of the structure of AHS harmonics</head><p>In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Fig. 1</ref> we present the visualization of the isosurface of the AHS harmonics which corresponds to the system dtp. The picture is placed in such a way that an observer looks at it from the side of small radius p.</p><p>As seen, for p -, 0 the isosurfaces have quasicrossings, forming the picture close to the grid of the crossing families of lines for the angles x = const , r9 = const.</p><p>This means that in the region p -0 AHS harmonics are factorized approximately. This example shows the way the visual analysis of the numeric data can reveal new regularities and structure of physical objects which are hidden in the numeric data. <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> shows the surfaces for angle 'p = const which indicate the variety of the forms and complex nature of the physical objects under study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Analysis of the structure of wave</head><p>In the case of vanishing angular momentum, J = 0, the system dtp has two bound states: the ground state, and one excited state. The relevant wave functions describe the probability of the system to be in in specific point of the configuration space. When studying such systems it is necessary to visualize the density of the probability. The isosurfaces of the density probability corresponding to the excited state have to be considered. <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> shows that the maximal density of the probability is attained in the regions, where the p-meson is close t o one of the two heavier particles. It is interesting to note that the wave function Q is positive and the isosurface Q = 0 approximately corresponds to the surface p = const. The situation with this zero iso-surface is similar to the case of a particle in a central symmetric field. But, in our case the variables do not separate. The first excited state has always zero in the radial variable and no zeroes in the angular ones. Another interesting feature is that the appearance of functions a local maximum of the probability density near the point of triple collision. These visualized features of the wave functions are important for the construction of models of physical processes, were the system dtp is considered to be in the first excited state.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Analysis of the AHS approach convergence</head><p>When estimating the approximation one should know the accuracy of the calculatiocs. Eowever, since in different spatial regions the wave function is calculated to a different accuracy, the choice of the criterion becomes difficult. In this situation one should have the possibility to look at the approximation for the whole wave function in the whole configuration space without going into details. <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> shows the isosurfaces of the absolute value of the first term of expansion of the wave function corresponding to the first excited state.</p><p>It demonstrates that the main contribution comes from the first term of expansion. This is essentially important and points to the fact that the expansion over the AHS harmonics of the wave function under study converges uniformly in the whole configuration space. This point is very important for the reliability of numeric results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Future work</head><p>In this study we present a starting example of the role of visualization in the quantum Coulomb threebody problem. This is a first attempt to use enhanced visualization techniques in this area. For example, we have to consider the more general cases, J # 0. In those cases the wave functions will depended on six variables and animation of pictures in internal coordinates through the variation of Euler angles would be useful. We have to construct the hyperspherical basis for systems with J # 0 and to examine its topological structure by using visualization. This is a major direction of further research. In muon physics there are not only the bound states of great interest but also the quasistationary states and the processes of elastic and unelastic scattering. Numerical results for some physical issues are still absent or differ one from another very strongly depended on the method chosen. The animation tools will be implemented to see how well it works for the investigation of the S-wave scattering processes in three-body systems. This visualization process will also allow to study the behavior of the quantum three-body systems in the quasi-classical approach. We hope to explain some physical properties of the pCF-processes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(See color plates, p , CP-39.)</head><p>Improvements on the analysis of the convergency of the AHS-expansion for the wave functions are also planned.</p><p>There is still much work to be done in developing algorithms and tools to combine computation and visualization parts of our research project, like in <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref>. Due to the large scale computing power requirements these problems can be solved by using a massively parallel machine or a distributed computing environment.</p><p>The Qiraiitunz Cor~lomb ThI-ee-Bocli-Prol?lem -Visi/ali:citiori of Sirizirlcitiori Resrrlts arid Nrrrnerical Methods, D.I. Abramov et al., pp. 378-38 1.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>See color plates, p. </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The 7th AHS harmonics in the hyperspherical coordinate system (iso-surface of the zeros separating regions of positive and negative values of the wave function, threshold 0).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 Figure 3 :</head><label>23</label><figDesc>The 3rdAHS harmonics in Cartesian coordinates as explained in the Section 2 (iso-surfcce of threshold VOl Ue 0 1 ) The total wave function of the ground state with threshold 0.1Figure 4It shows the contribution of the 1st AHS harmonics to the ground state It shows that certain regions are separated</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Application of Transport Theory to Visualization of 3-D Scalar Data Fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer in Physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1991-08" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="406" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nielson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing and Modeling Scattered Multivariate Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Comp. Graphics and Appl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="1991-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illuminating the Fourth Dimension</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A I</forename><surname>Heng ; L</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ponomarev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Contemporary Physics, Vo1.31, No4</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="245" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Muon catalysed fusion</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adiabatic Representation in the Three-Body Problem with Coulomb Interaction. 1. The choice of the effective Hamiltonian</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ponomarev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Vinitsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Phys. B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1765" to="1771" />
			<date type="published" when="1979" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gusev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Puzynin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kostrykin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adiabatic Hyperspherical Approach to the Coulomb Three-Body Problem: Theory and Numerical Method</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kvitsinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Merkuriev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ponomarev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Few-Body Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="153" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integration of Visualization and Scientific Calculation in a Software System</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ruhle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Visualization 91</title>
		<meeting>Visualization 91<address><addrLine>San Diego</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE Computer Society Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="274" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
