<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">NON CONVENTIONAL METHODS FOR THE VISUALIZATION OF EVENTS FROM HIGH ENERGY PHYSICS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Drevermann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CERN Inst .f. Experiment alphysik d. Univ. Niels Bohr Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kuhn'</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CERN Inst .f. Experiment alphysik d. Univ. Niels Bohr Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nilsson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">CERN Inst .f. Experiment alphysik d. Univ. Niels Bohr Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">NON CONVENTIONAL METHODS FOR THE VISUALIZATION OF EVENTS FROM HIGH ENERGY PHYSICS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T20:29+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Visualitation of events in high energy physics is an iniportant tool to check hard-and software and to genemte pictures for presentation purposes. The radial pattern of all euents suggests the use of predefined projections, especially p&apos;/Z and Y / X. The representation can 6e improved by a &quot;fish-eye&quot; transformation and by angular projections, mhich produce straight track patte,rns aiid allow extensive magnifications. Three dimensional data of mdial structure are best displayed in the 3D \/-Plot, which has optimal track separation and presents all relevant information in a clear way.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The research in high energy physics is predominantly based on the investigation of collisions between two particles at high energy. The collisions are studied through an analysis of the particles emerging from the interactioii. Along the trajectories ("tracks") of these particles, points ("hits") are recorded in subsequent layers af tracking detectors and calorimeters. The set of all recorded hits is called an "event". A typical event recorded in the ALEPH [l] detector at the LEP collider at CERN, Geneva, is shown as front and side view in figures la,h. In this detector of cylindrical shape, a hoinogeneous magnetic field parallel to the cylinder axis curves the tracks to helices.</p><p>For the checking of hard-and software and for presentation purposes, the visualizat,ion of single events is an efficient tool. However, coinplexity of events and detectors is iiicreasiiig continuously. As a consequence, pictures of detectors and events are getting more and more coinplicated and, in the extreme, may even get incoinprehensible. Therefore, new ways of displaying events are needed.</p><p>The techniques described below were developed for the ALEPH detector. Besides many engineers, techiiicians and software specialists, about 350 physicists scliaftlichen Forschung, Austria 'Supported by grant of Fonds zur Forderung der wissen-from all over the world took part in the coiistruct,ioii of the detector and are responsible for runiiiiig it, for providing the necessary software and for data evaluation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Two dimensioaal Projectioiis</head><p>As most graphics programs are designed for general use, their performance may be insufficient for special applications. Example of conventioiial wire frame pictures are seen in figure 2, where one tries to gaiii 3D information through perspective methods. In figure 2a the cylindrical form of the detector is recognized, but its different components caiinot be distinguished. <ref type="figure">Figure 2b</ref> shows the central part of the image together with the hits recorded in the central detector (TPC). Obviously the picture needs simplification as dolie in figure 2c. The cylindrical shape of the TPC is recognized, however, since one cannot estimate the position of the hits perpendicular to the picture plane, one gets a mixture of a 3D and a 2D image.</p><p>As one is dealing with a very large number of events of the same general pattern, it is worthwhile to predefine convenient projections. Such projections are shown in figure l a and b. The froiit view of figure l a shows only those detector units, which would be drawn in a cross-section through the centre of the detector perpendicular to the cylinder axis (Z-axis). The detector is composed of very small inner detectors aiid large outer ones. In order to visualize them simultaneously, a so called "fish-eye" transformat ion is allplied to the normal Y/X projection. In this nonlinear transformation the distaiice p = d w of a point is replaced by pf = p/(l + u p ) .  </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">.......... . . ..-. ... . . ..-a ... .......... . . .--... -....... ......... ......... .......... .......... . . . ...-. . . . ..a-.-.. . I I ' : . . . . ....... // , :</formula><p>. * . I . . can be shown [a, 51, that these two projections allow t,o extract all relevant information. This is generally not, possible with only two linear projections. The particle trajectories are reconstructed from the hits sampled in the detector. In order to check the relevant hard-and software, one must be able to recognize tracks when looking at a display of the hits only. Therefore, it is of interest to understand how our visual system reacts when seeing a series of points forming lines, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3a</ref> shows a set of straight tracks drawn as solid lines and as a series of points (3b). A inagnification of the center gives recognizable tracks if drawn as lines, but if displayed as a series of points, track recognition is heavily deteriorated. After a vertical compression the tracks can again be identified (compare the bottom of figure a and b). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 3c,d</ref> show the same three lines of points in a clear environment (c) and in a very noisy one (d). The short vertical line is well recognized in the noisy environment. The ,.</p><p>. . ' 1. . *.</p><p>. . * long one is recognized after compression (see bottom of figure 3d), whereas the diagonal line is not, as the direction of conipression is not adequate. One leariis that, contrary to computerized pattern recognition, which has no problem to find the tracks, human pattern recognition needs the data to be adequately presented. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">Figure 4a</ref> shows a group of TPC tracks in Y/S Of main interest for physics are tracks of not too low 1110mentum. i.e. tracks, which exit from the TPC (see as <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">example the tracks 1,2,3)</ref>. The picture is displayed in figure 4b enlarged in vertical and compressed in horizontal direction, so that tracks are more easily identified. A further magnification in vertical direction does not improve track recognition due to the track curvature.</p><p>One can show that slightly curving tracks are a p proximately linear in the angular projections cp/p (4c), cp/Z (not shown here) and 9/19 (shown below in figure iiiiproved. If iiiagiiified further by a 2D linear transformatioil (tlie parallelogram in 4d is transformed to the rectangular window 4e), the crossing of the tracks 1,2,3 becomes very clear. The very sinal1 measuring errors of the tracking detectors get visible; this means that, screen or eye resolution do not limit the use of visual analysis, which in this respect is no longer handicapped compared to computerized track finding and reconstruction.</p><p>In conclusion, track recognition is considerably improved through linearization via angular projections aiid subsequent compression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">The Three Dimensional V-Plot</head><p>Figures 5a,b shows TPC hits from two orthogonal [2, 51 sides in Y/X and p ' / Z . In the following we will try to visualize the full 3D coiiteiit of such hits in one 3D picture. The best known method of drawing a point in 3D is shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">figure 5c</ref>, where the 3D point is represented by two image points connected by a straight vertical line. Such pairs of points have three degrees of freedom. The two image points are gained through two linear projections overlaid upon the same image.</p><p>However, this method cannot be applied in the case of a large number of hits and does not allow compression. Therefore we will try to find two angular projections, which allow coinpression and, if overlaid, yield a picture, which is easy to understand. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5d</ref> shows the same tracks as 5a,b in tlie conipressed angular projection p / R . The p/d projection yields a picture where tracks are already compressed and well separated (e). The angular projections p/R and cp/d describe best the interesting features of a track: p/R gives linear track images, where inoiiientuin and charge can be estimated from t,he gradient,, cp/d yields linear track images parallel to the p-axis, where track direct,ion, cp and il, can be est,iniated, hut not momentum and charge.</p><p>Whereas the overlay of p/R aiid p/O would produce a useless image, t,he adValitcages of both projections are conserved, if the two syniiiietric projec-  <ref type="figure">= b a z ( d ) -R, where R,,,,, is cho-</ref>sen such that D=O for hits at the outer surface of the tracking detector. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5f</ref> shows the overlay of <ref type="figure">cp/(d + k . D) and p/(d -.k . D)</ref>. Normal, low curva-ture helices give images in the form of a "V", hence the name of the picture: "V-Plot" .</p><p>The V's are images, which are easy to recognize due to their siiiiple pattern and the high level of track compression. The position of the V gives the track direction <ref type="bibr">('p</ref>  <ref type="figure">and d )</ref> , the V-direction (i.e.upwards or downwards) gives the sign of the curvature (= charge of the particle), the angle between the V arms is a measure of tlie particle momentum. It is the aim of 3D tracking detectors to measure just these quantities, which can be easily estimated visually from the V-plot, without relying on pattern recognition programs. Due to the high track compression, deviations from exact helices are enlarged (see the kink of track 8 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">figure  5</ref>). The measuring errors of the TPC get also visible, a necessary condition for thorough checking (see also discussion above).</p><p>Another aim of visual analysis is to recognize particle correlations. Tracks close to each other in space are close in the V-Plot. Tracks which cross in space are displayed as V's, where the two arms cross each other at the same value of 'p. From the V-plot in figure 5f one can deduce that there is no' pair of tracks crossing in space except for tracks 2 and 5, which have the starting point in common (i.e. one sees the decay of a neutral particle into a positive and a negative one). It was shown elsewhere [3, 4, 51, that the V-Plot technique C a l i be successfully applied for the visualization of data from other detector configurations, especially in the case of events with so many tracks, that other projections fail.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions</head><p>Tlie complexity of data from experiments in high energy physics limits the use of conventional 2D and 3D methods. When taking into account the predomiiiantly radial structure of the data, one is led to apply nonlinear transformations to generate good pictures. 3D data can be visualized by overlaying appropriate symmetric 2D projections, which leads to the V-Plot. However, tlie price to be paid is the use of more abstract representations. In short, the purpose of visual representations, namely to transfer data from the computer to the human brain, can still be accomplished. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Acknowledgements</head><p>The successful construction and running of the ALEPH detector by the collaboration provided the events, for which the methods described in this paper were developed, where we have had input from many of our colleagues in ALEPH. We owe special thanks to Chris Grab, Salvador Orteu, Mark Parsons, Raimund Vogl and Rongfen Xu for their valuable coiitributions to the program and to Jiirgeii Iinoblocli, Dieter Schlatter and Jack Steinberger for helpful discussions and suggestions.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure l b shows</head><label></label><figDesc>the so called side view, which is a +/Z = p'/Z projection. p' changes sign, when crossing the interactively defined straight, line drawn in figure la. The images of the different subdetectors do not overlap and are therefore well discernible. Y/X and p'/Z are especially suitable for the understanding of data of radial structure, where practically all tracks emanate froin a point close to the center. It.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 :Figure 2 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Display of an event from the CERN ALEPH detector. (a) front view, (b) side view (T, TPC = tracking detectors, C = calorimeters) Wire frame picture of an event in the ALEPH detector. (a) TPC and calorimeters, (b) part of (a) with TPC hits, (c) TPC and hits. , ._".. ..</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Identification of tracks from hits.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>... ,,,:::.. . 3 i s , . . * . . . . . . *.Cl **: ............... :........</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Picture compression to improve track visibility. (a) Y/X, (b) Y/X with horizontal inagnification and vertical compression, (c) p / p , (d) p / p coinpressed, (e) cp/p with horizontal magnification and vertical compression.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Y+Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Explanation of the 3D V-Plot. (a) Y/X, (b) p'/Z, (c) perspective picture of a 3D point, (d) p/R, (e) p/dl (f) V-Plot 5e) [a, 4, 51. Via a horizontal compression of the linearized hacks (4d), track identification is considerably</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>tions p/(O + IC . R ) and cp/(dk . R) are used instead. Picture interpretation is improved, if R is replaced by D</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The methods described above get more efficient if colors are used, which allow to correlate objectshits, tracks , detector unitson different subpictures. Figure G shows the front view of ALEPH (a), the V-plot of the TPC hits (b) and, aa a link between them, the cp/p projection (c).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Display of an ALEPH event. (a) Y/X, (b) V-Plot of TPC hits, (c) a section of the V-Plot</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Decamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucl. Instr. Meth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">294</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Drevermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Grab</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">hit. Jour. Mod. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Drevermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Grab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nilsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the international conference on Comput.-ing in High, Energy Physics 91</title>
		<editor>N.Magnenat, Thiamine and D.Thalmann</editor>
		<meeting>the international conference on Comput.-ing in High, Energy Physics 91<address><addrLine>Tsukuba, Japaii</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1991" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">545</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>New Trends in Animation and Visualization</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is there a Future for event display</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Drevermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Iiuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nilsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of tlie 1992 CERN School of Computing</title>
		<meeting>tlie 1992 CERN School of Computing<address><addrLine>Aquila, Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to be published. (See color plates</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Noti Converitional Methods.foI-the Visrrali:ntiot1 of Evetits from Higll Et1el-g)&apos; Plz)3sics</title>
		<editor>H. Drevermann, D. Kuhn, and B.S. Nilsson</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="386" to="390" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
