<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Time-Varying Multivariate Volume Data Using Matrix of Isosurface Similarity Maps</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Exploring Time-Varying Multivariate Volume Data Using Matrix of Isosurface Similarity Maps</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T19:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Time-varying multivariate data visualization</term>
					<term>isosurface</term>
					<term>similarity map</term>
					<term>visual interface</term>
					<term>path recommendation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>directions, respectively. (d) and (e) show the isosurface view with surface silhouettes and original surfaces, respectively.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Many scientific simulations produce time-varying multivariate volume data that can span hundreds or thousands of time steps and consist of tens of variables. Additionally, ensemble data sets are common nowadays, where a simulation is conducted in multiple runs with different configurations. This leads to the multiplied amount of data to be studied. Understanding the underlying physical phenomena in this kind of data often requires key insights to be discovered through observations. This need places analysis and visualization of time-varying multivariate data at the heart of scientific visualization. There are two dominant techniques to visualize volumetric data sets: direct volume rendering and isosurface rendering. Direct volume rendering relies on the specification of a transfer function that maps scalar values to colors and opacities for rendering. The visualization can highlight particular values or value ranges with high opacity while deemphasizing non-interesting ranges with low or zero opacity. Isosurface rendering explicitly extracts one or multiple isosurfaces from the volume data and renders these surfaces as the visual data representation. The rendering can reveal important data features or structure if the corresponding isovalues are salient or representative. In this work, we focus on the less-explored surface-based analysis in the context of time-varying multivariate data visualization. Our goal is to investigate volumetric data evolution over space and time and across multiple variables and ensembles by extracting a range of isosurfaces, computing their similarities, identifying representative surfaces, and presenting a visual interface to organize, summarize, and explore the underlying time-varying multivariate data set.</p><p>Several key challenges are involved with this approach. First, studying the similarities for all the surfaces across time steps and variables leads to a very large number of similarity maps. For instance, for a data set of 100 time steps and ten variables, the total number of similarity maps amounts to 55,000. These include 1000 self-similarity maps, 49,500 temporal similarity maps, and 4,500 variable similarity maps (refer to Section 1 in the Appendix). Without an effective way to organize and visualize them, examining such a large number of similarity maps would become a daunting task. Second, even though similarity maps can help us see the summarized information, we still need to examine related isosurfaces in the original spatial view to identify where and how they are (dis)similar. However, since a single similarity map typically compares tens or even hundreds of isosurfaces, it is not practical for users to manually select the related isosurfaces for further examination. This task will be even more exhausting when the temporal development of a variable is studied as thousands of isosurfaces may be involved. Third, rendering just a few surfaces may already lead to serious occlusion and clutter which prevents clear observation and comparison. This calls for new techniques that render a number of surfaces with minimal occlusion while preserving their spatial relationships or context. Finally, it could take hours to compute pairwise isosurface similarities for only a single volume if no approximation, downsampling, or acceleration solutions are considered <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. This makes it impractical to apply the same computation process to generate similarity maps for a typical time-varying multivariate data set, although the process is only done once. Therefore, it is imperative to seek a cost-effective solution to make the similarity computation scalable.</p><p>We tackle the above challenges and present the matrix of isosurface similarity maps (MISM), a new approach for comparative visualization of time-varying multivariate volume data. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> sketches the diagram of our MISM framework. During preprocessing, self-similarity maps are first computed for each volume of the data. For each self-similarity map, we then select a set representative isovalues and compute the corresponding isosurfaces. Finally, each of these isosurfaces is simplified to save storage space and support runtime interaction. Furthermore, the information acquired from self-similarity map computation will be used to derive temporal and variable similarity maps. At runtime, all similarity maps (self, temporal, and variable) will be used to construct MISM. We provide a list of functions for users to explore the collection of similarity maps and compare the underlying isosurfaces. The contributions of our work are the following:</p><p>• We extend the isosurface similarity map (ISM) to study the similarity across the temporal and variable domains. We select representative isovalues from the self-similarity maps and use them to efficiently compute the temporal-and variable-similarity map. • We design MISM, a matrix-based visual interface to organize these similarity maps and present various ways (i.e., temporal clustering, variable grouping, filtering, recommendation, and comparison) for effective relationship overview, level-of-detail exploration, and comparative study. • We leverage and modify a silhouette-based method to visualize a number of related isosurfaces in a visually succinct manner. This allows users to examine the similarities and differences of a large number of surfaces in the isosurface view, presenting essential information while reducing occlusion and clutter. • We demonstrate the usefulness of our approach with case studies of several time-varying multivariate data sets and one ensemble data set. We evaluate our system with two experts. The results show that MISM enables users to gain a deep understanding of the data across the spatial, temporal, and variable domains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p>Data analysis and visualization. Analysis and visualization of timevarying multivariate volumetric data is an important yet challenging topic in scientific visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27]</ref>. For time-varying data, researchers have studied efficient volume rendering based on spatiotemporal coherence <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>, transfer function specification <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, and direct rendering of multiple time steps into a single image <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>. They also experimented with illustration-inspired <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> and importance-driven <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref> techniques for visualizing time-varying data. For multivariate data, researchers have investigated query-driven visualization using compound range queries <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> and fuzzy queries using textual pattern matching <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. They also explored variable correlation including point-wise correlation coefficients and gradient similarity measure <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, causal relationships between variables using transfer entropy <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref>, variable grouping using mutual information (surprise and predictability) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, and information flow between variables based on association rules (informativeness and uniqueness) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. We investigate the relationships among different volumes of time-varying multivariate data by extracting representative isosurfaces from each volume based on its similarity map and computing the similarity maps among representative isosurfaces from volumes of different time steps and variables.</p><p>Visual abstraction and interface. Time-varying multivariate data are high-dimensional and complex, which poses great challenge to effective visual exploration and comparison. The conventional way of only visualizing these data in the original space-time view does not solve the inherent occlusion and clutter problem, nor does it offer a viable solution for data feature or relationship selection, exploration, and tracking. Therefore, researchers have studied various alternatives that map data and their relationships to lower-dimensional, often abstract spaces and representations to assist relationship overview, interaction, and navigation <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>. Examples include the tri-space (i.e., spatial, temporal, and variable) interface that allows exploration of the temporal and variable dimensions of data along with the spatial context <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, multifieldgraphs for studying correlation fields in a hierarchical manner <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, interactive storyboard for overall time-varying data visualization and feature exploration <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>, attribute cloud that enables users to examine high-dimensional multivariate attributes in a 2D space <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>, recurrence plot that shows temporal similarity between two time-dependent signals as a matrix for recurrence detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref>, AniViz for animation creation from time-varying multivariate volume data <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, TransGraph for investigating the transition relationships in time-varying data <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, multivariate transfer function interface design that tightly couples parallel coordinates plots and dimension projection plots <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, and iTree for compacting, indexing, and exploring time-varying data <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. We design a visual interface that organizes the matrix of ISMs for overview, filtering, and summarization, as well as detailed examination of volume relationships over spatial, temporal, and variable domains.</p><p>Comparative visualization. To study data similarities and differences, one can employ comparative visualization to compare different time steps, spatial locations, data variables, or modalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. Gleicher et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> proposed a general taxonomy of visual designs for comparison in information visualization based on the three building blocks of juxtaposition, superposition, and explicit encodings. Verma and Pang <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> pointed out that scientific data can be compared at the image, data, or feature level, depending on the level of data abstraction. They studied comparative visualization tools for analyzing flow fields which allow the comparison of individual streamlines and stream ribbons as well as a dense field of streamlines. Woodring and Shen <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> developed a volume shader for time-varying multivariate data visualization. The shader allows users to select multiple data volumes to create comparative visualization along with the presence of contextual information. Schneider et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> presented a solution for interactive comparison of scalar fields using isosurfaces. They defined features in two scalar fields by largest contour segmentation and matched these features using a similarity measure based on their spatial overlap. A thumbnail gallery of feature pairs and a graph representation are used to show all relationships between individual contours. Lampe et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> designed a curve-centric volume reformation technique to create compelling comparative visualizations. The technique deforms the volume surrounding a curve and preserves the spatial neighborhood to the curve, thus permitting arc-length parameterized data visualizations in parallel for comparison. Malik et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref> presented a comparative visualization technique that uses a multi-image view and an edge explorer for dimensional measurement using 3D X-ray computed tomography. Their generic solution can be applied to other application areas such as parameter study of imaging modalities and detection of artifacts in data sets. Schmidt et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref> designed a comparative visualization tool named VAICo for visualizing similarities and differences in large image sets. This tool not only preserves contextual information but also enables detailed analysis of subtle variations. Our purpose is to investigate the evolution of time-varying data in the context of multiple variables using surface-based visual representation. We achieve this goal by clustering and filtering a large number of ISMs organized as a matrix along with comparative surface summarization and rendering techniques that reveal the spatial relationships of the corresponding isosurfaces.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DESIGN REQUIREMENTS</head><p>To investigate the physical phenomenon of the multifaceted timevarying multivariate data sets, experts need to understand the relationships among time steps, variables, and value ranges, which are often complicated and dynamic. The relationships of value ranges of multiple variables may exhibit various patterns even at a single time step, and these relationships may evolve over time and develop into different patterns. Understanding these relationships can hardly be achieved without an effective visual analytics system. We formulate the design requirements of such a system as follows:</p><p>R1. Overview. The system should provide two levels of overview. First, it should allow users to observe the overall relationships between variables and time steps at the volume level, helping them answer questions such as which variables are more similar, which time steps are more similar, and which variables exhibit more frequent changes than the others? Second, it should allow users to understand the relationships at the isovalue level. Similar questions should be answered at this level with more detail: which ranges of isovalues lead to the relationships discovered at the volume level?</p><p>R2. Identification of representatives. The system should quantify the similarities among time steps, variables, and isovalues and derive the representative ones. This provides users more quantitative evidence to verify the relationships they observe from the overview and to reduce the search space for detailed exploration.</p><p>R3. Relationship-centric exploration. The system should provide multiple modes to investigate various types of relationships, including the relationships among value ranges for a given variable at a specific time step, the relationships among variables at a specific time step, the relationships of the same variable at different time step, the temporal evolution of the relationships of two variables, and the relationships of a specific feature and others (which may not reside in the same variable), etc. The system should be able to quantify each type of relationship and the interface should be optimized to allow exploring each type of relationships efficiently.</p><p>R4. Multi-step comparison path. The dynamic relationships among variables may require comparisons of hundreds of surfaces to be demonstrated. The system should decompose these complicated relationships into a path of multiple comparison steps. Each step should reveal a facet of the relationships with a reasonable number of surfaces that can be effectively rendered for clear visual comparison. In addition, the system should also maintain the consistency between surfaces in consecutive steps to preserve the user's mental map.</p><p>R5. Path customization. Users should be able to interact with the system to customize paths focusing on certain variables of interest or a specific type of relationship described in R3. The customized path should answer questions such as how does a feature evolve over time, what are the surfaces related to the selected one over time, and what are the most different surfaces from the selected one over time?</p><p>R6. Path animation. The system should produce an animation that concisely describes the comparison path with isosurface rendering. The animation should answer the questions in R1 with more detail: it not only indicates which isosurfaces are (dis)similar, but also describes how they are (dis)similar by providing the isosurfaces in the spatial view. For effective visual comparison, the isosurfaces at each animation frame may need to be rendered in different styles, allowing the more important ones to be observed clearly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">MATRIX OF ISOSURFACE SIMILARITY MAPS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Overview</head><p>Based on our analysis of requirements in Section 3, we design MISM as the main visual representation and interface for exploring the underlying time-varying multivariate data set. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, our interface consists of four components: parameter panel, matrix view, isovalue view, and isosurface view. The matrix view is the core component of our system. It displays MISM in multiple modes to allows the observation of both an overview of the data set (R1) and different types of relationships among variables (R3). The matrix of maps allows the relationships to be understood both at map-level (volumes) and celllevel (isosurfaces). With visual hints provided by the MISM display, users can easily identify the variable/isovalues of interest and interact with the matrix view to navigate the related variables/isovalues. The key function we introduce for navigating MISM is path recommendation (R4 and R5): users can select two or more similarity maps in MISM and we recommend a traversal path that maximizes certain criteria (e.g., the smoothest, or most surprising path). In conjunction with the isovalue and isosurface views, animating the path in MISM and displaying the corresponding isosurfaces enable users to conveniently tour through the underlying data set (R6).</p><p>As described in the Appendix, we define three types of similarity maps in this paper: the self-similarity map (SSM) of the isosurfaces from individual volumes, the temporal similarity map (TSM) of the isosurfaces from the same variable at different time steps, and the variable similarity map (VSM) of the isosurfaces from different variables at the same time step. The definition of similarity follows that of the ISM approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>. The matrix view provides four display modes to explore different types of relationships: (1) the single-variable mode that displays a single SSM to explore a single volume; (2) the singlepair mode that displays a VSM or TSM and the two corresponding SSMs for comparison of two volumes (e.g., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> (a)); (3) the all-pairs mode that displays all SSMs and VSMs for selected variables at a given time step (e.g., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref> (a)); and (4) the evolution mode that displays all SSMs and VSMs for selected variables and time steps through clustering and filtering (e.g., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> (b)). Only the evolution mode displays multiple time steps, where the horizontal direction represents the selected variables and all related variable pairs, and the vertical direction represents representative time steps. SSMs of the selected variables and all related VSMs are displayed but not TSMs.</p><p>Interaction and typical workflow. We propose a set of interactive functions for navigating the huge matrix of similarity maps (see <ref type="figure">Figure</ref> 2). We cluster temporal sequences and group variables to reduce the exploration space (R2). We also highlight representative cells in a similarity map to attract user attention and guide the exploration (e.g., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>). A typical workflow to explore a data set using MISM is as follows. Users will start by examining the matrix view in the evolution mode, which shows the SSMs and VSMs of all the representative time steps and variables. This provides users an overall understanding of the data set and guides them to discover the time steps and variables of interest. Then, users can simply click and drag to form a path that reveals the temporal development of the selected variables and time steps. Users can further create waypoints to edit the traversal path so that the connections to additional features can be discovered. In the evolution mode, users can easily click an SSM to enter the singlevariable mode or click a VSM to enter the single-pair mode for detailed exploration. They can specify a time step to explore the relationship among all variables in the all-pairs mode as well. Finally, they can create paths to investigate the isovalues in these detailed modes.</p><p>Next, we introduce temporal clustering and variable grouping (Sec-tion 4.2), path recommendation and graph construction (Section 4.3), and silhouette-based rendering and animation (Section 4.4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Clustering and Grouping</head><p>We reduce the size of MISM along the temporal and variable dimensions through clustering temporal sequences and grouping variables, respectively. This not only allows users to quickly identify the representative time steps or variables for exploration, but also produces more compact paths and animations for efficient knowledge discovery. We define a similarity measure between volumes using TSMs or VSMs and use it to derive the similarity between two time steps or two variables. We apply affinity propagation <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> to cluster the temporal sequences based on the similarity measure. Affinity propagation automatically determines the number of clusters, which naturally reflects how frequently the variables change along time in a data set. For variables, we use k-means clustering to group the variables into the desired number of groups. In the following, we only describe our similarity measure for temporal clustering, as the detail for variable grouping is the same. Similarity measure. We evaluate the similarity of two volumes based on the similarities among their isosurfaces. Two volumes are considered to be similar if for each isosurface in one volume, a similar isosurface can be identified in the other volume. Our similarity measure is analogous to the mean of closest point distances defined on two curves by considering each volume as a curve and each isosurface of the volume as a point on the curve. Formally, the similarity of an isosurface S and a volume V is defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">S (S , V) = min S∈V S (S , S),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where the similarity between two isosurfaces, S (S , S), can be looked up from TSMs or VSMs. The similarity of two volumes V i and V j is defined as the weighted average of the similarity of each isosurface in one volume to the other volume, i.e.,</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">S</formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">(V i , V j ) = ∑ S p ∈V i w S p S (S p , V j ) ∑ S p ∈V i w S p + ∑ S q ∈V j w S q S (S q , V i ) ∑ S q ∈V j w S q ,<label>(2)</label></formula><p>where the weight w S p for an isosurface S p is derived based on its representativeness ranking, which is used for selecting the most representative isovalues (Section 1 in the Appendix). Note that the similarity between any pair of volumes is in [0, 1], which has the same range as the similarity between any pair of isosurfaces. Temporal clustering. Temporal clustering evaluates the combined similarity between two time steps as the summation of similarities calculated for each of the variables using Equation 2. Affinity propagation is applied to cluster the time steps based on their combined similarities. For each cluster, the clustering algorithm identifies one exemplar, which is considered as the representative time step for that cluster.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Path Recommendation</head><p>MISM has a two-tiered structure: maps at the coarse matrix level and cells at the fine map level. The map-level captures the overall relationships among volumes, while the cell-level allows the detailed relationships among isosurfaces to be discovered. Given two userspecified maps (cells) as the start and end points, path recommendation identifies a series of intermediate maps (cells) to construct a path for traversal. We create an animation for the generated path, showing the isosurfaces corresponding to a map (cell) at one animation frame. Users can adjust the weights of different terms to define the desired path. They may visit the maps or cells to discover affinity relationships or compare distinct features. The differences between frames can be minimized or maximized for generating a smooth animation or increasing information gain. They can specify the start and end points of a path in the matrix view, and drag any point along the path to add waypoints. We identify a path that minimizes the total cost between the user-specified points.</p><p>We introduce the following types of paths: (1) map-level paths for the evolution mode, (2) cell-level paths for all the four modes, and (3) variable traversal paths for only the all-pairs mode. All three types of paths are built with similar constructions. In the following, we discuss map-level paths in detail. For the other two, we only explain their differences with respect to map-level paths. We denote a similarity map between two variables A and B at time step τ as M AB,τ and their corresponding volume as V A,τ and V B,τ . Note that M AB,τ can refer to an SSM when A = B or a VSM when A = B. However, it does not refer to a TSM (which is not displayed in the matrix view) as the indices do not specify two different time steps. We use M AB,τ [i, j] to denote a cell in M AB,τ at the i-th row and the j-th column, and S A,τ,i and S B,τ, j to denote the two isosurfaces corresponding to the i-th row and j-th column, respectively. We may ignore τ in the notation for simplicity when time is not discussed. We define the difference D(, ) between two elements as 1 − S (, ).</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">B C A A A B C D τ τ − 1 τ + 1 B C A A A B C D B C A A A B C D (wtsC ( ) + wtgC ( )) α (wtsC ( ) + wtgC ( )) α B C A B (a) (b) SA,τ,i SB,τ,j A B B SB,τ,j C (i, j) . . . . . . τ (j, l) A B (i, j) SA,τ+1,i SB,τ+1,j τ + 1 SC,τ,l SB,τ,j A B SA,τ,1 SA,τ,m SC,τ,1 SC,τ,m SB,τ,j B C (c) (d)</formula><p>Map-level path. We identify the map-level path between two similarity maps as the shortest path in a map-level graph. A map-level graph is a directed graph whose nodes are all SSMs and VSMs and whose edges are all the possible transitions from one map to another, as illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3 (a)</ref>. Specifically, we consider two kinds of transitions: (1) variable transition between similarity maps at the same time step sharing at least one common variable, as shown by the blue arrows; and (2) temporal transition between similarity maps at neighboring time steps, as shown by the red arrows.</p><p>Weighing the edges appropriately is critical to obtaining a path that shows the desired features. In our approach, the weight of an edge corresponding to a transition is a linear combination of the target cost C tg and the transition cost C ts raised to a user-specified power exponent α: (w tg C tg +w ts C ts ) α , where w tg and w ts are the weights of C tg and C tg , respectively. We include α to further distinguish the edge costs, so that the shortest path is less likely to end up with a path with a larger average cost but a smaller number of edges. Consider the transition M AB → M BC (from the yellow node to the green node) in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">V B , V C )</formula><p>between the two corresponding volumes V B and V C . When the target cost is weighed positively, the shortest path is more likely to visit the maps corresponding to variables with similar structures by minimizing the cost. When the target cost is weighed negatively (we use 1 − C (M BC )), the resulting path tends to visit the variables with different behaviors for the most surprise. The transition cost is the penalty when we replace the isosurfaces to display for M AB to those for M BC . It can be weighed positively in the linear combination, so that the shortest path minimizes the transition cost and maintains a smooth animation between neighboring frames; otherwise, it can be weighed negatively using 1 − C (M AB → M BC ) to visit the maps with diverse information.</p><p>A variable transition from a VSM M AB,τ to another M BC,τ indicates that the focus of analysis shifts from one pair of variables (A and B) to another pair (B and C). After the transition, we replace the isosurfaces of A with the ones of C in the isosurface view. Therefore, we weigh the corresponding edge by the difference of their volumes, i.e., D(V A,τ , V C,τ ). The edge weight for transitions between a VSM and an SSM can be defined similarly by letting A = B. For coherence, variable transitions should take place only if necessary. To avoid the paths from jumping back and forth among the variable pairs, we include a sufficiently large jumping cost in the variable transition.</p><p>A temporal transition between two VSMs M AB,τ and M AB,τ+1 describes the evolution of the two variables A and B over time. The corresponding edge weight is defined as (D(</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">V A,τ , V A,τ+1 ) + D(V B,τ , V B,τ+1 ))/2.</formula><p>Cell-level path. Similar to the map-level path, the cell-level path is the shortest path between two cells in a directed cell-level graph. Each node in the cell-level graph represents one cell and each edge represents one transition. For the cell-level graph, we consider three kinds of transitions, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref> (c): (1) variable transition (the blue arrows) between cells in two similarity maps at the same time step sharing at least one common variable; (2) temporal transition (the red arrow) between cells in two similarity maps corresponding to the same pair of variables at different time steps; and (3) isovalue transition (the green arrows) between cells in the same similarity map. Similarly, the edge weight is a linear combination of transition cost and target cost. The target cost is given by the difference of the two isosurfaces corresponding to the target cell. The transition cost is defined by the difference between the isosurfaces that are not shared by the two cells. For example, for a variable transition M AB,τ [i, j] → M BC,τ [ j, k], the transition cost is the difference between S A,τ,i and S C,τ,k , i.e., D(S A,τ,i , S C,τ,k ).</p><p>We further provide two options for users to improve the cell-level path. First, we allow users to specify the exact endpoint as cells, or simply select a map that contains the endpoint. When a map is specified, the cell with minimum cost is automatically identified on the map. In this case, we create an edge from each cell in the map to a dummy node with zero weight and compute the shortest path. Second, we design a scheme to further reduce the average cost between cells. The shortest path often tends to minimize the total cost along the path by reducing the number of cells. It is possible to identify a path with a minimum number of undesired transitions. Therefore, finding a path with the smallest average weight between nodes is more desired in our scenario. Since this problem is NP-hard, we provide an approximate solution here. We start with the shortest path identified by Dijkstra's algorithm and compute the average weightw along the path. Then, we create a cell-level reduced weight graph. This graph contains the same edges as the original cell-level graph, but the weight of each edge is reduced bȳ w. The edges with negative weights are eliminated by assigning a small weight (0.001 in our implementation) to them. Note that the edges with weights smaller thanw have a minimum cost now. This allows a longer path with more desirable transitions to be identified as the shortest path in the reduced weight graph. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> (b) and <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref> show two cell-level paths produced by the reduced weight and original graphs, respectively. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 4</ref>, we can see that without reducing the weights, the path only visits one cell in each map at similar locations, even under the setting of w tg = 0.1 and w ts = −1, which suppose to show more distinguished isosurfaces. In contrast, with the reduced weight graph, the path usually visits multiple cells in each graph to increase the information gained, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1 (b)</ref>. For a quantitative comparison, we evaluate the average weight of the two paths in the original graph. The path produced by the reduced weight graph can effectively bring down the average weight from 0.227 to 0.172.</p><p>Variable traversal path in all-pairs mode. A variables traversal path visits a chain of variable pairs that covers every variable for a complete understanding of relationships among variables at a given time step. For example, this chain can be &lt; A, B &gt;→&lt; B,C &gt;→&lt; C, D &gt;→&lt; D, A &gt; for a data set with four variables. Given a userspecified cell (and therefore a pair of variables to start), we determine the order of variables to visit using a greedy strategy: at each step, we select the unvisited variable that is most similar to the current variable.</p><p>The variable traversal path is identified in a variable traversal graph which is constructed similarly as the cell-level graph with variable transitions and isovalue transitions. The definitions of transition cost and target cost are the same as the ones described for the cell-level graph. The only difference is that variable transitions are constrained to take place between only boundary cells following the order of the maps being visited. For example, consider the two pairs of variables &lt; A, B &gt; and &lt; B,C &gt; to be neighbors along the path, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">Figure 3</ref>  This forces the path to enter and leave a similarity map at the boundaries to build a more complete path visiting a large portion of value range for each variable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Surface Rendering and Animation</head><p>We render the isosurfaces using an approach based on per-pixel link lists <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> for real-time order independent transparency. The rendering is performed in two passes. The first pass generates a link list for each pixel to store the fragments that are rendered to that pixel. The second pass sorts fragments at the same pixel according to their depth and blends the fragments in the sorted order. Inspired by the silhouette-based rendering <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, we only render the silhouettes for the less important isosurfaces to reduce visual clutter. We combine these two approaches by checking whether a fragment belongs to the silhouettes before storing the fragment in the link lists. The fragments of the less important isosurfaces that are not related to the silhouettes are discarded to reduce the storing and sorting effort. Using our approach, rendering some surfaces as silhouettes not only allows clearer observation but also has a lower cost than rendering all surfaces in full.</p><p>An animation will be produced when a path is specified in the matrix view. As shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>, with the evolution mode of the matrix view, we also display the isovalue view to show the evolution of isovalues corresponding to the rendered isosurfaces. We synchronize the animation across the matrix, isovalue, and isosurface views. The path is displayed in both the matrix and isovalue views with the current animation step highlighted. We display a timeline in the isovalue view. Users can drag it to play a specific animation step. They can also drag the highlighted isovalues in the isovalue view to create additional waypoints and modify the path. When multiple variables are involved in an animation, the isosurfaces are colored according to their corresponding variables, as indicated by the legends in the isosurface view (e.g., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1 (d)</ref>). We create an animated transition for each variable transition on the path to gradually transit from one variable to another. When a single variable is used in an animation, we color the isosurfaces according to their representativeness. The representativeness ranking is indicated by the legends shown in the isosurface view, with the most representative one displayed on the left (e.g., <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13 (a)</ref>). By default, we render the complete isosurface for the most representative one and the silhouettes for the others. Users may switch the focus to render any representative isosurface as a complete one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Data Sets and Timing Performance</head><p>We used several time-varying multivariate data sets with different sizes and characteristics for our experiment. The data sets and timing performance are reported in  <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 1</ref>. The average timing results for computing an SSM, an isosurface and its simplified version, a TSM, and a VSM using a CPU/GPU, and the total computation time for the entire data set using the CPU/GPU cluster.  TITAN X GPUs). The computation of the distance fields and similarity maps (SSMs, TSMs, and VSMs) was performed in the GPU, while isosurface extraction and surface simplification were performed in the CPU. The timing for SSM (256 × 256) includes the time to compute distance fields, joint histogram, and mutual information. The time costs for surface extraction and simplification mainly depend on the complexity of the surface and the number of triangles involved. The timing for TSM or VSM <ref type="bibr">(16 × 16)</ref> includes the time to compute joint histogram and mutual information. The time cost to compute a TSM or VSM mainly depends on the size of distance fields. In our experiment, since the computation of similarity maps or isosurfaces consists of largely independent tasks, we use 8 CPU cores and 8 GPUs of the CPU/GPU cluster to speed up the computation in parallel, reducing the total computation time for each data set to a day or less. We further examine the accuracy and speed-up of our similarity map computation. Our solution introduces two major variants to speed up the computation: using approximation (APP) to replace GPU-accelerated marching cubes (MC) for surface generation and using downsampled (DS) distance fields instead of the ones with original (ORI) resolution. We evaluate the performance of different combinations of these two </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DS-MC</head><formula xml:id="formula_6">X = {x 1 , • • • , x n } and X = {x 1 , • • • , x n }, MSE is computed as MSE(X, X ) = 1 n n ∑ i=1 |x i − x i | 2 .<label>(3)</label></formula><p>For the climate data set, we collect the results using ten sample time steps, and for the others, we use five sample time steps. Note that this already contains 1.3 million to 2 million similarity values per data set so that we can draw a reliable conclusion. In <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>, we can see that using downsampled distance fields produces mostly the same similarity values, with the largest MSE being 0.0134 for the ionization data set. Surprisingly, we find that DS-APP outperforms ORI-APP in terms of MSE for all the data sets, probably because distance fields of the original resolution may be more sensitive to the errors introduced by the approximation. DS-APP produces reasonable results with MSE smaller than 0.05 except for the atmospheric data set (0.1637). In terms of efficiency, DS itself speeds up the computation by more than 10×. APP does not lead to large speed boost with ORI, but it can further increase the performance of DS, resulting in 30× to 300× speed-up.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Case Studies with Expert Evaluation</head><p>Combustion data set. This data set comes from direct numerical simulation of temporally evolving turbulent non-premixed flames. The simulation generates five variables: heat release (HR), mixture fraction (MF), vorticity (VORT), mass fraction of hydroxyl radical (YOH), and scalar dissipation rate (CHI). Initially, the thin planar scalar layers are placed in the middle of the computational domain. The layers evolve into complex isosurfaces as they interact with the surrounding turbulence. Combustion reactions occur within the scalar layers. We invited a domain expert with 20 years of experience in turbulent combustion modeling and simulation to explore this data set using MISM. The exploration started with the evolution mode of the matrix view with four variables (HR, MF, VORT, and YOH), as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">Figure 5</ref>. The expert commented that the similarity maps at different representative time steps are able to summarize the overall data characteristics. For each individual variable, at earlier time steps, since the scalar layers are planar, all scalars are well correlated, and most regions of the SSMs in the bottom rows are purple. As time goes on, these scalar layers are distorted by turbulence. Meanwhile, the scalar layers are thickened since small-scale turbulence enhances scalar mixing. As the scalar layers are thickened and interact with turbulence, the isosurfaces corresponding to lower and higher values become dissimilar. Therefore, the positive correlations (purple cells) only appear along the diagonals of the SSMs in the top rows. The expert further pointed out that the matrix view demonstrates the relationship development of YOH and MF over time. YOH and MF are perfectly correlated, when combustion reaction time scales are much shorter than turbulence time scales. This condition is closely satisfied at later time steps, as the YOH-MF VSMs in the top rows show a strong correlation near the diagonal regions. On the contrary, at earlier time steps, the fast chemistry condition is not satisfied. This leads to no evident correlation of these two variables at earlier time steps. The SSMs in the bottom rows confirm this by exhibiting more uniform correlations. In addition, the expert found that the relationship between VORT and MF is interesting, since the VORT-MF VSMs gradually develop into a pattern with a purple upper-left triangle and a green lower-right triangle. The expert stated that the physical origin of this trend could not be fully understood at this moment, but it was likely related to the effects of HR on turbulence. This demonstrates the potential of our work for revealing physics behind the data set.</p><p>Then, the expert analyzed the relationships among four variables (VORT, CHI, MF, and YOH) at time step 111 using the all-pairs mode of the matrix view. Time step 111 is the first time step of the last temporal cluster. The all-pairs mode facilitates better comparison of the VSMs. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6 (a)</ref>, the expert found that the pattern of the YOH-MF VSM is different from others. As already observed in the evolution mode, the diagonal of YOH-MF VSM is mostly purple, indicating  strong correspondence between the value ranges in YOH and MF. The only exception is the top-right corner corresponding to larger isovalues of YOH and MF, which is mostly green. This means that the larger isovalues of these two variables are less relevant to each other. The expert explained that the value of YOH is the highest in the reaction zone and decreases toward the fuel and oxidizer sides, which correspond to the lower and higher values of MF, respectively. Therefore, there is no evident correlation of YOH and MF at higher values of each variable. The expert selected a purple cell in this VSM, as highlighted in the blue circle, to generate a variable traversal path. A positive target weight (w tg = 1) was used to identify a path demonstrating similar isosurfaces for each of the variable pairs: YOH and MF, MF and CHI, CHI and VORT, and VORT and YOH. A small transition weight (w ts = 0.1) was used to maintain the minimum smoothness between the consecutive animation frames. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref> (b) to (e) show four animation frames presenting the similar isosurfaces. The similarity of isosurfaces seen in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6</ref> (c) indicates that the variations of CHI on isosurfaces of MF occur mainly at large scales, which happens mostly for thin scalar layers with high values of CHI. The regions where the CHI and MF isosurfaces collapse correspond to the thin layers with steep scalar gradients (high values of CHI). In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Figure 6 (d)</ref>, while the isosurfaces of CHI and VORT are complex, the expert pointed out that low CHI regions correspond to high VORT regions, because strong vortical motions tend to mix scalars and reduce their gradients.</p><p>Finally, the expert switched to the evolution mode of the matrix view to further investigate the relationship between YOH and MF. Two purple cells were specified as the starting and ending points in the YOH-MF VSMs. Two paths were generated for comparison: one with a positive target weight (w tg = 1) and the other with a negative target weight (w tg = −1). The transition weight w ts was set to 0 to eliminate the influence of transition cost, and α was set to 4 to allow more edges with smaller cost. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7 (a)</ref> shows the path with the positive target weight and the isosurfaces in three animation steps along the path. The path passes only the purple regions near the centers of the VSMs, corresponding to the middle range isovalues of YOH and MF. In the isosurface view, it can be seen that the blue isosurfaces occupy similar regions as the corresponding orange ones at all the three time steps, due to the correlation of YOH and MF. In contrast, the path with the negative target weight goes through the green regions at the bottomright corners of the VSMs, even if it starts and ends at purple cells, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Figure 7</ref> (b). This path mostly relates to the high MF isosurfaces and the low YOH ones. In the isosurface view, it can be seen that the blue and orange isosurfaces are disjoint in the space. As the wrinkling history of isosurfaces due to turbulence is different for isosurfaces present in different regions, the dissimilarity is expected.</p><p>Atmospheric data set. A set of 3D numerical experiments is performed to explore the mechanical impacts of Graciosa Island on the dry boundary layer evolution under varying wind speed and surface friction setups. The simulations are conducted using the Cloud Model 1 (CM1 release 19 <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>). The full data set has 32 ensemble simulations which are comprised of four basic wind speeds <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref>, and 20 m/s), four wind directions (west, east, north, and south), and two bottom boundary conditions (friction/no friction). Two variables, the U and W components of the wind flow, are studied. To distinguish the variables under different simulation setups, we add the initials of the wind directions and speeds to the names of variables. For example, "E5U" stands for variable U with the east wind direction and speed 5 m/s.</p><p>We invited a domain expert with ten years of experience in atmospheric sciences to evaluate MISM using this data set. Since friction effects are more pronounced in lower wind speeds, the expert focused on the 5 m/s case to visualize and analyze flow variability. The expert first investigated the evolution of variable U under different wind directions with friction and 5m/s wind setup. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8 (a)</ref> shows the matrix view in the all-pairs mode at time step 13. The SSMs at the diagonal show that the west and east have similar patterns, and so do the SSMs of the north and south. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8 (b)</ref>, the isovalue view shows a similar relationship. The representative isovalues distribute similarly for the four wind directions at time step 2 (bottom). In contrast, at time step 13 (top), the distributions form two different patterns. The expert explained that this means from time step 2 to 13, the west and east show much larger flow variability compared to the north and south, which is attributed to the west-east orientation of the island located at the center of the simulation domain. The representative isovalues spread out in different directions for the west and east, but the representatives of the south and north are still similar to those in the first time step. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8 (c)</ref> shows that the isosurface of the north (orange) has quite a different shape from that of the west (blue). Unlike the blue isosurface, the orange one covers both the upper and lower portions of the domain, although the isovalue is small. In contrast, the isosurfaces corresponding to small absolute wind speeds of the west (blue) and east (orange) have similar shapes, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8 (d)</ref>. Both isosurfaces reside in the lower portion of the domain, although their orientations are opposite. By selecting the isovalues representing larger wind speeds (as highlighted by the red circle in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8 (a)</ref>), the expert found that the corresponding isosurfaces are also similar, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Figure 8</ref> (e). These two isosurfaces occupy mostly the entire domain as the wind gets stronger. The expert commented that the east wind direction seems to be more interesting. It demonstrates more variation on the surfaces and in the isovalue view, due to a stronger island effect on incoming flow in this configuration.</p><p>Then, the expert compared four variables within the east wind direction: E5U, E5W, E1U, and E1W (i.e., variables U and W with wind speeds 5 m/s and 1 m/s). Only one temporal cluster is produced by affinity propagation, indicating a consistent pattern over time. Therefore, the expert used all individual time steps to explore their temporal relationships. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">Figure 9</ref> shows the overview of the evolution mode of the matrix view. In general, the expert found that the patterns of matrices in different rows are similar, which confirms the temporal clustering results. Note that, for E5U and E1U, the purple regions in the middle value range are growing over time. The expert commented that this is indicative of the non-steady simulation behavior. By displaying the isosurfaces, the expert found that the purple region corresponds to surfaces covering the entire domain. This trend indicates that, at the later time steps, the surfaces of different value ranges of U tend to cover more space and become more similar to each other. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10 (a)</ref> shows two isosurfaces of a larger isovalue of E1U at time step 2 (blue) and time step 13 (orange), respectively. It can be seen that the orange surface covers almost the entire domain, but the blue one is mainly located at the center of the domain.</p><p>The temporal development of variable W with wind speeds 5 m/s and 1 m/s seems to be slightly different. While the pattern in column E1W is more stable, the purple region in E5W is shrinking over time. This indicates that, unlike variable U, the isosurfaces of E5W appear to be similar at the beginning, but tend to be more distinguishable over time. Although the development trend is different, the expert found that E5W and E1W become more similar in the larger value range, since the upper-right corners of the E1W-E5W TSMs gradually transit from green to light green. At time step 2, the isosurfaces corresponding to a larger isovalue of E5W (blue) and E1W (orange) occupy different spatial regions, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10 (b)</ref>; but at time step 13, the two isosurfaces reside in the same region, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 10 (c)</ref>. However, the similarity is still not high, since the distance between different layers of the blue surfaces is much larger.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Additional Case Studies</head><p>Climate data set. This data set was generated from a simulation of salinity (SAL) and temperature (TEM) in the equatorial region from 20°S to 20°N for a period of 100 years. This data set contains 1200 time steps (one month per time step), from which temporal clustering identifies 13 representatives, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>. From the representatives, we can see that SAL exhibits a more stable pattern than TEM. Interestingly, although our temporal clustering does not consider the order of time steps, nine months in the first year are selected as representatives. Overall, the clusters are consistent with the monthly weather change in each year. But we can also notice that for two long periods of time, most of the time steps are placed in the same cluster, as highlighted in the blue rectangles.  Then, we examine the temperature change with the El Niño condition. We select time step 289 (with El Niño), as highlighted by the red bar in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 11</ref>, and compare it with time step 265 (without). Time step 265 corresponds to the same month as time step 289, but two years before. The single-pair mode of the matrix view displays the two SSMs on the left and the corresponding TSM on the right, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> (a). The arrows indicate TEM from low to high. We find that both SSMs share the same pattern: the low TEM isosurfaces are very similar to each other, indicated by a dark purple block; the medium TEM isosurfaces are moderately similar to each other and the low TEM ones but not that similar to the high TEM ones; and the high TEM isosurfaces are similar to each other but not that similar to the low and medium TEM ones. Similar patterns can be observed in the TSM as well, except that the high TEM isosurfaces do not share high similarity.</p><p>By selecting the cell highlighted in the blue circle, the isosurface view renders a high TEM isosurface (blue) and a low TEM one (orange) at time step 265 for comparison, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12 (b)</ref>. The high TEM isosurface is associated with a small region close to the ocean surface and the low TEM one covers the entire oceans at the bottom. By selecting the cell highlighted in the red circle, two isosurfaces at time step 289 are displayed, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> (c). We can see that the low TEM isosurface is mostly the same as the corresponding one at time step 265; but the high TEM isosurface is quite different, with the central and eastern equatorial Pacific Ocean covered, confirming the existence of El Niño. By selecting the cell highlighted in the green circle, we compare the two high TEM isosurfaces, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12 (d)</ref>.</p><p>The cells related to these two isosurfaces are highlighted by rectangles in the corresponding colors, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> (a). <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 12</ref> (e) shows two high TEM isosurfaces at time steps 265 and 241 (which is exactly two years before 265). Clearly, without the El Niño condition, the high TEM regions are similar in the same month across years.</p><p>Ionization data set. For this data set, we find that all SSMs show a similar pattern: the purple cells mostly concentrate along the diagonals leaving other regions in green. This indicates the strongly localized pattern for isosurfaces at different value ranges. We use map-level paths to trace the movement of the ionization front for each individual variable and show the corresponding isosurfaces in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref>. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> (a) to (c) correspond to H2 at three representative time steps at the beginning, middle, and ending stages, respectively. Obviously, the most representative isosurface shown in blue moves from left to right and demonstrates different shape characteristics. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> (a), we can also observe three other representative isosurfaces with a similar shape as the most representative one, displayed as the orange, red, and purple silhouettes. However, in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> (b), the other representative isosurfaces are occluded by the most representative one shown in blue. Therefore, we shift the focus to the orange one, as shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> (d). The blue, green, and purple silhouettes indicate that the isosurfaces form multiple layers of the same structure. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13 (c)</ref> shows the isosurfaces of H2 at the ending stage. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 13</ref> (e) to (h) show a similar process for H+ but with a different shape of the ionization front.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUDING REMARKS</head><p>To provide a convenient mechanism for users to browse through a large time-varying multivariate or ensemble data set in the form of isosurfaces, we present MISM, a visual interface that organizes a huge number of ISMs for navigation and exploration. We design effective solutions to achieve both computational scalability (by computing a massive number of self, temporal, and variable similarity maps using GPU-accelerated approximation) and visualization scalability (by presenting MISM at different levels of detail via clustering, grouping, and filtering schemes). To the best of our knowledge, both scalabilities have not been demonstrated previously in this context. With advanced features such as path recommendation and surface comparison, MISM is the first of its kind that supports flexible relationship exploration and examination among isosurfaces extracted from the multifaceted data, providing the capability that goes beyond a traditional animation playback could offer.</p><p>In the future, we would like to investigate an alternative semantic abstraction of MISM. This would sprout the opportunity to further simplify the relationships to a much condensed form for understanding. We would also like to create a static visualization variant that summarizes the isosurfaces in path animation, so that the relationships among the isosurfaces can be understood using a single image.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>MISM interface. The cells in the similarity maps are colored purple/white/green for high/medium/low values. A path is specified to reveal the connections between the isosurfaces of variable U corresponding to four different wind directions using the atmospheric ensemble data set. (a) shows the parameter panel. (b) shows the matrix view with a user-specified path. A summarized view of the matrix is displayed on the left and the representative SSMs and VSMs related to the path are displayed on the right. (c) shows the isovalue view. The blue, orange, green, and red paths correspond to the isovalues of U under the west, east, south, and north wind</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Top: map-level graph construction. (a) transitions in map-level graphs. (b) edge weights corresponding to two transitions between maps M AB and M BC . Bottom: transitions between cells. (c) transitions in cell-level graphs. (d) transitions in variable traversal graphs.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(b). The target cost C (M BC ) is the difference D(</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>timeFig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The path with the same start point and parameters asFigure 1(b). The example shown here uses the original cell-level graph instead of the reduced weight graph.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(d). We only allow transitions from the boundary cells M AB,τ [1, j] and M AB,τ [m, j] in map M AB,τ to the boundary cells M BC,τ [ j, 1] and M BC,τ [ j, m] in map M BC,τ that correspond to the same isosurface S B,τ, j .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>timeFig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Overview of the evolution mode of the matrix view with four variables (HR, MF, VORT, and YOH) of the combustion data set.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Variable traversal paths using time step 111 of the combustion data set. (a) shows a path with a positive target weight (w tg = 1, w ts = 0.1, and α = 4). (b) to (e) show four animation frames corresponding to the path in (a). variants (i.e., DS-MC, ORI-APP, and DS-APP) by comparing them to the ground truth (ORI-MC). The accuracy is evaluated by the mean of squared error (MSE). Giving two sets of values</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Cell-level paths in YOH-MF VSMs using the combustion data set. (a) shows a path with a positive target weight (w tg = 1, w ts = 0, and α = 4) and three corresponding animation frames. (b) shows a path with a negative target weight (w tg = −1, w ts = 0, and α = 4) and three corresponding animation frames.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Comparison of four wind directions with friction and wind speed 5 m/s using the atmospheric ensemble data set. (a) shows the all-pairs mode of the matrix view at time step 13. (b) shows the isovalue view at time steps 2 (bottom) and 13 (top). (c) to (e) show two isosurfaces of variable U corresponding to (c) small absolute wind speeds of the west and north, (d) small absolute wind speeds of the west and east, and (e) large absolute wind speeds of the west and east.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Overview of the evolution mode of the matrix view with two variables (U and W) produced under two wind speeds (5 m/s and 1 m/s) using the atmospheric ensemble data set.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 10 .Fig. 11 .</head><label>1011</label><figDesc>Isosurface rendering of (a) E1U at time steps 2 and 13, (b) E5W and E1W at time step 2, and (c) E5W and E1W at time step 13.time Overview of the entire climate data set of 1200 time steps.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 12 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>The single-pair mode of the matrix view using the climate data set. (a) shows the TSM comparing time steps 265 and 289. Time step 289 is associated with the El Niño condition. (b) and (c) show a high TEM isosurface (blue) and a low TEM one (orange) at time steps 265 and 289, respectively. (d) shows two high TEM isosurfaces at time steps 265 (blue) and 289 (orange). (e) shows two high TEM isosurfaces at time steps 241 (blue) and 265 (orange).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 13 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Isosurfaces corresponding to map-level paths using the ionization data set. (a) to (c) show the representative isosurfaces for H2 at time steps 31, 98, and 181, respectively. (d) shows the same isosurfaces as (b) but focusing on the orange isosurface. (e) to (g) show the same as (a) to (c) but for H+.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>• J. Tao, M. Imre, C. Wang, and N. V. Chawla are with University of Notre Dame. E-mail: {jtao1, mimre, chaoli.wang, nchawla}@nd.edu. • H. Guo and G. Sever are with Argonne National Laboratory. Email: {hguo, gsever}@anl.gov. • S. H. Kim is with The Ohio State University. E-mail: kim.5061@osu.edu. Manuscript received xx xxx. 201x; accepted xx xxx. 201x. Date of Publication xx xxx. 201x; date of current version xx xxx. 201x. For information on obtaining reprints of this article, please send e-mail to: reprints@ieee.org, and reference the Digital Object Identifier below. Digital Object Identifier no. xx.xxxx/TVCG.201x.xxxxxxx</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 2. The diagram of our framework. Self-similarity maps (SSMs) are computed for each volume of the data, from which we compute representative isovalues and isosurfaces and further derive temporal similarity maps (TSMs) and variable similarity maps (VSMs). At runtime, SSMs, TSMs, and VSMs are used to construct MISM for users to explore the underlying data set.</figDesc><table><row><cell>[1] surface approximation</cell><cell>SSMs [2] downsampled distance field</cell><cell>[1] joint histogram</cell><cell cols="2">TSMs &amp; VSMs [2] mutual information</cell><cell>temporal clustering</cell><cell>path</cell><cell>MISM</cell></row><row><cell>[3] joint</cell><cell>computation</cell><cell>computation</cell><cell></cell><cell>computation</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">recommendation</cell></row><row><cell>histogram</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>variable</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>computation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>grouping</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>[4] mutual information computation</cell><cell>[5] representative isovalue identification</cell><cell cols="2">[1] isosurface extraction</cell><cell>isosurfaces [2] surface simplification</cell><cell>interactive filtering</cell><cell cols="2">surface comparison</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The timing was collected using a CPU/GPU cluster (8 Quantum TXR231-1000R servers each with a dual Intel E5-2650 12-core CPU @ 2.2 GHz, 128 GB RAM, and 4 NVIDIA</figDesc><table><row><cell>data set atmospheric climate combustion ionization</cell><cell>dimension x × y × z × v × t 360 × 360 × 112 × 32 × 13 360 × 66 × 27 × 2 × 1200 480 × 720 × 120 × 5 × 122 600 × 248 × 248 × 8 × 199</cell><cell>distance field x × y × z 45 × 45 × 14 120 × 33 × 9 60 × 90 × 15 75 × 31 × 31</cell><cell>SSM 26.85s 4.85s 50.66s 25.99s</cell><cell>extraction 8.31s 0.18s 8.11s 4.34s</cell><cell>simplification 94.20s 1.82s 56.44s 14.40s</cell><cell>reduction 7.56× 9.39× 10.72× 12.42×</cell><cell>TSM 0.0953s 0.0810s 0.2290s 0.1936s</cell><cell>VSM 0.0941s 0.0778s 0.2275s 0.1919s</cell><cell>total 24.1h 10.9h 23.5h 20.1h</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p>This research was supported in part by NSF grants IIS-1456763, IIS-1455886, and CNS-1629914, DOE grant DE-AC02-06CH11357 and SciDAC program, and NVIDIA GPU grant program. The authors would like to thank the anonymous reviewers for their insightful comments.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A tri-space visualization interface for analyzing time-varying multivariate volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Akiba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Eurographics -IEEE VGTC Symposium on Visualization</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics -IEEE VGTC Symposium on Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="122" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AniViz: A template-based animation tool for volume visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Akiba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conceptual recurrence plots: Revealing patterns in human discourse</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Angus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wiles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="988" to="997" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An information-aware framework for exploring multivariate data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Biswas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dutta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Woodring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2683" to="2692" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isosurface similarity maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="773" to="782" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A benchmark simulation for moist nonhydrostatic numerical models</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fritsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Monthly Weather Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2917" to="2928" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Screen-space silhouettes for visualizing ensembles of 3D isosurfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Demir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kehrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustering by passing messages between data points</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dueck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="972" to="976" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of temporal similarity in field data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sadlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ertl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2023" to="2032" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing temporal patterns in large multivariate data using textual pattern matching</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Glatter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Daniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1467" to="1474" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual comparison for information visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Albers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Jusufi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TransGraph: Hierarchical exploration of transition relationships in time-varying volumetric data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2015" to="2024" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iTree: Exploring time-varying data using indexable tree</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="144" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable multivariate volume visualization and analysis based on dimension projection and parallel coordinates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1397" to="1410" />
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Volume analysis using multimodal surface similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Haidacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1969" to="1978" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progressive meshes</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hoppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH Conference</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGGRAPH Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="108" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient GPU-accelerated computation of isosurface similarity maps</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Imre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="184" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brushing of attribute clouds for the visualization of multivariate data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jänicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Böttinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1459" to="1466" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study of transfer function generation for time-varying volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jankun-Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of Eurographics -IEEE TCVG Workshop on Volume Graphics</title>
		<meeting>Eurographics -IEEE TCVG Workshop on Volume Graphics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Illustration-inspired techniques for visualizing time-varying data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Joshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rheingans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization Conference</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="686" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maximizing parallelism in the construction of BVHs, octrees, and k-d trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Karras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH/Eurographics Conference on High-Performance Graphics</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGGRAPH/Eurographics Conference on High-Performance Graphics</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="37" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization and visual analysis of multifaceted scientific data: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kehrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Curve-centric volume reformation for comparative visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lampe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Correa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1235" to="1242" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association analysis for visual exploration of multivariate scientific data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="955" to="964" />
			<date type="published" when="2016" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marching cubes: A high resolution 3D surface construction algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ACM SIGGRAPH Conference</title>
		<meeting>ACM SIGGRAPH Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="169" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive storyboard for overall time-varying data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="150" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing time-varying volume data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Computing in Science and Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative visualization for parameter studies of dataset series</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Heinzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="840" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalised recurrence plot analysis for spatial data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Marwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kurths</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Saparin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics Letters A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4-5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="545" to="551" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multifield-Graphs: An approach to visualizing correlations in multifield scalar data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sauber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Theisel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Seidel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="917" to="924" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VAICo: Visual analysis for image comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Heinzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruckner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2090" to="2099" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive comparison of scalar fields based on largest contours with applications to flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wiebel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Carr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hlawitschka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scheuermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1475" to="1482" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fast volume rendering algorithm for time-varying fields using a time-space partitioning (TSP) tree</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L.-J</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization Conference</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="377" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Query-driven visualization of large data sets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stockinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shalf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bethel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization Conference</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative flow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Verma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="624" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graphs in scientific visualization: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analyzing information transfer in time-varying multivariate data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Grout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="106" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Importance-driven time-varying data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1547" to="1554" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-variate, time-varying, and comparative visualization with contextual cues</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Woodring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="916" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High dimensional direct rendering of time-varying volumetric data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Woodring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of IEEE Visualization Conference</title>
		<meeting>IEEE Visualization Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="424" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time concurrent linked list construction on the GPU</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hensley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Grün</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Thibieroz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1297" to="1304" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
