<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">matExplorer: Visual Exploration on Predicting Ionic Conductivity for Solid-state Electrolytes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jiansu</forename><surname>Pu</surname></persName>
							<email>jiansu.pu@uestc.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hui</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Boyang</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Zhengguo</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Yanlin</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
							<email>zhuyanlin@uceri.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yunbo</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yong</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Computer Science and Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">are with VisBig Lab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Electronic Science and Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">matExplorer: Visual Exploration on Predicting Ionic Conductivity for Solid-state Electrolytes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A2B1C71314FD3189B7C1D9F8688C848D</idno>
					<note type="submission">received xx xxx. 201x; accepted xx xxx. 201x. Date of Publication</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.1" ident="GROBID" when="2022-06-13T13:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Interactive visualization</term>
					<term>machine learning</term>
					<term>materials discovery</term>
					<term>ionic conductivity</term>
					<term>high-dimensional data</term>
					<term>solid-state electrolytes</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. System overview: a) control panel view, providing some interactions and parameter setting; b) parallel coordinate view, revealing feature distributions of materials. Each axis represents each feature. Each data item is a line that runs through multiple coordinate axes; c) clustering view, representing the similarities of materials. C1 is the overview map of all data points after dimensionality reduction and clustering. C2 provides a comparison of multiple materials. The cursor is moved to the data point you are interested in, click it to select this data and add its detailed information to C2, select up to five. C3 shows the feature contributions for selected cluster through seven bars colored with the same color as the clusters; d)data encoding design view, displaying all the information of a material. All data points displayed in c1 are reduced versions. When the cursor hovers over the data points, more details will be displayed. e) model comparison view, comparing models through five metrics. In the radar chart, each model is depicted as a polygon and each metric is depicted as an axis.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>battery system with the highest overall performance. They have high energy density and cycle life, powerful and portable, and widely used in various fields, such as mobile phones to laptops <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[41]</ref>. The electrolyte plays an undoubtedly critical role in the LIB components. Electrolytes mainly exist in liquid form, whose ion conductivity reaches as high as 10 −2 Scm −1 , providing favorable conditions for LIBs to achieve high rate performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>. However, liquid organic electrolytes have many safety concerns, such as electrolyte leakage, flammable solvents, poor thermal stability, and many side reactions at the electrode interface, leading to heating and even explosions <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">42]</ref>. Compared with liquid electrolytes, solid electrolytes have many benefits, such as wider electrochemical window and higher stability, allowing solid-state batteries to gain higher safety, greater energy density and stronger cycling. Therefore, solid electrolytes can be used as the most suitable alternatives to organic liquid electrolytes. Unfortunately, the ionic conductivity of solid electrolytes is generally lower than that of liquid ones. Thus, they cannot take the place of the liquid electrolytes directly.</p><p>Searching for solid electrolytes with high ionic conductivity has always been challenging in the research field of solid electrolyte. Over the past few years, first-principles computation has played an important role in the successful prediction. However,the inefficient experiments and computational models, which usually consume considerable time and resources and are limited by their experimental conditions and theoretical basis, seriously hinder the progress of material discovery. Different from the traditional research methods, machine learning (ML) methods have been introduced for screening of solid electrolyte materials due to their efficient and powerful capability of recognizing complex patterns in data. A team from Stanford <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref> proposed a procedure of applying ML to screen solid electrolyte materials without experiments. However, their results are limited to the insufficient learning process by few ML models, and all results are interpreted only with knowledge, without any actual experiment verification. We enlarge the training sets and increase the learning rates by comparing different ML algorithms. We ultimately propose a visualization system to assist in the analysis and decision-making by intuitively presenting the performance of various models. Our system, including five parts, can display and explain the data from various perspectives, and then provide much guidance for manual screening of materials, avoiding blind attempts and experiments. The major contributions are summarized as follows: <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> We have implemented the visualization system to facilitate analysis, judgment, and decision-making to search solid electrolyte materials with high ionic conductivity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> We have proposed an interactive visual analysis including feature composition, model performance comparison, and final predication result presentation to assist the domain experts in selecting possible suitable solid electrolyte materials for further inspection in actual experimental environments.</p><p>(3) The effectiveness of our system has been proven through one actual case. One candidate for solid electrolyte materials has been selected by analyzing and interpreting the ML predication results visually for inspection in the lab. After several months, we finally prepared the material in the lab and tested its lithium ion conductivity with an acceptable result.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK 2.1 Necessity of Solid Electrolytes</head><p>LIBs are mainly composed of four parts, namely, the positive electrode, the negative electrode, the separator, and the electrolyte. Among the components, the electrolyte plays an especially crucial role because they are responsible for the conduction of ions between the electrodes. The performance of the electrolyte directly affects the capacity, using temperature, safety, and cycle performance of LIBs. Traditional electrolytes are usually composed of organic liquid electrolytes. Although the lithium ion conductivity of organic liquid electrolytes reaches as high as 10 −2 Scm −1 , providing favorable conditions for LIBs to achieve high rate performance; organic solutions are generally flammable and unstable, indicating safety risks. In addition, with the frequent use of LIBs, lithium ions are deposited unevenly and form lithium dendrites. When the dendrites grow excessively, they break off and no longer par-ticipate in the reaction, causing irreversible capacity loss to the battery system. Moreover, the grown dendrites pierce the separator between the positive and negative electrodes of the battery and result in a short circuit; thus, the hidden safety risks of the battery include overheating, spontaneous combustion, or explosion.</p><p>People spare no effort to find suitable alternatives because of these problems. They attempt to reduce the flammable nature of the liquid electrolytes to formulate safe electrolytes with enhanced battery performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">43]</ref>. However, this approach still cannot solve the lithium dendrite issues. Recently, the main focus of interest has already shifted to solid-state electrolytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">46]</ref>. Using solid electrolytes instead of traditional organic liquid electrolytes to assemble lithium metal batteries can effectively solve these problems. Compared with liquid electrolytes, solid electrolytes are naturally non-or less flammable, nonleaking, and nonvolatile. They not only ensure the safety of the battery, but also avoid the problem of short battery life caused by the drying up of the long-term circulating liquid electrolytes. Solid electrolytes generally have a wider electrochemical window than organic liquid electrolytes, further broadening the battery voltage range. They can also prevent the growth of lithium dendrites, thereby fundamentally avoiding the short-circuit phenomenon of the battery and restricting the large volume change in the lithium negative electrode during charging and discharging to a certain extent.</p><p>In summary, the use of solid electrolytes improves the safety, energy density and power density of lithium batteries, and broadens the battery operating temperature range and application fields. However, compared with liquid electrolytes, the ionic conductivity of solid electrolytes is low, and the cost is high; thus, realizing an industrial production is difficult. At present, no suitable material has been found. This condition has been the main bottleneck of solid electrolyte research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">ML Analysis for Material Screening</head><p>Over the past few years, first-principles computation has played an important role in the successful prediction in the field of material science. Traditional methods of material research are based on computational models or empirical or experimental trial-and-error approaches, which have long experimental period, consume abundant resources, and can be limited by their experimental conditions and theoretical basis. These problems in searching seriously hinder the progress of material discovery. Therefore, a new method is urgently required to speed up the discovery and design process of new materials. With the boom of material big data, data-driven, or ML methods have opened new paradigms for the discovery and design of materials due to its capability of recognizing complex patterns in data <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24]</ref>.</p><p>Rather than relying directly on intuition, ML technology offers the promising capability to construct accurate models rapidly and directly, through representing the material with key descriptors, such as a combination of chemistry, composition, and crystal structure; then, the desired material properties are obtained. Meredig et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref> constructed the ML models to screen for novel ternary compounds and predict 4500 new stable materials. Oliynyk and Mar <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref> applied various ML methods to solid-state chemistry about the crystal structure of the compounds and accelerated search for materials with desired properties. Sendek et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32]</ref> proposed a new large-scale computational screening method using ML methods based on the structure and electronic information to reduce the list of candidate materials from 12,831 to 21, showing promising electrolytes. Zhang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[44]</ref> proposed an unsupervised learning scheme for guiding material discovery, and demonstrate it for material discovery of solid-state lithium ion conductors. Chen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> summarized the process of ML and general algorithms in materials science. Traditional methods in material searching seriously hinders the progress of material discovery due to its high cost and limited theoretical basis. ML technology offers a promising capability to construct accurate models rapidly and directly; it reduces the cost of an expensive high-throughput first-principles and offers brand insights for material experts to build models; the prospective of data statistical features is more than the material physical and chemical properties. Recently, the material discovery and design using ML have received increasing attention, and great progress has been made in time efficiency and Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. The pipeline for screening and visual analyzing the certain predication results. Our system enables users to explore and analyze lithium containing materials data details from various perspectives. We first prepossessed the collected material data by taking steps in (a). Then the calculation results will be used by multiple ML models and evaluated in (b). After that the domain experts can interactively select potential candidate in (c) by exploring and analyzing the model performance, feature distribution, and predication results.</p><p>prediction accuracy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Interactive Visual Analysis</head><p>With the development and great success of ML due to its capability of recognizing complex patterns in data rapidly, it has been applied in multidisciplinary fields, including materials science. However, the use of these ML models has been hindered because of the inherent black box nature of ML models <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>. Most users lack ML knowledge and aim to determine the model execution in a certain approach, the decision making, and success or failures in certain situations <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>. Visual analytics community <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33]</ref> can tackle this problem by developing methods to open the black box of ML models.</p><p>Visual analytics techniques are straightforward and provide contextual information beyond summary statistics; they have been successfully applied in many fields <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">39]</ref>. Yue et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[40]</ref> constructed an interactive visual analytics system, namely, BitExtract that attempts to explore the evolutionary transaction patterns of Bitcoin exchanges over time through a large number of sequence views, thereby summarizing the development of the Bitcoin market. Ganuza et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> designed an interactive visual analysis application containing most maps commonly used in spinel minerals, which helped geologists analyze the statistical information more efficiently. Bernard et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> developed the dashboard networks to visualize multiple attributes in patient histories' these networks help understand variations in patient histories over time and between cohorts. Sun et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref> constructed a visualization system supporting different model comparisons and selection for demand forecasting based on the products with similar historical demands.</p><p>Visual analytics techniques also play an important role in helping users understand the models. Zhao et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[45]</ref> proposed a visual analysis system that aims to explain random forest models and predictions, through providing users with all tree information and the decision path in the random forest, which ultimately reflects the working mechanism of the model. Chen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref> proposed a new visual abstraction scheme to optimize the display of multiple scatter plots. Cavallo et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> proposed new interactive tools to guide cluster analysis, which can effectively explore and navigate large clustering spaces and improve the effectiveness of exploratory cluster analysis. Ma et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref> used a multifaceted visualization scheme including models, data instances, features, and local structures, which are designed to support the analysis of data poisoning attacks. Visualization techniques develop intuitive and straightforward methods to help users simplify problems and assist analysis and thinking; they can provide people with deep and unexpected insights in their research.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">DOMAIN BACKGROUND</head><p>The liquid electrolyte used in traditional LIBs has many potential safety concerns, such as leakage, flammability, and explosion. The solidstate electrolyte with higher energy density and safety is considered an ideal alternative. LIBs are mainly composed of four parts including the positive electrode, the negative electrode, the separator, and the electrolyte. The solid-state electrolyte is the core component, whose performance directly affects the performance of LIBs. Although researchers have begun to realize the importance and usefulness of the solid-state electrolyte, systematic and efficient methods that can find suitable electrolyte materials remain lacking.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Current Screening Workflows</head><p>To find the suitable candidate materials, five constraints are summarized from the first-principles as follows: low electronic conductivity, high metal stability, high structural stability, high oxidation decomposition stability, and high ionic conductivity, according to the requirements of working temperature, safety, stability, energy density, and environmental friendliness. The first four constraints are called prerequisite constraints, and the last high ionic conductivity is the most critical. We can obtain the first four attributes by formulas using parameters from the material project (MP) database. Nevertheless, obtaining an ionic conductivity is difficult; the last constraint is unavailable in the calculation formula.</p><p>The lithium ion conductivities of solid-state electrolytes are strongly affected by many features of materials, such as chemical composition, atomistic and electronic structure. 20 features closely related to ion conductivity, characterizing the local atomic arrangements and chemical properties of the crystals, are selected from the perspective of the internal chemical structure of materials to construct an ML prediction model. These 20 features are derived from 26 original properties describing the chemical structures and are accessible from the MP database.</p><p>The increase in the number of features or properties is a challenge to discovery of new desired materials. In addition, no single feature can determine the lithium ionic conductivities because many features play different roles in the ionic conduction of superconductors. Thus, many solid-state electrolytes were developed by inefficient and timeconsuming trial and error experiments due to the absence of a comprehensive analysis of these features. In the last decades, a few numbers of superionic conductors with desired room temperature conductivity were discovered and could not be applied in common products thus far. For lithium-containing materials, the number of allowed candidate solid-state electrolytes is in tens of thousands. This chemical space is extremely vast and complex to search through experiments. To this end, data-driven ML methods are gradually introduced into inroad materials science.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Raw data collection and processing</head><p>A total of 12,831 Li-containing compounds can be obtained from the MP database, as well as the corresponding DFT-calculated atomistic and electronic structure information, also called 26 original properties. First, we apply four prerequisite constraints to the 12,831 candidates, and then we can reduce the candidate materials from 12,831 to 343. These 343 candidate materials will be used to predict a set of ML models. If and only if the candidate's ionic conductivity is sufficiently high, then it is expected to be a suitable solid electrolyte material. To achieve this goal, we turn our attention to the ML methods.</p><p>Reed et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref> spent two years to obtain 40 types of materials with experimentally measured ion conductivity values available in the literature. We spent one year to obtain another 22 types from the reported literature. Thus, the training set has 62 samples to build a prediction model. We label these 62 materials as 0 or 1 according to the value of their ionic conductivity. If the value of the ion conductivity is higher than 10 −2 Scm −1 , then we label it as 1, which indicates that its ion conductivity is expected; otherwise, we label it as 0.</p><p>We also calculate the 20 features for the 343 remaining candidate materials, using 26 original properties. We apply the trained model to the 343 candidates and obtain 343 corresponding output labels. These 343 candidates are screened from the first four prerequisites, which indicate that the material corresponding to label 1 among the 343 output labels is a suitable solid electrolyte material expected, with low electronic conductivity, high metal stability, high structural stability, high oxidation decomposition stability, and high ionic conductivity. For this ML process, we trained the model by experimental data. Studies on the lithium ionic conductivities of superionic conductor have continued for decades, and many materials have been experimentally synthesized.</p><p>To build an appropriate database for the classifier and prediction model, we established a training set, which contained the structure and ionic conductivity information of 62 materials in the published literature and the online database. We build a "target" database, where material data were downloaded from the MP website, to search for new superionic conductor. We obtain the DFT-calculated atomistic and electronic structure information, which utilize the MP's Python module Pymatgen.22 for each of the 12, 831 Li-containing candidate materials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Feature exploration and dimensionality reduction</head><p>The computational cost and time cost of the selected 20 features are very high due to the particularity of the physical and chemical properties of the material data. We spend considerable time with domain experts to calculate the specific values of 20 features by adjusting the parameters and consultation data every time. We should screen the features by some methods because of the time cost, according to the suggestions of domain experts. We focused on the correlation of features and the impact on the final prediction performance to select the important features and reduce the calculation cost and time by selecting few important features.</p><p>In accordance with the work of Reed et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref> of Stanford University, we calculated 20 features of all materials in the data set. We initially calculated the Pearson correlation coefficient between the features and lithium ion conductivity, but found that the correlation is not strong. Thus, we selected the error rate of predicting the lithium ion conductivity, according to the logistic regression model to screen. We calculate the lowest error rate of the logistic regression algorithm under different types of feature combinations, and found that when the number of selected features is the material data 7, the error rate of the algorithm is the lowest, at approximately 0.03, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. Then, based on the features selected when the number is 7 and the error rate that reaches the minimum value, combined with the consideration of redundancy, over-fitting, and under-fitting <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">47]</ref>, the following seven features are selected for ML modeling: average atomic volume, AAV; standard deviation in Li neighbor count, SDLC; standard deviation in Li bond ionicity, SDLI; average Li-Li bonds per Li, LLB; packing fraction of sublattice, SPF; average straight-line path width, SLPW; average straight-line path electronegativity, SLPE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">ML methods</head><p>The ML models for predicting the ion conductivity of materials mainly consists of three parts, as follows: training data sets, a set of features describing each material, and an ML algorithm that maps features to target attributes of the ion conductivity. Rather than relying directly on intuition, ML technology offers the promising capability to construct Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>. The maximum error rate under different amounts of feature combinations. The condition of only one feature is not calculated because it can't be the most appropriate situation. The optimal selection number is seven.</p><p>accurate models rapidly and directly by representing the material with key descriptors, such as a combination of chemistry, composition, and crystal structure; then the desired material properties are obtained. Computers can rapidly learn from the training data sets, also called empirical data sets by using the ML technology. Then, we can rapidly obtain the mapping from input features to target labels, through which to construct models to make predictions for testing data sets.</p><p>We evaluate the predictive ability of several algorithms using leaveone-out cross validation (LOO-CV) to compare and select appropriate ML algorithms. This technique splits the training set into two parts, one sample set alone used as a verification and the remaining N-1 samples used as a brand training set. Then, we train the model on N-1 samples and attempt to predict the properties of the only one leaved-out sample. The cross-validation process is repeated N times, with each sample used exactly once as the validation data. Therefore, LOO-CV will obtain N results, and we will use the average to evaluate the final performance of the classifier. The first-principles is that simplicity is beauty because our research is a cross-field collaboration. We try many typical classification algorithms, such as logistic regression (LR), kneighbors (KNN), support vector machines (SVM), decision tree (DT), random forest (RF), Adaboost (ABt), and Gradient boosting (GBt). We also use several evaluation metrics to measure the performance of each algorithm. The evaluation metrics selected include accuracy, recall, F1-score, precision, and AUC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">USER-CENTERED DESIGN</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Design Process</head><p>Generally, the ML classification models represent the material with key descriptors, such as a combination of chemistry, composition, and crystal structure. Then, the desired material properties are obtained. Based on ML technology, computers can rapidly learn from the training data sets, also called empirical data sets. As a result, we can rapidly obtain the mapping from input features to target labels. Although ML seems to help people simplify the complex modeling process owing to its capability of recognizing complex patterns in data, it also brings certain problems and challenges, that is, you exact situation inside is unknown when an ML model is trained. People seek to know more details about the model mechanism that identifies the relationship between features and model prediction results, the performance of different algorithms on the same data set, selecting appropriate algorithms, and determining whether the prediction results have common regularities. From the perspective of visual analysis, exploring and explaining more patterns about the models, which may offer some insightful guidance or reference, are critical. Through face-to-face discussions with domain experts, our framework is finally proposed to help experts and scholars in the field of materials and those who may lack experience in using ML models, (1) to assist in the analysis, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref> to know more about the relationship between features and models, (3) to understand ML model mechanism better, (4) to compare different prediction results, and finally to reduce the exploration space for material discovery.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Task Analysis</head><p>We separated the analysis tasks into five parts as follows based on design goals (1) − (4) identified in Section 4.2:</p><p>T1. Constraint and interpretation analysis of electrolyte performance. Whether a material can be used as a solid electrolyte depends not only on its ionic conductivity, but also on some other preconditions. We attempt to analyze different constraint conditions, select different thresholds according to the actual situation, analyze the performance of the data set, and select the most appropriate constraint conditions and thresholds for subsequent analysis. In addition, a material contains many complex physical and chemical properties, which we cannot. We refer to the suggestions of domain experts, use some formula to calculate the original properties, and obtain 20 features.</p><p>T2. Analysis and exploration of features. For material data, 20 features indicate 20 dimensionalities, and the calculation and time costs are high. Therefore, we need to explore the existing 20 features, combine with the correlation between features, and analyze and select the important features. We performed a multiscale exploration, reduce the dimensionality of the features used for model calculation, and facilitate the information extraction and display of the visualization system.</p><p>T3. ML model selection. Different ML models can produce different effects on the same data set. We use different ML models to predict the material data set and display the prediction results and evaluation indexes of each model in the form of visualization. On the one hand, it can help domain experts to explore the application effect of different models. On the other hand, it can also help them integrate the prediction results of various models to explore the potential available materials.</p><p>T4. Overall analysis and visual display of the data set. Different from the supervised learning model, which requires well-labeled training data, unsupervised learning can be easily applied to large data sets, whether labeled or not. In the form of scatter diagram, we cluster the data set according to the selected features, and then visualize the clustering results. We can explore the potential correlation between materials by observing the distribution of materials on the scatter plot.</p><p>T5. Exploration and comparative analysis of specific cases. Through the overall analysis of the data set, we can find some noteworthy material data, and these materials are likely to satisfy our performance requirements. We provide a more intuitive method to assist the further analysis of domain experts. We can provide further guidance for the research by referring to the prediction results of different ML methods and the comparison of specific material properties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">VISUAL DESIGN</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Design Rationales</head><p>To address the analysis tasks in Section 4.2, a proper visual design should follow the design rationales below: R1. Overview and details: To achieve multi-scale analysis and satisfy the design tasks of T2 and T4, we conduct a search for information based on the principle of "Overview first, zoom and filter, then details on demand". First, the system should give users an overview distribution of all material properties and allow them to filter the data they wish to see. Users may also get detailed information about specific materials that they are interested in. R2. Coordinated multiple views: Our system should presents multiview information of material features, including the overall distribution of all material features and the location of the material in the feature reduction space. R3. Intuitive visual design for comparison: Intuitive representation is an essential element of numerous visualization systems. The parallel coordinate map, in particular, employs lines of different colors to represent two distinct materials. The information card in the area C2 in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> is utilized when merely comparing multiple materials. R4. Consistent encoding: The consistent use of visual encoding techniques across different data dimensions and scales can reduce visual complexity by preserving the mental map of a user to enhance understanding and simplify the exploration process. We achieved this by: 1) Using the same layout; both the material information card and the data encoding design view display features at the top, and the prediction result rectangle has a similar shape. 2) Employing color mappings that are uniform. Materials colors in different views of materials belonging to the same cluster are always constant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Control Panel View</head><p>This view mainly provides some customized selections for users, according to their needs and ideas to achieve better experience. In detail, the user can select controls to adjust the display effect of the parallel coordinate view. They can adjust the number of clusters to explore more patterns. In addition, we offer some extended functions. Users can change projection and clustering algorithms and select different final algorithms to be applied for the testing set. Then, clustering view and prediction grid view will change accordingly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Parallel Coordinates View</head><p>Our raw material data sets have many features of up to 20, and seven features even after optimization. The parallel coordinate is a very useful visual tool for analyzing and displaying multivariate data. It can visually and plainly display the distribution of data on different axes and reflect the relationship between multiple data. As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">4</ref>, each column, that is, each axis belongs to a dimensionality, and the variable value of each dimensionality corresponds to the position on the axis. Each data item is a line that runs through multiple coordinate axes. Here, we have 21 columns at most, including 20 columns to describe various features, and one column to describe the label value of the data items. The steepness and trough of the poly-lines only indicate the variation range of various feature value, whose range trend is indecisive for label classification. We should focus on the feature distribution of data on the same axis. For example, if the poly-lines of the same color are gathered at a certain position on the axis and can be distinguished from other colored poly-lines in distance, then the attribute represented by this axis is greatly helpful in judging the label category. The specific proportion of the training sets labeled 1 and 0 is shown from the last axis of the parallel axis. The positive items labeled 1 are depicted as orange, whereas the negative items labeled 0 are depicted gray. We can learn from the distribution of different colors on each axis to roughly judge the most contributing features, as we analyzed in Section 6.1. We can change the options on the control panel to determine which data to display in the parallel coordinate view, the transparency of the lines, the number of features displayed, and the mode of line display. In addition, when the user clicks on a material in the scatter chart, the line representing the material is highlighted in the parallel coordinate view.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Clustering View</head><p>Different from supervised learning models that require well-labeled training data, unsupervised learning can be easily applied to huge data sets regardless of whether or not attributes or labels exist. As a technology that can draw inferences from data features without explicitly labeling attributes, unsupervised learning has been well applied in many fields. Clustering analysis is a typical unsupervised learning method, the output of which includes samples of unknown categories, which are divided into several clusters, rather than predicting the targeted material property accurately for each candidate. Samples with some similarities are grouped into the same cluster. However, two typical problems are encountered when clustering high-dimensional data. One is that high-dimensional data usually contain many irrelevant or redundant attributes, which cause the possibility of clustering in all dimensionalities to almost zero. Another is that data distribution in high-dimensional space is sparser than that in low-dimensional space, leading to a common phenomenon, where the distance between the data in high dimensionality is almost equal. One of the approaches to solve these problems is to perform dimensionality reduction before clustering high-dimensional data. Dimensionality reduction can remove irrelevant and redundant features and can help reduce calculation cost. It is an indispensable tool widely used for analyzing and visualizing high-dimensional data. It can be further subdivided into two methods, namely, variable selection and feature extraction. The former directly selects the main features from the original features, whereas the latter extracts features from possible functions of original features.</p><p>We initially apply the t-SNE as the typical extract feature algorithm to the data sets and then cluster them using K-means algorithm. We calculate in advance that the optimal number of clusters is four. We can measure the similarity of data points based on the distance of the physical location by clustering high-dimensional data after dimensionality reduction. We obtain and visualize feature contributions for selected cluster through seven bars depicted with the same color, located above the clusters, as area C3 shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> to detect clusters and understand the features. These bars indicate which features contribute to the cluster most, and features that contrast various clusters are identified. From this view, we can detect clusters and perceive each cluster's features based on the similarity of data points with multiple features. When the user clicks on a material in the cluster view, the detailed information of the material is displayed in the area C2 in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> to further study the relationship between the materials with similar spatial distances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Data Encoding Design View</head><p>At first, our data encoding was only a simple scatter point, bordered with different colors to represent different model prediction results. After close discussion with domain experts to collect their feedback on visual design in an iterative manner, we realize that the original design contains limited visual information, and experts require richer visual information to know more about the features and atomic structures to evaluate the overall potential of materials. Therefore, we further improved our visual encoding design to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>. Besides, the current visual design is inspired by previous research on multidimensional data visualization. The current visual encoding design of each material mainly contains four parts, namely, 20 bars on the upper part of the outermost circle, six bars in the bottom half of the outermost circle, four arc blocks of the second outer circle, and the innermost circle with material names. The innermost circle is colored the same as its cluster. Twenty gray bars represent the 20 features selected that are most related to ionic conductivity. Six gray bars under the circle represent six main origin properties selected from the MP database. The 20 features and six properties offer guidance for domain experts to evaluate and verify the potential performance of materials in ionic conductivity. Four arc blocks located at the second outer circle depict the top four model performance. From left to right, four models as LR, ABt, GBt, and DT are shown in turn. For the testing data sets, if this material is predicted to be true by one model, then the corresponding arc block is drawn in dark gray; otherwise, it is colored light gray. For the training sets, the four arc blocks of positive samples are drawn in dark red and negative samples are drawn in pink. Therefore, the darker color around the data point shown in the scatter plot indicates that more models predict that the material is true.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6">Model Comparison View</head><p>We first obtain the ML experiment results of LOO-CV discussed in Section 3.4, and then the performance of various models is visualized on the basis of five metrics through the radar chart, as the lower part of E shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. The five vertices of the radar chart represent five variables as follows: accuracy, precision, recall, F1-score, and AUC. Contrary to other four metrics, we use the results subtracted from 1 as the final precision instead, because precision is expected to be as small as possible to maintain the consistency. The axis projected from the center to the five vertices, representing the scale from 0 to 1. Each model is an irregular pentagon, as shown in the radar chart, with different colors to reflect the comprehensive ability of the models. A complete pentagon indicates that the model performs more comprehensively on five metrics. When the mouse hovers over the pentagon area, the area is painted accordingly. When the mouse moves to the vertex of the pentagon, the value of that point is also prompted. We also provide another list view to display the specific values of each model on the five evaluation metrics. The color of the model in the list view is consistent with that in the radar chart, and users can click the sort button located on the right of each metric name to sort the models. From these views, users can not only intuitively obtain the overall performance of the model and the individual performance on each metric, but also compare the performance between various models through the completeness of pentagons and select the suitable one.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">SYSTEM EVALUATION 6.1 Case study</head><p>In this section, we present an exploration case to show how our system can help users interactively find potential target materials. A typical exploration process can be summarized as follows.</p><p>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>, we initially select basic settings in the control panel view. Then, we explore and analyze the feature distribution through parallel coordinate view from the following aspects: (a) the steepness and trough of the poly-lines only indicate the variation range of various feature value, whose range trend is indecisive for label Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. Some noteworthy points in the clustering view. Most circles contain many materials predicted to be positive by ML methods. We selected case 1 contains circle 10 and case 2 contains circle 1, circle 11 and circle 12. We enlarge the circles in cases to make readers see more clearly. It can be seen that the materials in the same circle have similar features and properties.</p><p>classification; (b) if the poly-lines of the same color are gathered at a certain position on the axis and can be distinguished from other colored poly-lines in distance, then the feature represented by this axis is greatly helpful in judging the label category; (c) if the poly-lines on a certain axis are chaotic and the colors are mixed, then this feature has no value, contrary to b). For example, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">4</ref>, The SLPE values of orange lines mostly range from 0.3 to 0.4, and gray ones range from 0.45 to 1. Therefore, SLPE may be one of the key features determining final classification. As for testing samples, we initially apply t-SNE to generate dimensionality reduction results, then we clustered them into four. We calculate the Calinski-Harabasz score, a typical metric of clustering performance, in advance to obtain that the optimal number of clusters is four. The clustering results are shown in area C1 in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</p><p>As area E shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>, the accuracy of all models ranges from 0.8 to 0.9. The F1-score is approximately 0.8, close to each other. The gray graphic is severely concave given its poor precision. Actually, none of the prediction results of SVM is positive, and the AUC of SVM is lower than those of the others evidently, indicating that SVM performs poorly on our dataset. DT has the best performance on AUC and precision and comparable performance on other metrics. The interpretability of DT is also better than others. It is a good option. We hope to obtain more positively predicted cases. Although it may contain some inaccurately classified materials, we can remove them through other approaches. Therefore, in the field of materials, we hope the results would rather contain some false positive cases than miss the true positive cases. From the perspective of the number of samples predicted to be positive, DT performs the most, GBt the second, ABt the third, and LR the forth. We visualize their prediction results in clustering view through filling the color of the corresponding arc block for each scatter point. As introduced in Section 5.4, the boundary of the scatter points has four arc blocks, corresponding to the prediction results of the four models, namely, DT, GBt, LR, and ABt as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>. Thus, we can know the predictions of the four algorithms on the material from the colors of the four arc blocks in the detail view. The overview map of the scatter chart reflects that the darker border color of the scatter indicates that more models predict that this material is positive.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows some noteworthy points in the visualization system. We circle these 14 positions with red. We also obtain some preliminary results through experimental verification or data search. Next, we put forward some opinions or thoughts on some important positions.</p><p>Case 1. In our first exploration, we found that circle 10 is a place worthy of further study; it includes Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 and Li 40 Al 8 O 32 as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">8</ref>. The two materials have similar spatial positions, and they have very similar features and original attributes, which are predicted as available materials by DT and GBt algorithms. We believe that if one of these materials is verified as an available material, then the other is more likely to be a potential available material. In our previous prediction, the ionic conductivity of Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 is approximately 10 −3 Scm −1 , which is at a high level. Considering the experimental conditions, synthesis cost, and other factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>, we decided to prepare Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 in the laboratory.</p><p>Considering the stability of raw materials, we try to avoid the decomposition of raw materials to produce gas or other products. We select the oxide system Li 2 O and Ga 2 O 3 with good stability as raw materials. We use the dry grinding method to mix the materials evenly, set the rotation speed of 200 r/min, single cycle for 15 min (operation for 10 min, stop for 5 min), and cycle for eight times. After a series of exploration on sintering temperature, we found that the reactants did not react when the temperature was lower than 500 °C, and the samples sintered at 750 °C for 24 h, consistent with Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 with high purity. Then, we double sintered the first sintered powder at 850 °C for 24 hours and analyzed the electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS) curve of the sample. Finally, the experimental measurement proved that Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 has good ionic conductivity, which is a useful solid Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. The specific comparison view of case 2 includes three circles: circle 1, circle 11 and circle 12. The similarity of spatial positions means the similarity of characteristics and properties, and it also means that the materials are more likely to have similar ionic conductivity. Circle 11 includes two materials with opposite ionic conductivity, so the materials near them are worth exploring, but after research we found that its ionic conductivity doesn't meet the requirements. The condition of circle 12 is similar with circle 11, but we found that one of the materials near the opposite materials is available. For circle 1, we found that the prediction result is different from the truth, which means our system can improve later. electrolyte material.</p><p>This case fully shows that our visualization method and system has a strong practical significance in the exploration of high ionic conductivity materials, and the model based on the prediction results of ML is valuable and feasible. According to our visualization analysis, Li 40 Al 8 O 32 with similar features is also likely to be a useful solid electrolyte material, which needs to be further verified by experiments.</p><p>Case 2. x Subsequently, we observed the four materials in circle 11 and found that the space distance between LiLa(TiO 3 ) 2 and Li 7 BiO 6 , which has been determined as unavailable material is small, but the ionic conductivity gap between the two materials is very large, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. Thus, the availability of Li 8 Sn 1 O 6 and Li 16 Si 2 O 12 near these materials is worth exploring. After we consult Reed et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref> and others' results, we found that the ionic conductivity of LiLa(TiO 2 ) 2 is 10 −3 Scm −1 , and the ionic conductivity of the three other materials is 10 −4 Scm −1 , which does not satisfy the threshold standard of high ion conductivity, and all are unavailable materials. Therefore, the regional theory near LiLa(TiO 2 ) 2 is no longer worth exploring. y We also found that the four materials above circle 12, three of which have been identified as unavailable, and Li 4 Bn 3 H 10 are identified as available materials, as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. Thus, Li 24 Ho 4 B 12 O 36 has exploratory value. We found that the material has been verified as available by experiments in Reed et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>. This finding proves that our system has reference significance for the exploration and discovery of potential available materials. z Circle 1 contains two materials as shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref>. Although the two materials are predicted to be false by four algorithms in our prediction results, Li 4 Ga 4 I 16 has been proven by Kahle et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref> as high ion conductivity material, and Li 4 In 4 I 16 has been proven to be available by our experiments. This finding shows that our algorithm prediction results have some shortcomings, and some improvement space for the algorithm itself still exists. However, the 2D space distance obtained by the reduction of the original properties of the material has a strong significance, and the materials with similar distance are more likely to show the same ionic conductivity.</p><p>In addition, some marked but not mentioned places, such as circle 2 and circle 14, which contain materials with similar spatial position and features, and all contain materials that have been verified as true or predicted as available by some ML algorithms. However, they have not been verified by experiments, and no relevant papers are available. However, it is more likely to contain potentially available materials, which can be the target of further research and experiment. Generally, our system has great reference value for the exploration of high ionic conductivity materials; it provides some possible directions for the domain experts to avoid blind search and complex experiments and save considerable costs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">Domain Expert Evaluations</head><p>We interviewed two domain experts to evaluate the effectiveness of the system. One of them focused on solid electrolyte research (denoted as EA), and the other had in-depth research in the field of new energy (denoted as EB). In the interview, we first explained the data source and parsing process, the ML model, and interface design method used. We also demonstrated how our system works. Subsequently, we showed them our case study and finally let them explore the system themselves. In general, they believe that combining the ML method to predict the ionic conductivity of solid electrolyte can avoid substantial firstprinciples calculations in the field of materials, save time, and is a promising direction. Their detailed feedback is summarized as follows:</p><p>Data analysis and processing. EB is satisfied with our original data processing process. He believes our analysis process from original data to seven features is reasonable in terms of material field. He said that "it is better to display and analyze multiple features at the same time, and it is better to display the most important features than 20 features at the same time." EA noticed our screening process based on the first four constraints and mentioned the threshold of constraints. He said that "the current threshold setting is reasonable, because we are considering the applicability of various materials under high requirements. Thus, the threshold can be appropriately narrowed. Although only few accurate materials are predicted, this condition is understandable. If the threshold is enlarged, our work will lose its meaning."</p><p>The selection of ML model. EA said that "the ML model selected for the project is basically consistent with the general selection of ML model in the material field, especially the emphasis on LR model." EB said that "four is a reasonable number; it can not only provide users with options, but also avoid the difficulty in controlling the analysis."</p><p>Interactive system design. After exploring the system, the two experts said that the system provides them with a very important reference, which is relatively valuable for their future research. EB first said that the static page of our system itself has a strong reference value. "If we want to study the ionic conductivity of some materials, then we need to search for relevant materials ourselves, but your work has made visual display of materials as much as possible, and we can identify which materials have been verified to be available through color at a glance, which are unavailable, and which remain to be studied." EA first looked for the location and prediction results of some materials he studied from the system, and then expressed some opinions in general, "I compared some of my previous studies and found that this system has a strong reference value. If I want to study some more materials, then I will try to start from the two positions (referring to circle 2 and circle 14 in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>), because the prediction results of these positions are attractive." At the same time, the two experts believe that the layout is very intuitive. Thus, people can see at a glance, and the function is rich; they can not only find the distribution of materials in the overall situation, but can also make a detailed exploration of material features according to the comparison chart. When we asked two experts about the prediction accuracy of the system, EB said that "ML itself is a type of auxiliary means. Although the possibility of inaccurate judgment exists, its reference value cannot be ignored." EA simply said, "this finding is a very important reference; even if the result is inaccurate, it is much better than no reference."</p><p>Limitations and improvement direction. Experts pointed out some limitations of our system, and both experts suggested that the original properties of each material can be fully displayed in the future. In addition, EB said, "because of the large amount of data and high repetition of lines, the line chart is not intuitive. In the future, we can try another method to compare the feature of all materials." EA said, "because the proportion of available materials in the data set itself is very low, there are few materials whose predicted results are true. We can try to show more dimensionalities of the predicted results, such as feature contribution, to provide more available information." At the same time, he also said, "the material predicted to be true may not be used in the experiment. At present, it is only a theoretical thing, and it needs further research in practice."</p><p>At the end of the interview, EA summed up the significance of our work to them in one sentence: "It's not that the combination of ML and visualization solves our problems all the time, but this work at least proves that this research method and idea is valuable and feasible, and can play a huge reference value in future work." EB said, "this system is not only a visualization platform, but also a bridge between the visualization field and the material field."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">DISCUSSION</head><p>In our work, we combined ML model with visual analysis techniques to explore and analyze the ionic conductivity of materials from multiple perspectives. However, our work and system still have some deficiencies and drawbacks, and we have some discussions on them.</p><p>Factors related screening constraints. We simplify the analysis and prediction parameters of solid electrolyte screening, and only consider five important factors: electronic conductivity, structural stability, oxidation stability, metal stability and ionic conductivity. Besides, the cost of experimental verification is also very expensive. To begin with, we used visualization technology to find out five samples that are most likely to be prepared in our collaborator's laboratory according to the algorithm results and expert experience. Finally, it took about one and a half years of repeated debugging and experiments to preliminary improve the preparation process of Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 , and finally the lithium ion conductivity was measured. Overall, modeling, prediction, analysis and verification, might be described as complex and difficult.</p><p>Factors behind prediction. In recent years, we have felt the difficulties of getting actual samples and the cost of increasing the sample size in the course of experiments and analysis, particularly in ML modeling and visualization activities. Even with the help of the results of material features generated from MP database as the test set, there are still problems of under-fitting and over-fitting, especially the imbalance between the number of positive and negative samples in the training set, which leads to too few true results. Because lithium ion conductivity can't be calculated by first-principles, it must be tested in the laboratory. In addition to preparing experiments in the laboratory by our collaborators, we use Natural Language Processing (NLP) to collect and process the materials synthesized and verified in other laboratories to expand our training set, It took us almost a year to expand the previous training set by 50%, so to some extent, this is one of the reasons why we have few real samples. However, domain experts are very confident in our data-driven ionic conductivity classification and prediction approach. They believe that with the development of high-throughput technology, the number of positive samples will gradually increase, and the value of subsequent analysis methods will be greater.</p><p>Generalization. At present, some research on ionic conductivity of materials adopts the doping method. By adding a small number of other elements or compounds, it can improve the properties of materials. After we successfully prepared Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 , we used the same idea and our system prove that gallium doped Li 2 La 3 Zr 2 O 12 can improve the ionic conductivity of the material. When the content of gallium doping is 16 at%, the ionic conductivity reaches a maximum of more than 10 −3 Scm −1 . In the further research, we will expand the collection of material doping data and the establishment of models, and verify our hypothesis through experiments, strive to increase the number of samples and significantly increase the number of real samples through doping, so that the prediction results are more convincing.</p><p>From relevance to causality. In our analysis, we found that the traditional data analysis and ML models can not be directly used for material analysis. On the one hand, it is difficult to collect data due to the high cost of material experiment; On the other hand, in the process of design goal establishment, performance simulation, preparation process research, and actual experimental design and analysis, they all have high knowledge density, which makes it easy for us to overlook some features and parameters that affect the final performance in the analysis based on the original method design and model parameter design based on correlation, and it makes verification difficult. Therefore, we plan to continue to try more causality based algorithms, such as graph neural networks, to improve the practicability of the prediction results while using visualization methods to provide intuitive and multi-dimensional analysis means to meet the requirements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">CONCLUSION</head><p>In this work, we demonstrate a multifaceted visualization system functioned with the feature distribution exploration, the similarity analysis in cluster perspective, the model performance comparison, and the material feature comparison to facilitate the screening of solid electrolyte materials. We provide five typical evaluation metrics for experts to compare and select the suitable model. Our system supports seven typical classification algorithms, namely, LR, KNN, SVM, DT, RF, AB, and GB, three typical projection algorithms, namely, tSNE, PCA, and MDS, and three typical clustering algorithms, such as KMeans, DBSCAN, and GNN. We use structured data to train the model and construct our visual system. Thus, in theory, any other task with structured dataset can be applied to our system.</p><p>Focusing on the result analysis and case studies above, we explore several meaningful and promising strategies when searching for expected candidate materials. Some strategies are proven true, some are true-predicted in others work, and the others, which have not been reported in relevant literature, offer many candidate research targets for our further research. Domain experts identify with the effectiveness and usefulness of our system. They agree that our work can avoid blind attempts, narrow down the target space greatly, and save much experiment cost.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. The feature distributions of data sets. This view includes 20 columns describing various features and one column describing the label value. Each sample is a line that runs through multiple coordinate axes. Samples are painted orange with label 1, and painted gray with label 0.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,316.55,49.37,250.59,79.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. The visual encoding design of each material. It contains four parts: 20 features displayed through bars on the upper part of the outermost circle, the six main original attributes displayed through bars in the bottom half of the outermost circle, the prediction results shown through the 4 arc blocks of the second outer circle and the innermost circle colored the same color with its cluster. The four arc blocks corresponds to four models as DT, GBt, LR and ABt. If this material is predicted to be positive by one model, then the corresponding arc block will be filled dark gray.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,307.55,49.49,250.58,212.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Fig. 8. The specific comparison view of case 1 includes Li 40 Ga 8 O 32 and Li 40 Al 8 O 32 .We prepared the former in the laboratory ,proved that it has good ionic conductivity and can be used as solid electrolyte material. Because of the similar features and properties, Li 40 Al 8 O 32 is also likely to be a useful solid electrolyte material.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,44.99,275.57,250.46,176.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="1,77.63,131.33,465.80,263.78" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="7,60.11,49.37,500.78,317.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>We would like to thank anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments and Prof. Zongkai YAN for participating this project as domain experts.This work was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant Nos. 61872066, and U19A2078), and the Science and Technology project of Sichuan(No. 2020YFG0056). This project is also partially by the science and technology project of Sichuan (No.2019YFG0504, 2020YFG0459, 2021YFG0314).</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review and characterization of progressive visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Angelini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Santucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-J</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Informatics</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">31</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of machine learning methods for the prediction of crystal system of cathode materials in lithiumion batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Attarian</forename><surname>Shandiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gauvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.commatsci.2016.02.021</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computational Materials Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="270" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using dashboard networks to visualize multiple patient histories: a design study on post-operative prostate cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bernard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kohlhammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ruddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1615" to="1628" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine learning for molecular and materials science</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cartwright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Isayev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">559</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7715</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="547" to="555" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustrophile 2: Guided visual clustering analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cavallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Demiralp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1109/TVCG.2018.2864477</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="276" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Machine learning: accelerating materials development for energy storage and conversion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">InfoMat</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="576" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual abstraction and exploration of multi-class scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1683" to="1692" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research on high-safety electrolytes and their application in lithium-ion batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Storage Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">583</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerating materials development via automation, machine learning, and high-performance computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-P</forename><surname>Correa-Baena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hippalgaonkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Duren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jaffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Stevanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wadia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Buonassisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Joule</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1410" to="1420" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The state of the art in integrating machine learning into visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Endert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nabney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Blanco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="458" to="486" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dermatologist-level classification of skin cancer with deep neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Esteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kuprel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Novoa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Swetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Blau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">542</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7639</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The spinel explorer-interactive visual analysis of spinel group minerals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ganuza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ferracutti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gargiulo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bjerg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gröller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Matković</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1913" to="1922" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Electrolyte additives for lithium ion battery electrodes: progress and perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Haregewoin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wotango</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B.-J</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy &amp; Environmental Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1955" to="1988" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-throughput computational screening for solid-state li-ion conductors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kahle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marcolongo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Marzari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy &amp; Environmental Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="928" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A cti v is: Visual exploration of industry-scale deep neural network models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kahng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kalro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interacting with predictions: Visual inspection of black-box machine learning models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krause</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2016 CHI conference on human factors in computing systems</title>
				<meeting>the 2016 CHI conference on human factors in computing systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5686" to="5697" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">30 years of lithium-ion batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Amine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advanced Materials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1800561</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A visual analytics system for multi-model comparison on clinical data predictions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fujiwara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.visinf.2020.04.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">PacificVis 2020 Workshop on Visualization Meets AI</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="131" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster-based visual abstraction for multivariate scatterplots</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2531" to="2545" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research on structural-activity model of solid electrolyte based on machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Electronic Science and Technology of China</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Master&apos;s thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards better analysis of machine learning models: A visual analytics perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Visual Informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Materials discovery and design using machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Materiomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent progress and trends in predictive visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Maciejewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers of Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="207" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accelerated discovery of stable lead-free hybrid organic-inorganic perovskites via machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ouyang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The stateof-the-art in predictive visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gleicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Maciejewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="562" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Explaining vulnerabilities to adversarial machine learning through visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Maciejewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1075" to="1085" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Driving style recognition for intelligent vehicle control and advanced driver assistance: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F.-Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="666" to="676" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combinatorial screening for new materials in unconstrained composition space with machine learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Meredig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Agrawal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kirklin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Saal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Doak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Choudhary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wolverton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review B</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">94104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of intermetallic compounds from traditional to machine-learning approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Oliynyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Accounts of chemical research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-flammable organic liquid electrolyte for high-safety and high-energy density li-ion batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Pham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E.-H</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-G</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-W</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Power Sources</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="19" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Machine learning-assisted discovery of solid li-ion conducting materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sendek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cubuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Antoniuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cheon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemistry of Materials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Holistic computational structure screening of more than 12000 candidates for solid lithium-ion conductor materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sendek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cubuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Duerloo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy &amp; Environmental Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="306" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hanwei Shen and etc. Visual analysis of meteorological satellite data via model-agnostic meta-learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shiyu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12650-020-00704-4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent advances in all-solid-state rechargeable lithium batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wilkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nano Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dfseer: A visual analytics approach to facilitate model selection for demand forecasting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-C</forename><surname>Pong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
				<meeting>the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dqnviz: A visual analytics approach to understand deep q-networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ganviz: A visual analytics approach to understand the adversarial game</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1905" to="1917" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flexible energystorage devices: design consideration and recent progress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advanced materials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4763" to="4782" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Messagelens: A visual analytics system to support multifaceted exploration of mooc forum discussions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-S</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi: 10. 1016/j.visinf.2018.04.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of PacificVAST</title>
				<meeting>PacificVAST</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018. 2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="49" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Visual Informatics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactive visualization for extracting bitcoin exchange intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Xuanwu Yue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Xinhuan</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Etc</forename><surname>Bitextract</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>doi: 10. 1109/TVCG.2018.2864814</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development status and prospect analysis of lithium ion battery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Aeronautics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2767" to="2775" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Research progress, challenges and prospects of all solid-state polymer lithium batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Energy Storage Science and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rational design of an ionic liquid-based electrolyte with high ionic conductivity towards safe lithium/lithium-ion batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pasupath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemistry-An Asian Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2810" to="2814" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised discovery of solid-state lithium ion conductors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Banerjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsunaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">iforest: Interpreting random forests via visual analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review on solid electrolytes for all-solid-state lithium-ion batteries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kotobuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Power Sources</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">389</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Studies on the Preparation and Modification of High Lithium Ion Conductivity LLZO/LLTO Solid-State Electrolyte Materials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Electronic Science and Technology of China</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
