<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sequen-C: A Multilevel Overview of Temporal Event Sequences</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jessica</forename><surname>Magallanes</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tony</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Suzanne</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Steven</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maria-Cruz</forename><surname>Villa-Uriol</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sequen-C: A Multilevel Overview of Temporal Event Sequences</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8C8A69D6A21730479831AD864FEB6C56</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.1" ident="GROBID" when="2022-06-13T13:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Temporal event sequence visualization</term>
					<term>clustering</term>
					<term>hierarchical aggregation</term>
					<term>multiple sequence alignment</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Fig. 1: Screenshots of Sequen-C for a dataset with 258 event sequences illustrating the methodology. The hierarchical aggregation tree (top left) allows changing the number of clusters shown. The vertical level-of-detail of the multilevel overview can be transformed from coarse (bottom left) to fine (middle and bottom right). Sequence clusters are represented using an Align-Score-Simplify strategy (top right), which allows controlling the horizontal level-of-detail according to an information score.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Visual analytics of temporal event sequence data has applications in various domains such as electronic health records (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>) and web clickstream analysis (e.g. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref>). This type of data usually presents high variability and volume. Existing visual analytic techniques obtain a visual summary (overview) of event sequences using techniques such as sequential pattern mining or sequence clustering, with the purpose of understanding common and deviating pathways. These techniques commonly follow the information-seeking mantra: "overview first, zoom and filter, then details on demand" <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref>; which means that the starting point of the exploration is the given overview.</p><p>Finding the optimal level-of-detail of the initial overview, simplified but informative, is an ongoing challenge. Current visualization systems limit users to a single overview as the starting point of the analysis, which can lead to missing insights unless the user drills down into specific aspects of the provided overview. Users should be allowed to seamlessly change the level-of-detail to explore alternative overviews, rather than being limited to a single one. We propose a technique to build and explore a multilevel overview of event sequences through hierarchical aggregation and the cluster data representation Align-Score-Simplify, where users can interactively transform the overview from a coarse level-of-detail to a fine one, allowing a seamless analysis of alternative overviews.</p><p>The multilevel overview presents k sequence clusters retrieved from a hierarchical aggregation or aggregate tree of event sequences. The leaves of the tree contain the original sequences and each node corresponds to a sequence cluster. Clusters present soft patterns as opposed to hard patterns <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, hence order of events is not strictly enforced at this step. The proposed Align-Score-Simplify data representation summarizes the sequences in a cluster (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>) using Multiple Sequence Alignment (MSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and an information score. The alignment of sequences within a cluster facilitates the identification of patterns and permutations (see highlight in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>) in the order of events.</p><p>The level-of-detail of the overview can be transformed across sequence clusters and longitudinally. The vertical level-of-detail is proportional to the number of clusters k. The higher k is, the finer the detail. Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the coarsest summary for k = 1, where k can go up to 258 (the total number of sequences in the dataset). The horizontal level-of-detail depends on the information score threshold I τ so that the higher I τ is, the coarser the cluster representation. Although users are able to interactively change the number of clusters, a set of recommended values for k are suggested by analysing the Average Silhouette Width metric curve <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</p><p>We present Sequen-C, a visual analytics framework that implements the proposed technique and allows detail-on-demand exploration of sequence clusterings. To illustrate the benefits of Sequen-C, we have used two real-world datasets in the clinical domain: CUREd (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>) and MIMIC-III (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6</ref>). The contributions of the present work are:</p><p>• A technique to build and explore a multilevel overview of event sequences, from coarse to fine vertical or horizontal level-ofdetail, using hierarchical aggregation and a novel Align-Score-Simplify cluster data representation. • A novel approach to explore sequence clusterings, where a ranked set of alternative optimal number of clusters are provided. • Sequen-C, a visual analytics system that allows multilevel and detail-on-demand exploration of sequences, and the inspection of attributes at cluster, unique sequence, or individual record level. • Two case studies involving domain experts in the clinical domain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Summarization of temporal event sequences</head><p>Many techniques have been proposed to build a visual summary or overview of temporal event sequences. Early techniques display individual events in a timeline according to their time of occurrence <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>. Other ones aggregate sequences sharing the same event order using icicle plots <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>, Sankey diagrams <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>, or transition matrices <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>. They visualize all event permutations, complicating the interpretability as volume and variability increase. Scalability has been addressed by obtaining an overview of relevant (e.g. frequent) sub-sequences through sequential pattern mining (SPM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41]</ref>. Despite SPM being able to summarize datasets with high volume and variability, hierarchical exploration in the level-of-detail is not possible.</p><p>Frequence <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> builds a coarse level-of-detail overview of frequent patterns, from which sub-patterns with finer level-of-detail are interactively mined, however, this method relies on existing event type hierarchical categories. Coreflow <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> obtains an overview of branching patterns using a three-step recursive algorithm, which allows its hierarchical exploration by expanding branches into sub-branches; nevertheless, the interaction is constrained to the clicked branches and no support is provided hinting users towards alternative levels-of-detail which might provide valuable insights. Other approaches merge and replace events <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, define temporal queries <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref>, define milestone events <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> or use regular expressions <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>.</p><p>User-driven operations applied to the overview are key for visual exploratory data analysis. However, the choice of the initial overview remains crucial <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Our paper proposes a methodology to build a multilevel overview of temporal event sequences, which can be trans-formed from coarse to fine level of details, using sequence clustering and multiple sequence alignment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Event and Sequence Clustering</head><p>Event clustering: Outflow <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> visualizes common pathways using a Sankey-like diagram, and to reduce visual clutter, events are clustered according to their outcome. However, the clustering is limited to events within the same layer. Gotz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> propose a technique for dynamic hierarchical aggregation of events, where users can choose alternative groupings within a hierarchy of events, according to their correlation with outcome. Scribe Radar <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> builds a hierarchy of event types based on their frequency and a six-level naming hierarchy. These approaches rely on an existing hierarchy of event types (e.g. hierarchical classification of clinical codes), which do not necessarily exist in every domain or dataset. Our paper focuses in the hierarchical aggregation of sequences rather than event types, and we build the hierarchy without using a priori knowledge.</p><p>Sequence clustering: Wang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref> build an overview of user behavioral patterns by clustering users with a similar clickstream history, and are visualized using a Packed Circle view. The overview successfully captures the hierarchy of nested clusters, however, the event sequences are not included. Wei et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> build an overview of clickstream clusters mapped onto a 2D plane. The sequential information is visually encoded but the separation of different clusters is difficult to interpret. Another strategy is to explicitly encode the event sequences stacked and grouped by cluster, comparing them side to side <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref>. Li et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> uses a density-based clustering method and visualizes clusters using a Voronoi map and a pattern graph. The latter two do not facilitate the comparison of sequences within or amongst clusters. Treemaps are commonly used to visualize hierarchical clusters <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref>, but this type of view does not encode sequential information. Other approaches to cluster sequences include tensor analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> and Hidden Markov Models <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> with a focus on obtaining evolution patterns.</p><p>Vasabi and Sequence Synopsis are the techniques most similar to this work. Vasabi <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref> builds an overview of sequence clusters by first extracting the most common events (e.g. tasks) in the dataset and then clustering sequences using those events as features of the clustering. The technique successfully extracts and represents a fixed number of sequence clusters. However, their cluster representation does not allow to identify event permutations or see the events that were omitted in the event extraction step, and the number of clusters cannot be changed. Sequence Synopsis <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> clusters event sequences based on the minimum description length, where clusters are represented by a sequential pattern and a set of corrections; as indicated by Chen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, a potential drawback of their cluster representation is that missing events are not explicitly encoded and that scalability could be improved by supporting hierarchical visual summary (e.g. explore alternative number of clusters). To the best of our knowledge, there is no existing technique to explore different sequence clusterings that at the same time provides an interpretable representation of the sequences in a cluster -the present work aims to tackle this problem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Sequence alignment</head><p>Alignment is a common analytic strategy in temporal event data that allows to explore the events happening right before and after a given event <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. Existing techniques usually allow alignment by a single event <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45]</ref>, and more recently by two <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50]</ref> or multiple <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> events. Multiple Sequence Alignment (MSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> was initially proposed to align biological sequences and understand how they relate to each other. Bose et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> applies this algorithm to temporal event sequences to find common behaviour and deviations in a process, with applications in domains such as clinical workflows <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52]</ref>. MSA has also been used to obtain a consensus sequence (i.e. a set of common events) to represent a set of event sequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref>. We apply an MSA approach to represent the common events in a sequence cluster to allow comparison of commonalities and deviations within and across clusters.</p><p>We propose a technique to build and explore a multilevel overview of event sequences through hierarchical aggregation. A multilevel overview is a visual summary which can be interactively transformed from coarse to fine level-of-detail <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. Our overview displays a number of sequence clusters retrieved from an aggregate tree; where each sequence cluster is represented with the steps Align-Score-Simplify.</p><p>The overview can be interactively transformed vertically and horizontally. The vertical level-of-detail is controlled with the number of clusters retrieved from the tree. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2-C</ref> shows how the higher in the hierarchy (i.e. smaller number of clusters), the coarser the overview; whereas the lower in the hierarchy (i.e. larger number of clusters), the finer the details. The horizontal level-of-detail refers to the level of simplification of each cluster representation according to its information score (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>). The initial overview shows the best number of clusters according to the Average Silhouette Width metric <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, but we also offer a set of alternative values that might provide valuable overviews.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Building the aggregate tree</head><p>To build the aggregate tree from the input unique temporal event sequences, we use a bottom-up aggregation approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Every input unique sequence starts in a single cluster, then pairs of similar clusters are iteratively aggregated until a single cluster is obtained. The leaves of the final tree contain the input unique sequences, each internal node in the tree contains an aggregated representation of their child nodes, and the root node aggregates the whole dataset (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2-B</ref>).</p><p>Alg. 1 shows how to build the aggregate tree T from the list of unique sequences S = {s 1 , s 2 , ..., s N }, being N the number of input unique sequences in the dataset. In the last iteration, T is the root node of a binary tree, and all possible sub-trees can be obtained by recursively retrieving its left and right children until reaching the leaves.</p><p>First, the distance matrix d is initialized. This N × N matrix provides the pairwise distances of all the input sequences in S. D qgram computes the pairwise distance of two sequences as the cosine distance of their qgram profiles <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref>, where the q-gram profile of a sequence is the vector of all sub-sequences of q consecutive events. The implementation of the stringdist package in R <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref> was used, with q = 1. This allows clustering sequences according to the count of shared events regardless of their permutations in order. For example, the distance between sequences "abcde" and "deabc" is zero and both sequences are likely to end up in the same cluster. In case a stricter ordering of events had to be considered, D qgram should be replaced by another distance metric (e.g. Levenshtein edit distance <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>).</p><p>A node in T is defined as Node(l, r, λ , α); where l and r are the left and right children, λ the alignment of the sequences at that node, and α, the simplified λ used to represent the cluster. The set T is initialised with as many leaves as input sequences (line 3). For each s in S, a leaf is Node(l = / 0, r = / 0, λ = α = s); with no children, and where the alignment λ and cluster representation α are the sequence s itself.</p><p>The iterative process stops when T contains a single node (line 4). For each iteration a new node n a∪b is created by merging the closest pair of nodes (n a , n b ), and d and T are updated according to n a∪b . The closest pair of nodes (n a , n b ) is that for which the value in d is the minimum (line 5). Then aggregate returns a new node n a∪b whose left child is n a and right child is n b , with alignment λ and a summarized representation α of the sequences in n a and n b . Alg. 2 outlines how to build the cluster data representation of the newly aggregated node n a∪b . d and T are updated by adding the new node n a∪b and removing the nodes n a and n b used for the aggregation (lines 7-10). The distance matrix d is updated by inserting the pairwise distance from the new node n a∪b to all nodes in T (line 7), and by removing from d the i th row and j th column containing n a and n b . The method D cqgram (line 7) computes the distance between two clusters using the average agglomeration method <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> defined as the average of all pairwise distances between the sequences in both clusters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Cluster data representation: Align-Score-Simplify</head><p>To represent a cluster, we propose the steps Align-Score-Simplify (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>). The sequences in a cluster are aligned using Multiple Sequence  Alignment (MSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Then an information score is computed for each column in λ . And last, the columns in λ with an information score below a threshold I τ are merged and simplified.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T = {Node(l, r, λ , α) | l = / 0, r = / 0, λ = α = s, ∀ s ∈ S}; /*</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Align</head><p>To perform the Align and obtain the alignment matrix λ , the input unique sequences in S are formatted as sequences of characters, where each character represents an event type. All elements in λ are either single characters or gaps (-). The MSA algorithm inserts gaps (-) in those input sequences to maximize the number of equal events columnwise. To achieve this, two costs are used: gap open penalty (when inserting gaps), and gap substitution score (encouraging equal columnwise events).</p><p>We use the progressive approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> to carry out the multiple alignment of sequences, which iteratively constructs a series of pairwise alignments by following a tree that represents the similarity between sequences, where the alignment of a node is built using the alignment of its child nodes (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2-B</ref>). Alignments can be constructed over a pair of sequences, a sequence and an alignment, or a pair of alignments. For a given set of sequences S, the N × M alignment matrix λ contains all the sequences in S aligned, being N the number of input unique sequences and M the length of the final alignment <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. The method MSA (line 14) returns λ for the sequences in the new node, computed using the alignments of its children n a .λ and n b .λ . In this paper, the algorithm was written in R and based on the Python library scikit-bio <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>, with gap open penalty = 0.8, match score = 3 for equal events, and mismatch score = −1 for non equal events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">Score</head><p>Once the alignment matrix λ for all the input unique sequences in a cluster (or node) is obtained, λ is simplified into the simplified alignment matrix α. To do this, an information score I j for each column j in λ is computed based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">I j = 1 − E j log 2 (|A| + 1)<label>(1)</label></formula><p>being A the set of unique event types in the alignment matrix λ , |A| the length of A, and E j the entropy of the event types in that column:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">E j = ∑ a∈A j ∪{−} ⎧ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎩ −P a log 2 P a G j , if a = '-', −P a log 2 (P a ), otherwise. (<label>2</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">)</formula><p>G j is the count of gaps in column j, P a is the probability of the event type a in that column, and A j is the set of unique event types in column j. To avoid I j from becoming negative, when E j &gt; log 2 (|A| + 1), E j = log 2 (|A| + 1). The probability P a is computed as the sum of probabilities of the unique sequences to which a belongs to, defining the probability of a unique sequence as its frequency divided by the total frequency of the cluster. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> illustrates how P and I are calculated for each alignment matrix λ in the aggregate tree T .</p><p>The information score provides a measure of how homogeneous a column is, with values in the range 0 ≤ I j ≤ 1. If a column contains mostly a single type of event, I j is closer to one, while if it mostly contains gaps or many distinct event types, I j is closer to zero. The vector I is computed according to Eqs. 1 and 2 (lines 15-17, Alg. 2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.3">Simplify</head><p>To simplify an alignment matrix λ , columns with a relatively low information score are iteratively merged to obtain the simplified cluster representation matrix α (lines 19 to 26, Alg. 2). The matrix α is N ×M , where M is the length of the simplified alignment, being M ≤ M.</p><p>Alg. 2 shows how given a pair of consecutive columns with information score I j and I j+1 below a threshold I τ (line 20), the characters in λ i, j are concatenated to the beginning of λ i, j+1 . Such concatenation is repeated for each row in the alignment for the selected columns, then column j is added to the list of columns to be removed (listRemove). The matrix α is the resulting simplified alignment and contains the same columns as λ except for the columns in listRemove, i.e. the columns categorized as candidates for a horizontal merge (line 27). Note that α will have elements that are a concatenation of characters, whereas λ only contains single characters. Those elements in α that are a concatenation of characters represent the merged sub-sequences.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> shows an example about how Simplify works. The events in λ (represented as characters) in columns 1 to 2 and 6 to 10 are row-wise merged into a single position in the final simplified matrix of alignment α. The visual encoding of these row-wise merged events is further explained in Section 5. Alg. 2 finishes by creating the new node n a∪b , assigning n a and n b as its child nodes, λ as its alignment, and α as its  data representation (line 28). Note that the original alignment matrix λ is also kept as it is used to build the alignment of subsequent nodes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.4">Multilevel data representation</head><p>The proposed data representation allows to explore the overview vertically and horizontally. The vertical level-of-detail is proportional to the number of clusters k in the overview. The larger k is, the finer the overview, where 1 ≤ k ≤ N, being N the number of input unique sequences. For example, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2-B</ref> shows how as the aggregate tree is cut at a higher level in the hierarchy (e.g. k = 1 or k = 2), clusters have a higher intra-cluster variation so the number of merged columns increase, resulting in a coarser overview. As the tree is cut at a lower level in the hierarchy (e.g. k = 4 or k = 5), clusters have a lower intra-cluster variation so the column-wise information score gets closer to 1, resulting in a finer overview. Ultimately, when one cluster contains a single sequence (k = 6), all columns in the alignment matrices have an information score of 1, showing an overview with the highest level-of-detail possible.</p><p>The horizontal level-of-detail of the overview depends on the threshold I τ , where 0 ≤ I τ ≤ 1. The larger I τ is, the coarser the represen-tation of clusters becomes horizontally. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> shows the representation for an example cluster for several I τ values, when I τ = 0 no events are merged showing full detail and as it moves towards I τ = 1 the number of merged events increase.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Finding optimal overviews</head><p>Users are able to explore all clustering combinations in the aggregate tree. The average silhouette width metric <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> measures the quality of a clustering to find the optimal number of clusters which reflect homogeneous and well-separated distinct groups. We use this metric to suggest a set of optimal number of clusters, which result in a set of overviews with an optimal vertical level-of-detail. For a given number of clusters k, the average silhouette width z(k) is defined as the mean z(s) of all the elements in the dataset, where z(s) is the silhouette value of the element s. In our case, s is each of the input unique sequences used to build the aggregate tree. As defined by Rousseeuw <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>, z(s) is given by: z(s) = v(s)−u(s) max(u(s),v(s)) , where u(s) is the average distance between element s and the other elements in the same cluster, v(s) is the average distance between s and the elements in the nearest cluster (neighboring cluster), and −1 ≤ z(s) ≤ 1. Kaufman and Rousseeuw <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref> suggest that the most optimal k is that one for which z(k) is the largest (global maxima). In some cases, the most optimal k might still be too many or too few clusters for the user. To provide a balance between number of clusters and quality of clustering, we propose to obtain the peaks (local maxima) in the z(k) function. A set of optimal overviews are indicated by the global and local maxima in z(k). These will indicate relative good partitioning of the sequences and therefore provide a good visual overview.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Complexity analysis</head><p>The time complexity of buildAggregateTree (Alg. 1) is O(Nnl 2 ), where N is the number of input unique sequences, l the maximum sequence length, and n the average number of sequences per node. The function aggregate is repeated N − 1 times, being the Align step (MSA) the most time consuming (O(nl 2 )). Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">1</ref> compares the time for several subsets of the data used in our case studies, and as observed, the maximum sequence length in the dataset highly impacts the alignment time. Around 300 to 500 input unique sequences with an average sequence length of 7 to 10 events can be aligned relatively fast (&lt; 10s). To achieve real time interaction, Algs. 1 and 2 are precomputed, except for the Score and Simplify steps that are calculated on the fly as the value of k and I τ change. Further details about the implementation and time analysis can be found in Appendices A and B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">ANALYTIC TASKS</head><p>The following analytic tasks were defined through a series of interviews and feedback sessions with three groups of stakeholders in the clinical domain (emergency services, cardiac intensive care, and outpatients). Our experts shared a common goal: discover a summary of the distinct clinical pathways clustering patients following a similar journey. They wanted to understand common and deviating scenarios to optimise the delivery of healthcare. Their event data sequences were partially derived from processes. For example, an ambulance does not arrive at the scene unless a call requesting such service happens first, but a patient might be prescribed a series of drugs in indistinct order. In this context, the use of soft patterns <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> is more appropriate -as the clustering should ensure that sequences with a similar set of event types are in the same cluster, regardless of event permutations, as opposed to enforcing a strict event ordering within cluster. Appendix C shows domain-specific examples for the following tasks.</p><p>T1. Explore common and deviating pathways: help users to explore and discover which clusterings summarize better the most common (and deviating) pathways in the data. Clusters will group sequences that share a set of event types, regardless of their order. T2. Interpret the sequences that constitute a cluster: the visualization should allow users to compare the most common event orderings (and permutations) within and across clusters using sequence alignment. T3. Focus the analysis on a selected set of records: allow queries in the dataset to focus on sequences with specific characteristics. T4. Obtain details on demand: provide coordinated views so that users can request finer details of interesting items in the overview.</p><p>Users should be able to go from the highest level of aggregation (i.e. clusters), passing through sequences grouped by their unique sequence, to individual sequences and their raw data including event timestamps and duration. T5. Aggregate and compare context information for selected groups of records: the system should allow to aggregate and compare data attributes (e.g. age, gender, country) for selected clusters, unique sequences, or individual sequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">VISUALIZATION SYSTEM: SEQUEN-C</head><p>Sequen-C was designed according to the analytic tasks outlined in the previous section. The GUI is implemented in Java and it is composed by three coordinated views (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>): multilevel overview, unique sequence view, and individual sequence view; and the attribute analysis view.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">The multilevel overview: cluster view</head><p>The multilevel overview (Fig. <ref type="figure">4-A</ref>) shows a variable number of sequence clusters, where each cluster is visually encoded according to the data representation matrix α constructed using the steps Align-Score-Simplify. Users can interact with this view through two sliders to transform the horizontal and vertical level-of-detail of the overview.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.1">Visual encoding</head><p>Event types are represented as coloured boxes with a height proportional to the number of records and color indicates the event type. Equal event types in consecutive rows are merged to reduce visual clutter. Sequences in a cluster are ordered by similarity, and gaps (-) in the alignment are encoded as spaces between events. The final height of a cluster is proportional to the number of records it contains, however, sometimes clusters might contain too few records in proportion to the whole dataset ending up not visible. In such cases the height is scaled up by a constant number of pixels and the cluster is surrounded by a dotted line, allowing users to identify deviating pathways (T1).</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> shows how each of the elements in the representation matrix contains either one or multiple event types, where an element with multiple event types corresponds to the row wise merged sub-sequences in the Simplify step. Sub-sequences contained in a single element are represented using a box divided by colored bars, where each bar is colored by event type and ordered as per the sub-sequence. This visual encoding allows to derive the original sequences forming a cluster (T2). To reduce visual clutter, when the number of events in the merged sub-sequence increases, bars can be ordered by event type to show proportion, or colored in gray to show the number of merged records.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1.2">Transforming the level-of-detail</head><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">4-E</ref> shows the two sliders used to transform the level-of-detail of the overview: the cluster slider and the information score slider. The cluster slider transforms the vertical level-of-detail by changing the number of clusters k in the range 1 ≤ k ≤ N, being N the number of input unique sequences. A combobox next to the cluster slider shows the current number of clusters and contains the list of alternative optimal number of clusters (Sect. 3.3), to guide users in finding a set of pathways that best summarize the data (T1). Alternatively, users can break down a selected cluster into its two child sub-clusters, and so on, until a cluster with a single sequence is reached (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>). The information score slider transforms the horizontal level-of-detail by changing the information score threshold I τ in the range 0 ≤ I τ ≤ 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Unique sequence view</head><p>This view shows the individual sequences in the selected clusters, grouped by unique sequence (T4). The sequences are visually encoded as an ordered sequence of boxes arranged horizontally and colored by event type (Fig. <ref type="figure">4-B</ref>), along with their identifier and frequency. Sequences are shown without any simplification allowing the inspection of the full sequences in the selected clusters (T2,T4). These sequences can be sorted by frequency or similarity, or aligned by a selected event.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Individual sequence view</head><p>This view shows the individual sequences (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4-C</ref>) of the selections in the unique sequence view and the overview (T4), along with their temporal information and raw data attributes. Following a Gantt chart approach, each individual sequence is visualized as a horizontal sequence of events, positioned along the horizontal axis according to their timestamp. A table of attributes is displayed next to the Gantt chart, where each column represents a data attribute at either individual sequence level or individual event level (T5).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">Attribute analysis view</head><p>The distribution of a data attribute can be analysed for a selected set of records (T3), or compared amongst clusters and unique sequences (T5). This view shows one stacked bar chart per attribute in the dataset (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4-D</ref>), where a chart contains one vertical bar per value, each bar is divided in sub-bars representing series, and series are identified Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>: Sequen-C visualization system (CUREd dataset). In the multilevel overview (A), cluster C5 is selected and its unique sequences are shown in the unique sequences view (B), where unique sequence S9 is selected, showing its 411 individual sequences in the individual sequences view (C). The attribute analysis (D) shows how attributes of the selected data relate to the whole dataset. (E) highlights some of the available controls. by a unique color. Series can be interactively hidden to focus on only one or compare a reduced number of series. Three types of charts are provided: 1) Selected data: compares the selected data against the rest of the records in the dataset. For a given attribute, this type of bar chart shows one series colored in red for the records contained in the selected clusters or unique sequences, and another series (in grey) for the rest of data. 2) Sequence: it plots one series for each unique sequence shown in the unique sequence view. 3) Cluster: it compares all clusters in the overview, and assigns one series per cluster (e.g. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-B</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">Filters and Selections</head><p>Records can be removed from the overview by applying filters based on data attributes, frequency, date range, event occurrence; including filters by day of the week, month, or year (T3). A filter is specified by an attribute, operator, and value. For example, the filter event = A translates to "show only sequences that contain event A at least once". Users can select sections of a cluster, such as events and sub-sequences, or sequences in the unique sequence view by drawing a square with the mouse. These selections are added to the unique sequence view and individual sequence view, and are plotted in the attribute analysis view (T4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CASE STUDIES</head><p>In line with the analytic tasks (T1 to T5), we present two case studies using real-world datasets: CUREd and MIMIC-III (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">CUREd: Analyzing emergency service calls</head><p>The CUREd research database <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> contains timestamped events and demographic data related to telephone calls made to the emergency service (calls to 999 or 111), throughout Yorkshire and the Humber region. Calls can lead to different pathways, including ambulance conveyance to the Emergency department (ED) and admissions to inpatient facilities. A three month subset of the dataset was used, containing 25,243 calls relating to 21,805 unique patients, and 57 data attributes. The data were processed so that an individual sequence represents all the events of multiple calls and incidents for the same patient. We conducted an analysis session along with members of the Centre for Urgent and Emergency Care Research (CURE).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.1">Overview of main pathways</head><p>After loading the data, the overview shows 200 clusters ordered by frequency. Clusters are well separated and present little intra-cluster variation (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). The first four clusters represent 85% of the data and the remaining patterns are repetitions or variations of the main four. To get a coarser overview, the number of clusters is changed to 4 (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-A</ref>). These clusters cover the pathways (T1): Cluster C1 (34.9%), ambulance service and attendance to the emergency department; Cluster C2 (24.7%), ambulance service and conveyance to a hospital; Cluster C3 (23.6%), ambulance arrives to destination but no conveyance is made. Cluster C4 (16.8%): call closed, no ambulance service.</p><p>The attribute area classification code is a classification based on socio-economic information derived from the postcode of the incident. Comparing the area classification code of the four clusters (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-B</ref>), some clusters predominate more in certain area codes than others. Hospital transfers (cluster C2) happen for 43.5% of calls coming from area code 4BD and 53.1% of calls from area 2A2, while 72.3% of calls from area 8C3 are in cluster C4. The age attribute (amb callage) indicates that cluster C4 is more common amongst younger people, meaning that calls from area 8C3 or people in their 20s can usually be handled without an ambulance service resource attending. Conversely, cluster C3 is more common for people in their 80s (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-B</ref>). According to the attribute symptom: 59.7% of calls due to chest pain end in an attendance to the emergency department (cluster C1) whereas 45.3% of calls due to a psychiatric incident fall in cluster C4 (T5). To further explore cluster C1, a filter is applied to show only sequences containing at least one emergency department event (T3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Calls leading to the emergency department</head><p>The analyst chooses 11 as the number of clusters, suggested by the system as one of the optimal number of clusters (T1), and orders clusters by similarity. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-C</ref> shows that the first six clusters (C1 to C6) contain about 96% of the filtered data and represent patients with usually only one call to the emergency service. These six clusters categorize visits depending on whether the visit to the emergency department is either followed by a triage event (TRI), seen by a health professional (SBH) to arrange treatment, or both (T2). According to the attribute attendance disposal (i.e. how the visit was concluded), in most cases where a triage event is not followed by an SBH event (clusters C3 and C6) is because the patient left the department before being treated. Cluster C5 contains the highest percentage of data (81.1%) with 6180 individual sequences; its attribute analysis indicates that 52% of these patients were admitted to a hospital bed and that this cluster is slightly more common amongst women (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-C</ref>).</p><p>Interestingly, the event "patient left emergency department" (LED) is only present in clusters C1 to C4. The attribute analysis showed that the age of these patients go from 0 to 15 years old, and that the Children's hospital is the only ambulance destination (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-C</ref>) (T5).</p><p>The absence of the event LED in other hospitals might be due to a different configuration in the event log capturing system. Clusters C7 to C9 suggest that about 3.7% of patients have called the emergency service twice or more. In order to find out how many calls were made before the first ambulance service resource attended: clusters C7 to C9 are aligned by the first occurrence of the events CAL (call) and SCE (ambulance arrived scene) (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-C</ref>). Sequences in cluster C7 contain many more calls before the first SCE event (T2); which suggests that these patients had to "try" more times to get an ambulance service for the first time compared to clusters C8 and C9. To investigate whether these multiple calls were made in the same day the ambulance service was provided, cluster C7 was added to the individual sequence view (T4). Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5-D</ref> shows that most of these multiple calls were made in the same day and therefore relate to the same incident. Individual scenarios in this cluster need further exploring.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2">MIMIC-III</head><p>The MIMIC-III database <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> contains data for 58,976 patient admissions to acute and critical care units at a tertiary hospital, organised in 26 tables containing demographic data and timestamped clinical events from admission to discharge. In this case study, an individual sequence represents all the events for a single admission, obtained from the admissions, transfers, and prescriptions tables. This case study was developed in collaboration with a consultant cardiologist (i.e. the analyst). A query was added to show patients with a primary or secondary diagnosis of Atrial Fibrillation (AF) (code 42731 in the DIAGNOSES ICD table). The subset data contained 1,425 patient admissions, and 448 event types, from which 438 are types of prescriptions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.1">Overview of care unit and prescription patterns</head><p>The overview of the 1,425 individual sequences was explored by the analyst and us, selecting different number of clusters and breaking down into more granular detail within interesting clusters, the final overview shows 33 sequence clusters. The commonest care units for patients with AF were the: Cardiac Surgery Recovery Unit (CSRU), Coronary Care Unit (CCU), Medical Intensive Care Unit (MICU), and Surgical Intensive Care Unit (SICU). By default clusters were ordered by similarity. The first 18 clusters, comprising 55% of all the admissions, started attendance to the Emergency Department (ED) with subsequent transfer to an inpatient care unit (T2). Clusters were ordered by frequency. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6</ref>-A shows that, in general, the selected clustering either groups patients sharing a specific drug but admitted to different care units (e.g. Furosemide and Potassium Chloride predominate in cluster C4), or patients admitted to a specific care unit that can be subdivided into different treatments (e.g. admission to CSRU in cluster C1) (T1). Clusters with less than 1% of frequency represent more exceptional outlier scenarios with less intra-cluster variation and very similar set of drugs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6-D</ref>) (T2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.2">Comparing attributes across clusters</head><p>Focusing on the main clusters (C1 to C9), for each care unit, there is a cluster of patients admitted directly to that care unit and a second cluster of patients passing through ED before being transferred to that unit (e.g. clusters C2 and C6). As observed in Clusters C1 and C5, this is different in the case of the CSRU unit, where most patients do not pass through ED first (T2). Most of the patients in cluster C1 were treated with Metoprolol; whereas most in cluster C5 were treated with Warfarin. To inspect these patients, clusters C1 and C5 were analyzed in the attribute analysis view (T5), Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6-B</ref> shows that patients in cluster C5 tend to have longer lengths of stay (11 days in average) compared to cluster C1 (7 days in average). The analyst mentioned that this is likely to be associated with the requirement for careful dose titration with Warfarin and that "such observations could be helpful to healthcare planning; outpatient dosing could justifiably be targeted at this cluster to reduce length of stay and free up valuable hospital beds".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.2.3">Details on-demand for records of interest</head><p>The analyst was curious to explore the clusters showing a higher mortality (C3 and C8) and their relation with a first or second diagnosis of AF. C3 and C8, containing admissions to MICU and SICU respectively, were added to the individual sequence view (T4). Attributes diagnosis1, diagnosis2, and discharge location were added to the Gantt chart table, and sequences were ordered by diagnosis2 and discharge location. This showed that, for C3 and C8, there is a significant higher number of deaths when AF is a second diagnosis compared to when it is a first diagnosis (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">6-C</ref>). This might be probably because first non atrial fibrillation diagnoses might be more serious conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.3">Domain expert overall feedback</head><p>The domain experts (E1, E2, E3) confirmed the plausibility of the findings or considered that they required further investigation. In a separate session, we asked them to provide feedback about the usefulness of Sequen-C and the vertical and horizontal level-of-detail controls. E1 said that the clustering suggested by the system was useful "to discover how patient journeys differ beyond what we would expect". E3 stated that this type of analysis "can help to better understand clinical workflow data to improve services". E2 particularly liked the functionality of exploring the attributes for a selected cluster. Experts found that the vertical level-of-detail control allows one to "rapidly and intuitively manipulate the granularity [of the visualization]" (E3) and that increasing the number of clusters is useful when looking for outliers (E1).</p><p>E1 indicated that "often the high frequency events [in the cluster view] are the most important" as these pathways would usually be the ones targeted for interventions to improve outcomes, however sometimes the interest could be in rare scenarios "that may have led to an adverse event". E1 found useful having the flexibility of adjusting the horizontal level-of-detail to focus on both scenarios. Expert E2 said that the horizontal slider was useful to "cluster noise". Experts mentioned that it was sometimes confusing to know which sub-sequences had collapsed when the horizontal slider was changed and that they would prefer changing I τ in smaller steps. Experts E1 and E3 mentioned that they would like to continue using the system to link additional data to expand the pathways and explore longer term clinical outcomes data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION</head><p>We presented a technique to create and explore a multilevel overview of event sequences through hierarchical aggregation and a novel cluster representation Align-Score-Simplify. Users can interactively transform the overview from coarse to fine vertical or horizontal level-of-detail, allowing the exploration of sequence clusterings (vertical) and the interactive summarization of clusters (horizontal). Moreover, we provide a set of optimal number of clusters that represent alternative good overviews to the default one. The visual analytics framework, Sequen-C, allows multilevel and details-on-demand exploration, and the inspection of data attributes at cluster, unique sequence, or individual record level.</p><p>Two case studies using real-world datasets were presented, where findings obtained with Sequen-C were validated with domain experts. One of the experts mentioned that traditionally, obtaining this type of findings would involve several meetings between stakeholders and analysts, while with Sequen-C, they were able to interactively answer multiple questions about the patterns in a single session, consequently saving them valuable time. The analysts in the CUREd case study mentioned that these analyses are helping them gain "insights into which calls are likely to need a hospital transfer and which may benefit from a different response" and that "knowing these patterns might help assist decision making for call handlers".</p><p>Although the presented case studies include a relatively high number of event types (MIMIC-III, 448 event types) and a high number of individual sequences (CUREd, 21,805 individual sequences), the visualization presents scalability limitations. Events are color-coded, making it difficult to distinguish more than a certain number of event types via color (e.g. 12), and navigating long lists of event types (e.g. &gt; 20) is complicated. In the latter case, a hierarchy of event types could facilitate this interaction.</p><p>An advantage of the cluster representation is that the event types in the simplified sub-sequences are explicitly encoded, which allows to understand variability and in some cases derive the original sequences. However, the Align-Score-Simplify approach presents three main limitations. 1) Future work is needed to determine the optimal value of the information score I τ . 2) With increased number of event types, the representation of merged sub-sequences suffer from visual clutter. Future work is needed to provide alternative designs that better summarize simplified sub-sequences and improve the interpretation of information loss. 3) The alignment step of the approach is too time consuming, it is affected by the choice of gap and substitution costs, and it would benefit from an event type categorization (e.g. care units, prescriptions), so that events can be aligned based on their meaning rather than the name of the event type. Alternative alignment methods could be proposed (e.g. based on the longest common sub-sequence).</p><p>We have created a flexible overview that allows users to uncover hidden insights. However, the current technique still depends, at some level, on the nature of the dataset, and the knowledge and hypotheses of domain experts. Future work is needed to validate the current technique in other domains besides the clinical one. Lines of future research are to consider in the clustering aspects such as event type importance, event ordering (with strategies to avoid noise) and other data attributes, and provide a visual cluster representation that encodes such attributes.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2: (A) Building aggregate tree T for input unique sequences S = {s 1 ,...s 6 )}. (B) Each node in T has an alignment matrix λ for its child sequences, a row-wise probabilities vector P, and a column-wise information score vector I. Two or more consecutive columns in λ with I j &lt; 0.8 are not coloured. (C) Multilevel overviews for a range of number of clusters k retrieved from T , where black blocks represent merged columns.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,314.75,49.13,237.02,312.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3: Cluster data representation (top left) and visual encoding (top right) for S = {s 1 ,...s 6 } and I τ = 0.6 using the Align-Score-Simplify strategy. The Simplify step produces the simplified alignment matrix α. Using α, the visual encoding is built and event types in the merged sub-sequences are represented using ordered colored bars. Changing I τ (bottom) transforms the horizontal level-of-detail. Note how this shows the most common event orderings (e.g. a-b-c-h) and permutations in the order (e.g. b-a and j-i highlighted with dashed lines).</figDesc><graphic coords="5,53.63,49.13,376.94,236.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5: Multilevel overview for 21,805 patients who made calls to emergency services, obtained from the CUREd dataset.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,44.99,49.49,513.14,288.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Fig. 6: Overview of 1,425 admissions of patients with a first or second diagnosis of Atrial Fibrillation, obtained from the MIMIC-III dataset.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,316.31,218.69,215.18,135.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>loop until one node remains (root node) */</figDesc><table /><note>4 while |T | &gt; 1 do /* aggregate the closest pair of nodes */ 5 (n a , n b ) = argmin d[n i , n j ]; ∀ pairs, n i , n j ∈ T 6 n a∪b = aggregate(n a , n b ); /* update distance matrix */ 7 d[n a∪b , n] = d[n, n a∪b ] = D cqgram (n a∪b , n); ∀ n ∈ T 8 remove distances containing n a and n b from d; /* update nodes set T */ 9 remove n a and n b from T ; 10 add n a∪b to T ; 11 end 12 return T Algorithm 2: Data representation of a cluster Data: nodes n a and n b Result: aggregated node n a∪b 13 Function aggregate(n a , n b ): /* Align: compute λ from children nodes */ 14 λ = MSA(n a .λ , n b .λ ); /* Score: column-wise information score I */ 15 for j ← 1 to m do 16 Compute I j according to Eq. 1 and Eq. 2 17 end /* Simplify: collapse columns based on I */ 18 listRemove = / 0; 19 for j ← 1 to m − 1 do 20 if I j &lt; I τ and I j+1 &lt; I τ then 21 for i ← 1 to n do 22 λ i, j+1 = concatenate(λ i, j , λ i, j+1 ); 23 end 24 add j to listRemove; 25 end 26 end /* assign the simplified alignment to α */ 27 α = delete columns in listRemove from λ ; /* create new node n a∪b */ 28 n a∪b = Node(n a , n b , λ , α); 29 return n a∪b</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Characteristics of datasets used in the case studies (in bold), and time performance for algorithms buildAggregateTree and aggregate for different subsets of the data. The time for buildAggregateTree does not include the function aggregate, which is broken down according to the Align, Score and Simplify steps. Experiments were run on a MacBook Pro, 2.9 GHz Quad-Core Intel Core i7, 16GB (Appendices A and B).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Dataset</cell><cell>Percentage</cell><cell cols="2">No. sequences Individual Unique</cell><cell>No. event types</cell><cell cols="2">Length of sequences Average Maximum</cell><cell cols="3">Execution time (s) aggregate AggregateTree build Align Score &amp; Simplify</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell>CUREd</cell><cell>25% 50% 75% 100%</cell><cell>20,124 20,901 21,520 21,805</cell><cell>240 481 722 962</cell><cell>11 11 11 11</cell><cell>9.96 13.07 16.24 22.70</cell><cell>13 19 28 177</cell><cell>0.0 0.1 0.2 0.4</cell><cell>9.3 59.1 225.5 3984.7</cell><cell>10.1 30.9 74.5 301.0</cell><cell>19.4 90.1 300.2 4286.0</cell></row><row><cell>MIMIC-III</cell><cell>25% 50% 75% 100%</cell><cell>442 770 1,097 1,425</cell><cell>328 656 983 1,311</cell><cell>158 242 338 448</cell><cell>6.07 7.31 8.45 10.67</cell><cell>8 10 12 96</cell><cell>0.1 0.2 0.5 1.5</cell><cell>3.5 16.9 73.4 995.4</cell><cell>9.7 35.6 86.9 317.5</cell><cell>13.2 52.7 160.8 1314.3</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>The authors wish to thank CONACYT and The Health Foundation (PathAnalyse project) for supporting this work, and the anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments. CUREd Research Database is an independent project funded by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Applied Research Collaboration Yorkshire and Humber (NIHR200166). The views expressed in this publication are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of NIHR or the Department of Health and Social Care. Paul D Morris (PD) was funded by the Wellcome Trust [214567/Z/18/Z]. For the purpose of Open Access, PD has applied a CC BY public copyright licence to any Author Accepted Manuscript version arising from this submission.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Data clustering: algorithms and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Aggarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Reddy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trace alignment in process mining: opportunities for process diagnostics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J C</forename><surname>Bose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Van Der Aalst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Business Process Management</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="242" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Workflow mining and outlier detection from clinical activity logs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bouarfa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dankelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of biomedical informatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1185" to="1190" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model-based clustering and visualization of navigation patterns on a web site</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Cadez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heckerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Meek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data mining and knowledge discovery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring multivariate event sequences using rules, aggregations, and selections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cappers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Wijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="532" to="541" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence synopsis: Optimize visual summary of temporal event data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence braiding: Visual overviews of temporal event sequences and attributes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Di</forename><surname>Bartolomeo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dunne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coping with volume and variety in temporal event sequences: Strategies for sharpening analytic focus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1636" to="1649" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hierarchical aggregation for information visualization: Overview, techniques, and design guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Elmqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="439" to="454" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A visual interface for multivariate temporal data: Finding patterns of events across multiple histories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fails</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karlson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shahamat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2006 IEEE Symposium On Visual Analytics Science And Technology</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="174" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progressive sequence alignment as a prerequisite to correct phylogenetic trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D.-F</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Doolittle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of molecular evolution</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CHROMA: consensus-based colouring of multiple alignments for publication</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Goodstadt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ponting</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="845" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Soft patterns: Moving beyond explicit sequential patterns during visual analysis of longitudinal event datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE VIS 2016 Workshop on Temporal &amp; Sequential Event Analysis</title>
				<meeting>the IEEE VIS 2016 Workshop on Temporal &amp; Sequential Event Analysis</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DecisionFlow: Visual analytics for highdimensional temporal event sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Stavropoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1783" to="1792" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual cluster analysis in support of clinical decision intelligence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ebadollahi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">AMIA Annual Symposium Proceedings</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2011</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">481</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual analysis of high-dimensional event sequence data via dynamic hierarchical aggregation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shrestha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Borland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="450" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual progression analysis of event sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="426" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Eventthread: Visual summarization and stage analysis of event sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MIMIC-III, a freely accessible critical care database</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pollard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Other</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific data</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Finding groups in data: an introduction to cluster analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rousseeuw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CUREd: Creating a research database to improve urgent and emergency care system research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuczawski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In EUSEM Abstracts. Prague</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">512</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dpvis: Visual analytics with hidden markov models for disease progression pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Anand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Severson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ghosh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Frohnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lundgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peekquence: Visual analytics for event sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Verma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM SIGKDD 2016 Workshop on Interactive Data Exploration and Analytics</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generating consensus sequences from partial order multiple sequence alignment graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1008" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binary codes capable of correcting deletions, insertions, and reversals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Levenshtein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Soviet physics doklady</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1966">1966</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="710" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ssrdvis: Interactive visualization for event sequences summarization and rare detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracting and visualizing branching patterns from event sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dontcheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="538" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns and sequences: Interactive exploration of clickstreams to understand common visitor paths</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dontcheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Logview: Visualizing event log clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Makanju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Zincir-Heywood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Milios</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sixth Annual Conference on Privacy, Security and Trust</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008. 2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="108" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temporal event sequence simplification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Monroe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2227" to="2236" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The challenges of specifying intervals and absences in temporal queries: A graphical language approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Monroe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morales Del Olmo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Millstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
				<meeting>the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2349" to="2358" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vasabi: Hierarchical user profiles for interactive visual user behaviour analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Henkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Andrienko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Thonnard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turkay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequence: interactive mining and visualization of temporal frequent event sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 19th international conference on Intelligent User Interfaces</title>
				<meeting>the 19th international conference on Intelligent User Interfaces</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="162" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lifelines: using visualization to enhance navigation and analysis of patient records</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mushlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The craft of information visualization</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="312" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Silhouettes: a graphical aid to the interpretation and validation of cluster analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rousseeuw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of computational and applied mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The eyes have it: A task by data type taxonomy for information visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Craft of Information Visualization</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="371" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data mining in the development of mobile health apps: Assessing in-app navigation through markov chain analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stragier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vandewiele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Coppens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ongenae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Van Den Broeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Turck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>De Marez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of medical Internet research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e11934</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The scikit-bio development team. scikit-bio: A bioinformatics library for data scientists, students, and developers</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Approximate string-matching with q-grams and maximal matches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ukkonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theoretical computer science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The stringdist package for approximate string matching</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Van Der Loo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The R Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activitree: Interactive visual exploration of sequences in event-based data using graph similarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vrotsou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Johansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="945" to="952" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unsupervised clickstream clustering for user behavior analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2016 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
				<meeting>the 2016 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="236" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SEGID: Identifying interesting segments in (multiple) sequence alignments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual cluster exploration of web clickstream data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sundaresan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-L</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2012 IEEE Conference on Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring flow, factors, and outcomes of temporal event sequences with the Outflow visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wongsuphasawat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2659" to="2668" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LifeFlow: visualizing an overview of event sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wongsuphasawat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Guerra Gómez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Plaisant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Taieb-Maimon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems</title>
				<meeting>the SIGCHI conference on human factors in computing systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1747" to="1756" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using visualizations to monitor changes and harvest insights from a global-scale logging infrastructure at twitter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wongsuphasawat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2014 IEEE Conference on Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="122" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">(s-qu)eries: Visual regular expressions for querying and exploring event sequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zgraggen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Drucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Deline</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
				<meeting>the 33rd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2683" to="2692" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Idmvis: Temporal event sequence visualization for type 1 diabetes treatment decision support</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chanana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dunne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="512" to="522" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating alignment approaches in superimposed time-series and temporal event-sequence visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Di</forename><surname>Bartolomeo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jimison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dunne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2019 IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="5" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual comparison of event sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dontcheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
				<meeting>the 33rd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="259" to="268" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of trace alignment quality and its application in medical process mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Marsic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Farneth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Burd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2017 IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics (ICHI)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
