<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Baby Names, Visualization, and Social Data Analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Wattenberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Baby Names, Visualization, and Social Data Analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T18:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Design Study</term>
					<term>Time-Varying Data Visualization</term>
					<term>Human-Computer Interaction</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>The NameVoyager, a web-based visualization of historical trends in baby naming, has proven remarkably popular. This paper discusses the interaction techniques it uses for smooth visual exploration of thousands of time series. We also describe design decisions behind the application and lessons learned in creating an application that makes do-it-yourself data mining popular. The prime lesson, it is hypothesized, is that an information visualization tool may be fruitfully viewed not as a tool but as part of an online social environment. In other words, to design a successful exploratory data analysis tool, one good strategy is to create a system that enables &quot;social&quot; data analysis.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>In February of 2005, my wife published her first book, a guide to American baby names called The Baby Name Wizard <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> which used a data-analysis approach to understanding name styles. To help call attention to the book, I created a web-based visualization applet, the NameVoyager <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, which lets users interactively explore name data specifically, historical name popularity figures. The gambit succeeded and without any advertising the applet drew more than 500,000 site visits in the first two weeks after launch. Two months afterwards it is maintaining an average of 10,000 visits a day. Perhaps more important is that evidence suggests many people are engaging deeply with the visualization, spending considerable time and discovering for themselves facts and insights about name trends.</p><p>The broad popularity and effectiveness of the NameVoyager is especially interesting because it is, in essence, an exploratory data analysis application for a data set of 6,000 time series. In many situations, ranging from education to retirement planning, it is important to encourage users to interact with complex data sets. Understanding the factors that led a statistical exploration program to become a minor fad may shed light on the broader problem of encouraging users to engage in their own personal data mining expeditions.</p><p>An important piece of the puzzle is the public nature of a webbased application. As of April 2005, Google finds more than 11,000 references to the NameVoyager, many of which turn out to be lengthy sequences of comments on blogs and discussion sites. These comments provide clues as to how and why users are spending time with the applet. This data is in no way a scientific survey, but it does represent a large body of field usage information in which patterns emerge.</p><p>In hundreds of spontaneous comments, users are seen to be engaged in extended exploratory data analysis, identifying trends and anomalies and forming conjectures. These self-reports also lead to an observation about the NameVoyager: usage patterns are strongly social, and seem more closely related to those of online multiplayer games than to a conventional single-user statistical tool. Indeed, users seem to fall neatly into Richard Bartle's wellknown categorization of online game players <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> as explorers, achievers, socializers, or killers. This stands in contrast to the traditional view of information visualization as a task-oriented problem-solving activity. We hypothesize that the broad popularity of the NameVoyager stems from features that not only give it a game-like sense of fun, but that make it especially suitable for "social" data analysis. We then suggest some general properties which may encourage this type of usage of visualizations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">THE NAMEVOYAGER</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Data</head><p>The NameVoyager is based on a data set, derived from public Social Security Administration (SSA) information that tracks baby name trends in the United States. For each decade since 1900 the SSA publishes lists of the most popular 1,000 boys and girls names, along with the exact number of babies given these names. These lists were downloaded, collated, cleaned, and normalized by the author of the Baby Name Wizard book to produce a data set containing popularity time series for roughly 6,000 distinct names.</p><p>These time series turn out to be meaningful in many ways. A graph of the popularity of a given name reveals a great deal about its overall cultural connotations and "feel," and names whose popularity is correlated over time tend to seem similar. (For more information, see The Baby Name Wizard.)  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visualization method</head><p>The method used to visualize the data is straightforward: given a set of name popularity time series, a set of stacked graphs is produced, as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>. Such stacked graphs are common in print information design and have recently been used in several information visualization projects such as ThemeRiver <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and Artifacts of the Presence Era <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. The x-axis corresponds to date, and the y-axis to total frequency for all names currently in view, in terms of occurrences per million babies. Each stripe represents a name, and the thickness of a stripe is proportional to its frequency of use at the given time step.</p><p>In keeping with contemporary American custom, the stripes are colored pink for girls and blue for boys. The brightness of each stripe varies according to the most recent popularity data, so that currently popular names are darkest and stand out the most. The idea behind this color scheme is twofold. First, names that are currently popular are more likely to be of interest to viewersmany people will probably want to know statistics on Jennifer, but few are looking for Cloyd. Second, the fact that the brightness varies provides a way to distinguish neighboring name stripes without relying on visually heavy borders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Interaction</head><p>The NameVoyager follows Shneiderman's mantra of "overview first, zoom and filter, details on demand" <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. When the applet starts, the viewer sees a set of stripes representing all names in the database. Filtering this data is achieved via an extremely simple mechanism. A user may type in letters, forming a prefix; the applet will then visualize data on only those names beginning with that prefix.</p><p>The applet reacts directly with each keystroke, so it is not necessary for the user to press return or to click a submit button. Not only does this instant interaction save the user some work, but it helps demonstrate how to mine the data. A user might not think that searching the data set by prefix would be interesting, but seeing the striking patterns for single letters like O or K could encourage further exploration. In addition, the applet moves smoothly between states, so that when a letter is typed, an animated transition helps preserve context. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> shows an example: typing "JO" will yield a graph with prominent stripes for popular names such as John, Jonathan, Joseph, and Joyce, along with many thinner stripes for less popular names like Josette. Because the initial letters of a name contribute strongly to its sound, names that start with the same letters often have similar graph patterns. As a result, the simple mechanism of filtering by prefix is effective in highlighting interesting name trends. Typing "O" produces the graph in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure  2</ref>, with an easily identifiable pattern of popularity of O names at the beginning and end of the 1900s, but a significant dip midcentury. Typing "LAT" highlights a trend in the African-American community in the 1970s, comprising names such as LaToya, LaTanya, LaTisha, and so on, as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Figure 3</ref>. Name stripes are ordered alphabetically on the screen from top to bottom to aid in identifying such prefix-based cultural clusters. To learn details of a name, a viewer can use the mouse. Hovering over a name stripe will produce a pop-up box with numerical details for a given name at a given point in time. Clicking on a name stripe produces a graph of the popularity of that name alone. This interaction technique may be compared to dynamic query systems such as starfield displays <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> or TimeSearcher <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. The keyboard interaction may be viewed as an alternative to the Alphaslider of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. A key distinction between the graphical display of the NameVoyager and the visualization used in TimeSearcher, is the NameVoyager's use of a graph that sums all the time series. This technique seems likely to be of use in many other situations where summing is a natural operation, such as investigating product sales data. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Technical Implementation</head><p>The NameVoyager is a Java applet, written using JDK 1.1 so that it may run in a wide variety of browsers. All the name data (a 60K zip file) is loaded at startup and parsed into Java objects, so that it may be accessed rapidly.</p><p>To make the animated transitions run smoothly, not all 6,000 stripes are drawn; instead, a simple level-of-detail calculation is performed so that only stripes wider than 2 pixels are rendered to the screen. As a result, in practice the applet only draws about 200 or fewer stripes per frame. In an initial version of the applet, this culling of names caused prominent and irritating white stripes in the graph, where the white background would "show through" the undrawn stripes. Replacing the white background with a neutral gray, halfway between the blue and pink tones of the name stripes, was a simple and effective remedy: the background was still visible but barely noticeable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.1</head><p>Traffic and Web Comments As mentioned in the introduction, the NameVoyager received a remarkable number of visits within weeks of launch. The applet has been downloaded more than 900,000 times as of mid-April. It has also been extensively discussed on the web, in blogs, discussion forums, and similar sites.</p><p>This intense level of conversation is further evidence that users were engaging deeply with the applet and of its widespread popularity. It is not uncommon to find discussions in the comments section of a blog that contain dozens of posts. Such long discussions occur even when it is not related to the topic of the web site-for instance, one of the most extensive sets of comments was found on a forum in a well-known libertarian magazine site.</p><p>The comments also provide an unusual and informative window into the user experience, and we quote them extensively below. Comments that have been posted to the web are clearly not a scientific sample, since only the most enthusiastic users will comment. Nonetheless, examining these comments suggests some interesting hypotheses regarding the source of popularity of the NameVoyager.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">The Target Audience and the Surprise Factor</head><p>As one might expect, there are many positive comments from people in the target audience for the visualization-users who have a strong interest in names and therefore might be interested in buying the book. Two examples (all quotes in this paper are taken from public web sites) illustrate this:</p><p>"This is perfect, as baby names weigh heavily on my mind these days." "Useful fodder for historical fiction, too, if you're looking for typical names for a given age and time period." A surprising observation is that many people outside the target audience found themselves enjoying the applet. The surprise here is not the author's, but of the users themselves. Some sample quotes:</p><p>"Surprisingly addictive" "This rules, even though it's about baby names" "Cool… by the way, I don't like babies or children."</p><p>This "surprise factor" is a reason for optimism. It is common to want users to explore a set of data that they may have little inherent interest in. A good example is the amount of effort and money that American companies spend to encourage their employees to understand 401(k) plans. It is therefore worthwhile to look for clues to what made the NameVoyager appeal to people who profess boredom with the topic of baby names.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">SOCIAL DATA ANALYSIS</head><p>One of the most consistent themes seen in comments about the NameVoyager is that exploring the data has become a social activity. Many people mention group usage, for instance: "I happened upon it at work today and it affected the productivity of our entire department."</p><p>Of special interest, however, is that when a group of people uses the applet, they often do so in a social, collaborative fashion, engaging in a dialogue as they mine the data. This is true even for loosely knit groups of web users. For example, here are some quotes from the comments section of one blog:</p><p>"For a challenge, try finding a name that was popular at the beginning of the sample <ref type="bibr">(around 1900)</ref> These quotes, which are just a small part of the full exchange, illustrate two points. First, they show how a group of people is using the NameVoyager as a stimulus to conversation and repartee.</p><p>They also reveal an effective style of data analysis: this group of people is diving very deeply into the data set! They are setting each other pattern-finding challenges, noting outlying data points, and making guesses about causal relations. Each person seems to be building on the findings of the others, making the group as a whole extremely effective at mining the data-and having fun at the same time. Strange or surprising pieces of information serve as a kind of trophy for the finder. We refer to this process of data mining through dialogue, one-upmanship, and repartee as social data analysis. It is a version of exploratory data analysis that relies on social interaction as source of inspiration and motivation.</p><p>We hypothesize that viewing exploratory data analysis as a social activity may explain much of the reaction to the NameVoyager. Its popularity among people who do not find the data intrinsically interesting, for instance, could partly be due to the fact that these users are enjoying the social activity surrounding the applet. In the next sections, to understand better the social structure of this type of exploratory data analysis, we consider the different roles that users may play.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Roles in Social Data Analysis</head><p>As in any social system, it seems that people using the NameVoyager have a wide range of styles of interaction with each other. Comments on the web suggest that there are four distinct types of users. Interestingly, these types seem to align closely with a taxonomy developed by Richard Bartle <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> in the context of an early class of online social environment called a MUD.</p><p>Bartle suggested that denizens of such online multiplayer environments typically fall into one of four types: achievers, socializers, explorers, and killers. Below we describe how each of these roles seems to correspond to a particular type of NameVoyager user. While this is only a preliminary classification, it may be of use to designers in thinking about how people use data visualization in social contexts, and also provides additional evidence that use of the NameVoyager takes place in a complex social environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Achievers</head><p>The context of the NameVoyager is a site designed to help expectant parents name their babies, so the stated "goal" of the applet is to find a good name. As described in Section 3.3, many people do exactly that:</p><p>"We want something slightly retro, nice, and not too popular, and this visualization gives us all that."</p><p>Such users correspond to the Achievers in Bartle's classification: people who try to "achieve within the game's context."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.3</head><p>Socializers A second class of NameVoyager users consists of people whose main concern is their interactions with others, and who place their data exploration in a personal social context. These people, corresponding to Bartle's "Socializers," use screenshots and data from the applet as a catalyst for conversation and storytelling about themselves and their friends and family. A common sight on a blog is a person posting a screenshot of the graph of their own name's popularity, or a friend's, with humorous comments. A typical quote of this type is:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>"Runes name doesnt show up at all… but my name has suddenly gotten popular … I HAD IT FIRST! heh"</head><p>Often people talk about family members as they speculate about names, and see the changing popularity numbers as a kind of personal plotline: "my grandmother was named Coral and from what I can tell the name appeared out of nowhere in 1880…is it from a celebrity or something?" "I got: 'No names starting with LINUS were in the top 1,000 names in any decade.' Translation: Your son' s name will NEVER be cool." "Woo! Emily (being me) was number 1 in 2003! go me!" Such relationship-oriented and storytelling behavior in the context of information visualization has been observed before in depictions of email archives <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.4</head><p>Explorers Many users of the NameVoyager seemed to delight in unearthing odd names or unusual clusters. One person posted a screenshot created after typing "ETH": it showed the name Ethel being gradually and completely eclipsed by the trendy name Ethan. Another found the dramatic cluster of names starting with "LAT" (Latisha, Latoya, etc.) described in section 2.3. A well-known pundit used the NameVoyager to comment on the changing statistical distribution of names over the past century These users were certainly not using the NameVoyager to name children, but rather were mining for nuggets of information that they could show to others as trophies of their expedition. They are directly analogous to Bartle's Explorers, people who want to learn as much as possible about the environment and who delight in discovering odd or unexpected features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Killers</head><p>The last type in Bartle's taxonomy is the Killer, someone who enjoys imposing themselves on others and causing distress. One might think that there would be no Killers in the gentle world of baby names, but one would be wrong. A common theme is that certain users take pleasure in singling out names for ridicule. For these people the NameVoyager is a delightful source of fresh targets:</p><p>"It is also damn entertaining to me (and the real reason why I am writing this) that I can type in Lexus and find that people actually name their kids Lexus."</p><p>(Lest there be any doubt about the pugilistic nature of the quote's author, note that it was found on a site called www.youandwhosearmy.com.)</p><p>"Britney, Brittney, Britany, Brittany, Brittani, Britannie, Britni. Enough already."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DESIGN HYPOTHESES FOR SOCIAL DATA ANALYSIS</head><p>The evidence above suggests that a large part of the power and popularity of the NameVoyager derives from the fact that it encourages a social style of data analysis. What leads users to approach data analysis as a social activity? Certain factors are obvious. The NameVoyager is easily accessible on the web so that a large group of people can see it. The interaction design, referred to on the web with such terms as "cool," "fantastic," and "whizzy," means that applet is something that people may be eager to associate themselves with, like a fashionable piece of clothing.</p><p>These factors, however, would apply to anything trendy on the web, whether a funny Flash animation or witty personality quiz. Are there any aspects of the NameVoyager's popularity that are specific to information visualization? We present three hypotheses below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Common Ground But Unique Perspective</head><p>The first hypothesis is that a combination of common ground with unique individual perspectives will encourage social data analysis.</p><p>In the case of the NameVoyager, the common ground is shared understanding of cultural connotations of names. The authors of these comments are sharing results of their data mining because they know that their readers will understand the cultural references. The fact that the data is presented as a timeline over a standard period, 1900 to present, also provides a common context on which users overlay personal and cultural knowledge.</p><p>At the same time, we hypothesize that it is helpful for each person to have a naturally unique perspective on the data. This individual viewpoint can serve as a kind of icebreaker in the conversation. It also means that, because each person is approaching the data in a different way, a group may collectively explore more pieces of the data. Evidence for this hypothesis comes from <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, which described a system that encouraged community participation by highlighting unique pieces of knowledge that an individual might have. A well-respected educational method known as the Jigsaw Classroom [3] uses a similar technique.</p><p>In the case of the NameVoyager, each person has one obvious point of entry: their own name. Names of relatives and close friends are also common conversation starters. Some sample comments illustrate this: "I was appalled to note that my name is now in the top 100, while it was about 700 th when I was born…"</p><p>"My given name peaked in 1900 (or earlier) and has been on the slide ever since. Seems to be off the radar now. Elmer is more popular these days!" "It also confirmed my suspicion that our eight-month-old son's name, Jackson, was rapidly gaining in popularity. Dangit, and we thought he would avoid having 4 kids in kindergarten with the same name!!!" Thus usage of the NameVoyager thus follows a pattern in which people look at different aspects of the data set, but have an expectation that their particular findings will be interesting and understandable to others. We term this pattern the "common ground but unique perspective" principle.</p><p>Applying this principle in other situations may require some flexibility in the data set, but it may also be possible to guide people without modifying the data. For instance, imagine a visualization tool designed to help people understand different stock market investment strategies. Using well-known companies or events as landmarks could provide common ground. At the same time, there are several unique perspectives that people might take: for instance, looking at how their own company's stock has performed, or how the market as a whole did at significant points in their life. It is possible that the visualization could be tailored to bring out these perspectives.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Expressive Spectator Interface</head><p>In many cases a group of two or more people used the NameVoyager together. This is to be expected in the case of two parents-to-be trying to find a name they both like, but also seemed to occur in other contexts; as one person wrote, "We spent hours typing in the names of everyone we know."</p><p>When a group uses a single-input software tool like the NameVoyager, there are two distinct user roles. At any given moment, one person will be active, controlling the input, while others in the group will act as spectators. (These spectators may of course be active in other ways, talking with each other and making suggestions to the user controlling the input.) Traditionally, interface designers have focused on the active participant, but recently it has been suggested designing for the spectator role creates important special considerations <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. A natural hypothesis is that a social data analysis tool should support spectators as well as active participants.</p><p>Does the NameVoyager interface have special properties that create a good spectator experience? Two notable features of the NameVoyager are the smooth animation between states and the unusually prominent text entry area. The animation was initially added for the simple reason that it looked good, while the text area indicates to novice users that they should start typing. These two features, however, also give the NameVoyager an effective spectator interface.</p><p>The prominent text area makes it easy for someone peering over the shoulder of a user to see what is being typed. The immediate letter-by-letter changes in the graphs give the display a live-action quality, allowing spectators to see each step of the user's thinking process. The animation emphasizes the results of the typing, and links successive states in a coherent progression. This avoids the jarring feeling-familiar to anyone watching television while someone else wields the remote control-of seeing a series of sudden, unexpected changes.</p><p>Because both input and output are amplified, the NameVoyager interface falls in the "expressive" quadrant of the spectator interface taxonomy discussed by Reeves et al. in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. (The other quadrants are termed "suspenseful," "magical," and "secretive.") We suggest that for information visualization, where clarity and common understanding are critical, the "expressive" style of spectator interface is best-and that there may be features, such as animated transitions, that have larger value for groups than single users.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Discovery Transfer</head><p>The final hypothesis about how the NameVoyager encourages social data exploration is that it allows people to share the state of the visualization at any point in their explorations. Because the interaction model is so simple-just a matter of typing a few letters-it is very easy to guide other people to the same state. And indeed, many comments on the web are written in the imperative voice:</p><p>"Take a look at K and see how it exploded in the last decade or two" "Type in Adolph for example" "You want some real fun, run 'Hillary'"</p><p>What people are doing here, by hand, is creating a kind of pointer into the application-that is, making a reference into a particular state following interaction. The ability for users to transfer their discoveries to others may be critical to the conversation surrounding the NameVoyager.</p><p>Solitary, asychronous usage can in this way become a shared experience. The ease of "showing off" discoveries also fosters a motivating sense of pride and competitiveness. Thus a natural design principle might be that information visualization software ought to provide " application-state pointers" if it is intended to support collaborative analysis. Such pointers could involve special URLs for later reference or some other technology. A good example of an application-state pointer in a commercial visualization tool comes from the web interface to the Spotfire system <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, which allows users to make comments about an online analysis. When reading a comment, another user can view the exact state of the visualization (slider position, data, etc.) seen by the comment' s author.</p><p>Note that allowing application-state pointers may impose some subtle constraints. Some graph layout algorithms, for example, involve random numbers, or depend on a long history of user manipulations. These algorithms would need to be modified to allow different people to see consistent views.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSION AND FUTURE DIRECTIONS</head><p>The NameVoyager is a visualization of baby name popularity data, using keyboard-based interaction and smooth animation to allow users to explore a set of 6,000 time series. The applet has proven extremely popular, attracting hundreds of thousands of users in the space of two months. In addition, thousands of comments about the visualization have been written on the web.</p><p>This paper has explored the reaction to the NameVoyager, using these web comments as evidence. This methodology is somewhat unusual, but the sheer amount of online discussion of the NameVoyager provides a useful source of detailed descriptions from real users, and is a fruitful source of hypotheses about how and why the NameVoyager is effective.</p><p>The comments reveal that the NameVoyager is popular even among people who have no vested interest in looking for namesthe applet is somehow appealing to people even when it is not solving an immediate problem. Moreover, users seem to be doing extensive data mining with the application, finding for themselves subtle patterns in the data. These facts make it all the more interesting to understand the NameVoyager' s popularity, since it may serve as a model for other situations, especially in education, where the goal is to impart insight into a set of data that may not be immediately relevant to a user.</p><p>A central observation made from comments found on the web is that usage of the NameVoyager often involves a high degree of dialogue between users. It seems, at least in some cases, to be a social activity in which users discuss findings, set each other puzzles, and draw inspiration from one another. We believe this type of activity, which we term social data analysis, is the key to the efficacy and popularity of the applet. The collaborative, distributed nature means that people can join forces and share knowledge; the social aspect, because it is intrinsically enjoyable, may explain the applet' s appeal to users who state that they do not like babies or are not interested in baby names.</p><p>Understanding the patterns of social data analysis seems like a promising area for future research. This paper uses Bartle' s taxonomy of players in multi-user online games as a starting point for understanding the different roles of people interacting with the NameVoyager. A natural area for further investigation would be to test this idea, perhaps through user interviews and questionnaires.</p><p>We have also proposed several design principles for social data analysis, each of which requires validation. It would be interesting, for example, to explore how effective " spectator interfaces" might differ from standard interfaces. Indeed, is there a simple experiment that might show that some feature, such as animated transitions, has no value for a single user but provides a significant benefit for a group?</p><p>Similarly, it would be helpful to investigate methods that allow groups to coordinate their investigation. Application-state pointers, we hypothesize, may be one way to do so, but present engineering and algorithmic challenges, as well as more conceptual ones. How should such pointers behave, for instance, in an application where the underlying data is constantly changing? The common ground / unique perspective hypothesis says that it is helpful for users to have unique entry points into a data set. Are there ways to encourage these unique viewpoints? Could there be interfaces that show which parts of a data set have been explored less heavily, giving people an incentive to find overlooked gems?</p><p>Given the variety of questions to be asked, we believe exploring further frameworks and design principles related to social data analysis will be a fruitful avenue of investigation.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The NameVoyager 1 Rogers Street, Cambridge MA 02142 mwatten@us.ibm.com 1 IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization 2005 October 23-25, Minneapolis, MN, USA 0-7803-9464-X/05/$20.00 ©2005 IEEE.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Names beginning with O</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Names Beginning with LAT</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Although people may differ in their tastes, most Americans would agree on the likely ethnicity of a Rodrigo or a LaTanya, or the likely age of an Ethel versus a Heather. Similarly, many names relate to celebrities, pop culture icons, or historical figures. This common ground is what makes conversation about the data possible and interesting. Some sample quotes: "Look what the Simpsons did to the name Bart." "Roosevelt has two spikes right about where you' d expect them." "I love the fact that Xander and Willow show up on the list in the 90s, thereby confirming the existence of Buffy fans as hardcore as me."</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>Many thanks are due to the members of the Collaborative User Experience group at IBM for comments on the ideas in this paper, and to the anonymous referees for several helpful suggestions. I am especially grateful to Fernanda Viégas for introducing me to many of the social facets of information visualization. Laura Wattenberg provided significant input into the NameVoyager design and helpful comments on this paper.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The alphaslider: a compact and rapid selector</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ahlberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ahlberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Visual Information Seeking: Tight Coupling of Dynamic Query Filters with Starfield Displays. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Jigsaw Classroom: Building cooperation in the classroom (2 nd ed)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aronson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Patnoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
			<publisher>Addison Wesley Longman</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Players Who Suit MUDs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bartle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.mud.co.uk/richard/hcds.htm" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of MUD Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ThemeRiver: Visualizing Theme Changes over Time</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Havre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hetzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nowell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic Query Tools for Time Series Data Sets, Timebox Widgets for Interactive Exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hochheiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Think different: increasing online community participation using uniqueness and group dissimilarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ludford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cosley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Frankowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Terveen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://babynamewizard.com/namevoyager/lnv0105.html" />
		<title level="m">NameVoyager</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing the Spectator Experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Reeves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Benford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>O' Malley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The eyes have it: A task by data type taxonomy for information visualizations</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shneiderman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 1996 IEEE, Visual Languages</title>
		<meeting>1996 IEEE, Visual Languages</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Spotfire</forename><surname>Decisionsite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Inc</forename><surname>Spotfire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Somerville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Viégas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Potter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Donath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Digital Artifacts for Remembering and Storytelling. Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Artifacts of the Presence Era: Using Information Visualization to Create an Evocative Souvenir</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Viégas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Perry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Donath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Baby Name Wizard</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wattenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Broadway</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
