<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">DataSpace: 3-D Visualizations of Large Databases</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Anupam</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dar</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Leibfried</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Petajan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07974</postCode>
									<settlement>Murray Hill</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Houston</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Clear Lake</addrLine>
									<postCode>77058</postCode>
									<region>Texas</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">DataSpace: 3-D Visualizations of Large Databases</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-02-19T18:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>DataSpace is a system for interactive 3-D visualization and analysis of large databases. DataSpace utilizes the display space by placing panels of information, possibly generated by different visualization applications, in a 3-D graph layout, and providing continuous navigation facilities. Selective rearrangements and transparency can be used to reduce occlusion or to compare or merge a set of images (e.g. line graphs or scatter plots) that are aligned and stacked in depth. A prototype system supporting the basic 3-D graphic operations (layout, zoom, rotation, translation, transparency) has been implemented. We provide several illustrative examples of DataSpace displays taken from the current system. We present the 3-D display paradigm, describe the query, layout and rendering steps required to create a display, and discuss some performance issues. See Color Plates, pages 144, 145.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Advances in data collection and storage technology have greatly exceeded those in data analysis and visualization. The ever expanding use of information management systems by businesses and government has resulted in an overwhelming amount of information. However, this information "mine" is often underutilized, due to a lack of effective analysis and visualization tools for large databases. Such tools must be cost effective, offer interactive performance and integrate querying and visualization of the data. For example, information stored in a relational database can currently be queried using a declarative textual language like SQL; however the results can only be viewed in tabular form. Moreover, a user may wish to interactively construct a complex query by viewing previous query results in some graphical form and iteratively refining his/her queries.</p><p>DataSpace is designed to support interactive analysis and visualization of large, high dimensionality databases, i.e. large sets of data with a high number of attributes. A partic-ular problem associated with visualization of large databases is inadequate display space. DataSpace utilizes display space by placing panels or windows of information in a 3 dimensional environment using 3-D computer graphics technology. Windows are organized as nodes in a 3-D graph to facilitate optimal window arrangement and to present information in the 3-D graph itself. For example, 5 dimensional data can be visualized as a 3-D lattice of 2-D plots.</p><p>The essential advantage of such 3-D information display is the ability to continuously scale the information panels by changing the distance between the panel and the point of view (POV), thereby allowing more panels in the display. Much of the information in a distant (small) panel remains directly accessible (e.g.,graph shape, color, text format). At the same time, the ability to "perturb" (slightly change) the POV provides strong depth cues, helping the user get oriented in the graph layout. A disadvantage of 3-D graphics is occlusion of background objects by foreground objects. This problem is addressed in DataSpace by three basic mechanisms. Most importantly, DataSpace allows the user to interactively change the POV in order to expose background objects at will. DataSpace also supports the use of transparency in the 3-D graph, allowing all objects (panels) to become partially transparent so that background objects are visible through foreground objects. Transparency can also be used to compare and/or merge a set of images (e.g. line graphs) that are aligned and stacked in depth, such that the individual images can still be distinguished by slight changes in POV and selective changes in transparency. Finally, the user can reconfigure all objects in a nonoccluding arrangement from a given POV. For example, a 3-D lattice of panels can be converted continuously (using animation) into a tiling of panels at the same distance from the POV.</p><p>Since different visualizations may be suitable for different data types, the ability to customize the presentation is important. A large variety of data presentation formats have been developed for specific types of data. For exam-ple, geographic and demographic information, financial graphical location. Generating the appropriate node image data, and sales data may require different visualization in either case requires specific expertise: normalizing the methods, such as maps, scatter plots, and tables. DataSpace data in the first case, generating the map display in the seccan be used as a 3-D window manager, allowing the user to ond. Rather than incorporating such specialized capabilities incorporate displays generated by different visualization in <ref type="table">DataSpace, we chose a more flexible and open approach,  systems into a unified graphical environment.</ref> designing DataSpace as a 3-D window manager controlling</p><p>The query and visualization cycle time must be short, or else the opportunity for insight may be diminished due to human memory and attention limitations. Achieving an acceptable iteration time requires fast computer processing, including database access and graphics presentation, as well as efficient human analysis. The effectiveness and speed of human processing depends on many factors, such as the intuitiveness of the display and the quality of the graphics presentation, including its format and resolution. In addition to considering such factors in DataSpace. we also strive to reduce the computer processing time by using efficient 3-D display algorithms and by incorporating techniques for speeding up query evaluation time.</p><p>windows created by other applications. Currently such applications include Trellis <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>, SeeNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, SeeSoft <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> and IMACS <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</p><p>Section 2.1 provides several illustrative examples of the DataSpace display graph, using 2-D tiling, a 3-D lattice and a hierarchical layout. A more detailed discussion of the display graph, the visualization process required to create it, the interaction between DataSpace and other applications and performance issues is given in Section 3. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">The DataSpace Paradigm</head><p>The underlying display model used to organize and present information in DataSpace is a 3-D display graph, comprised of nodes located in a 3-D space and edges connecting those nodes. The layout of the graph as well as the display properties of the nodes and edges, such as color and transparency, may be controlled via the user interface. Typically a node represents a set of data items, while edges represent relationships between those data items. For example, consider analyzing a database of telephone calls. Each node may represent a segment of the customer population. The color of the border of the node may indicate the number of customers in that segment. An edge between two nodes may represent phone calls made between the two sets of customers. The edge color may be used to indicate the average length of a call, and the edge width may be related to the total cost of the calls.</p><p>Nodes in the graph may contain 2-D or 3-D graphical images. An important feature of DataSpace is that the contents of a node may be generated by a separate application, with DataSpace used to render the resulting node image. In our example, there may be different ways that the set of customers associated with a node may be viewed, for instance (1) as a scatter plot depicting their total monthly phone bill, or (2) as points on a map, depicting their geo- shows panels arranged in a 2-D matrix with fifteen rows and eighteen columns. The panels represent the usage of telecommunication services by different companies over a period of time. Each panel represents, using a line graph, the usage a particular telecommunication service by some company over a period of time. The panels are arranged such that each row shows the usage of different services by the same company, and each column depicts the usage of the same service by different companies. Such an arrangement can provide an holistic view of the data.</p><p>We would like to impress upon the reader that even when nodes are reduced to a size smaller than a post stamp, it is still possible to observe the patterns that appear on individual nodes. Interesting nodes can be selected for closer or comparative viewing. For example, <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows a single 1. We recommend to the reader to look at the color plates corresponding to the black and white figures in the text.</p><p>node blown up to its full size for closer inspection. If a direct comparison of multiple nodes is desired, then a three-dimensional presentation using orthographic projection together with transparency may be used (see <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>).  <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows panels arranged in a 3-D lattice and viewed in perspective projection, such that panels farther from the viewer are rendered smaller then panels that are closer. This appears to provide a vanishing point and perspective foreshortening much as that provided by a pinhole camera <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref>. In contrast, orthographic projections, as in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>, render like objects at the same size regardless of their distances from the viewer. Tn <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> and <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> each plane displays data for a different company, using scatter plots in <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> and line graphs in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. The perspective projection allows the user to quickly get oriented in the display space, and is convenient for navigation-The orthographic projection is useful for '"paging through" planes and for amqxuing data on multiple planes using transparency and selective rearrangement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2">3-D Lattice with PerspectCve Projections</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.3">Ortbgrk@ic Projectim with Trampamncy</head><p>Two modes of transparency are provided in DataSpace: with overlay transparency, all the panel background pixels are fully transparent* resulting in a uniform combination of the visual information (foreground) of stacked nodes. With blefid&amp; transparency, the planes are not fully transparent. Consequently, the observed intensity of a panels diminishes as its distance from the viewer is increased, providing a sense of depth.</p><p>Overlay transparency is typically useful when the depth dimension is unordered. As an example, <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> shows the same panels as in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>, arranged in a 3-D lattice such that each plane represents information on a different cornpany, and viewed using orthographic projection with overlay transparency. Nodes ~Jigned directly behind each other <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>. Orthographii Projection with Overlay Transparency correspond to services provided to different companies over the same time period. By using overlay transparency and a different color for each company's information, the user may visually compare and/or combine the information displayed on multiple nodes or planes. Blended transparency may be more appropriate when the depth dimension corresponds to some ordered attribute of the data, such as its time dimension. The degree of transparency can be adjusted to control the number of node images that are visible. For example, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 4</ref> demonstrates the use of blended transparency with multiple stacked nodes, each containing a scatter plot point cloud together with a fitted curve. As te level of transparency is increased from the figure on the kft to the middle figure and then to the figure on the right, the points and curves from previously occluded nodes become gradually more visible. Graphical selection can be used to reduce the number of nodes, rows, columns or depth plans displayed on the screen. For example, we may wish to compare only the two companies represented by the first and third plane in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.4">Hierarchkal Laymt with Edges</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">The Visualization Process</head><p>Given a database to be visualized, DataSpace provides tools for the user to select a particular data set and to specify an initial display graph, by mapping attributes of the data into nodes and edges and determining how the nodes and edges are to be Iaid out and rendered in three dimensional space. The steps involved in this process, outlined in <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>, are as follows:</p><p>1. The raw data is cleaned and loaded into a database. 2. The user chooses a database to be explored. The schema of the database is presented to the user, allowing the user to select a subset of the data to be visualized. We provide a tabular query interface similar to Query-By-Example (QBE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, which is typical of many relational commercial database systems. 3. Attributes of the data are mapped to nodes and edges, resulting in a graph topology. 4. Nodes are assigned a Z (depth) value, i.e. they are distributed to different Z-planes. 5. Nodes are assigned X and Y values, resulting in a layout of the graph in 3-D. 6. Node contents are rendered. The node content may be generated by DataSpace or by a separate application. 7. Edges are rendered, including properties such as color, thickness and transparency. 8. A 3-D display graph is now displayed on the screen, which the user can manipuIate or modify. The user can also go back to an earlier point in the visuahzation process, such as to change the display graph layout or select a different data set to explore.</p><p>Note that these steps may not necessarily need to be done sequentially. In particular, the node contents can be generated by a separate application (step 6) while the 3-D graph layout is being computed (steps 4,5  <ref type="figure">Figure 6</ref>. The Visualization Process</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3-ddisplag</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Automatic Layout of a 3-D Graph</head><p>A large body of work has been devoted to graph layout in 2-D <ref type="bibr">[lo]</ref>. The goal of this work is to place nodes and edges so as to increase the coherence of the drawing, typically by reducing edge lengths or the number of edge crossings. Graph drawing in 3-D was also investigated, but finding a layout that will "Iook good" when the graph is arbitrarily rotated is a very difficult problem. In addition, many existing algorithms perform an exhaustive search of the space of layout possibilities, making them prohibitively slow for large graphs.</p><p>We intend to address graph layout using both theoretical and ad-hoc approaches. Firstly, since we are interested in finding layouts that reflect attributes of the underlying database in a manner designated by the user, the layout search space may be quite constrained. For example, the user may request that a specified set of nodes be placed all on the same plane, or alternatively that they be positioned directly behind each other. Secondly, while DataSpace supports perspective projections and rotation, we believe these will be used by users primarily for reorientation purposes. We expect DataSpace to be used mostly in orthographic projection, and hence we focus on layouts optimized for viewing from the "front". In particular, we intend to explore the use of 3-D layouts obtained by separately (or in parallel) determining a 2-D layout for the nodes and a 3-D depth assignment, and then combining the two. Thirdly, we believe that the negative effects of edge crossings can be reduced by drawing appropriate beginning and end parts of each edge while not drawing the middle <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, by changing the thickness and color of edges, and by the use of edge transparency.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Active W indows</head><p>As illustrated in Section 2, DataSpace may be used as a 3-D window manager for other visualization applications. We now discuss in more detail how DataSpace interacts with those applications.</p><p>In the present system the display panels managed by DataSpace are passive, i.e. they are "snapshots" generated by the applications rather than true windows into the application. We use postscript as the snapshot format of choice, since it supports scaling of the images. At the other extreme, DataSpace could be used to manage active windows, allowing the user full interaction with any visible application window. For example, the user may wish to graphically select (e.g. by highlighting) an area of a window and then apply to it some application-specific function, with the result being reflected in the window. However, it is difficult to support full interaction with any window in conjunction with 3-D navigation in DataSpace. Clearly having DataSpace simply manage live application windows, as in existing 2-D window managers, is not a viable option, since it would require the applications to handle scaling and rotation, as well as transparency. Therefore, if the output from the window applications is to be reflected in the DataSpace display, then this output must be intercepted by DataSpace in order for it to handle scaling, rotation and transparency. In addition, DataSpace must project graphical input from the user, directed at a particular window, to the 2-D coordinate system supported by that win-dow's application. For example, DataSpace may need to translate a combination of mouse clicks and drags into highlighting a rectangular area on an arbitrarily scaled and rotated window.</p><p>Within the spectrum going from fully active to no active windows, we selected an intermediate design point that we feel is both useful and feasible. We plan to extend the current "passive" DataSpace system by letting the user interact with application windows when those windows are at their full size. That is, a user may "pull" an application snapshot to the "front" of the display, enlarging it to its full size. At this point DataSpace can replace the passive snapshot by a live application window. Since the window has the same size as its snapshot, the node image seen by the user will be the same. However the border of the window may change to indicate to the user that the window is now active, and that the user may interact through it with the application using application-specific controls. When done, the user may "push" the application window back, making it smaller. DataSpace will transparently replace the window by its (new) snapshot and then scale the snapshot down and reposition it in the 3-D display graph (this process can be viewed as a generalization of window iconification and deiconification).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Performance Issues</head><p>There are two basic ways in which node images can be rendered in DataSpace: texture mapping, which directly applies an image to the node, and graphical construction, which creates the image as a collection of primitives operations, such as pixel, line, polygon and text drawing. Real time texture mapping currently requires expensive specialpurpose hardware, such as an SGI Reality Engine TM. The cost of such hardware may go down in the near future, as texture mapping chips become available for workstations and PCs. In DataSpace, texture mapping is used primarily for continuous scaling of windows that are perpendicular to the user's direction of view. Such restricted scaling can be done more cheaply than using pixel-by-pixel resealing. In addition, the need for texture mapping in DataSpace may be reduced by drawing graphical objects and text directly, provided a description of the graphics and text data is available. For example, <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> was generated using texture mapping, <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> was generated using polygon drawing, <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> was generated using a combination of texture mapping (for node background) and polygon drawing (for the line graphs).</p><p>We plan to augment DataSpace with heuristics for automatically choosing whether to render node images using texture mapping, graphical construction from descriptive data, or a combination of both. The choice will be based on the availability of resources, such as texture and physical mem-ory and rendering hardware, for these two classes of operations, as well as the complexity of the node contents. Additionally, heuristics may be introduced to trade-off the speed and quality of the rendering.</p><p>[2] is a front end to the S statistical package [l] providing multiple presentation formats, such as scatter plots, line charts and bar graphs. The existence of such specialized visualization systems motivated us to design DataSpace as a general, open 3-D display paradigm, in which panels gen-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.1">Transparency and Space Partitioning Trees</head><p>erated by other applications can be incorporated.</p><p>Space partitioning trees provide a spatial ranking of display objects that has three benefits: (a) it allows for an efficient computation of composite transparency from a given POV by an orderly progression from the back of the display to its front, (b) it supports fast view volume clipping as a set operation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, (c) it obviates the need for z-buffer calculations, which are expensive and at present require special hardware support. Affine transformations, required for changes in the POV such as scaling, rotation and translation (panning), can be performed efficiently on partitioning trees. Due to these considerations DataSpace has been integrated with Polymnia <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, a library that provides an efficient implementation of partitioning trees.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Related Work</head><p>Most current research on 3-D visualization is in the context of scientific visualization, which deals with rendering of physical data with intrinsic geometric properties (see e.g., <ref type="bibr">[ 151)</ref>. Similarly, work in virtual reality uses 3-D graphics to model physical environments, such as a building, a room or a desk, which may represent real world entities or abstract data <ref type="bibr">[16]</ref>. In contrast, we focus on visualization of largescale abstract data, typical of business applications. We use 3-D graphics to provide the user with an intuitive and flexible presentation tool. Hence, the 3-D display in DataSpace is not constrained by trying to emulate the physical world. Other research work with related goals is listed below <ref type="bibr">Keim et al [9]</ref> describe visual feedback queries for exploring large databases. The main goal is to maximize usage of the screen, by assigning each data item to one pixel on the screen, and using the color and position of the pixel to indicate the relevance of the data item to the query. 3-D arrangements were not explored.</p><p>Faloutsos and Lin [ 131 developed an algorithm for mapping points in a high-dimensional space to points in a lower-dimension space. We intend to incorporate their algorithm in DataSpace, allowing a user to visualize highdimensionality data by plotting is as 2-D or 3-D point clouds, optionally augmented by curve or surface fitting.</p><p>Many systems were developed to support visualization of a specific type of abstract data. For example, SeeSoft <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> is a system for visualization of large text software projects, typically involving multiple programmers and organized using many files. SeeNet <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> is a system for visualizing connections in networks, such as the long distance network. Trellis</p><p>The DataSpace 3-D graph design has been inspired by other 3-D layout and visualization systems. Among others, we were influenced by Reiss's study of 3-D visualization of programs [ 121; by the lattice model in [ 111, and by the cone tree metaphor for presenting hierarchical information <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusions</head><p>We described DataSpace, a system for interactive 3-D visualization and analysis of large databases. DataSpace provides a new visualization paradigm based on 3-D layout of information panels or windows, augmented with continuous navigation, selective rearrangement and transparency.</p><p>A prototype system supporting the basic 3-D graphic operations has been implemented. We believe that the 3-D graph paradigm used in DataSpace is both general and powerful. We provided several illustrative examples of DataSpace displays taken from the current system, including both 3-D visualizations generated by DataSpace from raw data, as well as panels generated by other applications and embedded in a DataSpace display graph. (Unfortunately, it is difficult to appreciate the full value of dynamic 3-D presentations by viewing static images like the ones in this paper.) We also discussed performance issues and indicated directions for future work, in particular transforming DataSpace into a 3-D window manager controlling both passive and active windows.</p><p>The most effective applications of DataSpace are those in which the large size or high dimensionality of the data make it difficult to visualize using existing 2-D visualization systems. For example, the Trellis system is capable of generating a large number of high-dimensional arrays of 2-D plots, however, the problem of managing the plots is essentially left to the user. Addressing this problem by embedding static Trellis display in DataSpace has proven quite useful. We are extending DataSpace to provide interactive visualization, allowing the user to dynamically select data and analyze it, by integrating the database interface, graph layout, node rendering and 3-D navigation components. The DataSpace system is currently being used, among others, in exploring telephone call data for market analysis and fraud detection purposes.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 . 2 -</head><label>12</label><figDesc>D Tiling with Node Blow-up Figure 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 . 3 -</head><label>23</label><figDesc>D Lattice with Perqaective Projection</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Progressive Blended Transparency</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>shows a 3-D hierarchical node layout with connecting edges, viewed in perspective projection. The underlying data is a synthetic organizational structure. Nodes represent people, rendered by (random) photographs, while edges represent management (or relationships. This structure allows the user to quickly navigate a large organizational hierarchy and get additional information about individuals or organizations of interest['I'].</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Hierarchical Layout with Edges 3 The DataSpace Architecture</figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the Proceedings on Information Visualization (INFOVIS '95) 0-8186-7201-3/95 $10.00 © 1995 IEEE</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Proceedings of the Proceedings on Information Visualization (INFOVIS '95)</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The New S Language</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chambers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<publisher>Wadsworth &amp; Brooks/Cole Advanced Books and Software</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Pacific Grove CA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Cleveeand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">*Visualizing Data</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Hobart Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SeeSoft -a Tool for VisuaEizing Line Oriented Software Statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">6</forename><surname>Eick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Steffen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sumner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="957" to="968" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-11" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing Network Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Eick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wilks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Visualizations and Graphics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge Representation Support for Data Archeotogy</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bra&amp;man</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Selfridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Terveen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Borgida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Halper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kirk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mcguiness</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Resnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. CHUM-92</title>
		<meeting>CHUM-92<address><addrLine>Baltimore MD</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992-11" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="464" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Jnteractive Solid Modeling Via Partitioning Trees</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Naylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of GrapAics Interface</title>
		<meeting>of GrapAics Interface</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1392-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="18" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cone Trees: Animated 3-D Visualizations of Hierarchical Information</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mackinlay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. CHI&apos;94</title>
		<meeting>CHI&apos;94</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994-04" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="94" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Query-By-Example</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zloof</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the National Computer Conference</title>
		<meeting>of the National Computer Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975-05" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="438" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supporting data Mining of Large Databases by Visual Feedback Queries</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H-P</forename><surname>K&amp;gel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Seidl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of 10th international Conference on Data Engineering</title>
		<meeting>of 10th international Conference on Data Engineering<address><addrLine>Houston, TX</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Algorithms for Automatic Graph Drawing: an Annotated Bibliography</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Eadse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tamassia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Lattice model for Data Display</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hibbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Visualization &apos;94</title>
		<meeting>Visualization &apos;94<address><addrLine>Washington DC, Ott</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="317" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">3-D Visualization of Program Information&quot; (Extended Abstract and System Demonstration</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Reiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">FastMap: A Fast Algorithm for Indexing, Data-Mining and Visualization of Traditional and Multimedia Datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Faloutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K-I</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>to appear in SIGMOD &apos;95</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Foley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Dam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Cornputer Graphics Principles and Practice</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hewitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Visualization in Scientijc Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Piementel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Teixeira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Virtual Reality: Through the New Looking Ghss</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd Edition, TAB Books</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
